<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1256698-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1256698" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="11458851" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021113">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1256698-A2" status="new" fvid="23617944">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1256698</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021113</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02010596-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02010596</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020510</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="IT-TO20010444-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>IT</country>
          <doc-number>TO20010444</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010511</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F01D   9/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F01D   9/04        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F01D  17/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F01D  17/16        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F01D  17/16B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F01D   9/04B</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Axialturbine mit variabler Statorgeometrie</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Axial turbine with a variable-geometry stator</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Turbine axiale avec stator à géométrie variable</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>FIATAVIO SPA</name>
            <address>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>AVIO S.P.A.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>FIATAVIO S.p.A.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Via Nizza 312</street>
              <city>10127 Torino</city>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>DALLE CRODE DOMENICO</name>
            <address>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SCHIPANI CLAUDIA</name>
            <address>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SPANO ENNIO</name>
            <address>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>DALLE CRODE, DOMENICO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SCHIPANI, CLAUDIA</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SPANO, ENNIO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>DALLE CRODE, DOMENICO</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Via Paolo Della Cella, 22 int. 12</street>
              <city>10148 Torino</city>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>SCHIPANI, CLAUDIA</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Via Piffetti, 36</street>
              <city>10143 Torino</city>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>SPANO, ENNIO</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Corso Peschiera, 268</street>
              <city>10139 Torino</city>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Jorio, Paolo</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>STUDIO TORTA S.r.l., Via Viotti, 9</street>
              <city>10121 Torino</city>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>An axial turbine (1) for aeronautical applications has a
casing (8) housing a stator (11), which is provided with
an array of airfoil profiles (33), which are positioned
angularly equidistant from one other about the axis (3)
of the turbine (1), define associated spaces (35)
between one another for the passage of a flow of gas and
are hinged to an annular structure (20, 21), each one
about an associated hinge axis (40) incident to the axis
(3) of the turbine (1); in service, the airfoil profiles
(33) are simultaneously actuated to rotate by an
identical angle of adjustment by means of a ring (51)
actuated by actuators (55) outside the casing (8) and
connected to each airfoil profile (33) via an associated
lever (72).
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="75" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="110"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to an axial turbine
for aeronautical applications and, in particular, for an
aeronautical jet engine. As is known, an aeronautical
engine comprises a compressor unit, a combustion chamber
arranged downstream from the compressor unit and a
turbine unit, which is in turn arranged downstream from
the combustion chamber and, generally, comprises three
axial turbines, which are designated as high-, medium-
and low-pressure turbines depending upon the pressure of
the gas passing through them.</p>
    <p num="0002">Each axial turbine comprises a succession of
stages, each one of which consists of a stator
comprising an array of fixed vanes and a rotor
comprising an array of vanes that rotate about the axis
of the turbine.</p>
    <p num="0003">The efficiency of a known axial turbine and
consequently of the associated aeronautical engine
varies substantially as a function of the various
operating conditions of the aeronautical engine itself.</p>
    <p num="0004">Indeed, the flow rate and thus the velocity of the
gas passing through the turbine stages vary as a
function of engine operating conditions, while the
geometry and relative position of the vanes of the
stages themselves are set at the design stage in 
accordance with a fixed compromise configuration so as
to achieve a satisfactory average efficiency for any gas
flow rate and for any engine operating condition.</p>
    <p num="0005">It has been found necessary to improve turbine
efficiency and thus the overall efficiency of the
associated aeronautical engine under the various
operating conditions of the engine.</p>
    <p num="0006">The purpose of the present invention is to produce
an axial turbine for aeronautical applications, which
turbine allows said requirement to be met in a simple
and functional manner.</p>
    <p num="0007">The present invention provides an axial turbine for
aeronautical applications having an axis of symmetry and
comprising a case and at least one stator housed in said
case and comprising a support structure and an array of
airfoil profiles positioned angularly equidistant from
one other about said axis of symmetry and defining
respective spaces between them for passage of a flow of
gas, and means for connecting each said airfoil profile
to said support structure, characterised in that said
connecting means comprise hinge means to permit each
said airfoil profile to rotate relative to said support
structure about an associated first hinge axis incident
to said axis of symmetry, and in that it also comprises
angular positioning means for simultaneously rotating
said airfoil profiles about said respective first hinge 
axes by an identical angle of adjustment.</p>
    <p num="0008">The invention will now be described with reference
to the attached drawings, which illustrate a nonlimiting
embodiment of the invention, in which:
<sl><li>Figure 1 is a partial schematic radial section of a
preferred embodiment of the axial turbine for
aeronautical applications produced according to the
invention;</li><li>Figure 2 is a radial section analogous to Figure 1
and illustrates a specific feature of the turbine in
Figure 1 at a larger scale;</li><li>Figure 3 is a partial front perspective view of the
turbine in Figure 1;</li><li>Figure 4 is a different radial section of the
turbine in Figures 1 and 2 and illustrates another
specific feature of the turbine; and</li><li>Figure 5 is an analogous figure to Figure 2 and
illustrates, with some parts removed for clarity, a
variant of the turbine in the preceding figures.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0009">In Figure 1, the number 1 indicates an axial
turbine (shown schematically and in part), which is part
of an aeronautical engine (not shown) comprising a
compressor unit, a combustion chamber arranged
downstream from the compressor unit and a turbine unit.
The turbine unit is in turn arranged downstream from the
combustion chamber and comprises three turbines 
respectively of high, medium and low pressure through
which there passes an axial flow of expanding gases
produced in the combustion chamber.</p>
    <p num="0010">The turbine 1 in particular defines the medium-pressure
turbine of the associated aeronautical engine,
has an axis 3 of symmetry coincident with the axis of
the engine itself and comprises an engine shaft 4
rotatable about the axis 3 and a case or casing 8
housing a succession of coaxial stages, only one of
which is denoted 10 in Figure 1.</p>
    <p num="0011">With reference to Figures 1 and 2, the stage 10
comprises a stator 11 and a rotor 12 keyed to the engine
shaft 4 downstream from the stator 11. The stator 11 in
turn comprises a hub 16 (shown schematically and in
part), which is integrally connected to the casing 8 by
means of a plurality of spokes 17 (Figure 2) angularly
equidistant from one another about the axis 3 and
supports the engine shaft 4 in known manner.</p>
    <p num="0012">With reference to Figures 2 and 3, the stator 11
also comprises two annular platforms or walls 20, 21,
which are arranged in mutually facing positions between
the hub 16 and the casing 8, have the spokes 17 passing
through them and are coupled one with the casing 8 and
the other with the hub 16 in substantially fixed datum
positions by means of connecting devices 24 that impart
degrees of axial and/or radial freedom to said walls 20, 
21 with respect to the casing 8 and the hub 16 in order
to compensate, in service, for the differences in
thermal expansion between the various components.</p>
    <p num="0013">The walls 20, 21 each comprise an associated
plurality of sectors 25, 26 that are circumferentially
adjacent to one another (Figure 3) and have respective
surfaces 27, 28 facing each other, which radially
delimit an annular duct 30 with a diameter increasing in
the direction of travel of the flow of gas.</p>
    <p num="0014">The walls 20, 21 carry an array of hollow vanes 32,
which are angularly equidistant from one another about
the axis 3, have the spokes 17 passing through them and
comprise respective airfoil profiles 33 housed in the
duct 30, circumferentially delimiting between them a
plurality of spaces 35 to allow passage of the flow of
gas (Figure 3).</p>
    <p num="0015">As shown in Figure 2, each vane 32 also comprises
an associated pair of hinging flanges 36, 37, which are
tubular, cylindrical, arranged on opposite sides of the
associated profile 33 and integral with the profile 33
itself. The flanges 36, 37 of each vane 32 are mutually
coaxial along an axis 40, which is substantially
orthogonal to the surfaces 27, 28 and incident to the
axis 3 and forms an angle other than 90° to said axis 3,
said flanges engaging in respective circular seats 41,
42 made in the walls 20 and 21, respectively, to permit 
the profile 33 to rotate about the axis 40 relative to
said walls 20, 21.</p>
    <p num="0016">Each profile 33 comprises a tail portion delimited
by a top surface 45 slidably coupled with the surface 27
and by a base surface 46 slidably coupled with the
surface 28.</p>
    <p num="0017">The zones of the surfaces 27 and 28 to which
surfaces 45 and 46 respectively are coupled have a shape
complementary to respective ideal surfaces defined by
the rotation about the axes 40 of the median lines of
said surfaces 45 and 46.</p>
    <p num="0018">The flange 36 of each vane 32 ends in a threaded
cylindrical section 48, which is coaxial with the flange
36 itself and is connected to an angular positioning and
synchronising unit 50 capable of rotating the vanes 32
simultaneously about their respective axes 40 through
the same angle, keeping the profiles 33 in the same
orientation to each other.</p>
    <p num="0019">The unit 50 is part of the turbine 1 and comprises
a mobile synchronising ring 51 arranged around the wall
20 and slidably coupled with a guide track 52, which
delimits an internal portion 53 of said casing 8 and
keeps the ring 51 in a fixed radial position coaxial
with the axis 3.</p>
    <p num="0020">In order to limit friction forces, a layer of a
material that can withstand the in-service temperatures 
of the turbine 1 and has a relatively low coefficient of
friction is interposed between the ring 51 and the
portion 53. According to a variant that is not
illustrated, a series of rolling elements, preferably
spaced apart from each other circumferentially by a
cage, is interposed between the ring 51 and the portion
53.</p>
    <p num="0021">As shown in Figure 4, the unit 50 also comprises
two actuators 55 known per se arranged outside the
casing 8 in mutually diametrically opposite positions,
only one of which is shown schematically.</p>
    <p num="0022">The actuators 55 are connected in a known manner
(not shown), for example by hinges, to a fixed frame, in
particular to the casing 8 of the turbine 1 and each
comprise an associated end fork 56 movable in a
direction substantially tangential relative to the axis
3.</p>
    <p num="0023">The actuators 55 cause the ring 51 to rotate about
the axis 3 in both directions by means of associated
interposed lever transmissions 58, only one of which is
shown in Figure 4.</p>
    <p num="0024">The transmission 58 is part of the unit 50 and
comprises a cylindrical transmission body 59, which has
an axis 60 that is incident to the axis 3 and forms,
together with said axis 3, an angle equal to that formed
by the axes 40. The body 59 extends axially through the 
casing 8 in an intermediate position between the ring 51
and the fork 56; it is connected to the casing 8 in a
fixed axial position and in angularly rotatable manner
and carries two opposed radial levers 61, 62. The lever
61 is fixed, at one end, to the body 59 and is connected
at the opposite end to the fork 56 by means of a hinge
pin 65 carried by said fork 56 and a ball joint 66
interposed between the pin 65 and the lever 61. The
lever 62, on the other hand, is housed in the casing 8,
comprises an end portion 67, which is coaxial with the
body 59, is connected to said body 59 in a fixed angular
position by axial interposition of a grooved sleeve 68
and engages, in rotatable manner about the axis 60, in a
blind positioning seat 69 made in a sector 25a.</p>
    <p num="0025">As shown in Figures 2 and 3, the ring 51 is
connected to each vane 32 by means of an associated
lever 72, which extends radially relative to the axis 40
of the portion 48 towards the ring 51 and is fixed to
the vane 32 by means of a locking ring 74 screwed to
said portion 48.</p>
    <p num="0026">With reference to Figures 2 and 4, the levers 62,
72 have respective end portions 75 connected to the ring
51 by means of respective connecting devices 76 that are
part of the unit 50.</p>
    <p num="0027">Each device 76 comprises an associated hinge pin
78, which is integral with the ring 51 and has an axis 
80 that is incident to the axis 3 and forms, with said
axis 3, an angle equal to that formed by the axes 40,
60.</p>
    <p num="0028">Each device 76 also comprises an associated ball
joint or bearing 82, which in turn comprises a spherical
seat 84 fixed to the associated end portion 75 and a
spherical head 86, which engages rotatably in the
spherical seat 84 and is fitted slidingly on the
associated pin 78.</p>
    <p num="0029">During rotation of the ring 51 about the axis 3,
each ball joint 82 compensates for the differences in
relative orientation between the lever 62, 72 and the
pin 78. At the same time, the sliding connection between
the spherical heads 86 and the pins 78 and that between
the ring 51 and the track 52 makes it possible to
compensate for the differences in trajectory of the
levers 62, 72 in the radial direction relative to the
ring 51 and in the axial direction relative to the axis
3 respectively.</p>
    <p num="0030">According to the variant shown in Figure 5, the
ring 51 is held by a retaining device 90 in a fixed
axial position relative to the track 52, while the
devices 76 are replaced by respective connecting devices
92, each comprising an associated fork 94 integral with
the ring 51 and defining a radial slot 95 relative to
the axis 3. Each device 92 also comprises an associated 
hinge pin 98, which differs from the pin 78 in that it
is integrally joined to the end portion 75 of the
associated lever 62, 72 and in that it comprises an
integral spherical end portion 99, which is connected
slidably against two flat surfaces facing each other,
which define the slot 95.</p>
    <p num="0031">The sliding connection between the spherical
portion 99 and the fork 94 allows compensation both of
the differences in relative orientation and the
differences in trajectory in radial and axial directions
between the levers 62, 72 and the ring 51 during the
rotation of said ring 51.</p>
    <p num="0032">With reference to Figures 1 to 4, during assembly
of the turbine 1, once the vanes 32 have been mounted
between the associated sectors 25, 26 and the ring 51
provided with the pins 78 has been fitted around the
wall 20, the levers 72 are fitted on the portions 48
while simultaneously sliding the spherical heads 86 onto
the associated pins 78. The levers 72 are then fixed to
the vanes 32, keeping the profiles 33 identically
oriented about the respective axes 40, while the levers
62 are connected to the wall 20 by inserting the end
portions 67 into the seats 69. Once the stator 11 has
been connected to the casing 8, the remaining
transmissions 58 to be connected to the actuators 55 are
mounted. </p>
    <p num="0033">With regard to the variant in Figure 5, once the
levers 72 have been fixed to the vanes 32, the ring 51
is connected axially to the stator 11, while fitting the
forks 94 directly onto the spherical portions 99 of the
pins 98, said ring finally being locked radially
relative to the track 51. By using the device 92 to
connect the levers 72 to the ring 51, the levers 72
themselves are mounted directly and solely on the casing
8, without it being necessary to produce the seats 69 of
the sectors 25a by means of a die-casting die differing
from that provided for the other sectors 25.</p>
    <p num="0034">In service, the actuators 55 are operated so as to
vary the angular position of the ring 51 continuously or
discontinuously about the axes 3 and, thus, the ring 51
synchronously effects rotation of the vanes 32 about
their respective axes 40 by an identical angle of
adjustment, so keeping the profiles 32 in identically
oriented positions relative to one another about said
axes 40.</p>
    <p num="0035">Rotation of the profiles 33 modifies the geometry
of the spaces 35 and, in particular, modifies the
minimum area for passage of the gases in each space 35,
said area being defined by the extent to which the
trailing edge of one profile 33 projects onto the dorsal
face of the adjacent profile 33 and commonly being
designated the "throat area". </p>
    <p num="0036">With particular reference to the front perspective
view in Figure 3, clockwise rotation of the ring 51 and
thus of the profiles 33 brings about a reduction in the
passage area of each space 35 and thus a reduction in
the gas flow rate through the stage 10. Conversely,
anticlockwise rotation of the ring 51 brings about an
increase in the passage area of each space 35 and thus
an increase in the gas flow rate.</p>
    <p num="0037">It is clear from the above that, by hinging the
profiles 33 to the walls 20, 21 and rotating said
profiles 33 by means of the unit 50, it is possible to
create a variable-geometry axial turbine 1 that is more
efficient than known, fixed-geometry axial turbines.
Indeed, synchronously rotating the profiles 33 to vary
the passage area of the spaces 35 makes it possible to
adjust the gas flow rate through the stage 10, as a
result of which the turbine 1 can operate under optimal
conditions whatever the operating conditions of the
associated aeronautical engine.</p>
    <p num="0038">Using the ring 51 makes it possible to synchronise
the rotation of the profiles 33 about their respective
axes 40 in a simple and precise manner, while the
devices 76, 92 transmit the rotational motion between
the ring 51 and the levers 62, 72, said devices being
rotatable about the mutually incident axes without
jamming and simultaneously with very tight clearances. 
Indeed, it is essential for the components of the unit
50 to be relatively rigid and to be interconnected with
tight clearance, but with the least possible friction
forces in order to ensure that angular displacement of
the profiles 33 is accurate and always identical for all
profiles in the presence of elevated operating
temperatures.</p>
    <p num="0039">In particular, as already explained, the devices 92
permit very simple and relatively fast mounting of the
unit 50 on the turbine 1. At the same time, the pin 98
provides substantially punctiform contact between the
actual spherical portion 99 and the fork 94, said
contact being distinguished by relatively low friction
forces, and allows coupling clearance to be limited
where the spherical portion 99 is made in a single piece
with the pin 98, i.e. without using a spherical head
fitted on said pin.</p>
    <p num="0040">Moreover, the particular structure defined by the
walls 20, 21 and by the hub 16 means that the stresses
may be led from the engine shaft 4 into the casing 8 via
the spokes 17, but not via the vanes 32.</p>
    <p num="0041">Finally, on the basis of the above, it is clear
that modifications and variations can be made to the
turbine 1 described and illustrated without extending it
beyond the scope of protection of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0042">In particular, the unit 50 could differ from that 
described and illustrated by way of example. The devices
76 and/or 92 could differ from those illustrated, for
example the spherical head 86 of the pin 78 could be
connected to a fork carried by the associated lever 72
and be radial relative to the associated axis 40,
instead of engaging in the spherical seat 84, and/or the
transmissions 58 could be other than of the lever type.</p>
    <p num="0043">Moreover, the vanes 32 could be of a shape other
than that illustrated and/or be hinged to the walls 20,
21 in a manner other than that shown.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>Axial turbine (1) for aeronautical applications
having an axis of symmetry (3) and comprising a case (8)
and at least one stator (11) housed in said case (8) and
comprising a support structure (16, 20, 21) and an array
of airfoil profiles (33) positioned angularly
equidistant from one other about said axis of symmetry
(3) and defining respective spaces (35) between them for
passage of a flow of gas, and means (36, 37, 41, 42) for
connecting each said airfoil profile (33) to said
support structure (16, 20, 21); characterised in that
said connecting means (36, 37, 41, 42) comprise hinge
means (36, 37, 41, 42) to permit each said airfoil
profile (33) to rotate relative to said support
structure (16, 20, 21) about an associated first hinge
axis (40) incident to said axis of symmetry (3), and in
that it also comprises angular positioning means (50)
for simultaneously rotating said airfoil profiles (33)
about said respective first hinge axes (40) by an
identical angle of adjustment.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>Turbine according to Claim 1, characterised in
that said angular positioning means (50) comprise
actuating means (55) and synchronising means (51)
interposed between said actuating means (55) and said
airfoil profiles (33).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>Turbine according to Claim 2, characterised in
that said synchronising means (51) comprise a
synchronising ring (51) that is rotatable about said
axis of symmetry (3) and in that said angular
positioning means (50) also comprise first transmission
means (72, 76) interposed between each said airfoil
profile (33) and said synchronising ring (51) and second
transmission means (58) interposed between said
actuating means (55) and said synchronising ring (51).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>Turbine according to Claim 3, characterised in
that it comprises circumferential guide means (52)
cooperating with said synchronising ring (51) to keep
the synchronising ring (51) itself in a position coaxial
with said axis of symmetry (3).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>Turbine according to Claim 4, characterised in
that said circumferential guide means (51) comprise a
circumferential track (51) delimiting said case (8).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>Turbine according to any one of Claims 3 to 5,
characterised in that said first transmission means (72,
76) comprise a control lever (72) that is radial with
respect to the associated first hinge axis (40) and
integral with said associated airfoil profile (33).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>Turbine according to any one of Claims 3 to 6,
characterised in that said second transmission means
(58) comprise a transmission lever (62) actuated by said
actuating means (55) so as to rotate relative to said
case (8) about a second hinge axis (60) incident to said
axis of symmetry (3).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>Turbine according to Claim 6 or 7, characterised
in that at least one of said first (72, 76) and second
(58) transmission means comprise connecting and relative
mobility means (76; 92) interposed between each said
lever (62, 72) and said synchronising ring (51) to
transmit the rotational motion and, in service, to
compensate for differences in trajectory/orientation
between said synchronising ring (51) and each said lever
(62, 72) during rotation.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>Turbine according to Claim 8, characterised in
that said connecting and relative mobility means (76;
92) comprise a hinge pin (78; 98) interposed between
said associated lever (62, 72) and said synchronising
ring (51) and having a joint axis (80) incident to said
axis of symmetry (3) and a spherical head (86; 99)
interposed between said hinge pin (78; 98) and one of
said associated levers (62, 72) and said synchronising
ring (51).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>Turbine according to Claim 9, characterised in
that said spherical head (99) is integral with said
hinge pin (98).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>Turbine according to Claim 9, characterised in
that said hinge pin (78) and said spherical head (86)
are connected together slidingly along said joint axis
(60).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>Turbine according to any one of Claims 9 to 11,
characterised in that said synchronising ring (51) is
coupled with said case (8) in a fixed axial position;
said connecting and relative mobility means (76; 92)
comprising an elongate seat (95) made in one (72) of
said levers (62, 72), and said synchronising ring (51)
and engaged slidingly by said spherical head (99).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>Turbine according to Claim 12, characterised in
that said hinge pin (98) is integral with said
associated lever (62, 72); said elongate seat (95) being
defined by a slot parallel to said axis of symmetry (3)
and carried by said synchronising ring (51).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>Turbine according to Claim 12 or 13,
characterised in that said elongate seat (95) is defined
by a fork (94).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>Turbine according to any one of Claims 9 to 14,
characterised in that said joint axis (80) and said
first hinge axes (40) form identical angles with said
axis of symmetry (3).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>Turbine according to Claim 7, characterised in
that said actuating means (55) are arranged outside said
case (8) and in that said second transmission means (58)
comprise a transmission body (59) extending through said
case (8), angularly integral with said transmission
lever (62) and actuated by said actuating means (55) so
as to rotate about said second hinge axis (60).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>Turbine according to any one of the preceding
claims, characterised in that said first hinge axes (40)
form an angle other than 90° to said axis of symmetry
(3).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="18">
      <claim-text>Turbine according to any one of the preceding
claims, characterised in that said support structure
(16, 20, 21) comprises a hub (16) integrally connected
to said case (8) and a pair of annular walls (20, 21)
interposed between said hub (16) and said case (8) and
radially delimiting said spaces (35); said hinge means
(36, 37, 41, 42) being interposed between each said
airfoil profile (33) and said annular walls (20, 21).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="19">
      <claim-text>Turbine according to Claim 18, characterised in
that it comprises a plurality of elements (17)
connecting said hub (16) to said case (8) and each
extending through a said associated airfoil profile
(33).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="20">
      <claim-text>Turbine according to Claim 18 or 19,
characterised in that said hinge means (36, 37, 41, 42)
comprise, for each said airfoil profile (33), a pair of
circular seats (41, 42) each made in a said associated
annular wall, and a pair of hinge portions (36, 37)
arranged on opposite sides of said airfoil profile (33),
integral with said airfoil profile (33) and each
rotatably engaging in an associated circular seat (41,
42).</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
