<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1253550-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1253550" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="25289064" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021030">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1253550-A1" status="new" fvid="23586509">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1253550</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20021030</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02252884-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02252884</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020424</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="US-84309301-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>84309301</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010426</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G06K  17/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G06K  17/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G06K  17/00</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">System und Verfahren zum Datenzugriff auf Finanzbroschüren</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">System and method for accessing financial propectus data</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Système et procédé d'accès aux données d'un prospectus de finance</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>CFPH LLC</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>CFPH, L.L.C.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>CFPH, L.L.C.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>299 Park Avenue, 32nd Floor</street>
              <city>New York, NY 10171</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GINSBERG PHILLIP M</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GINSBERG, PHILLIP M.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>GINSBERG, PHILLIP M.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>25 Broad Street, Penthouse C</street>
              <city>New York, New York 10004</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Jones, David Colin</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Withers &amp;amp; Rogers, Goldings House 2 Hays Lane</street>
              <city>London SE1 2HW</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>Methods and systems for accessing prospectus
data are provided. These methods and systems utilize
electronically readable media incorporated into a
printed financial prospectus to provide access to data
in an electronic format. A suitable device may then be
used to read data from the electronically readable
media and store the data on a computer system. The
information provided by the prospectus therefore
contains both human-readable and electronically
readable information. The data may be provided in a
summary form, in a standardized form, or in any other
suitable form in order to facilitate subsequent
analysis of the data. The data may also be encrypted
while stored in the electronically readable media.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="92" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="107"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Background of the Invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0001">This invention relates to automation
processes for accessing financial prospectus data.
More particularly, this invention relates to methods
and systems for enabling users of prospectuses to
easily access the financial information contained
therein.</p>
    <p num="0002">A prospectus is a written document providing
information concerning an offering of financial
securities. A prospectus contains narrative
information on, for instance, the type and
classification of security, the type of business
associated with a security, potential risk factors, use
of proceeds, and security voting rights. A prospectus
may also include both consolidated and detailed
financial information on the associated business and
the security itself. Information in the form of data
in the prospectus may, for instance, include
underwriter compensation, dilution data, operations
data, summary of accounting policies, inventories,
property and equipment, leases and other assets, short-term
borrowing and long-term debt, employee benefit
plans, management salaries, income taxes and
authorization of common and preferred stock. The 
amount of data contained in a prospectus may be
extensive.</p>
    <p num="0003">Prospectuses are available in printed form,
typically as a booklet, suitable for distribution to
potential purchasers of securities. If the prospectus
is associated with a federally-regulated security, it
has to be submitted to the Securities Exchange
Commission (SEC) where it is entered into their
Electronic Data Gathering, Analysis, and Retrieval
System (EDGAR). The prospectus information is then
accessible by the general public over the SEC-maintained
database. The files in EDGAR are in either
plain text or Hypertext Mark-up Language (HTML) form.
Unofficial Portable Document Format (PDF) files may
also be submitted to the SEC. All of these file types
are in a human-readable form but not in electronically
readable form. Further, the information and data
contained in financial prospectuses may be in a variety
of formats and arrangements which may make the
information and data difficult to read, analyze and
interpret.</p>
    <p num="0004">Therefore, the information and data presented
in prospectuses may be difficult to manage because of
its volume, form, format and arrangement. Thus, it is
desirable to provide methods and systems for prospectus
data management. Such methods would facilitate the
provision of data in a manner that is electronically
accessible and more easily usable.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Summary of the Invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0005">These and other objects of the invention are
accomplished with the principle of the present 
invention by providing methods and systems for
prospectus data management.</p>
    <p num="0006">In accordance with the invention, these
methods and systems provide prospectus data management
by the use of electronically readable media
incorporated into (e.g., encapsulated on the cover) a
printed prospectus where the media stores important
financial information and data. The prospectus
information is therefore available in both a human-readable
and electronically readable format. The
electronically readable media may be in the form of,
for instance, bar codes, magnetic strips or embedded
chips. The data can be read from the prospectus using
a suitable device. Multiple electronically readable
media types may be provided for storage of different
data, i.e. salaries, assets, etc. The prospectus data
that is electronically readable may be in a summary
form. The data may also be in a standardized form.
Additionally, the electronically readable information
and data may be in an encrypted form where decryption
software is subsequently needed to read data.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Brief Description of the Drawings</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0007">These and other objects and advantages of the
invention will become apparent upon reading the
following detailed description and upon reference to
the drawings in which:
<sl><li>FIG. 1 is a depiction in accordance with one
embodiment of the present invention showing the front
cover of a printed prospectus with an electronically
readable media encapsulated on it;</li><li>FIG. 2 is a depiction of a table in
accordance with one embodiment of the present invention 
where the data table shown could be of a type found in
a securities' prospectus; and</li><li>FIG. 3 is a flow chart of the process in
accordance with one embodiment of the present invention
in which the prospectus electronically readable media
is accessed.</li></sl></p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Detailed Description of the Preferred Embodiments</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0008">An illustrative depiction of a system 10 in
accordance with certain embodiments of the present
invention is shown in FIG. 1. The prospectus may be
presented to a user in a conventional, human-readable,
printed form 11. Typically, the printed matter is in a
booklet form. Electronically readable media 12 may be
encapsulated on the cover 13 of the printed prospectus.
The electronically readable media may be optical bar
codes, magnetic strips, embedded computer chips or any
other suitable readable electronic data storage media.
There may be multiple electronically readable media 12
types encapsulated on the prospectus cover containing
different categories of data such as salary, assets,
underwriter information, etc. The information
contained in the electronically readable media may be
read using a suitable device 14 by a user. For
example, device 14 may be a bar code scanner, smart
card scanner, or any other suitable device connected to
a personal, portable, or hand-held computer, or any
other suitable device.</p>
    <p num="0009">The information contained in the
electronically readable media 12 may contain voluminous
data tables such as those shown in FIG. 2. Data
tables 20 may include information such as the previous
performance of securities for the business, borrowing 
information, information on the security itself, and
any other prospectus data as is well known in the art.</p>
    <p num="0010">One embodiment of a process 30 for using
system 10 is shown in FIG. 3. As illustrated, at
step 31, specific information and data from the
prospectus may be reviewed and chosen for inclusion in
the electronically readable media. The data chosen may
be included in a summarized form -- that is, not all
prospectus data but only selected portions may be
chosen for inclusion in the electronically readable
media.</p>
    <p num="0011">The data may be stored in a standardized
format to facilitate ease of data reading, and
subsequent interpretation and analysis. In particular,
the use of standardized data forms may allow subsequent
mathematical manipulation of financial data in a more
efficient manner. For instance, the data may be
contained in a standardized format so that, when read,
it may be in an appropriate input form to a database
where mathematical algorithms may subsequently be
applied. The process of arrangement of the data in a
standardized form is shown at step 32.</p>
    <p num="0012">At step 33, the information and data may be
converted to an encrypted form in one embodiment using
any of a wide variety of mathematical encryption
methods as known in the art. The encrypted data may
then be stored in the electronically readable media 12.</p>
    <p num="0013">At step 34, the information and data may be
read from the electronically readable media 12 using a
suitable device. For instance, a bar code may be read
by an optical scanner. The prospectus information and
data may be transferred to and stored on a variety of
suitable computer systems, including, but not limited 
to, personal computers. If data had been encrypted,
decryption software installed on a personal computer,
or other suitable device, may be needed to convert
information to a decrypted form as illustrated by
step 35. Encryption of the information and data may be
used, for instance, to restrict reading of data to
users who had purchased the decryption software.</p>
    <p num="0014">Finally, the data may be processed on the
computer to aid the user in evaluating the subject of
the prospectus, as shown at step 36. This processing
may include generating graphs, spreadsheet tables, or
any other suitable data processing technique as known
in the art.</p>
    <p num="0015">Thus, it is apparent that it has been
provided, in accordance with the invention, a
prospectus data management system that fully satisfies
the objects, aims and advantages set forth above.
While the invention has been described in conjunction
with specific embodiments thereof, it is evident that
many alternatives, modifications and variations as fall
within the spirit of the appended claims exist.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A system for prospectus data management,
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>at least one electronically readable
media incorporated into a printed financial prospectus
where data is stored; and</claim-text><claim-text>a suitable device that reads the data
contained in the electronically readable media.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The system of claim 1, wherein the data
is stored in the electronically readable media in a
summary format.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The system of claim 1, wherein the data
is stored in the electronically readable media in a
standardized format.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The system of claim 1, wherein different
categories of the data are stored in more than one
electronically readable media type.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The system of claim 1, wherein the data
is stored in an encrypted format prior to storage in
the electronically readable media.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The system of claim 1, wherein the
electronically readable media is incorporated into a
cover of the printed financial prospectus.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A method for accessing prospectus data,
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>storing the data in the electronically
readable media which is incorporated into a printed
financial prospectus; and</claim-text><claim-text>reading the data from the electronically
readable media using a suitable device.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The method of claim 7, further
comprising determining data to be stored in the
electronically readable media.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>The method of claim 7, further
comprising storing the data in a summary format.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>The method of claim 7, further
comprising storing the data in a standardized format.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>The method of claim 7, further
comprising utilizing more than one electronically
readable media type for separate storage of data
categories.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>The method of claim 7, further
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>encrypting the data prior to storing in
the electronically readable media; and</claim-text><claim-text>utilizing decryption computer software
after reading for decryption of the data.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>The method of claim 7, wherein the
electronically readable media is incorporated into a
cover of the printed financial prospectus.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>A printed prospectus, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>at least one page having printed
financial data; and</claim-text><claim-text>an electronically readable media
containing an electronically readable version of the
printed financial data.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
