<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1258400-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1258400" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="18989775" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021120">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1258400-A2" status="new" fvid="23614996">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1258400</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021120</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02010665-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02010665</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020513</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001143669-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001143669</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010514</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B60R  21/01        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B60R  21/01        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B60R  21/0132      20060101A N20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B60R  21/0132      20060101C N20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B60R  21/16        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B60R  21/16        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B60R  21/0132</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L60R21:0132T</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L60R21:01N1A</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L60R21:01N3</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Erkennungssystem der Schwere eines Aufpralls</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Collision severity determining system</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Système de détermination de gravité d'une collision</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TOYOTA MOTOR CO LTD</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TOYOTA JIDOSHA KABUSHIKI KAISHA</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>TOYOTA JIDOSHA KABUSHIKI KAISHA</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1, Toyota-cho</street>
              <city>Toyota-shi, Aichi 471-8571</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>IMAI KATSUJI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>IYODA MOTOMI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MIYATA YUJIRO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>IMAI, KATSUJI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>IYODA, MOTOMI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MIYATA, YUJIRO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>IMAI, KATSUJI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>c/o TOYOTA Jidosha Kabushiki Kaisha, 1, Toyota-cho</street>
              <city>Toyota-shi, Aichi-ken 471-8571</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>IYODA, MOTOMI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>c/o TOYOTA Jidosha Kabushiki Kaisha, 1, Toyota-cho</street>
              <city>Toyota-shi, Aichi-ken 471-8571</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>MIYATA, YUJIRO</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>c/o TOYOTA Jidosha Kabushiki Kaisha, 1, Toyota-cho</street>
              <city>Toyota-shi, Aichi-ken 471-8571</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Leson, Thomas Johannes Alois</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Patentanwälte Tiedtke-Bühling-Kinne &amp;amp; Partner, Bavariaring 4</street>
              <city>80336 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A collision severity determining system for determining severity of a collision
of a vehicle includes a first deceleration detector disposed in a central portion of a
vehicle body for detecting a vehicle deceleration in a longitudinal direction of the
vehicle, and a second deceleration detector disposed in a front portion of the vehicle
for detecting a deceleration in the longitudinal direction. A controller of the system
calculates a velocity change amount of the vehicle by integrating the vehicle
deceleration with respect to time, and determines severity of the vehicle collision by
comparing the vehicle deceleration with a threshold value corresponding to the same
velocity change amount. When a problem, such as a failure or breakdown of the
second deceleration detector, occurs, the severity determining unit operates in a
predetermined fail-safe mode for selecting an appropriate one of severity
determination maps stored in the controller, and makes a severity determination based
on the selected severity determination map.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="76" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="87"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <heading>1. <u style="single">Field of the Invention</u></heading>
    <p num="0001">The invention relates to a collision severity determining system that
operates at the time of activation of an occupant protection device, and provides a
result of severity determination which can be used for adjusting, for example, the
power level of deployment of the occupant protection device, such as an airbag
system, thus assuring more appropriate occupant protection.</p>
    <heading>2. <u style="single">Description of Related Art</u></heading>
    <p num="0002">Occupant protection devices, such as airbag systems, which are
installed on vehicles are known in the art. The timing of activation of such an
occupant protection device is adjusted based on changes in the deceleration of the
vehicle with time, which is detected by a deceleration sensor, or the like, incorporated
in the vehicle. In order to activate the occupant protection device at a more
appropriate time, it is important to detect collision of the vehicle with sufficiently high
reliability. As one type of a device for detecting collision of the vehicle, Japanese
Laid-Open Patent Publication No.10-152014 discloses an activation control system
which includes a floor sensor disposed substantially at the center of a vehicle chassis
and a front sensor or sensors disposed in a front portion of the vehicle. The control
system controls activation of an occupant protection device based on decelerations
detected by the floor sensor and the front sensor(s). With such an activation control
system, the occupant protection device can be appropriately activated by referring to a
deceleration(s) detected by the front sensor(s), even when it is difficult to detect an
impact only by means of the floor sensor.</p>
    <p num="0003">For achieving further reliable occupant protection at the time of a
collision of the vehicle, it is preferable to determine severity of the collision, namely,
a degree of the vehicle collision that causes a secondary collision of the occupant
against an object within the passenger compartment, and adjust the level of the power
for activating the occupant protection device in accordance with the collision severity.
The severity determination can be made based on a deceleration detected by the floor
sensor while referring to a deceleration(s) detected by the front sensor(s) as in the case
where the activation of the occupant protection device is detected. </p>
    <p num="0004">In the meantime, the vehicle is provided with a predetermined fail-safe
mode, so as to ensure appropriate occupant protection even when any problem
occurs to the vehicle. For example, an ECU (electronic control unit) provided at a
predetermined position in the vehicle monitors vehicle conditions, including those of
an engine and a brake system, at regular intervals. Upon occurrence of any problem
to the vehicle, the vehicle generates a certain warning or alarm, and starts operating in
a predetermined fail-safe mode designed for securing the safety of the vehicle
occupant.</p>
    <p num="0005">The vehicle operates in the above-described fail-safe mode in various
situations, which includes the case where a problem occurs to the front sensor or
sensors. In the case of a vehicle equipped with an occupant protection device capable
of determining the collision severity, results of severity determination obtained with
the same output value of the floor sensor may differ depending upon the
deceleration(s) detected by the front sensor(s). In view of this case, it has been
proposed to program the occupant protection device in advance to use a lower
threshold value than in normal cases, for determining the collision severity in the fail-safe
mode.</p>
    <p num="0006">Examples of problems that can occur to the front sensor include, for
example, a failure of the front sensor during normal use, which is an extremely rare
occasion, breakdown of the front sensor itself due to a collision of the vehicle,
disconnection of a communication line or lines around the front sensor upon a vehicle
collision, and so forth. The problems arising from these different causes make it
impossible to detect a deceleration from the front sensor for use in severity
determination.</p>
    <p num="0007">To ensure sufficiently high occupant protection reliability, it is
preferable to determine the severity of a collision in an appropriate manner,
depending upon the cause of the problem that occurs to the front sensor. As described
above, the occupant protection device may be pre-programmed to use a lower
threshold value upon occurrence of a problem to the front sensor, for determining the
collision severity in the fail-safe mode. However, it would be more desirable to
determine the collision severity depending upon the cause of the problem occurring to
the front sensor, in order to achieve more appropriate occupant protection. </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0008">It is therefore an object of the invention to provide a severity
determining system that is able to determine severity of a collision with improved
accuracy even when a problem occurs to a front sensor or sensors.</p>
    <p num="0009">To accomplish the above and/or other object(s), there is provided
according to one aspect of the invention a collision severity determining system for
determining severity of a collision of a vehicle, which system includes: (a) a first
deceleration detector disposed substantially in a central portion of a body of the
vehicle so as to detect a vehicle deceleration in a longitudinal direction of the vehicle,
(b) a second deceleration detector disposed in a front portion of the vehicle that is
located ahead of the first deceleration detector, so as to detect a deceleration at the
front portion in the longitudinal direction of the vehicle, (c) a velocity change amount
calculating unit that calculates a velocity change amount of the vehicle by integrating
the vehicle deceleration detected by the first deceleration detector with respect to
time, (d) a severity determining unit storing two or more severity determination maps
defined by the vehicle deceleration detected by the first deceleration detector and the
velocity change amount, each of the severity determination maps representing a
threshold pattern consisting of threshold values with which the vehicle deceleration is
compared so as to determine severity of the collision of the vehicle, and (e) a problem
detecting unit that generates a problem detection signal that indicates that a problem
has occurred to the vehicle, when detecting an absence of a signal indicative of the
deceleration transmitted from the second deceleration detector. In the severity
determining system, when the severity determining unit receives the problem
detection signal from the problem detecting unit, the determining unit operates in a
predetermined fail-safe mode for selecting an appropriate one of the two or more
severity determination maps, and determines severity of the collision of the vehicle,
based on the selected severity determination map.</p>
    <p num="0010">With the collision severity determining system constructed as
described above, the problem detecting unit detects an abnormality in transmission of
a signal indicative of the deceleration from the second deceleration detector, and the
severity determining unit operates in the fail-safe mode to determine severity of the
vehicle collision. In this manner, the collision severity can be determined in a
desirable manner even when a problem has occurred to the second deceleration
detector. </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0011">The foregoing and/or further objects, features and advantages of the
invention will become more apparent from the following description of preferred
embodiments with reference to the accompanying drawings, in which like numerals
are used to represent like elements and wherein:
<sl><li>FIG. 1 is a view showing a hardware configuration of a severity determining
system according to one exemplary embodiment of the invention, used with an
occupant protection device;</li><li>FIG. 2 is a view showing a motor vehicle in which the severity determining
system shown in FIG. 1 is installed;</li><li>FIG. 3 is a functional block diagram schematically showing the configuration
of the severity determining system shown in FIG. 1;</li><li>FIG. 4 is a graph showing examples of severity determination maps stored in a
severity determining unit of the system of FIG. 3;</li><li>FIG. 5 is a graph showing data obtained from a vehicle at the time of different
types of collisions thereof;</li><li>FIG. 6 is a graph showing relationships between time T as measured from the
beginning of a collision and a velocity change amount VG;</li><li>FIG. 7 is a table summarizing selection of low and high maps in a fail-safe
mode;</li><li>FIG. 8 is a view showing a shift of an operating mode of the severity
determining system from a normal mode to a fail-safe mode; and</li><li>FIG. 9 is a view showing a control routine executed by the severity
determining system of one exemplary embodiment for making a severity
determination in the fail-safe mode.</li></sl></p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0012">FIG. 1 schematically illustrates a hardware configuration of a
collision severity determining system 20 according to one exemplary embodiment of
the invention when it is used with an occupant protection device. In FIG. 1, an airbag
device 50 is illustrated as a typical example of the occupant protection device.
According to this embodiment of the invention, an airbag 52 stored in the airbag
device 50 is adapted to deploy at a high power level or at a low power level according 
to a result of determination (i.e., the severity of a collision) obtained by the severity
determining system 20.</p>
    <p num="0013">In addition to the severity determining system 20 of the embodiment,
there is provided an activation device (not shown) that determines whether the airbag
device 50 should be activated. If the activation device determines the airbag device
50 should be activated, the airbag is activated to deploy at a high or low power level
according to the collusion severity determined by the severity determining system 20
as described above.</p>
    <p num="0014">FIG. 2 illustrates the severity determining system 20 when it is
installed on a motor vehicle 10. FIG. 3 is a block diagram schematically illustrating a
functional arrangement of the severity determining system 20.</p>
    <p num="0015">As shown in FIG. 1 and FIG. 2, the severity determining system 20
of the embodiment includes a floor sensor 22 disposed in the vicinity of a console box
mounted in a central portion of the vehicle 10, and a left front sensor 24 and a right
front sensor 26 mounted on front portions of respective side members of the vehicle
10. The floor sensor 22 serves to detect a vehicle deceleration (hereinafter referred to
as "floor G"), and the left and right front sensors 24, 26 serve to detect vehicle
decelerations (hereinafter referred to as "front LG" and "front RG") in the
longitudinal direction (i.e., the running direction) of the vehicle 10. Here, instead of
those front sensors 24 and 26, one front sensor may be disposed at the center of the
front portion of the vehicle 10.</p>
    <p num="0016">The severity determining system 20 of the embodiment has a
predetermined fail-safe mode in which collision severity is determined when the left
front sensor 24 or the right front sensor 26, in particular, has any problem, such as a
failure or breakdown of the sensor. When the left and right front sensors 24, 26
operate normally, on the other hand, the severity determining system 20 determines
collision severity in a normal mode, as described later.</p>
    <p num="0017">Referring first to Fig. 1, the construction of the severity determining
system 20 will be described in detail. The severity determining system 20 of the
embodiment includes a microcomputer 40, which has a function of determining the
severity of a collision of a vehicle based on the floor G detected by the floor sensor 22
and the front LG and RG detected by the front sensors 24 and 26. The microcomputer
40 includes a CPU 42 as its central component, and further includes a ROM 44 
storing operation programs, a RAM 46 capable of temporarily storing data, and an
input/output (I/O) circuit 48.</p>
    <p num="0018">For example, the CPU 42 is arranged to start sampling of a signal
from the floor sensor 22 at a predetermined frequency (e.g., 2kHz) after the floor
sensor 22 detects a predetermined value of the floor G. Then, when at least one of the
front LG and RG, detected by the front sensors 24 and 26, becomes greater than a
predetermined threshold value, the microcomputer 40 senses a possibility of a vehicle
collision, and proceeds to perform a predetermined control operation. Furthermore,
the microcomputer 40 determines whether a vehicle collision is occurring (i.e., the
vehicle is in collision with an object) based on the front LG and RG detected by the
front sensors 24 and 26, and determines the collision severity based on the floor G
detected by the floor sensor 22 while referring to the detected front LG and RG. A
functional arrangement of the microcomputer 40 will be apparent from the functional
block diagram of FIG. 3 showing the severity determining system 20.</p>
    <p num="0019">Next, an operation of the severity determining system 20 will
hereinafter be described with reference to the functional block diagram of FIG. 3. As
shown in FIG. 3, a determining unit 30 of the system 20 receives, via a signal input
unit 28, a signal indicative of the floor G detected by the floor sensor 22 and signals
indicative of the front LG and RG detected by the front sensors 24 and 26, at a
predetermined sampling frequency.</p>
    <p num="0020">When at least one of the front LG and RG detected by the front
sensors 24, 26 becomes greater than the predetermined threshold value, the
determining unit 30 assumes a vehicle collision and starts a preparatory operation for
severity determination. The determination unit 30 includes a velocity change amount
calculating unit 32 for calculating a velocity change amount VG which is obtained by
integrating the floor G with respect to time, and a severity determining unit 36 that
determines collision severity according to the floor G and velocity change amount VG
in the event of a collision. The velocity change amount calculating unit 32 calculates
the velocity change amount VG associated with the floor G, according to an
expression (1) shown below. By integrating the floor G to obtain the velocity change
amount VG, noises can be removed, thus permitting more desirable severity
determination.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">VG = ∫G (t) dt</st32:df> 
The severity determining unit 36 incorporates a severity determination map as
shown in FIG. 4, in which the vertical axis represents the floor G and the horizontal
axis represents the velocity change amount VG. Using this severity determination
map, the severity determining unit 36 determines collision severity based on the floor
G detected by the floor sensor 22. Then, the power level of the airbag device 50 for
inflating the airbag 52 is determined based on the result of severity determination.</p>
    <p num="0021">The severity determination map as shown in FIG. 4 includes two
different threshold patterns STH-H and STH-L which will be explained below. Each
threshold pattern STH-H, STH-L represents thresholds or reference values for
determining whether the collision severity is at a high level or at a low level. Namely,
the severity is determined as being at a high level (i.e., high severity) if a point
determined by the floor G and the velocity change amount VG is located above the
selected threshold pattern, and is determined as being at a low level (i.e., low severity)
if a point determined by the floor G and the velocity change amount VG is located
below the selected threshold pattern. Thus, even with substantially the same value of
the floor G detected upon collisions, the severity may be determined as HIGH, which
requires the airbag 52 to deploy at a high power level, or may be determined as LOW,
which requires the airbag 52 to deploy at a low power level, depending upon the mode
of the vehicle collision.</p>
    <p num="0022">Thus, the severity determination map used in the embodiment
includes a HIGH map in which the threshold values STH are set relatively high
(pattern STH-H), and a LOW map in which the threshold values STH are set
relatively low (pattern STH-L). When the vehicle undergoes an offset collision, or
the like, at a high speed, which normally causes a great impact to the occupant, it is
preferable that the collision severity be likely to be determined as being HIGH even
with a relatively small floor G, and therefore the LOW map is used for the severity
determination. Conversely, when the vehicle undergoes a head-on collision, or the
like, at a low speed, which normally causes a relatively small impact to the occupant,
it is preferable that the collision severity be likely to be determined as being LOW,
and therefore the HIGH map is used for the severity determination.</p>
    <p num="0023">The determination as to whether the LOW map or HIGH map is used
is made according to the mode of the vehicle collision, referring to the front LG and
RG detected by the front sensors 24, 26. The threshold pattern STH-H in the HIGH
map and the threshold pattern STH-L in the LOW map are respectively predetermined 
for each vehicle model, based on data obtained in collision tests, virtual simulations,
and the like.</p>
    <p num="0024">If the front LG, RG are normally detected by the front sensors 24, 26
and signals indicative of the front LG, RG are normally transmitted to the severity
determining system 20, the collision severity can be determined with reference to the
detected front LG, RG. In some cases, however, the detection signals are not
transmitted from the front sensors 24, 26 because of a certain problem or abnormality.
Hence, the severity determining system 20 of the embodiment has a function of
performing severity determination even in the case where no detection signal is
transmitted from the front sensors 24, 26.</p>
    <p num="0025">In view of the above situation, the determining unit 30 of the severity
determining system 20 includes a problem detecting unit 34. The problem detecting
unit 34 monitors the front LG and RG transmitted from the front sensors 24 and 26 at
certain intervals, and determines occurrence of a problem when no signal indicative of
the front LG and RG is detected. Here, the "problem" is to be interpreted to include,
for example, the cases where the front sensor(s) 24, 26 fails during normal use, which
is an extremely rare occasion, where the front sensor(s) 24 and 26 is/are broken down
due to a collision of the vehicle, and where a communication cable or cables leading
to the signal input unit 28 is/are disconnected. The problem detecting unit 34
recognizes the type of the problem as described above, and sends a problem detection
signal that includes the type of the problem thus recognized, to the severity
determining unit 36.</p>
    <p num="0026">A predetermined fail-safe mode is set in advance in the severity
determining unit 36, and is implemented when the unit 36 receives a problem
detection signal from the problem detecting unit 34. In the fail-safe mode, the
severity determination is made depending upon the type of the problem of the front
sensor(s) 24, 26 included in the problem detection signal from the problem detecting
unit 34. In a fail-safe operation performed when the front sensor(s) 24, 26 is/are
faulty, the LOW map as shown in FIG. 4 is used for determining the collision
severity. In a fail-safe operation performed in the cases where the front sensor(s) 24,
26 is/are broken down due to a collision of the vehicle and where a communication
cable connected to the signal input unit 28 is cut off (which cases will be generally
referred to as "breakdown of the front sensor(s) 24, 26"), the severity determining unit
36 selects one of the LOW map and the HIGH map, based on the velocity change 
amount VG measured a predetermined time Tm after no signal indicative of the front
LG and RG is detected, and determine the collision severity with reference to the
selected map.</p>
    <p num="0027">Hereinafter, the manner of selecting the LOW map or the HIGH map
in the above-described fail-safe mode implemented depending upon the type of the
problem will be described.</p>
    <p num="0028">A failure of the front sensor(s) 24, 26, which is an extremely rare
case, can be recognized or confirmed by the problem detecting unit 34 which
regularly monitors output signals from the front sensors 24 and 26. When a failure of
the front sensor(s) 24, 26 is detected, a certain warning may be given to the occupant
by means of an alert lamp or the like so that the occupant will have the vehicle
repaired immediately, thus eliminating the problem of the failure of the front sensor(s)
24, 26. However, there is a possibility that the vehicle runs into a traffic accident
before the front sensors 24, 26 are repaired. In this case, it is desirable to set the
severity determination mode so that the airbag system 50 can deal with a high-speed
collision, or the like, that causes a great impact to the occupant.</p>
    <p num="0029">In the present embodiment, therefore, when the problem arises from
a failure of the front sensor(s) 24, 26, the severity determining unit 36 selects the
LOW map for determining the collision severity.</p>
    <p num="0030">In the case where the front sensor(s) 24, 26, or the like, is broken
down due to a collision of the vehicle, an intensity of impact to the occupant varies
depending on a collision mode. In the graph of FIG. 5, the vertical axis represents the
front LG (or RG) (m/s<sup>2</sup>) detected by the front sensor 24 (or 26) and the horizontal axis
represents the velocity change amount VG (m/s) obtained by integrating the floor G
with respect to time. FIG. 5 shows data detected in the case (high-speed OBD) where
the vehicle undergoes a high-speed offset collision with a relatively soft obstacle, and
the case where the vehicle undergoes a low-speed head-on collision. In the case of
the high-speed offset collision, the front LG (or RG) reaches a peak when the
velocity change amount VG is still small. Thus, the high-speed offset collision is one
of collision modes in which a large impact tends to be applied to the occupant, and
therefore the severity determination is made using the LOW map so that the severity
is more likely to be determined as being HIGH.</p>
    <p num="0031">In the case of the low-speed head-on collision, on the other hand, the
front LG (or RG) gradually changes as the velocity change amount VG increases, and 
assumes a relatively high value at its peak in the later stage of the collision, though
the peak value is still much lower than that of the high-speed offset collision. The
low-speed head-on collision represented in the graph is one of collision modes in
which a small impact tends to be applied to the occupant, and therefore the severity
determination is made using the HIGH map so that the severity is more likely to be
determined as being LOW.</p>
    <p num="0032">A broken line in FIG. 5 represents a boundary line based on which
one of the HIGH map and the LOW map is selected. Namely, a collision that shows a
relatively high front LG (or RG) in the initial stage of the collision (on the left-hand
side of the boundary line) may be determined as a collision mode in which the
severity determination is made using the LOW map so that the severity is more likely
to be determined as being HIGH. To the contrary, a collision that shows a relatively
high front LG (or RG) in the later stage of the collision (on the right-hand side of the
boundary line) may be determined as a collision mode in which the severity
determination is made using the HIGH map so that the severity is more likely to be
determined as being LOW.</p>
    <p num="0033">The above-described breakdown of the front sensor(s) 24, 26 or its
peripheral wiring due to a vehicle collision is supposed to occur when the front LG
(RG) reaches its peak. The graph in FIG. 6 shows a relationship between time T
measured from a point of time when the vehicle collides with an object, and the
velocity change amount VG. As shown in the graph, in the case of the high-speed
offset collision, the front sensor 24, 26 or the like tends to break down (become
inoperative) before the velocity change amount VG increases to a certain level. In
this case, therefore, the detected velocity change amount VG is kept at a relatively
low value. In the case of the low-speed head-on collision, on the other hand, the front
sensor 24, 26 or the like tends to break down after the velocity change amount VG
exceeds a certain level. In this case, the detected velocity change amount VG has a
higher value than that in the case of the high-speed offset collision.</p>
    <p num="0034">In view of the above tendencies, a certain reference value KTH is set
between the low value and the high value of the velocity change amount VG as
described above. If the detected velocity change amount VG is larger than the
reference value KTH, the collision in question is determined as one of collision
modes in which the severity determination is made using the HIGH map so that the
severity is more likely to be determined as being LOW. If the detected velocity 
change amount VG does not exceed the reference value KTH, on the other hand, the
collision in question is determined as one of collision modes in which the severity
determination is made using the LOW map so that the severity is more likely to be
determined as being HIGH.</p>
    <p num="0035">The table of FIG. 7 summarizes selection of the HIGH map or the
LOW map by the severity determining unit 36 in the fail-safe mode.</p>
    <p num="0036">In order to achieve desired occupant protection, much care is
desirably taken to determine whether the severity determining unit 36 is brought into
the fail-safe mode that is implemented when the front sensor 24, 26, or the like,
breaks down due to a collision.</p>
    <p num="0037">For example, the fail-safe mode may be established by mistake when
the transmission of the front LG or RG is interrupted due to noise on communication
lines, or other factors. In the embodiment of the invention, therefore, the problem
detecting unit 34 does not immediately transmit a problem detection signal indicating
breakdown of the front sensor 24, 26, or the like, to the severity determining unit 36,
when no signal indicative of the front LG, RG is transmitted from the front sensors
24, 26 in a normal mode, as shown in Fig. 8. Rather, the problem (i.e., no
transmission of the front LG or RG) is judged as being caused by breakdown of the
front sensor 24, 26 when a predetermined time Tm elapses after the transmission of
the front LG or RG is stopped. Thus, the severity determining unit 36 is brought into
the fail-safe mode upon a lapse of the predetermined time Tm. By waiting for the
predetermined time Tm before entering the fail-safe mode, the severity determining
unit 36 is prevented from being brought into the fail-safe mode by mistake when the
transmission of the front LG or RG is temporarily stopped due to noise, or any other
reason.</p>
    <p num="0038">Upon entering the fail-safe mode, the severity determining unit 36
determines which of the LOW map and the HIGH map is used, depending upon
whether the velocity change amount VG detected at this time is higher or lower a
reference value KTH similar to that of FIG. 6. The reference value KTH is
predetermined for each vehicle based on data obtained in collision tests, virtual
simulations, and the like.</p>
    <p num="0039">As described above, even when a problem occurs to the front sensor
24 or 26, the severity determining system 20 operates in the fail-safe mode, and
determines the collision severity with high accuracy according to the severity 
determination map as shown in FIG. 4, which map involves the floor G and velocity
change amount VG. In particular, when the front sensor 24 or 26 breaks down or
becomes inoperative because of a collision of the vehicle, one of the LOW map and
HIGH map is appropriately selected, using the reference value KTH and the velocity
change amount VG. Accordingly, as shown in FIG. 4, the severity determination is
performed using the LOW map in the case of a high-speed offset collision (ODB) in
which it is preferable to determine the severity as being HIGH. In the case of a low-speed
head-on collision in which it is preferable to determine the severity as being
LOW, on the other hand, the severity determination is performed using the HIGH
map.</p>
    <p num="0040">As described above, the severity determining system 20 of the
embodiment as shown in FIG. 1 is used with the airbag device 50 as an occupant
protection device. Hereinafter, the structure of the airbag device 50 will be briefly
described. The airbag device 50 includes an airbag 52, two inflaters 54 that supply
gas to the airbag 52, two firing devices 56 which fire a gas generating agent (not
shown in FIG. 1), and two drive circuits 58 that supply electric current to the
respective firing devices 56 to fire the gas generating agent in response to a severity
determination signal from the microcomputer 40. With the two inflaters 54 thus
provided, the airbag 52 can be rapidly deployed at a high power level when both of
the inflaters 54 are actuated simultaneously, and can also be deployed at a low power
level when the two inflaters 54 are actuated at different points of time. In this
embodiment, the airbag 52 is deployed at a high power level when the severity
determining system 20 determines the collision severity as HIGH, and is deployed at a
low power level when the severity determining system 20 determines the collision
severity as LOW. According to the embodiment of the invention, even upon
occurrence of a problem that makes it impossible to detect a signal indicative of the
front LG or RG from the front sensor 24 or 26, the severity determining system 20
operates in the fail-safe mode so as to enable deployment of the airbag device 50 that
is favorable or advantageous to the occupant. Thus, the severity determining system
20 of the embodiment constantly achieves desired occupant protection with high
reliability.</p>
    <p num="0041">FIG. 9 shows a control routine for determining collision severity
when the severity determining system 20 of the present embodiment operates in a fail-safe 
mode, which is established when no signal is transmitted from the front sensor 24
and/or front sensor 26.</p>
    <p num="0042">The severity determination routine of FIG. 9 is implemented by the
microcomputer 40 as shown in FIG. 1. First, the problem detecting unit 34
determines in step S100 whether no signal indicative of the front LG or RG is
transmitted from the front sensors 24, 26. If no signal transmission is detected in step
S100, the problem detecting unit 34 then determines in step S102 whether the
problem arises from a failure of the front sensor(s) 24, 26 or from breakdown of the
front sensor(s) 24, 26, or the like, which is caused by the vehicle collision. If a failure
of the front sensor(s) 24, 26 is determined in step S102, the HIGH map is used for
determining collision severity in step S108, so that the severity is more likely to be
determined as being LOW. After executing step S108, the routine of FIG. 9 is
finished.</p>
    <p num="0043">If no failure of the front sensors 24, 26 is detected in step S102, on
the other hand, step S104 is executed, assuming that a vehicle collision has occurred,
to determine whether the predetermined time Tm has elapsed since the front LG or
RG became unable to be detected. When step S104 determines that the time Tm has
elapsed, the vehicle is determined as being in a collision state, and step S106 is
executed to determine whether the current velocity change amount VG of the vehicle
is greater than the predetermined reference value KTH. If the velocity change amount
VG is determined as being greater than the reference value KTH in step S106, the
severity determination is performed in step S108 using the HIGH map so that the
severity is more likely to be determined as LOW, and thereafter the routine is
finished. Conversely, if the velocity change amount VG is determined as not greater
than the reference value KTH in step S106, the severity determination is performed in
step S110 using the LOW map so that the severity is likely to be determined as HIGH,
and thereafter the routine is finished.</p>
    <p num="0044">In the embodiment as described above, the microcomputer 40 is
adapted to perform overall control of the severity determining system 20, including
control in the fail-safe mode. The invention, however, is not limited to this
arrangement. For example, an ECU (electronic control unit) may be provided at a
certain position within the vehicle 10 as shown in Fig. 2, for regularly monitoring the
operating states of the front sensors 24 and 26, as well as the engine, brake system and
the like, so as to operate the severity determining system 20 in the fail-safe mode as 
described above upon occurrence of a problem. In this case, the microcomputer 40
may be constructed as a part of the ECU.</p>
    <p num="0045">In the illustrated embodiment, the severity determining system 20 is
applied to the airbag device 50 which is employed as the occupant protection device.
However, the severity determining system of the invention may be applied to a
seatbelt pretensioner system serving as an occupant protection device, which
automatically takes up the seatbelt in the event of a collision. Further, the severity
determining device 20 may be applied to both the airbag device and the seatbelt
pretensioner system.</p>
    <p num="0046">While the invention has been described with reference to exemplary
embodiments thereof, it is to be understood that the invention is not limited to the
exemplary embodiments or constructions. To the contrary, the invention is intended
to cover various modifications and equivalent arrangements. In addition, while the
various elements of the exemplary embodiments are shown in various combinations
and configurations, which are exemplary, other combinations and configurations,
including more, less or only a single element, are also within the spirit and scope of
the invention.</p>
    <p num="0047">A collision severity determining system for determining severity of a collision
of a vehicle includes a first deceleration detector disposed in a central portion of a
vehicle body for detecting a vehicle deceleration in a longitudinal direction of the
vehicle, and a second deceleration detector disposed in a front portion of the vehicle
for detecting a deceleration in the longitudinal direction. A controller of the system
calculates a velocity change amount of the vehicle by integrating the vehicle
deceleration with respect to time, and determines severity of the vehicle collision by
comparing the vehicle deceleration with a threshold value corresponding to the same
velocity change amount. When a problem, such as a failure or breakdown of the
second deceleration detector, occurs, the severity determining unit operates in a
predetermined fail-safe mode for selecting an appropriate one of severity
determination maps stored in the controller, and makes a severity determination based
on the selected severity determination map.

Selected Figure: FIG. 3</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A collision severity determining system for determining severity of a
collision of a vehicle, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a first deceleration detector disposed substantially in a central portion of a
body of the vehicle so as to detect a vehicle deceleration in a longitudinal direction of
the vehicle;</claim-text><claim-text>a second deceleration detector disposed in a front portion of the vehicle that is
located ahead of the first deceleration detector, so as to detect a deceleration at the
front portion in the longitudinal direction of the vehicle;</claim-text><claim-text>a velocity change amount calculating unit that calculates a velocity change
amount of the vehicle by integrating the vehicle deceleration detected by the first
deceleration detector with respect to time;</claim-text><claim-text>a severity determining unit storing two or more severity determination maps
defined by the vehicle deceleration detected by the first deceleration detector and the
velocity change amount, each of the severity determination maps representing a
threshold pattern consisting of threshold values with which the vehicle deceleration is
compared so as to determine severity of the collision of the vehicle; and</claim-text><claim-text>a problem detecting unit that generates a problem detection signal that
indicates that a problem has occurred to the vehicle, when detecting an absence of a
signal indicative of the deceleration transmitted from the second deceleration detector,</claim-text></claim-text>
wherein
   when receiving the problem detection signal from the problem detecting unit,
the severity determining unit operates in a predetermined fail-safe mode for selecting
an appropriate one of the two or more severity determination maps, and determines
severity of the collision of the vehicle, based on the selected severity determination
map.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A severity determination system according to claim 1, wherein:
<claim-text><claim-text>when receiving no problem detection signal from the problem detecting unit,
the severity determining unit determines severity of the collision of the vehicle, by
using one of the two or more severity determination maps that is selected based on the
deceleration detected by the second deceleration detector.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A severity determination system according to claim 1 or 2, wherein the
severity determining unit determines the severity as being at a low level when the
vehicle deceleration is not greater than a corresponding threshold value on the
threshold pattern of the selected severity determination map, and determines the
severity as being at a high level when the vehicle deceleration is greater than a
corresponding threshold value on the threshold pattern of the selected severity
determination map.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A severity determination system according to claim 3, wherein the two or
more severity determination maps comprises a high map representing a first threshold
pattern, and a low map representing a second threshold pattern having threshold
values that are lower than those of the first threshold pattern.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A severity determination system according to claim 4, wherein the
predetermined fail-safe mode of the severity determining unit is established when a
problem based on a failure of the second deceleration detector is detected, and
wherein the severity determining unit makes a collision severity determination by
using the low map in the case of the failure of the second deceleration detector.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A severity determination system according to claim 4, wherein the
predetermined fail-safe mode of the severity determining unit is established when a
problem based on a breakdown of the second deceleration detector or a peripheral
portion thereof due to the vehicle collision is detected, and wherein the severity
determining unit selects one of the low map and the high map based on the velocity
change amount obtained upon a lapse of a predetermined time after transmission of
the signal indicative of the deceleration is stopped, and makes a collision severity
determination by using the selected one of the low map and the high map.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A severity determination system according to claim 6, wherein the severity
determining unit selects the low map for use in severity determination when the
velocity change amount obtained upon the lapse of the predetermined time is smaller
than a predetermined reference value, and selects the high map when the velocity
change amount is larger than the predetermined reference value.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>An apparatus comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>an occupant protection device that protects an occupant of a vehicle against a
collision, the occupant protection device having at least two power levels; and</claim-text><claim-text>a collision severity determining system that determines severity of the
collision of the vehicle, which comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) a first deceleration detector disposed substantially in a central
portion of a body of the vehicle so as to detect a vehicle deceleration in a longitudinal
direction of the vehicle;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) a second deceleration detector disposed in a front portion of the
vehicle that is located ahead of the first deceleration detector, so as to detect a
deceleration at the front portion in the longitudinal direction of the vehicle;</claim-text><claim-text>(c) a velocity change amount calculating unit that calculates a
velocity change amount of the vehicle by integrating the vehicle deceleration detected
by the first deceleration detector with respect to time;</claim-text><claim-text>(d) a severity determining unit storing two or more severity
determination maps defined by the vehicle deceleration detected by the first
deceleration detector and the velocity change amount, each of the severity
determination maps representing a threshold pattern consisting of threshold values
with which the vehicle deceleration is compared so as to determine severity of the
collision of the vehicle; and</claim-text><claim-text>(e) a problem detecting unit that generates a problem detection signal
that indicates that a problem has occurred to the vehicle, when detecting an absence of
a signal indicative of the deceleration transmitted from the second deceleration
detector, wherein, when receiving the problem detection signal from the problem
detecting unit, the severity determining unit operates in a predetermined fail-safe
mode for selecting an appropriate one of the two or more severity determination
maps, and determines severity of the collision of the vehicle, based on the selected
severity determination map,</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the occupant protection device is activated with one of the at least two
power levels that is selected based on a result of severity determination of the
collision severity determining system.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
