<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1252976-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1252976" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="9913156" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021030">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1252976-A1" status="new" fvid="23588091">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1252976</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20021030</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02252703-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02252703</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020417</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="GB-0109747-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>GB</country>
          <doc-number>0109747</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010420</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B25D  17/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B25D  17/20        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B25D  17/24        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B25D  17/24</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Schlaghammer mit Schwingungsdämpfer</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Percussion hammer with vibration damping mechanism</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Marteau à percussion avec amortisseur de vibrations</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>BLACK &amp; DECKER INC</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>BLACK &amp; DECKER INC.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Black &amp;amp; Decker Inc.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Drummond Plaza Office Park 1423 Kirkwood Highway</street>
              <city>Newark Delaware 19711</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>BECHT REIMUND</name>
            <address>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>FAATZ HEINZ-WERNER</name>
            <address>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GENSMANN STEFAN D</name>
            <address>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HANKE ANDREAS</name>
            <address>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>PLIETSCH REINHARD</name>
            <address>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>BECHT, REIMUND</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>FAATZ, HEINZ-WERNER</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GENSMANN, STEFAN D.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HANKE, ANDREAS</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>PLIETSCH, REINHARD</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>BECHT, REIMUND</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Gerhard-Von-Dietz Strasse 13</street>
              <city>65597 H-hnfelden 1</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>FAATZ, HEINZ-WERNER</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Buchenbuschweg 20</street>
              <city>61389 Schmitten</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>GENSMANN, STEFAN D.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>In Den Wiesen 4</street>
              <city>56132 Fr-cht</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>HANKE, ANDREAS</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Sonnering 1</street>
              <city>65520 Bad Camberg</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>PLIETSCH, REINHARD</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Schubertstrasse 3</street>
              <city>65611 Brechen</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Bell, Ian Stephen</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Black &amp;amp; Decker, Patent Department 210 Bath Road</street>
              <city>Slough, Berkshire SL1 3YD</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A hand held electrically powered hammer, comprising a housing (4, 5) within
which is located a motor (2), a hollow spindle (40) within which is located for
reciprocation therein a piston (38) and forwardly of the piston a ram (58) and a metal
casing (42) which encloses at least part of the spindle (40) so as to form an air filled
chamber between the spindle and the casing. A hammer drive arrangement (30, 32,
34) is provided which converts the rotary drive of the motor to a reciprocating drive to
the piston and a tool holder body (66) is located at the forward end of the spindle in
which a tool or bit (68) may be releasably mounted for limited reciprocation. The
reciprocation of the piston is arranged to rcciprocatingly drive the ram via a closed air
cushion such that repeated impacts from the ram are transmitted to a tool or bit
mounted in the tool holder body. The hammer additionally comprises a damping
mass (70) which is located within the chamber which damping mass is connected to
the hammer housing (4, 5) via at least one spring element (90, 98) so as to oscillate
back and forth along the spindle to minimise the vibration of the hammer housing. At
least one spacer element (72a, b) is provided for positioning the damping mass (70)
with respect to the spindle (40) and the metal casing (42) so that a small gap is present
between the mass and the spindle and a small gap is present between the mass and the
casing such that oscillation of the damping mass within the chamber generates air
turbulence within the chamber for facilitating heat transfer from the spindle to the
metal casing. Thus, the damping mass has the dual function of vibration damping and
spindle cooling.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="78" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="55"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">This invention relates to hand held electrically powered hammers, and in
particular to demolition hammers.</p>
    <p num="0002">Such hammers generally comprise a housing within which is located an
electric motor and a gear arrangement for converting the rotary drive of the motor to a
reciprocating drive to drive a piston within a hollow spindle, which spindle is located
within the hammer housing. The spindle may be formed from a single part or from
more than one part, for example from a rearward hollow cylinder, within which a
piston and ram reciprocate and a forward cylindrical tool holder body, within which a
tool or bit may be releasably mounted. A ram is located in front of the piston within
the spindle so as, in normal operating conditions, to form a closed air cushion within
the spindle between the piston and the ram. The reciprocation of the piston
reciprocatingly drives the ram via the air cushion. A beatpiece is generally located
within the spindle and transmits repeated impacts that it receives from the ram to a
tool or bit releaseably mounted for limited reciprocation in front of the beatpiece in a
tool holder portion of the spindle. The impacts on the tool or bit are transmitted to a
workpiece against which the tool or bit is pressed in order to break up or make a bore
in the workpiece.</p>
    <p num="0003">Some hammers may also be employed in combination impact and drilling
mode in which the spindle, and hence the bit inserted therein, will be caused to rotate
at the same time as the bit is struck by the beatpiece. The present invention is also
applicable to such hammers.</p>
    <p num="0004">One problem with such hammers is that the reciprocating parts and repeated
impacts between the parts cause large vibrations to be transmitted via the handles of
the hammer to the user. This is uncomfortable for the user, particularly over
prolonged periods of use and can contravene safety standards. </p>
    <p num="0005">This problem has been solved in the past by forming a vibration damping
linkage between the handles of the hammer and the main housing of the hammer.
However, the linkages have to be rigid enough for the handles to guide the hammer
while also providing damping. Also, the user of the hammer tensions the linkage
when the hammer is urged against a workpiece and this changes the damping effect of
the linkage. This means that such linkages tend to be relatively complex.</p>
    <p num="0006">This problem has also been solved for a pneumatic hammer, for example as
disclosed in DE815,179 by mounting masses on opposing sides of the spindle, with
each mass mounted between two springs so that each of the masses can oscillate
parallel to the axis of the spindle due to the forces from the two springs. The masses
oscillate in phase and in the same direction as the ram and are arranged to oscillate as
near to resonance as possible. However, this gives rise to the problem of
synchronising movement of the masses. If the masses are not exactly synchronised
then a torque at right angles to the direction of mass vibration is generated which is
transmitted to the user of the hammer via the hammer housing. This problem has
been addressed in DE31 22 979 which describes an electrically powered hammer to
which a dampening housing is attached. The dampening housing comprises two
moveable masses each connected to a compression spring. The channels in which the
masses are located are interconnected so that generation of an over pressure in one
channel results in a corresponding over pressure in the other channel in order to
synchronise movement of the masses. However, the arrangement disclosed in DE31
22 979 is relatively complex and takes up a lot of space.</p>
    <p num="0007">The problem of synchronising masses can also be overcome for a pneumatic
hammer by using a single mass as described in DE24 03 074 in which there is
described a hammer housing which is enclosed by a handle housing. Around the
hammer housing is located a cylindrical mass which is able to reciprocate along the
hammer housing on the end of a coil spring. Optimum vibration reduction is achieved
if the spring constant of the coil spring is adapted to the beat frequency of the
hammer. </p>
    <p num="0008">A second problem is that the reciprocating parts and repeated impacts cause
heat generation within the hammer and some means is required to transfer the
generated heat away from the spindle and the parts within the spindle. If the parts
within the spindle are operating at high temperatures then they are more prone to wear
and eventually to failure. In particular any seals between the piston and the spindle
and the ram and the spindle are susceptible to damage at higher temperatures.
Hammers are generally operated in very dusty environments and it is critical to the
prolonged operation of the hammer that there is no dust ingress into the spindle. As
there are several ports in the spindle through which air can flow into and out of the
spindle, cooling of the spindle using air flows can easily introduce dust into the
spindle. Therefore, cooling of the spindle is generally achieved by passive heat
transfer from the metal spindle either via air pockets or directly to metal housing parts
surrounding the spindle. However, the cooling achieved by such passive heat transfer
is relatively limited.</p>
    <p num="0009">The present invention aims to overcome the problems discussed above by
providing a system which both reduces the vibration of the hammer housing and cools
the spindle, without taking up much space within the hammer housing.</p>
    <p num="0010">According to the present invention there is provided a hand held electrically
powered hammer, comprising a housing within which is located:
<sl><li>a motor;</li><li>a hollow spindle within which is located for reciprocation therein a piston and
forwardly of the piston a ram;</li><li>a metal casing which encloses at least part of the spindle so as to form an air
filled chamber between the spindle and the casing,</li><li>a hammer drive arrangement which converts the rotary drive of the motor to a
reciprocating drive to the piston;</li><li>a tool holder body located at the forward end of the spindle in which a tool or
bit may be releasably mounted for limited reciprocation; 
arranged such that the reciprocation of the piston reciprocatingly drives the ram via a
closed air cushion such that repeated impacts from the ram are transmitted to a tool or
bit mounted in the tool holder body, characterised in that the hammer additionally
comprises:
<sl><li>a damping mass which is located within the chamber which damping mass is
connected to the hammer housing via at least one spring element so as to oscillate
back and forth along the spindle to minimise the vibration of the hammer housing;
and</li><li>at least one spacer element for positioning the damping mass with respect to
the spindle and the metal casing so that a small gap is present between the mass and
the spindle and a small gap is present between the mass and the casing such that
oscillation of the damping mass within the chamber generates air turbulence within
the chamber for facilitating heat transfer from the spindle to the metal casing.</li></sl></li></sl></p>
    <p num="0011">The use of a damping mass oscillating within a chamber surrounding the
spindle for reducing the vibration of the hammer housing is also used according to the
present invention for generating air turbulence between the spindle and a metal casing
part surrounding the spindle. When the damping mass moves forwardly along the
spindle an overpressure is generated in front of the mass which causes air to flow
rearwardly through the gaps between the mass and the spindle and the mass and the
metal housing. When the damping mass moves rearwardly along the spindle an
overpressure is generated behind the mass which causes air to flow forwardly through
the gaps between the mass and the spindle and the mass and the metal housing. This
air turbulence between the spindle and the metal casing can facilitate a three times
increase in heat transfer away from the spindle as compared to passive heat transfer
via an air pocket in which no turbulence occurs. According to the present invention
the same components are used for the dual purpose of reducing the vibration
transmitted to a user of the tool from the hammer housing and for cooling the spindle
to improve the operation and lifetime of the hammer. </p>
    <p num="0012">The hammer according to the present invention may comprise a beatpiece
located for reciprocation within the spindle between the ram and a tool or bit mounted
within the tool holder body for transferring impacts from the ram to a tool or bit
mounted within the tool holder body. The incorporation of a beatpiece improves the
sealing of the interior of the spindle from the tool holder body through which dust
may enter.</p>
    <p num="0013">For reducing any compensating vibrations due to the oscillation of the
damping mass in a direction which is not parallel to the spindle, the metal casing and
the the damping mass preferably encircle the spindle and the damping mass is
preferably mounted so that it is concentric with the spindle. For a simple calibration
of the mass and the spring or springs to compensate for vibrations in other parts of the
hammer it is preferred that the damping mass comprises a single piece cylinder.
Preferably, the mass is connected to the hammer housing via two springs one located
forwardly of the mass between the mass and a forward housing part and the other
located rearwardly of the mass between the mass and a rearward housing part. It is
further preferred for a simple design in which the oscillating motion of the mass is
easily controlled that the spring or each spring is a coil spring which encircles the
spindle. Preferably, the mass is made of a relatively high density material such as
steel or brass so that the mass does not take up too much space. For optimised
vibration reduction in the hammer housing, the mass and the spring or springs are
preferably arranged so that the mass oscillates back and forth along the spindle out of
phase, preferably approximately 180° out of phase, with the beat frequency of the
other hammer parts.</p>
    <p num="0014">The air turbulence in the chamber preferably includes air flows between the
mass and the spindle and air flows between the mass and the metal casing.</p>
    <p num="0015">The or each spacer element may be formed integrally with the damping mass.
Alternatively, the or each spacer element may comprise a guide arrangement which is
slideably mounted on the spindle. The damping mass may be mounted on such a 
guide arrangement and the guide arrangement may be shaped to form at least one
channel between the damping mass and the spindle through which air can flow.
Preferably, the at least one channel is formed between a radially inward facing part of
the guide arrangement and the outer surface of the spindle. This increases the amount
of air flow over the surface of the cylinder to aid cooling. However, the location of
the channels between a radially inward facing part of the guide arrangement and the
outer surface of the spindle will also reduce the surface area of contact between the
guide arrangement and the spindle and so can reduce the friction generated between
the guide arrangement and the spindle as the guide arrangement slides back and forth
along the spindle, which again facilitates improved cooling of the spindle. In an
especially preferred embodiment in which the damping mass and the magnesium
casing encircle the spindle, the or each guide arrangement is a guide ring, and
preferably two such guide rings are used, one located at either end (forward and
rearward end) of the damping mass. Where the guide arrangement is one or more
guide rings, the channels may be formed between ribs formed on the radially inward
facing surface of the guide ring. The use of such ribs also reduces the surface area of
engagement between the guide ring and the spindle which will reduce the friction
generated as the guide ring slides along the spindle.</p>
    <p num="0016">The hammer according to the present invention may additionally comprise a
fan arrangement for generating an airflow and a labyrinth formed by parts of the
hammer housing for directing the airflow over the outer surface of the metal casing.
Having an airflow over the metal casing, which airflow may be a flow of dusty air
from the environment of the hammer, facilitates heat transfer from the metal casing.
By cooling the metal casing in this way the cooling of the spindle via the turbulent air
in the chamber is further improved. The fan may be rotatingly driven by the motor to
avoid a need for extra means on the hammer for powering the fan. Preferably, the fan
generates an airflow which passes over the motor, through the fan and then through
the labyrinth and over the metal casing before being exhausted from the hammer
housing. Thus, the fan can perform the dual function of cooling the motor and 
cooling the metal casing to facilitate cooling of the spindle. The fan is preferably a
radial fan.</p>
    <p num="0017">The present invention is particularly suited for use in a heavy duty demolition
hammer wherein the hammer drive arrangement comprises a crank arm arrangement.
The more powerful hammers have a higher the requirement for cooling of the spindle.</p>
    <p num="0018">The hammer housing may comprise an inner metal housing arrangement in
which the motor, hammer drive arrangement and at least part of the spindle are
mounted and an outer plastic housing rigidly fixed to the inner metal housing which
outer housing comprises a handle. In this case the metal casing surrounding the
spindle may be rigidly fixed to a forward portion of the inner metal housing
arrangement. Then the damping mass may connected to the hammer via a first
forward spring which extends between the mass and a part of the metal casing and via
a second rearward spring which extends between the mass and a part of the metal
housing arrangement.</p>
    <p num="0019">Preferably the air filled chamber between the spindle and the casing
communicates with at least one other air space formed within the hammer, for
example with the interior of the inner metal housing arrangement and/or with a space
between the ram and the beatpiece. This is important if the chamber surrounds the
vent holes in the spindle through which air must pass to vent the air cushion between
the piston and the ram on entry into idle mode.</p>
    <p num="0020">One form of rotary hammer according to the present invention will now be
described by way of example with reference to the accompanying drawings in which:
<sl><li>Figure 1 shows a partially cutaway longitudinal cross section through a
demolition hammer incorporating a vibration damping and spindle cooling
arrangement according to the present invention; </li><li>Figure 2 shows a partially cutaway enlarged longitudinal cross-section of the
spindle portion of the demolition hammer shown in Figure 1;</li><li>Figure 3 shows a longitudinal cross-sectional view of the damping mass used
in the vibration damping and spindle cooling arrangement of Figures 1 and 2;</li><li>Figure 4a shows a longitudinal cross-section of one of the guide rings for
guiding the damping mass shown in Figure 3;</li><li>Figure 4b shows a perspective view of the guide ring of Figure 4a from the left
hand side of Figure 4a;</li><li>Figure 4c shows a radial cross-section of through a portion of the guide ring of
Figure 4a;</li><li>Figure 5a shows a side view of the guide ring of Figure 4a from the left hand
side of Figure 4a;</li><li>Figure 5a shows a side view of the guide ring of Figure 4a from the right hand
side of Figure 4a;</li><li>Figure 6a shows a longitudinal cross-section through a forward spring holder
for supporting the forward end of a forward spring of the vibration damping and
spindle cooling arrangement of Figures 1 and 2;</li><li>Figure 6b shows a longitudinal cross-section through a rearward spring holder
for supporting the rearward end of a rearward spring of the vibration damping and
spindle cooling arrangement of Figures 1 and 2;</li><li>Figure 7a shows a longitudinal cross-section through the spindle of the
demolition hammer shown in Figures 1 and 2;</li><li>Figure 7b shows a side view of the spindle of the demolition hammer shown in
Figures 1 and 2;</li><li>Figure 8a shows a longitudinal cross-section through a magnesium casing part
which surrounds the spindle and damping mass arrangement of Figures 1 and 2;</li><li>Figure 8b shows a longitudinal cross-section through the magnesium casing of
Figure 8a at 45° to the cross-section shown in Figure 8a; and</li><li>Figure 8c shows a perspective view from the front of the magnesium casing
part of Figures 8a and 8b.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0021">A demolition hammer incorporating a vibration damping and spindle cooling
arrangement according to the present invention is shown in Figures 1 and 2. The
hammer comprises an electric motor (2), a gear arrangement and a piston drive
arrangement which are housed within a metal gear housing (5) surrounded by a plastic
housing (4). A rear handle housing incorporating a rear handle (6) and a trigger
switch arrangement (8) is fitted to the rear of the housings (4, 5). A cable (not shown)
extends through a cable guide (10) and connects the motor to an external electricity
supply. Thus, when the cable is connected to the electricity supply and the trigger
switch arrangement (8) is depressed the motor (2) is actuated to rotationally drive the
armature of the motor. A radial fan (14) is fitted at one end of the armature and a
pinion is formed at the opposite end of the armature so that when the motor is
actuated the armature rotatingly drives the fan (14) and the pinion. The metal gear
housing (5) is made from magnesium with steel inserts and rigidly supports the
components housed within it.</p>
    <p num="0022">The motor pinion rotatingly drives a first gear wheel of an intermediate gear
arrangement which is rotatably mounted on a spindle, which spindle is mounted in an
insert to the gear housing (5). The intermediate gear has a second gear wheel which
rotatingly drives a drive gear . The drive gear is non-rotatably mounted on a drive
spindle which spindle is rotatably mounted within the gear housing (5). A crank plate
(30) is non-rotatably mounted at the end of the drive spindle remote from the drive
gear, which crank-plate is formed with an eccentric bore for housing an eccentric
crank pin (32). The crank pin (32) extends from the crank plate into a bore at the
rearward end of a crank arm (34) so that the crank arm (34) can pivot about the crank
pin (32). The opposite forward end of the crank arm (34) is formed with a bore
through which extends a trunnion pin (36) so that the crank arm (34) can pivot about
the trunnion pin (36). The trunnion pin (36) is fitted to the rear of a piston (38) by
fitting the ends of the trunnion pin (36) into receiving bores formed in a pair of
opposing arms which extend to the rear of the piston (38). The piston is reciprocally
mounted in a cylindrical hollow spindle (40) so that it can reciprocate within the
hollow spindle. An O-ring seal (42) is fitted in an annular recess formed in the 
periphery of the piston (38) so as to form an air tight seal between the piston (38) and
the internal surface of the hollow spindle (40).</p>
    <p num="0023">Thus, when the motor (2) is actuated, the armature pinion rotatingly drives the
intermediate gear arrangement via the first gear wheel and the second gear wheel of
the intermediate gear arrangement rotatingly drives the drive spindle via the drive
gear. The drive spindle rotatingly drives the crank plate (30) and the crank arm
arrangement comprising the crank pin (32), the crank arm (34) and the trunnion pin
(36) convert the rotational drive from the crank plate (30) to a reciprocating drive to
the piston (38). In this way the piston (38) is reciprocatingly driven back and forth
along the hollow spindle (40) when the motor is actuated by a user depressing the
trigger switch (8).</p>
    <p num="0024">The spindle is shown on its own in Figures 7a and 7b. The rearward end of the
spindle (40) in which is located the piston (38) is mounted within a circular recess
formed in the forward end of the gear housing (5). The circular recess is formed with
a plurality of radially inwardly extending ribs (7) which support the rearward end of
the spindle while enabling air to freely circulate between the interior of the gear casing
(5) and a chamber surrounding the spindle (40). The forward end of the spindle (40)
is mounted within a magnesium casing part (42) shown on its own in Figures 8a to 8c.
The rearward end of the magnesium casing (42) is formed with two opposing flanges
(44) in which are formed four bores (46). The bores (46) are formed so as to be
regularly spaced around the periphery of the rear of the magnesium casing (42). The
rearward end of the magnesium casing (42) is fitted over and butted up against a
circular rim extending from the forward end of the gear housing (5) and is then fitted
to the gear housing (5) via four screw bolts (not shown) which pass through the bores
(46) and extend into threaded bores in the gear housing (5).</p>
    <p num="0025">The spindle (40) is mounted in the magnesium housing (42) from the forward
end until an annular rearward facing shoulder (48) on the exterior of the spindle buts
up against a forward facing annular shoulder (50) formed from in set of ribs (51) in 
the interior of the magnesium casing (42). The ribs enable air in the chamber
surrounding the spindle (40) to circulate freely in the region between the ram (58) and
the beatpiece (64). An increased diameter portion (52) on the exterior of the spindle
fits closely within a reduced diameter portion (54) on the interior of the magnesium
casing (42). Rearwardly of the increased diameter portion (52) and the reduced
diameter portion (54) an annular chamber is formed between the external surface of
the spindle (40) and the internal surface of the magnesium casing (42) in which the
vibration reduction and spindle cooling arrangement according to the present
invention is located. This chamber is open at its forward and rearward ends as
described above. At its forward end the chamber communicates via the spaces
between the ribs (51) in the magnesium casing with a volume of air between the ram
(58) and the beatpiece (64). At its rearward end the chamber communicates via the
spaces between the ribs (7) in the recess of the gear casing (5) with a volume of air in
the gear casing (5).</p>
    <p num="0026">The volume of air in the gear casing (5) communicates with the air outside of
the hammer via a narrow channel (9) and a filter (11). Thus, the air pressure within
the hammer, which changes due to changes in the temperature of the hammer, are
equalised with the air pressure outside of the hammer. Also, the filter (11) keeps the
air within the hammer rear casing (5) relatively clean and dust free.</p>
    <p num="0027">A ram (58) is located within the hollow spindle (40) forwardly of the piston
(38) so that it can also reciprocate within the hollow spindle (40). An O-ring seal (60)
is located in a recess formed around the periphery of the ram (58) so as to form an air
tight seal between the ram (58) and the spindle (40). In the operating position of the
ram (58) (shown in the upper half of Figures 1 and 2), with the ram located behind
bores (62) in the spindle a closed air cushion is formed between the forward face of
the piston (38) and the rearward face of the ram (58). Thus, reciprocation of the
piston (38) reciprocatingly drives the ram (58) via the closed air cushion. When the
hammer enters idle mode (ie. when the hammer bit is removed from a workpiece), the
ram (58) moves forwardly, past the bores (62) to the position shown in the bottom half 
of Figures 1 and 2. This vents the air cushion and so the ram (58) is no longer
reciprocatingly driven by the piston (38) in idle mode, as is well known in the art.</p>
    <p num="0028">A beatpiece (64) is guided so that it can reciprocate within a tool holder body
(66) which tool holder body is mounted at the forward end of the magnesium casing
(42). A bit or tool (68) can be releasably mounted within the tool holder body (66) so
that the bit or tool (68) can reciprocate to a limited extent within the tool holder body
(66). When the ram (58) is in its operating mode and is reciprocatingly driven by the
piston (38) the ram repeatedly impacts the rearward end of the beatpiece (64) and the
beatpiece (64) transmits these impacts to the rearward end of the bit or tool (68) as is
known in the art. These impacts are then transmitted by the bit or tool (68) to the
material being worked.</p>
    <p num="0029">When a user of the hammer presses the bit or tool (68) onto a workpiece, the
bit or tool (68) is moved rearwardly in the tool holder body (66) to the position shown
in the upper half in Figures 1 and 2. The bit or tool (68) thus pushes the beatpiece
(64) rearwardly which pushes the ram (58) rearwardly to the positions shown in the
upper half of Figures 1 and 2. This rearward movement of the ram (58) causes the
ram to pass rearwardly over the bores (62) in the spindle (40) to close the air cushion
between the piston (38) and the ram (58). Thus, when the motor (2) is actuated and
the piston reciprocates the ram (58) is reciprocatingly driven to repeatedly impact the
beatpiece (64) and thereby impacts are repeatedly transmitted to the workpiece, via the
beatpiece (64) and the bit or tool (68).</p>
    <p num="0030">When a user removes the tool or bit from the workpiece, the next forward
reciprocation of the piston (38) drives the ram (58) forwardly. As the ram (58) is no
longer pushed rearwardly by the beatpiece (64) it moves forwardly past the bores (62)
in the spindle (40) to vent the air cushion and the next rearward movement of the
piston (38) does not pull the ram (58) rearwardly. Thus, reciprocation of the ram (58),
beatpiece (64) and tool or bit (68) is immediately arrested when the tool or bit (68) is
removed from the workpiece. </p>
    <p num="0031">The vibration damping and spindle cooling arrangement according to the
present invention comprises a cylindrical mass (70) which is supported co-axially
around the spindle (40) on two guide rings (72a, 72b), one of which is shown in more
details in Figures 4a to 5b so that a small annular gap is formed between the radially
inward facing surface of the mass (70) and the radially outward facing surface of the
spindle (40). The radially inward facing surface of each guide ring (72) is formed
with five of axially aligned ribs (74). The ribs (74) fit slideably over the outer surface
of the spindle (40) and provide a relatively low friction mounting for the guide rings
(72) on the outer surface of the spindle (40). The spaces between the ribs (74) form
channels through which air can flow. Each guide ring (72) has a thin annular portion
(76) which extends towards and supports an end of the damping mass (70) and a
thicker annular portion (78) which extends away from the damping mass (70). A
radially outwardly directed annular portion (80) is formed between the thin annular
portion (76) and the thick annular portion (78). Thus, the radially inward facing
surface at the front of the damping mass (70) is supported on the radially outwardly
facing surface of the thin (rearward facing) annular portion (76) of the front guide ring
(72a) and the radially inward facing surface at the rear of the damping mass (70) is
supported on the radially outwardly facing surface on the thin (forward facing)
annular portion (76) of the rear guide ring (72b). In this way the damping mass (70) is
supported, so that it is able to reciprocate back and forth along the spindle (40) in the
annular space between the outer surface of the spindle (40) and the inner surface of
the magnesium casing (42) with a small radial gap of between 0.5mm and the radial
thickness of the damping mass (70) preferably of approximately 2mm, between the
inner surface of the damping mass (70) and the outer surface of the spindle (40) and
with a small radial gap a small radial gap of between 0.5mm and the radial thickness
of the damping mass (70), preferably of approximately 2mm, between the outer
surface of the damping mass (70) and the inner surface of the magnesium casing (42).</p>
    <p num="0032">A forward spring guide (82) which is shown in more detail in Figure 6a is
formed with an L-shaped radial cross section with an annular radially inwardly
extending forward portion (84) and a rearwardly extending annular portion (86). The 
forward end of the forward spring guide (82) abuts a rearwardly facing internal
shoulder (88) formed inside the magnesium casing (42) by the series of ribs (51)
which also form the forwardly facing shoulder (50). A forward spring (90) is
supported between the forward spring guide (82) and the radially outwardly directed
annular portion (80) of the forward ring guide (72a). A rearward spring guide (92)
which is shown in more detail in Figure 6b is formed with an L-shaped radial cross
section with an annular radially inwardly extending rearward portion (94) and a
forwardly extending annular portion (96). The rearward end of the rear spring guide
abuts a part of the gear casing (5) within which the spindle (40) is mounted. A
rearward spring (98) is supported between the rearward spring guide (92) and the
rearward ring guide (72b).</p>
    <p num="0033">In this way the damping mass (70) is located between two springs (90, 98)
which apply opposing biasing forces to the opposite sides of the mass. Accordingly,
in a resting position the damping mass (70) is located at the point where the biasing
forces from the two springs (90, 98) balance.</p>
    <p num="0034">The fan (14) on the end of the armature shaft (12) of the motor (2) is rotatingly
driven when the motor (2) is actuated. When it is rotating the fan (14) draws air
axially into it from the motor housing (5a) through a fan inlet (100) which is formed
in the upper part of the motor housing (5a). The air pulled into the fan is used for
cooling the motor (2). The fan (14) expels air radially outwardly. The air expelled
from the fan is used to cool the magnesium casing (42) and is directed through a
labyrinth formed by various housing part over the outer surface of the gear casing (5)
and over the outer surface of the magnesium casing (42) as shown by the arrows in
Figure 2. An outer housing part (102) is fitted to the front of the plastic housing (4)
and extends around the magnesium casing (42) with an annular gap located between
the inner surface of the outer housing part (102) and the outer surface of the
magnesium casing. The outer housing part (102) is formed with a plurality of air
vents (104) through which air can escape. Thus, the air expelled from the fan (14) is
directed into this annular gap between the magnesium casing (42) and the outer 
housing part (102) and exits the outer housing part (102) via the air vents (104). This
air that passes over the magnesium housing part (42) cools the magnesium housing
part.</p>
    <p num="0035">The purpose of the damping mass (70) between the springs (90, 98) is to
compensate for vibrations of the hammer components so that the resulting vibrations
transmitted to the handle of the hammer which have to be withstood by a user are
minimised. The damping mass compensates for vibrations caused by the
reciprocation of the ram (58) within the spindle (40), the reciprocation of the piston
(38) and the parts driving the piston and the reverse impacts from the workpiece
which pass through the tool or bit (68) via the beatpiece (64) to the magnesium casing
(42). To do this the momentum of the following components have to be taken into
account:
<sl><li>momentum of the ram;</li><li>momentum of the piston and all masses which are fixed to the piston;</li><li>momentum of the housing parts and all masses fixed to the housing parts;</li><li>momentum of the reverse impacts from the workpiece (ie. of the beatpiece);
and</li><li>momentum of the hand arm system, including the load applied by the operator
when urging the bit or tool against a workpiece.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0036">Taking the above factors into account the mass of the damping mass (70) and
the spring constants of the springs (90, 98) are optimised, for example, using
computer modelling to achieve a minimum momentum of the housing at the beat
frequency of the different reciprocating/vibrating components contained in the
housing.</p>
    <p num="0037">In the arrangement shown in Figure 1 the vibration damping mass is made of
brass and has a mass of just less than the mass of the ram, so that the combined mass
of the damping mass (70), the guide rings (72) and the springs (90, 98) is
approximately equal to the mass of the ram. The springs are selected and arranged so 
that the damping mass (70) oscillates with a frequency which matches the beat
frequency of the other components of the hammer. When the hammer is operating,
the mass (70) reciprocates at the beat frequency of around 34Hz and 180° out of phase
with the beat frequency of the other component parts within the hammer housing in
order to minimise the amount of vibration which is transmitted to the hammer
housing. In order to do this the mass (70) is mounted around the spindle (40) between
two springs (90, 98) which act between the gear casing (5) (via the rear spring ring
(92)) and the magnesium casing (42) (via the forward spring ring (82)) which
magnesium casing is rigidly fixed to the gear casing (5).</p>
    <p num="0038">It should be noted that the travel of the damping mass (70), ie. the distance
over which it reciprocates, is also a factor and the greater the travel, the smaller the
mass of the damping mass (70) needs to be in order to provide the required vibration
damping.</p>
    <p num="0039">In addition, due to the small radial gaps between the damping mass (70) and
the spindle (40) and between the damping mass (70) and the magnesium casing (42),
as the damping mass (70) reciprocates in the air filled chamber between the spindle
(40) and magnesium casing (42) air turbulence is created. It should be noted that air is
free to move between the forward end of the front guide ring (72a) and the rearward
end of the rearward guide ring (72b) through the gap between the mass (70) and the
spindle (40) via the spaces between the ribs (74) formed on the radially inward facing
surfaces of the guide rings (72a, 72b). As the damping mass (70) moves forwardly
increased air pressure is created in front of the mass (70) and reduced air pressure is
created to the rear of the mass which causes air in the chamber to move rearwardly
past the mass (70). Then as the damping mass (70) moves rearwardly increased air
pressure is created to the rear of the mass (70) and reduced air pressure is created
forward of the mass which causes air in the chamber to move forwardly past the mass
(70). This air turbulence improves the heat transfer from the metal spindle (40) to the
air in the chamber and from the air in the chamber to the magnesium casing (42).
This heat transfer is further improved due to the airflow over the magnesium casing 
(42) generated by the fan (14) and described above. This provides greatly improved
cooling of the hammer spindle (40).</p>
    <p num="0040">The oscillating damping mass (70), in the Figures, displaces an air volume
equivalent to its cross sectional area of 1359mm<sup>2</sup> multiplied by the stroke length of
the mass, which is estimated to be 20mm. This results in an average (root mean
square) speed for the damping mass (70) of 3m/s. The radial cross-sectional area of
the sum of the air gaps between the mass (70) and the spindle (40) and the mass (70)
and the magnesium casing (42) is 770mm<sup>2</sup>. The speed of the air in the chamber
pumped by the oscillation of the damping mass (70) is assumed equal to 3m/s
multiplied by the ratio of the cross sectional areas of the mass and the gaps, ie.
1359/770 and so is calculated to have an average speed (RMS) of 5.3m/s. The heat
transfer coefficient between air and metallic parts is approximately 6.4 multiplied by
speed of air flow, resulting in a heat transfer between the turbulent air within the
chamber and the surrounding metal parts of 23.5W/K/m<sup>2</sup>. This approximately three
times higher than the heat transfer that occurs under non-turbulent, free convection
conditions.</p>
    <p num="0041">Due to the improved cooling of the spindle (40) which improves the cooling of
the reciprocating and impacting components within the spindle the lifetime of a
hammer according to the present invention is significantly improved. In particular,
the seals (42, 60) surrounding the piston (38) and ram (58) respectively are much less
prone to wear due to the reduction in operating temperatures they are required to
withstand when the present invention is utilised.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A hand held electrically powered hammer, comprising a housing (4, 5) within
which is located:
<claim-text><claim-text>a motor (2);</claim-text><claim-text>a hollow spindle (40) within which is located for reciprocation therein a piston
(38) and forwardly of the piston a ram (58);</claim-text><claim-text>a metal casing (42) which encloses at least part of the spindle (40) so as to
form an air filled chamber between the spindle and the casing,</claim-text><claim-text>a hammer drive arrangement (30, 32, 34) which converts the rotary drive of the
motor to a reciprocating drive to the piston;</claim-text><claim-text>a tool holder body (66) located at the forward end of the spindle in which a
tool or bit (68) may be releasably mounted for limited reciprocation;
arranged such that the reciprocation of the piston reciprocatingly drives the ram via a
closed air cushion such that repeated impacts from the ram are transmitted to a tool or
bit mounted in the tool holder body, characterised in that the hammer additionally
comprises:</claim-text><claim-text>a damping mass (70) which is located within the chamber which damping
mass is connected to the hammer housing (4, 5) via at least one spring element (90,
98) so as to oscillate back and forth along the spindle to minimise the vibration of the
hammer housing; and</claim-text><claim-text>at least one spacer element (72a, b) for positioning the damping mass (70) with
respect to the spindle (40) and the metal casing (42) so that a small gap is present
between the mass and the spindle and a small gap is present between the mass and the
casing such that oscillation of the damping mass within the chamber generates air
turbulence within the chamber for facilitating heat transfer from the spindle to the
metal casing.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to claim 1 additionally comprising a beatpiece (64)
located for reciprocation between the ram (58) and a tool or bit (68) mounted within
the tool holder body (66) for transferring impacts from the ram to a tool or bit
mounted within the tool holder body.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to claim 1 or claim 2 wherein the metal casing (42)
encircles the spindle (40) and the damping mass (70) encircles the spindle and is
concentric with the spindle.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to any one of the preceding claims wherein the damping
mass comprises a single piece cylinder (70).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to any one of the preceding claims wherein the damping
mass (70) is connected to the hammer housing (4, 5) via two springs one (90) located
forwardly of the mass between the mass and a forward housing part (42) and the other
(98) located rearwardly of the mass between the mass and a rearward housing part (5).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to any one of the preceding claims wherein the spring or
each spring is a coil spring (90, 98) which encircles the spindle (40).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to any one of the preceding claims wherein the damping
mass (70) is made from steel or brass.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to any one of the preceding claims wherein the damping
mass (70) and the spring or springs (90, 98) are arranged so that the mass oscillates
back and forth along the spindle (40) out of phase with the beat frequency of the other
hammer parts.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to claim 8 wherein the damping mass (70) oscillates
approximately 180° out of phase with the beat frequency of the other hammer parts.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to any one of the preceding claims wherein the air
turbulence includes air flows between the damping mass (70) and the spindle (40) and
air flows between the damping mass (70) and the metal casing (42).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to any one of the preceding claims wherein the or each
spacer element is formed integrally with the damping mass (70).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to any one of the preceding claims wherein the or each
spacer element comprises a guide arrangement (72) which is slideably mounted on the
spindle (40).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to claim 12 wherein the damping mass (70) is mounted
on the guide arrangement (72) and each guide arrangement is shaped to form at least
one channel between the damping mass and the spindle (40) through which air can
flow.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to claim 12 or 13 in which the damping mass (70) and
the metal casing (42) encircle the spindle (40) and wherein the or each guide
arrangement is a guide ring (72a, b).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to claim 14 when dependent on claim 13 wherein the
channels are formed between ribs (74) formed on the radially inward facing surface of
the guide ring (72a, b).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to any one of the preceding claims additionally
comprising a fan arrangement (14) for generating an airflow and a labyrinth formed by
parts of the hammer housing (4, 5, 102) for directing the airflow over the outer surface
of the metal casing (42).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to claim 16 wherein the fan (14) is rotatingly driven by
the motor (2).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="18">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to claim 16 or claim 17 wherein the fan (14) generates an
airflow which passes over the motor (2), through the fan and then through the
labyrinth and over the metal casing (42) before being exhausted from the hammer
housing (102).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="19">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to any one of claim 16 to 18 wherein the fan is a radial
fan (14).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="20">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to any one of the preceding claims wherein the hammer
drive arrangement comprises a crank arm arrangement (30, 32, 34).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="21">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to any one of the preceding claims wherein the hammer
housing comprises an inner metal housing arrangement (5) in which the motor (2),
hammer drive arrangement and spindle (40) are mounted and an outer plastic housing
(4) rigidly fixed to the inner metal housing (5) which outer housing comprises a
handle (6).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="22">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to claim 21 wherein the metal casing (42) is rigidly fixed
to a forward portion of the inner metal housing arrangement (5).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="23">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to claim 22 wherein the damping mass (70) is connected
to the hammer via a first forward spring (90) which extends between the mass and a
part of the metal casing (42) and via a second rearward spring (98) which extends
between the mass and a part of the metal housing arrangement (5).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="24">
      <claim-text>A hammer according to any one of the preceding claims wherein the air filled
chamber between the spindle (40) and the casing (42) communicates with at least one
other air space formed within the hammer.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
