<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1260379-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1260379" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="26615474" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021127">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1260379-A2" status="new" fvid="23611844">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1260379</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021127</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02011515-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02011515</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020522</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001152237-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001152237</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010522</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2002108131-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2002108131</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20020410</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B05D   1/26        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B05D   1/26        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B05D   5/04        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B05D   5/04        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/50        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/50        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/52        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41M   5/52</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L41M5:52C</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L41M5:52D</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L41M5:52G</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L41M5:52H</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L41M5:52K</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Tintenstrahlaufzeichnungsblatt</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Inkjet recording sheet</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Feuille pour l'impression à jet d'encre</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>FUJI PHOTO FILM CO LTD</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>FUJI PHOTO FILM CO., LTD.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>FUJI PHOTO FILM CO., LTD.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>210 Nakanuma Minami-Ashigara-shi</street>
              <city>Kanagawa 250-01</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KOIKE KAZUYUKI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NAGATA KOZO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TAKASHIMA MASANOBU</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YAMADA HISAO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KOIKE, KAZUYUKI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NAGATA, KOZO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TAKASHIMA, MASANOBU</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YAMADA, HISAO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>KOIKE, KAZUYUKI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Fuji Photo Film Co., Ltd., No. 200 Ohnakazato</street>
              <city>Fujinomiya-shi, Shizuoka-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>NAGATA, KOZO</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Fuji Photo Film Co., Ltd., No. 200 Ohnakazato</street>
              <city>Fujinomiya-shi, Shizuoka-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>TAKASHIMA, MASANOBU</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Fuji Photo Film Co., Ltd., No. 200 Ohnakazato</street>
              <city>Fujinomiya-shi, Shizuoka-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>YAMADA, HISAO</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Fuji Photo Film Co., Ltd., No. 200 Ohnakazato</street>
              <city>Fujinomiya-shi, Shizuoka-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>HOFFMANN - EITLE</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Patent- und Rechtsanwälte Arabellastrasse 4</street>
              <city>81925 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>An inkjet recording sheet comprising a support, on the support, a
colorant-receiving layer including a phenolic compound and at least one
organic mordant selected from the group consisting of a polyallylamines
and their derivatives, a polyvinylamine and their derivatives.</p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <heading>Field of the Invention</heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a recording material supplied for
inkjet recording using liquid inks, such as water-color inks (inks using a
dye or a pigment as the colorant) or oil inks, and solid inks, which are solid
at normal temperature and are melted and liquefied when applied for
printing, and, specifically, to an inkjet recording sheet which has excellent
ink-accepting performance, is free from bleeding over time and has high
light fastness and ozone-resistance.</p>
    <heading>Description of the Related Art</heading>
    <p num="0002">With the rapid development of industries of information
technologies in recent years, various information processing systems,
recording methods and recording devices suitable for these information
processing systems have been developed and put to practical use.</p>
    <p num="0003">Among these recording methods, an inkjet recording method has
come to be widely used for so-called "home uses" as well as office uses
because it has the advantages of enabling recording to various recording
materials, being provided with relatively inexpensive and compact
hardware (devices) and having excellent quietness.</p>
    <p num="0004">It has become possible to obtain so-called "photograph-like" high
image quality records along with the recent development of inkjet printers
having high resolution. Along with the progress of the hardware, various
recording sheets for use in inkjet recording have been developed. </p>
    <p num="0005">General characteristics required when this recording sheet is used
is inkjet recording are: (1) a rapid drying ability (high ink absorbing rate),
(2) proper and uniform diameter of dots (free from bleeding), (3) a good
granularity, (4) high dot circularity, (5) high color density, (6) high
chromaticity (no subdued tones), (7) a high water resistance, light fastness
and ozone resistance in a printed section, (8) a high whiteness of the
recording sheet, (9) a good preservability of the recording sheet (no
yellowing during long-term storage), (10) less deformability and good
dimensional stability (sufficiently small curling), (11) a high ability to be
run in hardware and the like.</p>
    <p num="0006">Further, in the use of photo-glossy paper used for the purpose of
obtaining so-called "photograph-like" high-quality recorded material,
glossiness, surface smoothness, printing paper feeling similar to that of a
silver salt photograph and the like are required in addition to the above
various characteristics.</p>
    <p num="0007">In recent years, inkjet recording sheets with a colorant-receiving
layer having a porous structure have been developed and put to practical
use with the intention to improve the various aforementioned
characteristics. This inkjet recording sheet has high ink-receiving
capability (quick drying characteristics) and high glossiness since it has
the porous structure.</p>
    <p num="0008">For instance, in Japanese Patent Application Laid-Open (JP-A) Nos.
10-119423 and 10-217601, inkjet recording sheets in which a colorant-receiving
layer containing fine inorganic pigment particles and a water-soluble
resin and having a high porosity is formed on a support are 
proposed.</p>
    <p num="0009">Due to their structure, these recording sheets, particularly these
inkjet recording sheets, which are provided with a colorant-receiving layer
having a porous structure and using silica as an inorganic pigment fine
particle, have high ink absorbancy and ink receiving capability high
enough to be able to form a having high resolution image and can exhibit
high glossiness.</p>
    <p num="0010">However, trace quantities of gases in the air, particularly ozone,
cause a recorded image to fade over time. The aforementioned recording
material comprising a colorant-receiving layer having a porous structure
has many apertures and therefore an image recorded thereon is easily
faded by the ozone gas in the air. For this, a resistance to the ozone in the
air (ozone resistance) is characteristic an extremely important for
recording material provided with a colorant-receiving layer having a high
porous structure.</p>
    <p num="0011">In order to prevent the aforementioned fading caused by ozone,
inkjet recording materials containing a sulfinic acid compound, a
thiosulfonic acid compound and a thiosulfinic acid compound are
proposed in JP-A No. 2001-260519. Also, an inkjet recording material
containing a thioether compound having a hydrophilic group is proposed
in EP 1,138,509. All of these compounds have an effect on ozone
resistance. However, there is a problem that this effect does not last long
and therefore these compounds can impart only insufficient ozone
resistance.</p>
    <p num="0012">An inkjet recording sheet containing a phenol derivative as a dye 
image fading preventive agent is disclosed in Japanese Patent Application
Publication (JP-B) No. 62-26319 with the intention of improving the image
preserving ability. However, although the recording sheet containing the
phenol derivative is improved in light fastness, it has the problem that
bleeding over time can not be sufficiently suppressed.</p>
    <p num="0013">Techniques in which a salicylic acid type compound is contained as
a preserving ability improving agent and a combination of a vapor-phase
method silica and a cationic compound is used, are proposed in JP-A No.
2001-191639. As the cationic compound, a diallylamine
hydrochloride/sulfur dioxide copolymer and basic poly aluminum
hydroxide are described in Examples. However, there is a problem that
the effects obtained by improving the resistances (light fastness and ozone
resistance) of these compounds are unsatisfactory.</p>
    <p num="0014">Also, an inkjet recording sheet containing salts of a hydroxy-substituted
aromatic group, salts of a carbonic group and salts of a
sulfonic group is proposed in JP-A No. 11-165461. These compounds are
added to suppress the hazing of an image receiving layer of the inkjet
recording sheet, but the disclosure does not refer to the improvements in
resistances (light fastness and ozone resistance). Also, there is no
description concerning a cationic polymer as a mordant for mordanting
dyes or a pigment capable of forming a porous layer and there is a problem
that only insufficient resistance to bleeding over time and ink absorbancy
can be provided.</p>
    <p num="0015">As mentioned above, an inkjet recording sheet has not yet been
provided, which is comprises a colorant-receiving layer having good ink 
absorbancy, is able to form of an image having high resolution, has an ink
receiving capability such that the formed image has superior light fastness,
resistance to bleeding over time and glossiness and at the same time,
possesses good preserving characteristics, particularly, ozone resistance
for a sufficiently long period of time.</p>
    <heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0016">Objects of the present invention are to solve the aforementioned
various problems and to provide an inkjet recording sheet which has good
ink-absorbancy, is free from bleeding over time and is also improved in,
particularly, ozone resistance and light fastness. The invention is thus
intended to attain the above objects.</p>
    <p num="0017">The invention is based on findings that the above objects can be
attained when using, particularly a combination of a phenolic compound
and a polyallylamine, polyvinylamine or their derivatives thereof as an
organic mordant.</p>
    <p num="0018">Means for solving the aforementioned problems are as follows.</p>
    <p num="0019">A first aspect of the inkjet recording sheet of the invention is an
inkjet recording sheet comprising a support, and on the support, a
colorant-receiving layer including: a phenolic compound; and at least one
organic mordant selected from the group consisting of polyallylamine and
derivatives thereof, and polyvinylamine and derivatives thereof.</p>
    <p num="0020">A second aspect of the inkjet recording sheet of the invention is the
inkjet recording sheet of the first aspect, wherein the phenolic compound
comprises phenolic hydroxy groups and further comprises at least one 
substituent group selected from the group consisting of carboxyl groups,
sulfo groups and salts thereof.</p>
    <p num="0021">A third aspect of the inkjet recording sheet of the invention is the
inkjet recording sheet of the first claim, wherein the colorant-receiving
layer comprises from 0.01 g/m<sup>2</sup> to 5 g/m<sup>2</sup> of the phenolic compound.</p>
    <p num="0022">A fourth aspect of the inkjet recording sheet of the invention is the
inkjet recording sheet of the first aspect, wherein a weight average
molecular weight of the organic mordant is from 500 to 100,000.</p>
    <p num="0023">A fifth aspect of the inkjet recording sheet of the invention is the
inkjet recording sheet of the first aspect, wherein the colorant-receiving
layer further comprises fine particles and a water-soluble resin.</p>
    <p num="0024">A sixth aspect of the inkjet recording sheet of the invention is the
inkjet recording sheet of the fifth aspect, wherein the fine particles
comprise at least one of silica fine particles, colloidal silica, alumina fine
particles and pseudo-boehmite.</p>
    <p num="0025">A seventh aspect of the inkjet recording sheet of the invention is the
inkjet recording sheet of the fifth aspect, wherein the fine particles
comprise at least 50 mass % relative to a total mass of solid components of
the colorant-receiving layer.</p>
    <p num="0026">An eighth aspect of the inkjet recording sheet of the invention is the
inkjet recording sheet of the fifth aspect, wherein the water-soluble resin
comprises at least one water-soluble resin selected from a group
consisting of polyvinyl alcohols and derivatives thereof, cellulose resins,
resins having an ether bond, resins having a carbamoyl group and resins
having a carboxyl group. </p>
    <p num="0027">A ninth aspect of the inkjet recording sheet of the invention is the
inkjet recording sheet of the fifth aspect, wherein the water-soluble resin
comprises from 9 to 40 mass % relative to a total mass of solid components
of the colorant-receiving layer.</p>
    <p num="0028">A tenth aspect of the inkjet recording sheet of the invention is the
inkjet recording sheet of the fifth aspect, wherein the fine particles in the
colorant-receiving layer comprise a mass (x), the water-soluble resin in the
colorant-receiving layer comprises a mass (y), and a mass ratio thereof
(x/y) is from 1.5 to 10.</p>
    <p num="0029">An eleventh aspect of the inkjet recording sheet of the invention is
the inkjet recording sheet of the fifth aspect, wherein the colorant-receiving
layer further comprises a crosslinking agent, which can crosslink
the water-soluble resin.</p>
    <p num="0030">A twelfth aspect of the inkjet recording sheet of the invention is the
inkjet recording sheet of the eleventh aspect, wherein the crosslinking
agent comprises a crosslinking agent selected from a group consisting of
boron compounds, aldehyde-based compounds, ketone-based compounds,
active halogen compounds, active vinyl compounds, N-methylol
compounds, melamine compounds, epoxy compounds, isocyanate-based
compounds, aziridine-based compounds, carbodiimide-based compounds,
ethylenimino-based compounds, halogenated carboxyaldehyde-based
compounds, dioxane-based compounds, compounds that include a metal,
polyamine compounds, hydrazide compounds, low-molecular weight
compounds that include at least two oxazoline groups, polymers that
include at least two oxazoline groups, multivalent acid anhydrides, acid 
chlorides, bissulfonate compounds and active ether compounds.</p>
    <p num="0031">A thirteenth aspect of the inkjet recording sheet of the invention is
the inkjet recording sheet of the eleventh aspect, wherein an amount of the
crosslinking agent used comprises from 1 to 50 mass % of an amount of
the water-soluble resin used.</p>
    <p num="0032">A fourteenth aspect of the inkjet recording sheet of the invention is
the inkjet recording sheet of the first aspect, wherein the colorant-receiving
layer further comprises a fastness improver.</p>
    <p num="0033">A fifteenth aspect of the inkjet recording sheet of the invention is
the inkjet recording sheet of the first aspect, wherein the colorant-receiving
layer further comprises a surfactant and a high boiling-point
organic solvent.</p>
    <p num="0034">A sixteenth aspect of the inkjet recording sheet of the invention is
the inkjet recording sheet of the first aspect, wherein a pH on a surface of
the colorant-receiving layer is from 3 to 8.</p>
    <p num="0035">A seventeenth aspect of the inkjet recording sheet of the invention
is the inkjet recording sheet of the first aspect, wherein a thickness of the
colorant-receiving layer is from 10 to 50 µm.</p>
    <p num="0036">An eighteenth aspect of the inkjet recording sheet of the invention
is the inkjet recording sheet of the first aspect, wherein the colorant-receiving
layer further comprises pores which have a median diameter of
from 0.005 to 0.030 µm.</p>
    <p num="0037">A nineteenth aspect of the inkjet recording sheet of the invention is
the inkjet recording sheet of the first aspect, wherein the support is
transparent, and a haze value of the colorant-receiving layer formed 
thereon is no more than 30 %.</p>
    <p num="0038">A twentieth aspect of the inkjet recording sheet of the invention is
the inkjet recording sheet of the first aspect, wherein the colorant-receiving
layer comprises a layer formed by a process including the steps
of: preparing a coating liquid containing at least fine particles and a
water-soluble resin; preparing a basic solution having a pH value of at
least 8; adding a crosslinking agent to at least one of the coating liquid and
the basic solution; applying the coating liquid to form a coated layer;
drying the coated layer; crosslinking and curing the coated layer by adding
the basic solution to the coated layer at a time that is at least one of (1)
simultaneous with the step of applying the coating liquid to form the
coated layer, and (2) before the coated layer exhibits a decreasing rate of
drying during the step of drying the coated layer.</p>
    <heading>DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
    <p num="0039">In an inkjet recording sheet according to the present invention, a
colorant-receiving layer containing a phenolic compound and an organic
mordant selected from a polyallylamine, polyvinylamine and their
derivatives is disposed on a support.</p>
    <p num="0040">The inkjet recording sheet of the invention will be hereinafter
explained in detail.</p>
    <p num="0041">The inkjet recording sheet of the invention has a structure
comprising a colorant-receiving layer is formed on a support. The
colorant-receiving layer comprises a phenolic compound and at least one
organic mordant selected from the group consisting of a polyallylamine, 
derivatives thereof, and a polyvinylamine and derivatives thereof.
Preferably, the colorant layer further comprises fine particles and a
water-soluble resin and may comprise other additives according to the
need.</p>
    <heading>(Organic mordant)</heading>
    <p num="0042">The colorant-receiving layer according to the invention contains at
least one organic mordant selected from the group consisting of a
polyallylamine and derivatives thereof, and polyvinylamine and derivatives
thereof. Each of these organic mordants may be contained as a
copolymer, which is obtained by copolymerizing the organic mordant
with another copolymerizable monomer. The polyallylamine in the
invention represents those prepared by polymerizing monoallylamines
(including salts thereof).</p>
    <p num="0043">Among organic mordants, compounds having a weight average
molecular weight of from 500 to 100000 are desirable to prevent bleeding
over time and improve ink absorbancy of the colorant-receiving layer.</p>
    <p num="0044">As the polyallylamine and derivatives thereof, various known
allylamine polymers and their derivatives may be used. Examples of
these derivatives include salts of a polyallylamines and acids (examples of
the acids include inorganic acids such as hydrochloric acid, sulfuric acid,
phosphoric acid and nitric acid, organic acids such as methanesulfonic
acid, toluenesulfonic acid, acetic acid, propionic acid, cinnamic acid and
(meth)acrylic acid or combinations of these acids and those in which only a
part of allylamine is converted into a salt), derivatives of a polyallylamine
obtained by a high molecular reaction (for example, polymers and the like, 
which include repeated structural units represented by the following
formulae (1) to (5)), and copolymers of a polyallylamine and other
copolymerizable monomers (specific examples of the monomer include
(meth)acrylates, styrenes, (meth)acrylamides, acrylonitrile and
vinylesters).
<img id="img-00110001" orientation="unknown" wi="162" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00110001.tif" inline="no" he="27"/><img id="img-00110002" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00110002.tif" inline="no" he="25"/><img id="img-00110003" orientation="unknown" wi="80" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00110003.tif" inline="no" he="35"/>
wherein R<sup>81</sup> to R<sup>84</sup> respectively represent an organic group which may have
a substituent; R<sup>85</sup> and R<sup>86</sup> respectively represent an organic group, which
may have a substituent (the same meanings as R<sup>81</sup> to R<sup>84</sup>), or a hydrogen
atom; R<sup>87</sup> represents a hydrogen atom or a methyl group; R<sup>88</sup> represents-COOR<sup>89</sup>,
-CN or -CONR<sup>90</sup>R<sup>91</sup>, where R<sup>89</sup> to R<sup>91</sup> respectively represent a
hydrogen atom, an aliphatic group or an aromatic group; and G<sup>-</sup>
represents a counter anion.</p>
    <p num="0045">The organic groups shown above denotes groups containing 
hydrocarbon portions and/or hydrogen halide portions and may include,
besides these portions, atoms such as hydrogen, carbon, nitrogen, oxygen,
sulfur, phosphorous, silicon, boron and a halogen and/or functional
groups consisting of combinations of these atoms. Examples of these
groups include (substituted) alkyl groups, (substituted) aralkyl groups,
(substituted) aryl groups, (substituted) acryl groups, (substituted) sulfonyl
groups and heterocycles.</p>
    <p num="0046">Specific examples of the organic group represented by R<sup>81</sup> to R<sup>84</sup>
include alkyl groups (e.g., methyl, ethyl, n-propyl, i-propyl, n-butyl, i-butyl,
sec-butyl, t-butyl, n-hexyl, cyclohexyl, n-octyl, 2-ethylhexyl, n-decyl, n-dodecyl,
octadecyl, 1,3-butadienyl and 1,3-pentadienyl); aralkyl groups
(e.g., benzyl, phenylethyl, vinylbenzyl, 1-phenylvinyl and 2-phenylvinyl);
and aryl groups (e.g., phenyl, naphthyl, tolyl and vinylphenyl).</p>
    <p num="0047">Moreover, examples of the organic group having a substituent
include a fluoroethyl group, trifluoroethyl group, methoxyethyl group,
phenoxyethyl group, hydroxyphenylmethyl group, chlorophenyl group,
dichlorophenyl group, trichlorophenyl group, bromophenyl group,
iodophenyl group, fluorophenyl group, hydroxyphenyl group,
methoxyphenyl group, hydroxyphenyl group, acetoxyphenyl group and
cyanophenyl group.</p>
    <p num="0048">Also, examples of the organic group having a hydroxyl group are
shown below. <img id="img-00130001" orientation="unknown" wi="94" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130001.tif" inline="no" he="17"/><img id="img-00130002" orientation="unknown" wi="95" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130002.tif" inline="no" he="18"/><img id="img-00130003" orientation="unknown" wi="37" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130003.tif" inline="no" he="24"/>
Also, organic groups shown below are given as examples.

   -CR<sup>101</sup>R<sup>102</sup>-COOR<sup>103</sup></p>
    <p num="0049">The above R<sup>101</sup> to R<sup>103</sup> respectively represent a hydrogen atom, an
aliphatic group or an aromatic group. A methyl group, ethyl group, butyl
group, benzyl group and phenyl group are given as examples of R<sup>101</sup> to R<sup>103</sup>.

   -CO-R<sup>104</sup>-COOH</p>
    <p num="0050">The above R<sup>104</sup> represents a divalent connecting group and
examples of this group include -CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>-, -CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>-, -CH=CH- and the
following groups.
<img id="img-00130004" orientation="unknown" wi="81" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130004.tif" inline="no" he="24"/>
   -COR<sup>105</sup>, -COOR<sup>106</sup>, -CONHR<sup>107</sup>, -CSNHR<sup>108</sup>, -SC<sub>2</sub>R<sup>109</sup> and
   -P(=O)(OR<sup>110</sup>)<sub>2</sub></p>
    <p num="0051">The above R<sup>105</sup> to R<sup>110</sup> respectively represent a hydrogen atom, an 
aliphatic group or an aromatic group. Examples of these groups include
a methyl group, ethyl group, propyl group, butyl group, octadecyl group,
benzyl group, phenyl group and -CH=CH-Ph.</p>
    <p num="0052">Also, R<sup>87</sup> represents a hydrogen atom or a methyl group, R<sup>88</sup>
represents -COOR<sup>111</sup>, -CN, or -CONR<sup>112</sup>R<sup>113</sup> and R<sup>111</sup> to R<sup>113</sup> respectively
represent a hydrogen atom, an aliphatic group or an aromatic group.</p>
    <p num="0053">Specific examples of R<sup>111</sup> to R<sup>113</sup> include a hydrogen atom, methyl
group, ethyl group, n-propyl group, i-propyl group, n-butyl group, i-butyl
group, sec-butyl group, t-butyl group, n-hexyl group, cyclohexyl group,
n-octyl group, 2-ethylhexyl group, n-decyl group, n-dodecyl group,
octadecyl group, allyl group, benzyl group, phenyl group, naphthyl group,
biphenyl group, 1,1,1-trifluoroethyl group and 2-hydroxy-3-chloropropyl
group.</p>
    <p num="0054">Specific examples of G<sup>-</sup> include halogen ions (Cl<sup>-</sup>, Br<sup>-</sup> and I<sup>-</sup>),
sulfonic acid ions, alkylsulfonic acid ions, arylsulfonic acid ions,
alkylcarboxylic acid ions and arylcarboxylic acid ions.</p>
    <p num="0055">There is no particular limitation to structures of these
polyallylamine derivatives. Although the obtained polymer is preferably
water-soluble or soluble in an organic solvent miscible with water, it may
be also used in the form of a water-dispersible latex particle.</p>
    <p num="0056">Specific examples of the polyallylamine and derivatives thereof
include compounds described in each of JP-B Nos. 62-31722, 2-14364,
63-43402, 63-43403, 63-45721, 63-29881, 1-26362, 2-56365, 2-57084,
4-41686, 6-2780, 6-45649, 6-15592, 4-68622, JP Nos. 3199227, 3008369,
JP-A Nos. 10-330427, 11-21321, 2000-281728, 2001-106736, 62-256801, 
7-173286, 7-213897, 9-235318, 9-302026, 11-21321, WO99/21901,
WO99/19372, JP-A No. 5-140213, Japanese Patent Application National
Publication (Laid-Open) No. 11-506488 and the like.</p>
    <p num="0057">As the polyvinylamine and derivatives thereof, various known
polyvinylamines and their derivatives may be used. Examples of such a
derivative are the same as those of the aforementioned polyallylamine.
Specific examples of the polyvinylamine and its derivatives include the
compounds described in JP-B Nos. 5-35162, 5-35163, 5-35164, 5-88846,
JP-A Nos. 7-118333, 2000-344990, JP Nos. 2648847, 2661677 and the
like.</p>
    <p num="0058">Among the above compounds, a polyallylamine and its derivatives
are particularly preferable.</p>
    <heading>(Phenolic compound)</heading>
    <p num="0059">The phenolic compound according to the invention is a compound
having at least one aromatic hydroxy group and represents a water-soluble
and hydrophobic compound. As the phenolic compound, those having a
substituent are desirable and these compounds may form salts.</p>
    <p num="0060">Examples of the above substituent include a carboxyl group, sulfo
group, cyano group, halogen atom, hydroxy group, alkoxy group, aryloxy
group, aliphatic group, aromatic group, acyloxy group, acyl group,
phosphono group, substituted amino group and heterocyclic group.</p>
    <p num="0061">Specific examples of these substituents are as follows.</p>
    <p num="0062">Examples of the above halogen atom include a fluorine atom,
chlorine atom and bromine atom. Examples of the above alkoxy group
include alkoxy groups having 30 or less carbon atoms, for example, a 
methoxy group, ethoxy group, benzyloxy group, phenoxyethoxy group and
phenethyloxy group. Examples of the above aryloxy group include
aryloxy groups having 30 or less carbon atoms, for example, a phenoxy
group, p-tolyloxy group, 1-naphthoxy group and 2-naphthoxy group.</p>
    <p num="0063">Examples of the above aliphatic group include an alkyl group,
alkenyl group, alkinyl group and aralkyl group. These groups further
may have a substituent. Among these groups, an alkyl group,
substituted alkyl group, alkenyl group, substituted alkenyl group, aralkyl
group and substituted aralkyl group are preferable and an alkyl group and
substituted alkyl group are particularly preferable. Also, the
aforementioned aliphatic group may be either chain aliphatic groups or
cyclic aliphatic groups and these chain aliphatic groups may be further
branched.</p>
    <p num="0064">Examples of the above alkyl group include straight-chain,
branched and cyclic alkyl groups. The number of carbons of the alkyl
group is preferably 1 to 30 and more preferably 1 to 20. The number of
carbons of the alkyl portion of the substituted alkyl group is also
preferably 1 to 30 and more preferably 1 to 20.</p>
    <p num="0065">Specific examples of the above alkyl group include a methyl group,
ethyl group, propyl group, butyl group, pentyl group, hexyl group, octyl
group, 2-ethylhexyl group, t-octyl group, decyl group, dodecyl group,
octadecyl group, cyclohexyl group, cyclopentyl group, neopentyl group,
isopropyl group and isobutyl group.</p>
    <p num="0066">Examples of the substituent of the above substituted alkyl group
include a carboxyl group, sulfo group, cyano group, halogen atom (e.g., a 
fluorine atom, a chlorine atom and a bromine atom), hydroxy group,
alkoxycarbonyl group having 30 or less carbon atoms (e.g., a
methoxycarbonyl group, ethoxycarbonyl group and benzyloxycarbonyl
group), aryloxycarbonyl group having 30 or less carbon atoms (e.g., a
phenoxycarbonyl group), alkylsulfonylaminocarbonyl group having 30 or
less carbon atoms (e.g., a methylsulfonylaminocarbonyl group and
octylsulfonylaminocarbonyl group), arylsulfonylaminocarbonyl group (e.g.,
a toluenesulfonylaminocarbonyl group), acylaminosulfonyl group having
30 or less carbon atoms (e.g., a benzoylaminosulfonyl group,
acetylaminosulfonyl group and pivaloylaminosulfonyl group), alkoxy
group having 30 or less carbon atoms (e.g., a methoxy group, ethoxy group,
benzyloxy group, phenoxyethoxy group and phenethyloxy group), arylthio
group and alkylthio group having 30 or less carbon atoms (e.g., a
phenylthio group, methylthio group, ethylthio group and dodecylthio
group), aryloxy group having 30 or less carbon atoms (e.g., a phenoxy
group, p-tolyloxy group, 1-naphthoxy group and 2-naphthoxy group) and
nitro group.</p>
    <p num="0067">Examples of the substituent of the above substituted alkyl group
also include an alkyl group having 30 or less carbon atoms,
alkoxycarbonyloxy group (e.g., a methoxycarbonyloxy group,
stearyloxycarbonyloxy group and phenoxyethoxycarbonyloxy group),
aryloxycarbonyloxy group (e.g., a phenoxycarbonyloxy group and
chlorophenoxycarbonyloxy group), acyloxy group having 30 or less carbon
atoms (eg., an acetyloxy group and propionyloxy group), acyl group having
30 or less carbon atoms (e.g., an acetyl group, propionyl group and benzoyl 
group), carbamoyl group (e.g., a carbamoyl group, N,N-dimethylcarbamoyl
group, morpholinocarbonyl group and piperidinocarbonyl group),
sulfamoyl group (e.g., a sulfamoyl group, N,N-dimethylsulfamoyl group,
morpholinosulfonyl group and piperidinosulfonyl group) and alkylsulfonyl
group having 30 or less carbon atoms (e.g., a methylsulfonyl group,
trifluoromethylsulfonyl group, ethylsulfonyl group, butylsulfonyl group
and dodecylsulfonyl group).</p>
    <p num="0068">Examples of the substituent of the above substituted alkyl group
also include an arylsulfonyl group (e.g., benzenesulfonyl group,
toluenesulfonyl group, naphthalenesulfonyl group, pyridinesulfonyl group
and quinolinesulfonyl group), aryl group having 30 or less carbon atoms
(e.g., a phenyl group, dichlorophenyl group, tolyl group, methoxyphenyl
group, diethylaminophenyl group, acetylaminophenyl group,
methoxycarbonylphenyl group, hydroxyphenyl group, t-octylphenyl group
and naphthyl group), substituted amino group (e.g., an amino group,
alkylamino group, dialkylamino group, arylamino group, diarylamino
group and acylamino group), substituted phosphono group (e.g., a
phosphono group, diethylphosphono group and diphenylphosphono
group), heterocyclic group (e.g., a pyridyl group, quinolyl group, furyl
group, thienyl group, tetrahydrofurfuryl group, pyrazolyl group,
isooxazolyl group, isothiazolyl group, imidazolyl group, oxazolyl group,
thiazolyl group, pyridazyl group, pyrimidyl group, pyrazyl group, triazolyl
group, tetrazolyl group, benzooxazolyl group, benzoimidazolyl group,
isoquinolyl group, thiadiazolyl group, morpholino group, piperidino group,
piperazino group, indolyl group, isoindolyl group and thiomorpholino 
group), ureide group (e.g., a methylureide group, dimethylureide group
and phenylureide group), sulfamoylamino group (e.g.,
dipropylsulfamoylamino group), alkoxycarbonylamino group (e.g., an
ethoxycarbonylamino group), aryloxycarbonylamino group (e.g., a
phenyloxycarbonylamino group), alkylsulfinyl group (e.g., a methylsulfinyl
group), arylsulfinyl group (e.g., a phenylsulfinyl group), silyl group (e.g., a
trimethoxysilyl group and triethoxysilyl group) and silyloxy group (e.g., a
trimethylsilyloxy group).</p>
    <p num="0069">It should be noted that the aforementioned carboxyl group, sulfo
group, hydroxy group and phosphono group which are the substituents of
the substituted alkyl group may respectively form a salt. As a cation used
for forming salts, organic cationic compounds, transition metal-coordinated
complex cations (e.g., compounds described in JP No.
2791143) or metal cations (e.g., Na<sup>+</sup>, K<sup>+</sup>, Li<sup>+</sup>, Ag<sup>+</sup>, Fe<sup>2+</sup>, Fe<sup>3+</sup>, Cu<sup>+</sup>, Cu<sup>2+</sup>, Zn<sup>2+</sup>,
Al<sup>3+</sup> or 1/2Ca<sup>2+</sup>) are preferable.</p>
    <p num="0070">Examples of the above organic cationic compounds include
quaternary ammonium cations, quaternary pyridinium cations,
quaternary quinolinium cations, phosphonium cations, iodonium cations,
sulfonium cations and dye cations.</p>
    <p num="0071">Specific examples of the aforementioned quaternary ammonium
cations include a tetraalkylammonium cations (e.g., a
tetramethylammonium cation and tetrabutylammonium cation) and
tetraarylammonium cations (e.g., tetraphenylammonium cation).
Examples of the aforementioned quaternary pyridinium cations include
N-alkylpyridinium cations (e.g., an N-methylpiridinium cation), N-arylpyridinium 
cations (e.g., an N-phenylpyridinium cation), N-alkoxypyridinium
cations (e.g., a 4-phenyl-N-methoxy-pyridinium cation)
and N-benzoylpyridinium cation. Examples of the aforementioned
quinolinium cations include an N-alkylquinolinium cations (e.g., an N-methylquinolinium
cation) and N-arylquinolinium cations (e.g., an N-phenylquinolinium
cation). Examples of the aforementioned
phosphonium cations include a tetraarylphosphonium cations (e.g.,
tetraphenylphosphonium cation). Examples of the aforementioned
iodonium cations include a diaryliodonium cations (e.g., a
diphenyliodonium cation). Examples of the aforementioned sulfonium
cations include a triarylsulfonium cations (e.g., a triphenylsulfonium
cation).</p>
    <p num="0072">Further, examples of the cations that form salts may include
compounds described in the paragraphs No. 0020 to No. 0038 in JP-A No.
9-188686.</p>
    <p num="0073">Examples of the alkenyl group included in the aforementioned
aliphatic group are straight-chain, branched and cyclic alkenyl groups.
The number of carbons of the alkenyl group is preferably 2 to 30 and more
preferably 2 to 20. The number of carbons of the alkenyl portion of the
substituted alkenyl group is also preferably 2 to 30 and more preferably 2
to 20. Specific examples of the alkenyl group include a vinyl group, allyl
group, pulenyl group, geranyl group, oleyl group, cycloalkenyl group (e.g.,
2-cyclopentene-1-yl group and 2-cyclohexene-1-yl group),
bicyclo[2,2,1]hepto-2-ene-1-yl and bicyclo[2,2,2]octo-2-ene-4-yl. Specific
examples of the substituent of the substituted alkenyl group include the 
same substituents as in the case of the aforementioned substituted alkyl
group.</p>
    <p num="0074">Examples of the alkinyl group included in the aforementioned
aliphatic group are straight-chain, branched and cyclic alkinyl groups.
The number of carbons of the alkinyl group is preferably 2 to 30 and more
preferably 2 to 20. The number of carbons of the alkinyl portion of the
substituted alkinyl group is also preferably 2 to 30 and more preferably 2
to 20. Specific examples of the alkinyl group include an ethynyl group,
propalgyl group and trimethylsilylethynyl group. Specific examples of the
substituent of the substituted alkinyl group include the same substituents
as in the case of the aforementioned alkyl group.</p>
    <p num="0075">Examples of the alalkyl group included in the aforementioned
aliphatic group are straight-chain, branched and cyclic alalkyl groups.
The number of carbons of the alalkyl group is preferably 7 to 35 and more
preferably 7 to 25. The number of carbons of the alalkyl portion of the
substituted alalkyl group is also preferably 7 to 35 and more preferably 7
to 25. Specific examples of the alalkyl group include a benzyl group,
methylbenzyl group, octylbenzyl group, dodecylbenzyl group,
hexadecylbenzyl group, dimethylbenzyl group, octyloxybenzyl group,
octadecylaminocarbonylbenzyl group and chlorobenzyl group. Specific
examples of the substituent of the substituted alalkyl group include the
same substituents as in the case of the aforementioned substituted alkyl
group.</p>
    <p num="0076">Examples of the aforementioned aromatic group include an aryl
group and substituted aryl group and the number of carbons of the aryl 
group is preferably 6 to 30 and more preferably 6 to 20. The number of
carbons of the aryl portion of the substituted aryl group is also preferably
6 to 30 and more preferably 6 to 20. Specific examples of the aryl group
include a phenyl group, α-naphthyl group and β-naphthyl group.</p>
    <p num="0077">Examples of the aforementioned acyloxy group include an acyloxy
group having 30 or less carbon atoms and an acetyloxy group and
propionyloxy group.</p>
    <p num="0078">Examples of the acyl group are an aliphatic acyl group, aromatic
acyl group and heterocyclic acyl group. The number of carbons of the
acyl group is preferably 1 to 30 and more preferably 1 to 20. The number
of carbons of the acyl group portion of the substituted acyl group is also
preferably 1 to 30 and more preferably 1 to 20.</p>
    <p num="0079">Specific examples of the acyl group include an acetyl group,
propionyl group, pivaloyl group, chloroacetyl group, trifluoroacetyl group,
1-methylcyclopropylcarbonyl group, 1-ethylcyclopropylcarbonyl group, 1-benzylcyclopropylcarbonyl
group, benzoyl group, 4-methoxybenzoyl group,
pyridylcarbonyl group and thenoyl group.</p>
    <p num="0080">Examples of the aforementioned phosphono group include a
phosphono group, diethylphosphono group and diphenylphosphono group.
The phosphono group may form a salt.</p>
    <p num="0081">Examples of the aforementioned substituted amino group include
an amino group, alkylamino group, dialkylamino group, arylamino group,
diarylamino group and acylamino group. Examples of the substituted
phosphono group include a phosphono group, diethylphosphono group
and diphenylphosphono group. </p>
    <p num="0082">Examples of the aforementioned heterocyclic group include
heterocyclic groups containing a nitrogen atom, oxygen atom and sulfur
atom, for example a furyl group, thienyl group, pyridyl group, pyrazolyl
group, isooxazolyl group, isothiazolyl group, imidazolyl group, oxazolyl
group, thiazolyl group, pyridazyl group, pyrimidyl group, pyrazyl group,
triazolyl group, tetrazolyl group, quinolyl group, benzothiazolyl group,
benzooxazolyl group, benzoimidazolyl group, isoquinolyl group,
thiadiazolyl group, morpholino group, piperidino group, thiomorpholino
group, tetrahydrofurfuryl group, piperazino group, indolyl group and
isoindolyl group. These heterocyclic groups may further have a
substituent. Examples of the substituent of the substituted heterocyclic
group include the same substituents as in the case of the aforementioned
substituted alkyl group.</p>
    <p num="0083">The substituent of the aforementioned phenolic compound may be
further substituted with the same substituent as in the case of the
aforementioned substituted alkyl group.</p>
    <p num="0084">The phenolic compound according to the invention is preferably
those soluble in water and those having at least one substituent selected
from a carboxyl group, sulfo group and salts thereof.</p>
    <p num="0085">Specific examples of the phenolic compound according to the
invention will be shown below; however these examples are not intended to
be limiting of the invention. <img id="img-00240001" orientation="unknown" wi="151" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00240001.tif" inline="no" he="34"/><img id="img-00240002" orientation="unknown" wi="152" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00240002.tif" inline="no" he="25"/><img id="img-00240003" orientation="unknown" wi="153" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00240003.tif" inline="no" he="28"/><img id="img-00240004" orientation="unknown" wi="153" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00240004.tif" inline="no" he="32"/><img id="img-00240005" orientation="unknown" wi="154" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00240005.tif" inline="no" he="33"/><img id="img-00240006" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00240006.tif" inline="no" he="37"/><img id="img-00240007" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00240007.tif" inline="no" he="35"/><img id="img-00250001" orientation="unknown" wi="162" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00250001.tif" inline="no" he="35"/><img id="img-00250002" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00250002.tif" inline="no" he="39"/><img id="img-00250003" orientation="unknown" wi="160" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00250003.tif" inline="no" he="36"/><img id="img-00250004" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00250004.tif" inline="no" he="36"/><img id="img-00250005" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00250005.tif" inline="no" he="38"/><img id="img-00260001" orientation="unknown" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00260001.tif" inline="no" he="36"/><img id="img-00260002" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00260002.tif" inline="no" he="34"/><img id="img-00260003" orientation="unknown" wi="160" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00260003.tif" inline="no" he="26"/><img id="img-00260004" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00260004.tif" inline="no" he="34"/><img id="img-00270001" orientation="unknown" wi="148" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00270001.tif" inline="no" he="43"/><img id="img-00270002" orientation="unknown" wi="149" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00270002.tif" inline="no" he="50"/><img id="img-00270003" orientation="unknown" wi="149" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00270003.tif" inline="no" he="24"/><img id="img-00270004" orientation="unknown" wi="150" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00270004.tif" inline="no" he="37"/><img id="img-00270005" orientation="unknown" wi="150" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00270005.tif" inline="no" he="44"/></p>
    <p num="0086">When the phenolic compound according to the invention is to be
contained in the colorant-receiving layer, it may be added in the condition
that the hydrophilicity thereof to water is heightened by mixing a water-soluble
organic solvent, for example, an alcohol compound (e.g., methanol,
ethanol, isopropyl alcohol, ethylene glycol, diethylene glycol, diethylene
glycol monobutyl ether, polyethylene glycol, polypropylene glycol, glycerol,
diglycerol, trimethylolpropane or trimethylolbutane), an ether compound
(tetrahydrofuran or dioxane), an amide compound (e.g.,
dimethylformamide, dimethylacetamide or N-methylpyrrolidone) or ketone
compound (e.g., acetone).</p>
    <p num="0087">When the phenolic compound according to the invention has only
insufficient water-solubility, a hydrophobic organic solvent, for example,
an ester compound (e.g., ethyl acetate, dioctyl adipate, butyl phthalate,
methyl stearate or tricrezylphosphate), an ether compound (e.g., anisole,
hydroxyethoxybenzene or hydroquinone dibutyl ether), a hydrocarbon
compound (e.g., toluene, xylene or diisopropylnaphthalene), an amide
compound (e.g., N-butylbenzenesulfonamide or stearic acid amide), an
alcohol compound (2-ethylhexyl alcohol, benzyl alcohol or phenethyl
alcohol), a ketone compound (e.g., hydroxyacetophenone, benzophenone
or cyclohexane) or the aforementioned water-soluble organic solvent may
be mixed therewith and the resulting mixture may be added. The form
when the resulting mixture is added may be an oil droplet, latex, solid
dispersion or polymer dispersion.</p>
    <p num="0088">The content of the above phenolic compound in the colorant-receiving
layer is preferably 0.01 to 5 g/m<sup>2</sup> and more preferably 0.05 to 3 
g/m<sup>2</sup>.</p>
    <heading>(Fine particle)</heading>
    <p num="0089">The colorant-receiving layer of the inkjet recording sheet acquires a
porous structure by containing a fine particle and this improves ink
absorbancy. It is preferable, particularly when the solid content of the
fine particle in the colorant-receiving layer is 50 mass % or more, and more
preferably exceeds 60 mass %, because a better porous structure can be
formed, whereby an inkjet recording sheet having sufficient ink
absorbancy is obtained. Here, the solid content of the fine particle in the
colorant-receiving layer denotes a content calculated based on
components other than water in the composition constituting the
colorant-receiving layer.</p>
    <p num="0090">The fine particle used in the invention may be either an organic fine
particle or an inorganic fine particle.</p>
    <p num="0091">Preferable examples of the organic fine particle include polymer fine
particles obtained by emulsion polymerization, microemulsion type
polymerization, soap-free polymerization, seed polymerization, dispersion
polymerization, suspension polymerization or the like. Specific examples
of the organic fine particle include powders, latexes and emulsion polymer
fine particles of polyethylene, polypropylene, polystyrene, polyacrylate,
polyamide, silicon resin, phenol resin and natural polymers and the like.</p>
    <p num="0092">Examples of the inorganic fine particle include a silica fine particle,
colloidal silica, titanium dioxide, barium sulfate, calcium silicate, zeolite,
kaolinite, halloysite, mica, talc, calcium carbonate, magnesium carbonate,
calcium sulfate, pseudo-boehmite, zinc oxide, zinc hydroxide, alumina, 
aluminum silicate, calcium silicate, magnesium silicate, zirconium oxide,
zirconium hydroxide, cerium oxide, lanthanum oxide and yttrium oxide.
Among these compounds, a silica fine particle, colloidal silica, alumina
fine particle or pseudo-boehmite is preferable from the viewpoint of the
formation of a good porous structure. These fine particles may be used as
primary particles, or formed into and used as secondary particles. The
average primary particle diameter of these fine particles is preferably 2 µm
or less and more preferably 200 nm or less.</p>
    <p num="0093">In the invention, the use of an inorganic fine particle is preferable
from the viewpoint of ink absorbancy and image stability. Further, silica
fine particles having an average primary particle diameter of 20 nm or less,
colloidal silicas having an average primary particle diameter of 30 nm or
less, alumina fine particles having an average fine particle diameter of 20
nm or less or pseudo-boehmite having an average pore diameter of 2 to 15
nm is more preferable. Particularly, silica fine particles, alumina fine
particles and pseudo-boehmites are preferable.</p>
    <p num="0094">Silica fine particles are generally classified roughly into wet method
particles and dry method (vapor-phase method) particles based on the
production method thereof. Among the wet methods, a method in which
an active silica is produced by acid-decomposition of a silicate and
properly polymerized and the polymerized silica is coagulated and
sedimented to obtain hydrate silica is predominantly used. On the other
hand, among the vapor-phase methods, methods for obtaining anhydrous
silica using the following processes are dominantly used: a flame
hydrolysis method involving high temperature vapor-phase hydrolysis of a 
silicon halide and an arc method in which quartz sand and cokes are
reduced under heating and vaporized by an arc in an electric furnace and
the resulting vapor is oxidized by air. The "vapor-phase method silica"
denotes the anhydrous silica fine particle obtained by the vapor-phase
method. As the silica fine particle to be used in the invention, the
vapor-phase method silica fine particle is particularly desirable.</p>
    <p num="0095">The vapor-phase method silica differ from the hydrate silica in the
density of a silanol group on the surface, the presence or absence of a
aperture and the like in qualities exhibited. The vapor-phase method
silica is suitable for the purpose of forming a three-dimensional structure
having a high aperture ratio. Although the reason for this is unclear, it is
estimated that in the case of hydrate silica, the density of a silanol group
on the surface of a fine particle is as many as 5 to 8/nm<sup>2</sup> and the silica fine
particles easily aggregated densely, whereas in the case of the vapor-phase
method silica, the density of a silanol group on the surface of a fine particle
is as small as 2 to 3/nm<sup>2</sup>, so that the silica tends to form a non-dense
flocculate with the result that the vapor-phase method silica has a
structure with a high aperture ratio.</p>
    <p num="0096">The vapor-phase method silica has the characteristics wherein
because it has a particularly large specific surface area, it has high ink
absorbancy and ink retention and also because it has a low refractive
index, providing the receptor layer with transparency and a high color
density and good color developing ability can be obtained if the silica is
dispersed until the silica particle is decreased to an appropriate particle
diameter. It is important for the receptor layer to be transparent with the 
view of obtaining a high color density and good color developing ability and
glossiness not only for use in, for example, OHPs for which transparency is
required, but also in the case of applying this sheet to recording sheets
such as photo-glossy paper.</p>
    <p num="0097">The average primary particle diameter of the aforementioned
vapor-phase method silica is preferably 30 nm or less, more preferably 20
nm or less, particularly preferably 10 nm or less and most preferably 3 to
10 nm. The aforementioned vapor-phase method silica can form a
structure having a large aperture ratio and improve the ink absorbing
characteristics efficiently when the average primary particle diameter is 30
nm or less because the particles are easily stuck together due to a
hydrogen bonding of a silanol group.</p>
    <p num="0098">Also, the silica fine particle may be used in combination with the
other aforementioned fine particles. When other fine particle are used
together with the aforementioned vapor-phase method silica, the amount
of the vapor-phase method silica in the total amount of fine particles is
preferably 30 mass % or more, and more preferably 50 mass % or more.</p>
    <p num="0099">As the inorganic fine particle to be used in the invention, an
alumina fine particle, alumina hydrate and a mixture or complex of these
materials are preferable. Among these materials, the alumina hydrate is
preferable because it absorbs and fixes ink well and a pseudo-boehmite
(Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>·nH<sub>2</sub>O) is particularly preferable. Although as the alumina hydrate,
those in various forms may be used, boehmite sol is preferably used as raw
material because a smooth layer is easily obtained thereby.</p>
    <p num="0100">As to the pore structure of the pseudo-boehmite, the average pore 
radius is preferably 1 to 30 nm and more preferably 2 to 15 nm. Also, the
pore volume is preferably 0.3 to 2.0 cc/g (ml/g) and more preferably 0.5 to
1.5 cc/g (ml/g). Here, measurements of the aforementioned pore radius
and pore volume are made by a nitrogen absorbing and desorbing method.
The measurements can be made using, for example, a gas absorbing and
desorbing analyzer (e.g., Omnisorp 369 (Trademark), manufactured by
Coaltar).</p>
    <p num="0101">Also, among alumina fine particles, a vapor-phase method alumina
fine particle has a large specific surface area and is hence preferable. The
average primary particle diameter of the vapor-phase method alumina is
preferably 30 nm or less and more preferably 20 nm or less.</p>
    <p num="0102">When the aforementioned fine particles are used for the inkjet
recording sheet, they may also be preferably used in the aspects disclosed
in each publication of JP-A Nos. 10-81064, 10-119423, 10-157277, 10-217601,
11-348409, 2001-138621, 2000-43401, 2000-211235, 2000-309157,
2001-96897, 2001-138627, 11-91242, 8-2087, 8-2090, 8-2091,
8-2093, 8-174992, 11-192777, 2001-301314 and the like.</p>
    <heading>(Water-soluble resin)</heading>
    <p num="0103">Examples of the water-soluble resin include polyvinyl alcohol-based
resins which have a hydroxy group as a hydrophilic structure unit
[e.g., a polyvinyl alcohol (PVA), acetocetyl modified polyvinyl alcohol,
cation modified polyvinyl alcohol, anion modified polyvinyl alcohol, silanol
modified polyvinyl alcohol and polyvinylacetal], cellulose-based resins [e.g.,
methyl cellulose (MC), ethyl cellulose (EC), hydroxyethyl cellulose (HEC),
carboxymethyl cellulose (CMC), hydroxypropyl cellulose (HPC), 
hydroxyethylmethyl cellulose and hydroxypropylmethyl cellulose], chitins,
chitosans, starch, resins having an ether bond [e.g., polyethylene oxide
(PEO), polypropylene oxide (PPO), polyethylene glycol (PEG) and polyvinyl
ether (PVE)] and resins having a carbamoyl group [e.g., polyacrylamide
(PAAM), polyvinylpyrrolidone (PVP) and polyacrylic acid hydrazide].</p>
    <p num="0104">Also, polyacrylates, maleic acid resins, alginates and gelatins
which have a carboxyl group as a dissociable group may be given as
examples.</p>
    <p num="0105">Among the above resins, particularly polyvinyl alcohol-based resins
are preferable. Examples of the polyvinyl alcohol include those described
in JP-B Nos. 4-52786, 5-67432, 7-29479, JP No. 2537827, JP-B No. 7-57553,
JP Nos. 2502998, 3053231, JP-A No. 63-176173, JP No. 2604367,
JP-A Nos. 7-276787, 9-207425, 11-58941, 2000-135858, 2001-205924,
2001-287444, 62-278080, 9-39373, JP No. 2750433, JP-A Nos. 2000-158801,
2001-213045, 2001-328345, 8-324105, 11-348417 and the like.</p>
    <p num="0106">Also, examples of water-soluble resins other than polyvinyl
alcohol-based resins include compounds described in the paragraphs No.
0011 to No. 0014 of the publication of JP-A No. 11-165461.</p>
    <p num="0107">These water-soluble resins may be used either singly or in
combinations of two or more. The content of the aforementioned water-soluble
resin is preferably 9 to 40 mass % and more preferably 12 to 33
mass % relative to the total mass of solid components of the colorant-receiving
layer.</p>
    <p num="0108">The aforementioned water-soluble resin and the aforementioned
fine particle primarily constituting the colorant-receiving layer of the inkjet 
recording sheet may respectively be a single raw material or may use a mix
of raw materials.</p>
    <p num="0109">The type of water-soluble resin to be combined with a fine particle,
especially a silica fine particle, is important for maintaining transparency.
When the aforementioned vapor-phase method silica is used, polyvinyl
alcohol type resins are preferable as the water-soluble resin. Among
these resins, polyvinyl alcohol type resins having a saponification degree of
70 to 100% are more preferable and polyvinyl alcohol type resins having a
saponification degree of 80 to 99.5% are particularly preferable.</p>
    <p num="0110">The aforementioned polyvinyl alcohol type resin has a hydroxyl
group in its structural unit. Because this hydroxyl group and a silanol
group on the surface of the aforementioned silica fine particle form a
hydrogen bond, a three-dimensional network structure in which a
secondary particle of the silica fine particle forms a network chain unit is
easily formed. It is thought that a colorant-receiving layer having a
porous structure with a high aperture ratio and sufficient strength is
formed by the formation of this three-dimensional network structure.</p>
    <p num="0111">In inkjet recording, the porous colorant-receiving layer obtained in
the above manner absorbs ink rapidly by a capillary phenomenon and can
form a highly circular dot that is free from ink-bleeding.</p>
    <p num="0112">Also, the polyvinyl alcohol type resin may be used in combination
with the aforementioned other water-soluble resins. When a combination
of other water-soluble resins and the aforementioned polyvinyl alcohol
type resin is used, the content of the polyvinyl alcohol type resin in the
total water-soluble resin is preferably 50 mass % or more and more 
preferably 70 mass % or more.</p>
    <heading>&lt;Ratio of the mass of the fine particle to the mass of the water-soluble
resin&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0113">The content mass ratio of the fine particle (x) to the water-soluble
resin (y) [PB ratio (x/y)] in the colorant-receiving layer greatly affects the
film structure and also film strength of the colorant-receiving layer.
Namely, as the content mass ratio [PB ratio] increases, the aperture ratio,
pore volume and surface area (per unit mass) increase, but the density and
strength tend to decrease.</p>
    <p num="0114">The aforementioned content mass ratio [PB ratio (x/y)] of the
colorant-receiving layer according to the invention is preferably 1.5 to 10
with the view of preventing the film strength from being reduced and the
film from being cracked, during drying, because of an excess PB ratio and
also preventing the ink absorbancy from being reduced resulting from the
aperture being easily clogged by the resin and from the aperture ratio
being reduced because of an excessively small PB ratio.</p>
    <p num="0115">When a recording sheet is passed through a carrier system of an
inkjet printer, stress may be applied to the recording sheet. Therefore, it
is necessary for the colorant-receiving layer to have sufficient film strength.
Also, the colorant-receiving layer must have sufficient film strength to
prevent the cracking and the peeling of the colorant-receiving layer when
the recording sheet is cut into sheets. Taking these cases into account,
the aforementioned mass ratio (x/y) is more preferably 5 or less, whereas it
is preferably 2 or more with the view of securing high speed ink
absorbancy in an inkjet printer. </p>
    <p num="0116">For instance, when a coating liquid prepared by thoroughly
dispersing a vapor-phase method silica fine particle having an average
primary particle diameter of 20 nm or less and a water-soluble resin in a
mass ratio (x/y) of 2 to 5 in an aqueous solution is applied to a support
and the applied layer is dried, a three-dimensional network structure in
which a secondary particle of the silica fine particle forms a network chain
unit is formed, so that a translucent porous film having an average pore
diameter of 30 nm or less, a aperture ratio of 50 to 80 %, a pore specific
volume of 0.5 ml/g or more and a specific surface area of 100 m<sup>2</sup>/g or more
can be formed with ease.</p>
    <heading>(Crosslinking agent)</heading>
    <p num="0117">In a preferred aspect of the colorant-receiving layer of the inkjet
recording sheet of the invention, the coated layer containing the water-soluble
resin further contains a crosslinking agent capable of crosslinking
the water-soluble resin. In a more preferred aspect of the colorant-receiving
layer of the inkjet recording sheet of the invention, the coated
layer contains both the fine particles and the water-soluble resin, and the
coated layer is a porous layer, which is cured by the crosslinking reaction
between the crosslinking agent and the water-soluble resin.</p>
    <p num="0118">For the crosslinking of the aforementioned water-soluble resin,
especially, a polyvinyl alcohol-based resin and a boron compound are
desirable. Examples of the boron compound may include borax, boric
acid and borates (e.g., orthoborates, InBO<sub>3</sub>, ScBO<sub>3</sub>, YBO<sub>3</sub>, LaBO<sub>3</sub>,
Mg<sub>3</sub>(BO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>, Co<sub>3</sub>(BO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>, diborates (e.g., Mg<sub>2</sub>B<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> and Co<sub>2</sub>B<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>), methaborates
(e.g., LiBO<sub>2</sub>, Ca(BO<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>, NaBO<sub>2</sub> and KBO<sub>2</sub>), tetraborates (e.g., 
Na<sub>2</sub>B<sub>4</sub>O<sub>7</sub>·10H<sub>2</sub>O) and pentaborates (e.g., KB<sub>5</sub>O<sub>8</sub>·4H<sub>2</sub>O, Ca<sub>2</sub>B<sub>6</sub>O<sub>11</sub>·7H<sub>2</sub>O and
CsB<sub>5</sub>O<sub>5</sub>)). Among these boron compounds, borax, boric acid and borates
are preferable and boric acid is particularly preferable because these
boron compounds cause a crosslinking reaction promptly.</p>
    <p num="0119">As a crosslinking agent for the aforementioned water-soluble resin,
the following compound other than boron compounds may be used.</p>
    <p num="0120">Examples of the crosslinking agent include aldehyde-based
compounds such as formaldehyde, glyoxal, succinaldehyde
glutaraldehyde, dialdehyde starch, dialdehyde derivatives of plant gum;
ketone-based compounds such as diacetyl, 1,2-cyclopentanedione and 3-hexene-2,5-dione;
active halogen compounds such as bis(2-chloroethyl)urea,
bis(2-chloroethyl)sulfone, 2,4-dichloro-6-hydroxy-S-triazine·sodium
salt; active vinyl compounds such as divinylsulfone, 1,3-bis(vinylsulfonyl)-2-propanol,
N,N-ethylenebis(vinylsulfonylacetamide),
divinylketone, 1,3-bis(acryloyl)urea and 1,3,5-triacryloyl-hexahydro-S-triazine;
N-methylol compounds such as dimethylolurea and
methyloldimethylhydantoin; melamine compounds such as
trimethylolmelamine, alkylated methylolmelamine, melamine,
benzoguanamine and melamine resin; epoxy compounds such as
ethyleneglycol diglycidylether, propyleneglycol diglycidylether,
polyethyleneglycol diglycidylether, diglycerin polyglycidylether,
spyroglycol diglycidylether, polyglycidylether of phenol resin;</p>
    <p num="0121">isocyanate-based compounds such as 1,6-hexamethylenediisocyanate
and xylylenediisocyanate; aziridine type
compounds described in each of U.S. Patent Nos. 3017280 and 2983611; 
carbodiimide-based type compounds described in U.S. Patent No.
3100704; ethyleneimino-based compounds such as 1,6-hexamethylene-N,N'-bisethyleneurea;
halogenated carboxyaldehyde-based compounds
such as mucochloric acid and mucophenoxychloric acid; dioxane-based
compounds such as 2,3-dihydroxydioxane; compounds that include metal
such as titanium lactate, aluminum sulfate, chrome alum, potassium
alum, zirconyl acetate and chromium acetate; polyamine compounds such
as tetraethylenepentamine; hydrazide compounds such as dihydrazide
adipate; and low-molecular weight compounds or polymers having two or
more oxazoline groups; multivalent acid anhydrides described in each of
U.S. Patent Nos. 2725294, 2725295, 2726162 and 3834902; acid
chlorides; bissulfonate compounds; active ester compounds described in
each of U.S. Patent Nos.3542558 and 3251972.</p>
    <p num="0122">The aforementioned crosslinking agents may be used either singly
or in combinations of two or more.</p>
    <p num="0123">The crosslinking and curing are preferably carried out by adding a
crosslinking agent to a coating liquid (hereinafter sometimes referred to as
"coating liquid A") containing the fine particle, the water-soluble resin and
the like and/or the following basic solution, and by adding a basic solution
(hereinafter sometimes referred to as "coating liquid B") having a pH of 8 or
more to a coated layer either (1) at the same time when the coating liquid A
is applied to form the coated layer or (2) before the coated layer shows the
decreasing rate of drying during the course of drying the coated layer
formed by applying the coating liquid A. The provision of the
aforementioned crosslinking agent is preferably made in the following 
manner taking the case of a boron compound as an example. To state in
more detail, when the colorant-receiving layer is a layer obtained by
crosslinking and curing a coated layer prepared by applying a coating
liquid (coating liquid A) containing the fine particle and the water-soluble
resin containing polyvinyl alcohol, the crosslinking and curing are
preferably carried out by adding a basic solution (coating liquid B) having a
pH of 8 or more to the coated layer (1) at the same time when the coating
liquid A is applied to form the coated layer, or (2) before the coated layer
shows the decreasing rate of drying during the course of drying the coated
layer formed by applying the coating liquid A. The boron compound may
be contained as the crosslinking agent in either the coating liquid A or the
coating liquid B or may be contained in both the coating liquid A and the
coating liquid B.</p>
    <p num="0124">The amount of the crosslinking agent to be used is preferably 1 to
50 mass % and more preferably 5 to 40 mass %.</p>
    <heading>(Other mordants)</heading>
    <p num="0125">In the invention, other mordants shown below may be used
together with the organic mordant according to the invention to improve
the water resistance of the formed image and the bleeding of the formed
image with time.</p>
    <p num="0126">As other mordants, cationic polymers (cationic mordants) as
organic mordants or inorganic mordants are preferable. Including the
mordant in the colorant-receiving layer allows the mordant to interact with
liquid ink containing an anionic dye as a colorant to stabilize the colorant,
whereby the water resistance and the resistance to bleeding over time can 
be improved. The organic mordant and the inorganic mordant may be
used either independently or in combination with each other.</p>
    <p num="0127">The mordant is made to be present such that the thickness of the
portion where the mordant is present is 10 to 60 %, and preferably 20 to
40%, of the thickness of the receptor layer. When the thickness of the
mordant portion is less than 10%, the bleeding over time may increase
whereas when the thickness of the mordant portion exceeds 60 %, the
color density and the ozone resistance may decrease.</p>
    <p num="0128">As to a method for making the thickness of the portion where the
mordant is present fall within the above range, a mordant layer having a
predetermined thickness may be formed using an optional method, for
example: (1) a method in which a coated layer containing the fine particle
and the water-soluble resin is formed and a solution containing the
mordant is applied or (2) a method in which a coating liquid containing the
fine particle and the water-soluble resin and a solution containing the
mordant were applied in an overlaying manner to form a multilayer. Also,
the inorganic fine particle, water-soluble resin and crosslinking agent may
be contained in the mordant-containing solution.</p>
    <p num="0129">As the above cationic mordant, a polymer mordant containing
primary to tertiary amino groups or a quaternary ammonium salt group as
a cationic group is used. A cationic non-polymer mordant may also be
used.</p>
    <p num="0130">As the aforementioned polymer mordant, those obtained as a
homopolymer of a monomer (mordant monomer) having primary to tertiary
amino groups and salts thereof or a quaternary ammonium salt group, or 
as a copolymer or a condensed polymer of the mordant monomer and other
monomers (hereinafter refereed to as "non-mordant monomer") are
preferable. Also, these polymer mordants may be used in any of the
forms of a water-soluble polymer and a water-dispersible latex particle.</p>
    <p num="0131">Examples of the aforementioned monomer (mordant monomer)
include trimethyl-p-vinylbenzylammonium chloride, trimethyl-m-vinylbenzylammonium
chloride, triethyl-p-vinylbenzylammonium chloride,
triethyl-m-vinylbenzylammonium chloride, N,N-dimethyl-N-ethyl-N-p-vinylbenzylammonium
chloride, N,N-diethyl-N-methyl-N-p-vinylbenzylammonium
chloride, N,N-dimethyl-N-n-propyl-N-p-vinylbenzylammonium
chloride, N,N-dimethyl-N-n-octyl-N-p-vinylbenzylammonium
chloride, N,N-dimethyl-N-benzyl-N-p-vinylbenzylammonium
chloride, N,N-diethyl-N-benzyl-N-p-vinylbenzylammonium
chloride, N,N-dimethyl-N-(4-methyl)benzyl-N-p-vinylbenzylammonium
chloride, N,N-dimethyl-N-phenyl-N-p-vinylbenzylammonium
chloride;</p>
    <p num="0132">trimethyl-p-vinylbenzylammonium bromide, trimethyl-m-vinylbenzylammonium
bromide, trimethyl-p-vinylbenzylammonium
sulfonate, trimethyl-m-vinylbenzylammonium sulfonate, trimethyl-p-vinylbenzylammonium
acetate, trimethyl-m-vinylbenzylammonium
acetate, N,N,N-triethyl-N-2-(4-vinylphenyl)ethylammonium chloride,
N,N,N-triethyl-N-2-(3-vinylphenyl)ethylammonium chloride, N,N-diethyl-N-methyl-N-2-(4-vinylphenyl)ethylammonium
chloride, N,N-diethyl-N-methyl-N-2-(4-vinylphenyl)ethylammonium
acetate;</p>
    <p num="0133">methyl chloride, ethyl chloride, methyl bromide, ethyl bromide, 
methyl iodide or quaternary compounds of ethyl iodide of N,N-dimethylaminoethyl(meth)acrylate,
N,N-diethylaminoethyl(meth)acrylate,
N,N-dimethylaminopropyl(meth)acrylate, N,N-diethylaminopropyl(meth)acrylate,
N,N-dimethylaminoethyl(meth)acrylamide,
N,N-diethylaminoethyl(meth)acrylamide,
N,N-dimethylaminopropyl(meth)acrylamide
and N,N-diethylaminopropyl(meth)acrylamide
or sulfonates, alkylsulfonates,
acetates or alkylcarboxylates obtained by substituting anions of these
compounds.</p>
    <p num="0134">Specific examples of these salts include
monomethyldiallylammonium chloride, trimethyl-2-(methacryloyloxy)ethylammonium
chloride, triethyl-2-(methacryloyloxy)ethylammonium
chloride, trimethyl-2-(acryloyloxy)
ethylammonium chloride, triethyl-2-(acryloyloxy)ethylammonium
chloride, trimethyl-3-(methacryloyloxy)propylammonium
chloride, triethyl-3-(methacryloyloxy)propylammonium
chloride, trimethyl-2-(methacryloylamino)ethylammonium
chloride, triethyl-2-(methacryloylamino)ethylammonium
chloride, trimethyl-2-(acryloylamino)ethylammonium
chloride, triethyl-2-(aryloylamino)ethylammonium
chloride, trimethyl-3-(methacryloylamino)propylammonium
chloride, triethyl-3-(methacryloylamino)propylammonium
chloride, trimethyl-3-(acryloylamino)propylammonium
chloride, triethyl-3-(acryloylamino)propylammonium 
chloride,</p>
    <p num="0135">N,N-dimethyl-N-ethyl-2-(methacryloyloxy)ethylammonium chloride,
N,N-diethyl-N-methyl-2-(methacryloyloxy)ethylammonium chloride, N,N-dimethyl-N-ethyl-3-(acryloylamino)propylammonium
chloride, trimethyl-2-(methacryloyloxy)ethylammonium
bromide, trimethyl-3-(acryloylamino)propylammonium
bromide, trimethyl-2-(methacryloyloxy)ethylammonium
sulfonate and trimethyl-3-(acryloylamino)propylammonium
acetate.</p>
    <p num="0136">Other than the above, N-vinylimidazole and N-vinyl-2-methylimidazole
are given as examples of a copolymerizable monomer.</p>
    <p num="0137">Also, allylamine, diallylamine and their derivatives and salts may
be utilized. Examples of these compound include allylamine, allylamine
hydrochloride, allylamine acetate, allylamine sulfate, diallylamine,
diallylamine hydrochloride, diallylamine acetate, diallylamine sulfate,
diallylmethylamine and salts thereof (examples of the salts include
hydrochlorides, acetates and sulfates), diallylethylamine and salts thereof
(examples of the salt include hydrochlorides, acetates and sulfates),
diallyldimethylammonium salts (examples of a counter anion of the salt
include chlorides, acetic acid ions and sulfuric acid ions). It should be
noted that these allylamines and diallylamine derivatives are generally
polymerized in the form of a salt and then desalted according to the need
because they are inferior in polymerizing ability when they are in an amine
state.</p>
    <p num="0138">Also, a unit of N-vinylacetamide or N-vinylformamide may be used
and converted into a vinylamine unit by hydrolysis after polymerized and 
salts of these compounds may also be utilized.</p>
    <p num="0139">The aforementioned non-mordant monomers denote monomers,
which exclude primary to tertiary amino groups or salts thereof or a basic
or cationic portion such as a quaternary ammonium base and do not exert
an interaction with a dye contained in inkjet ink or exert a substantially
small interaction with the dye.</p>
    <p num="0140">Examples of the aforementioned non-mordant monomer include
alkyl(meth)acrylates; cycloalkyl(meth)acrylates such as
cyclohexyl(meth)acrylate; aryl(meth)acrylates such as
phenyl(meth)acrylate; aralkyl esters such as benzyl(meth)acrylate;
aromatic vinyls such as styrene, vinyltoluene and α-methylstyrene; vinyl
esters such as vinyl acetate and vinyl propionate; allyl esters such as allyl
acetate; halogen-containing monomers such as vinylidene chloride and
vinyl chloride; vinyl cyanates such as (meth)acrylonitrile; and olefins such
as ethylene and propylene.</p>
    <p num="0141">As the aforementioned alkyl(meth)acrylate, alkyl(meth)acrylates
with an alkyl portion having 1 to 18 carbon atoms are preferable.
Examples of the alkyl(meth)acrylates include methyl(meth)acrylate,
ethyl(meth)acrylate, propyl(meth)acrylate, isopropyl(meth)acrylate, n-butyl(meth)acrylate,
isobutyl(meth)acrylate, t-butyl(meth)acrylate,
hexyl(meth)acrylate, octyl(meth)acrylate, 2-ethylhexyl(meth)acrylate,
lauryl(meth)acrylate and stearyl(meth)acrylate. Among these compounds,
methylacrylate, ethylacrylate, methylmethacrylate, ethylmethacrylate and
hydroxyethylmethacrylate are preferable. The aforementioned non-mordant
monomers may be used either singly or in combinations of two or 
more.</p>
    <p num="0142">Further, preferable examples of the aforementioned polymer
mordant may include polydiallyldimethylammonium chloride,
polymethacryloyloxyethyl-β-hydroxyethyldimethylammonium chloride,
polyethyleneimine, polyamido-polyamine resins, cationic starch,
dicyandiamidoformalin condensates, dimethyl-2-hydroxypropylammonium
salt polymers, polyamidine, dicyan type cationic
resins represented by a dicyandiamido-formalin polycondensate,
polyamine type cationic resins represented by dicyanamido-diethylenetriamine
polycondensate, epichlorohydrin-dimethylamine
addition polymer, dimethyldialliinammonium chloride-SO<sub>2</sub> copolymers,
diallylamine salt-SO<sub>2</sub> copolymers, (meth)acrylate-containing polymers
having a quaternary ammonium base substituted alkyl group at the ester
portion and styryl type polymers having a quaternary ammonium base
substituted alkyl group.</p>
    <p num="0143">Specific examples of the aforementioned polymer mordant include
those described in: JP-A Nos. 48-28325, 54-74430, 54-124726, 55-22766,
55-142339, 60-23850, 60-23851, 60-23852, 60-23853, 60-57836, 60-60643,
60-118834, 60-122940, 60-122941, 60-122942, 60-235134 and
1-161236, U.S. Patent Nos. 2484430, 2548564, 3148061, 3309690,
4115124, 4124386, 4193800, 4273853, 4282305 and 4450224, and JP-A
Nos. 1-161236, 10-81064, 10-119423, 10-157277, 10-217601, 11-348409,
2001-138621, 2000-43401, 2000-211235, 2000-309157, 2001-96897,
2001-138627, 11-91242, 8-2087, 8-2090, 8-2091, 8-2093, 8-174992,
11-192777, 2001-301314, JP-B Nos. 5-35162, 5-35163, 5-35164, 
5-88846, JP-A Nos. 7-118333, 2000-344990, JP Nos. 2648847 and
2661677.</p>
    <p num="0144">When the phenolic compound according to the invention made to
be contained in the colorant-receiving layer, an organic acid or an
inorganic acid may be added. The acid may be mixed with the phenolic
compound in advance or may be mixed by applying a coating liquid
containing the phenolic compound either simultaneously or successively.</p>
    <p num="0145">The surface pH of the colorant-receiving layer is adjusted to be from
3 to 8 and preferably from 5 to 7.5 by adding an acid. This is preferable
because the anti-yellowing characteristics of a white ground portion is
improved. The surface pH is measured according to the A method
(application method) among the surface pH-measuring methods
determined by Japan Technical Association of Paper Pulp Industries (J.
TAPPI). For instance, the measurement can be made using a paper pH
measurement set "Form MPC" which corresponds to the above A method
and manufactured by Kyoritsu Rikagaku Kenkyujyo.</p>
    <p num="0146">Specific examples of the acid include formic acid, acetic acid,
glycolic acid, oxalic acid, propionic acid, malonic acid, succinic acid,
adipic acid, maleic acid, malic acid, tartaric acid, citric acid, benzoic acid,
phthalic acid, isophthalic acid, glutaric acid, gluconic acid, lactic acid,
aspartic acid, glutamic acid, salicylic acid, metal salts of salicylic acid
(salts of Zn, Al, Ca, Mg and the like), methanesulfonic acid, itaconic acid,
benzenesulfonic acid, toluenesulfonic acid, trifluoromethanesulfonic acid,
styrenesulfonic acid, trifluoroacetic acid, barbituric acid, acrylic acid,
methacrylic acid, cinnamic acid, 4-hydroxybenzoic acid, aminobenzoic 
acid, naphthalenedisulfonic acid, hydroxybenzenesulfonic acid,
toluenesulfinic acid, benzenesulfinic acid, sulfanilic acid, sulfamic acid,
α-resorcylic acid, β-resorcylic acid, γ-resorcylic acid, gallic acid,
fluoroglycine, sulfosalicylic acid, ascorbic acid, erysorbic acid, bisphenolic
acid, hydrochloric acid, nitric acid, sulfuric acid, phosphoric acid,
polyphosphoric acid, boric acid and boronic acid. The amount of each of
these acids may be determined such that the surface pH of the colorant-receiving
layer is from 3 to 8.</p>
    <p num="0147">The above acids may be used in the state of a metal salt (e.g., salts
of sodium, potassium, calcium, cesium, zinc, copper, iron, aluminum,
zirconium, lanthanum, yttrium, magnesium, strontium or cerium) or in
the state of an amine salt (e.g., ammonia, triethylamine, tributylamine,
piperazine, 2-methylpiperazine and polyallylamine).</p>
    <heading>(Other components)</heading>
    <p num="0148">The inkjet recording sheet of the invention may further contain
various known additives according to the need. Examples of these
additives include ultraviolet absorbers, antioxidants, fluorescent
whitening agents, monomers, polymerization initiators, polymerization
inhibitors, anti-bleeding agents, antiseptics, viscosity stabilizers,
antifoaming agent, surfactants, antistatic agents, matt agents, anti-curling
agents and waterproof agents.</p>
    <p num="0149">It is preferable to use the phenolic compound according to the
invention in combination with fastness improvers such as an ultraviolet
absorber, antioxidant and anti-bleeding agent.</p>
    <p num="0150">Examples of these ultraviolet absorber, antioxidant and anti-bleeding 
agent which may be used together include alkylated phenolic
compounds (including hindered phenolic compounds),
alkylthiomethylphenolic compounds, hydroquinone compounds, alkylated
hydroquinone compounds, tocopherol compounds, thiodiphenyl ether
compounds, compounds having two or more thio-ether bonds, bisphenolic
compounds, O-, N- and S-benzyl compounds, hydroxybenzyl compounds,
triazine compounds, phosphonate compounds, acylaminophenolic
compounds, ester compounds, amide compounds, ascorbic acid, amine
type antioxidants, 2-(2-hydroxyphenyl)benzotriazole compounds, 2-hydroxybenzophenone
compounds, acrylates, water-soluble or
hydrophobic metal salts, organic metal compounds, metal complexes,
hindered amine compounds (including TEMPO compounds), 2-(2-hydroxyphenyl)-1,3,5-triazine
compounds, metal deactivators, phosphite
compounds, phosphonite compounds, hydroxyamine compounds, nitron
compounds, peroxide scavengers, polyamide stabilizers, polyether
compounds, basic auxiliary stabilizers, nucleic agents, benzofuranone
compounds, indolinone compounds, phosphine compounds, polyamine
compounds, thiourea compounds, urea compounds, hydrazide
compounds, amidine compounds, sugar compounds, hydroxybenzoic acid
compounds, dihydroxybenzoic acid compounds and trihydroxybenzoic
acid compounds.</p>
    <p num="0151">Among these, it is preferable to use at least one or a combination of
two or more types selected from alkylated phenolic compounds,
compounds having two or more thioether bonds, bisphenolic compounds,
ascorbic acid, amine type antioxidants, water-soluble or hydrophobic 
metal salts, organic metal compounds, metal complexes, hindered amine
compounds, polyamine compounds, thiourea compounds, hydrazide
compounds, hydroxybenzoic acid compounds, dihydroxybenzoic acid
compounds and trihydroxybenzoic acid compounds.</p>
    <p num="0152">Specific examples of these compounds include those described in
JP-A Nos. 10-182621, 2001-260519, JP-B Nos. 4-34953, 4-34513, JP-A
No. 11-170686, Japanese Patent Application No. 2001-152237, JP-B No.
4-34512, EP1138509, JP-A Nos. 60-67190, 7-276808, 2001-94829, 47-10537,
58-111942, 58-212844, 59-19945, 59-46646, 59-109055, 63-53544,
JP-B Nos. 36-10466, 42-26187, 48-30492, 48-31255, 48-41572,
48-54965, 50-10726, U.S. patents Nos. 2,719,086, 3,707,375, 3,754,919
and 4,220,711;</p>
    <p num="0153">JP-B Nos. 45-4699, 54-5324,Europian Patent (Laid-open) Nos.
223739, 309401, 309402, 310551, 310552 and 459416, German Patent
(Laid-open) No. 3435443, JP-A Nos. 54-48535, 60-107384, 60-107383,
60-125470, 60-125471, 60-125472, 60-287485, 60-287486, 60-287487,
60-287488, 61-160287, 61-185483, 61-211079, 62-146678, 62-146680,
62-146679, 62-282885, 62-262047, 63-051174, 63-89877, 63-88380,
63-88381, 63-113536;</p>
    <p num="0154">63-163351, 63-203372, 63-224989, 63-251282, 63-267594, 63-182484,
1-239282, 2-262654, 2-71262, 3-121449, 4-291685, 4-291684,
5-61166, 5-119449, 5-188687, 5-188686, 5-110490, 5-1108437, 5-170361,
JP-B Nos. 48-43295, 48-33212, U.S. Patent Nos. 4814262,
4980275 and the like.</p>
    <p num="0155">These other components may be used either singly or in 
combinations of two or more. These components may be added after they
are water-solubilized, made dispersible, made polymer-dispersible,
emulsified or made to be oil droplets. Also they may be encapsulated in a
microcapsule. The amount of these components when they are added is
preferably 0.01 to 10 g/m<sup>2</sup>.</p>
    <p num="0156">Also, the surface of the inorganic fine particle may be processed
using a silane coupling agent with the intention of improving the
dispersibility of the inorganic fine particle. As the silane coupling agent,
those having, in addition to a portion carrying out a coupling process, an
organic functional groups (e.g., a vinyl group, amino group, epoxy group,
mercapto group, chloro group, alkyl group, phenyl group and ester group)
are preferable.</p>
    <p num="0157">In the invention, the colorant-receiving layer coating liquid
preferably contains a surfactant. As the surfactant, all cationic type,
anionic type, nonionic type, amphoteric type, fluorine type and silicon type
surfactants may be used.</p>
    <p num="0158">Examples of the above nonionic surfactant include polyoxyalkylene
alkyl ethers and polyoxyalkylene alkylphenyl ethers (e.g., diethylene glycol
monoethyl ether, diethylene glycol diethyl ether, polyoxyethylene lauryl
ether, polyoxyethylene stearyl ether and polyoxyethylene nonylphenyl
ether), oxyethylene oxypropylene block copolymers, sorbitan fatty acid
esters (e.g., sorbitan monolaurate, sorbitan monooleate and sorbitan
trioleate), polyoxyethylenesorbitan fatty acid esters (e.g.,
polyoxyethylenesorbitan monolaurate, polyoxyethylenesorbitan
monooleate and polyoxyethylenesorbitan trioleate), 
polyoxyethylenesorbitol fatty acid esters (e.g., polyoxyethylenesorbitol
tetraoleate), glycerol fatty acid esters (e.g., glycerol monooleate),
polyoxyethyleneglycerol fatty acid esters (e.g., polyoxyethyleneglycerol
monostearate and polyoxyethyleneglycerol monooleate), polyoxyethylene
fatty acid esters (polyethylene glycol monolaurate and polyethylene glycol
monooleate), polyoxyethylenealkylamine and acetylene glycols (e.g.,
2,4,7,9-tetramethyl-5-decyne-4,7-diol and ethyleneoxide adducts and
propyleneoxide adducts of the diol). Among these compounds, the
polyoxyalkylene alkyl ethers are preferable. The nonionic surfactant may
be used in the first coating liquid and in the second coating liquid. Also,
the above nonionic surfactants may be used either singly or in
combinations of two or more.</p>
    <p num="0159">Examples of the amphoteric surfactant include an amino acid type,
carboxyammoniumbetaine type, an sulfonammoniumbetaine type, an
ammonium sulfate betaine type and imidazolium betaine type. Examples
described, for example, in U.S. Patent No. 3,843,368, JP-A Nos. 59-49535,
63-236546, 5-303205, 8-262742, 10-282619, and the like, may be
preferably used. As the amphoteric surfactant, amino acid type
amphoteric surfactants are preferable. Examples of the amino acid type
amphoteric surfactant include N-aminoacylic acids which are derived from
an amino acids (e.g., glycine, glutamic acid and histidic acid) and into
which a long-chain acyl group is introduced, and salts thereof. The
aforementioned amphoteric surfactants may be used either singly or in
combinations of two or more.</p>
    <p num="0160">Examples of the aforementioned anionic surfactant include fatty 
acid salts (e.g., sodium stearate and potassium oleate), alkyl sulfates (e.g.,
sodium laurylsulfate and triethanolamine laurylsulfate), sulfonates (e.g.,
sodium dodecylbenzenesulfonate), alkyl sulfosuccinates (e.g., sodium
dioctylsulfosuccinate), alkyl diphenyl ether disulfonates and alkyl
phosphates.</p>
    <p num="0161">Examples of the aforementioned cationic surfactant include
alkylamine salts, quaternary ammonium salts, pyridinium salts and
imidazolium salts.</p>
    <p num="0162">Examples of the aforementioned fluorine type surfactant include
compounds derived through an intermediate having a perfluoroalkyl group
by using a method such as electrolytic fluorination, telomerization or
oligomerization. For example, perfluoroalkyl sulfonates, perfluoroalkyl
carboxylates, perfluoroalkylethylene oxide adducts,
perfluoroalkyltrialkylammonium salts, perfluoroalkyl group-containing
oligomers and perfluoroalkyl phosphates.</p>
    <p num="0163">As the aforementioned silicon type surfactant, silicon oil modified
by an organic group and the silicon oil may have a structure in which the
side chain of a siloxane structure is modified by an organic group, a
structure in which both terminals are modified or a structure in which one
terminal is modified. Examples of the organic group modification include
an amino modification, polyether modification, epoxy modification,
carboxyl modification, carbinol modification, alkyl modification, aralkyl
modification, phenol modification and fluorine modification.</p>
    <p num="0164">The content of the surfactant in the invention is preferably from
0.001 to 2.0% and more preferably from 0.01 to 1.0% based on the 
colorant-receiving layer coating liquid. Also, when two or more liquids
are used as the colorant-receiving layer coating liquid, it is preferable to
add the surfactant to each coating liquid.</p>
    <heading>(High-boiling point organic solvent)</heading>
    <p num="0165">In the invention, the colorant-receiving layer preferably contains a
high-boiling point organic solvent for preventing curling. The
aforementioned high-boiling point organic solvent is a water-soluble or
hydrophobic organic compound having a boiling point of 150°C or more
under normal pressure. These organic solvents may be a liquid or a solid
at ambient temperature and may be a low molecule or a high molecule.</p>
    <p num="0166">Specific examples of the organic solvent include aromatic
carboxylates (e.g., dibutyl phthalate, diphenyl phthalate and phenyl
benzoate), aliphatic carboxylates (e.g., dioctyl adipate, dibutyl sebacate,
methyl stearate, dibutyl maleate, dibutyl fumarate and triethyl
acetylcitrate), phosphates (e.g., trioctyl phosphate and tricrezyl
phosphate), epoxies (e.g., epoxidated soybean oil and epoxidated fatty acid
methyl), alcohols (e.g., stearyl alcohol, ethylene glycol, propylene glycol,
diethylene glycol, triethylene glycol, glycerol, diethylene glycol monobutyl
ether (DEGMBE), triethylene glycol monobutyl ether, glycerol monomethyl
ether, 1,2,3-butanetriol, 1,2,4-butanetriol, 1,2,4-pentanetriol, 1,2,6-hexanetriol,
thiodiglycol, triethanolamine and polyethylene glycol),
vegetable oils (e.g., soybean oil and sunflower oil) and higher aliphatic
carboxylic acids (e.g., linoleic acid and oleic acid).</p>
    <heading>(Support)</heading>
    <p num="0167">As the support, a transparent support made of a transparent 
material such as a plastic or an opaque support made of an opaque
material such as paper may be used. It is preferable to use a transparent
support or a highly glossy opaque support to make use of the transparency
of the colorant-receiving layer.</p>
    <p num="0168">Materials usable for the aforementioned transparent support are
preferably those which are transparent and have qualities enough to
endure radiated heat when the recording sheet is used for OHPs and back
light displays. Examples of the material include polyesters such as
polyethylene terephthalate (PET); polysulfones, polyphenylene oxides,
polyimides, polycarbonates and polyamides. Among these materials,
polyesters are preferable and polyethylene terephthalates are particularly
preferable.</p>
    <p num="0169">Although there are no particular limitations to the thickness of the
aforementioned transparent support, the thickness is preferably 50 to 200
µm from the viewpoint of handling easiness.</p>
    <p num="0170">As the highly glossy opaque support, supports for which the
surface on the side on which the colorant-receiving layer is disposed have
a glossiness of 40% or more are preferable. The aforementioned
glossiness is defined as a value determined according to the method
described in JIS P-8142 (Test method for glossiness of a 75 degree mirror
surface of paper and paper board). Given as specific examples of such a
support are the following supports.</p>
    <p num="0171">Examples of the opaque support include highly glossy paper
supports such as art paper, coated paper, cast coated paper and baryta
paper which are used for a silver salt photographic supports; highly glossy 
films which are prepared and made opaque (may be processed by surface
calender treatment) by including a white pigment in a plastic film such as
polyesters such as polyethylene terephthalate (PET), cellulose esters such
as nitrocellulose, cellulose acetate and cellulose acetate butyrate,
polysulfone, polyphenylene oxide, polyimide, polycarbonate and
polyamide; or supports prepared by forming a polyolefin coated layer
containing or not containing a white pigment on each surface of the
aforementioned various paper support, the aforementioned transparent
supports or highly glossy films containing a white pigment or the like.</p>
    <p num="0172">White pigment-containing foam polyester films (e.g., foam PETs
which are made to contain a polyolefin fine particle and in which apertures
are formed by drawing) may be preferably given as examples. Moreover,
resin-coated paper to be used for silver salt photographic print paper is
also preferable.</p>
    <p num="0173">Although there is no particular limitations to the thickness of the
aforementioned opaque support, the thickness is preferably 50 to 300 µm
in view of handling characteristics.</p>
    <p num="0174">The aforementioned supports whose surface is processed by corona
discharge treatment, glow discharge treatment, flame treatment or
ultraviolet radiation treatment to improve wettability and adhesiveness
may be used.</p>
    <p num="0175">Next, base paper to be used for the aforementioned resin coated
paper will be explained in detail.</p>
    <p num="0176">The aforementioned base paper is made using wood pulp as a major
raw material and synthetic pulp such as polypropylene or synthetic fiber 
such as nylon or polyester in addition to the wood pulp as required.
Although any of LBKP, LBSP, NBKP, NBSP, LDP, NDP, LUKP and NUKP
may be used as the wood pulp, it is preferable to use LBKP, NBSP, LBSP,
NDP and LDP, which have a high proportion of short fibers in a large
amount.</p>
    <p num="0177">However, the ratio of LBSP and/or LDP is preferably 10 mass % or
more and 70 mass % or less.</p>
    <p num="0178">As the aforementioned pulp, chemical pulps (sulfate pulp and
sulfite pulp), which are reduced in impurities, are preferably used and
pulps which are improved in whiteness by performing bleaching treatment,
are useful.</p>
    <p num="0179">Sizing agents such as a higher fatty acid and alkylketene dimer,
white pigments such as calcium carbonate, talc and titanium oxide, paper
force strengthening agents such as starch, polyacrylamide and polyvinyl
alcohol, fluorescent whitening agents, water retentive agents such as
polyethylene glycol, dispersants, softening agents such as quaternary
ammonium, and the like may be added to the base paper as appropriate.</p>
    <p num="0180">The freeness of the pulp used in paper-making is preferably 200 to
500 ml in terms of value according to the provision of CSF. Also, as for
the fiber length after being beaten, the sum of 24 mesh residue mass %
and 42 mesh residue mass % prescribed in JIS P-8207 is preferably 30 to
70 %, and that the 4 mesh residue mass % is preferably 20 mass % or less.</p>
    <p num="0181">The basis weight of the base paper is preferably 30 to 250 g and
particularly preferably 50 to 200 g. The thickness of the base paper is
preferably 40 to 250 µm. The base paper may be provided with high 
smoothness by calendering in a paper-making stage or after paper-making.
The density of the base paper is usually 0.7 to 1.2 g/m<sup>2</sup> (JIS P-8118).</p>
    <p num="0182">Further, the rigidity of the base paper is preferably 20 to 200 g
under the conditions prescribed in JIS P-8143.</p>
    <p num="0183">A surface sizing agent may be applied to the surface of the base
paper. As the surface sizing agent, the same sizing agents as those which
may be added to the aforementioned base paper may be used.</p>
    <p num="0184">The pH of the base paper is preferably 5 to 9 when measured using
a hot-water extraction method prescribed in JIS P-8113.</p>
    <p num="0185">The polyethylene with which the surface and backface of the base
paper are coated is primarily low density polyethylene (LDPE) and/or high
density polyethylene (HDPE). Other linear low density polyethylene
(LLDPEs), polypropylene or the like may be used as a part of the
polyethylene.</p>
    <p num="0186">Particularly, the polyethylene layer on the side on which the
colorant-receiving layer is formed is preferably improved in opacity,
whiteness and hue by adding rutile or anatase type titanium oxide, a
fluorescent whitening agent and ultramarine blue to polyethylene in the
manner in which photographic print paper in a wide field is processed.
Here, the content of titanium oxide is preferably about 3 to 20 mass % and
more preferably 4 to 13 mass % based on the polyethylene. Although no
particular limitations are imposed on the thickness of the polyethylene
layer, it is preferably 10 to 50 µm on both of the surface and the backface.
Further, an undercoat layer may be disposed on the polyethylene layer to
impart adhesion to the colorant-receiving layer. As the undercoat layer, 
an aqueous polyester, gelatin and PVA are preferably used. Also, the
thickness of the undercoat layer is preferably 0.01 to 5 µm.</p>
    <p num="0187">The polyethylene coated paper may be used as glossy paper. Also,
polyethylene coated paper formed with a matted surface or silky pattern
surface, which is obtained from usual photographic print paper, by
performing so-called marking treatment when polyethylene is melt-extruded
on the surface of the base paper to carry out coating may also be
used as the polyethylene coated paper.</p>
    <p num="0188">The support may be provided with a back coat layer. Examples of
compounds which may be added to the back coat layer include white
pigments, aqueous binders and other components.</p>
    <p num="0189">Examples of the white pigment contained in the back coat layer
include white inorganic pigments such as light calcium carbonate, heavy
calcium carbonate, kaolin, talc, calcium sulfate, barium sulfate, titanium
dioxide, zinc oxide, zinc sulfide, zinc carbonate, satin white, aluminum
silicate, diatomaceous earth, calcium silicate, magnesium silicate,
synthetic amorphous silica, colloidal silica, colloidal alumina, pseudo-boehmite,
aluminum hydroxide, alumina, lithopone, zeolite, hydrated
halloysite, magnesium carbonate and magnesium hydroxide and organic
pigments such as styrene type plastic pigments, acrylic plastic pigments,
polyethylene, microcapsules, urea resins and melamine resins.</p>
    <p num="0190">Examples of the aqueous binder used for the back coat layer
include water-soluble polymers such as a styrene/maleate copolymer,
styrene/acrylate copolymer, polyvinyl alcohol, silanol modified polyvinyl
alcohol, starch, cationic starch, casein, gelatin, carboxymethyl cellulose, 
hydroxyethyl cellulose and polyvinylpyrrolidone and water-dispersible
polymers such as a styrenebutadiene latex and acrylic emulsion.</p>
    <p num="0191">Examples of other components to be contained in the back coat
layer include antifoaming agents, foam suppressors, dyes, fluorescent
whitening agents, antiseptics and waterproof agents.</p>
    <heading>(Production of an inkjet recording sheet)</heading>
    <p num="0192">The colorant-receiving layer of the inkjet recording sheet of the
invention is preferably formed using a Wet-on-Wet method. In this
method, the colorant-receiving layer is formed by a process including the
steps of: preparing a coating liquid containing at least fine particles and a
water-soluble resin; preparing a basic solution having a pH value of at
least 8; adding a crosslinking agent to at least one of the coating liquid and
the basic solution; applying the coating liquid to form a coated layer;
drying the coated layer; crosslinking and curing the coated layer by adding
the basic solution to the coated layer at a time that is at least one of (1)
simultaneous with the step of applying the coating liquid to form the
coated layer, and (2) before the coated layer exhibits a decreasing rate of
drying during the step of drying the coated layer.</p>
    <p num="0193">The crosslinking agent capable of crosslinking the aforementioned
water-soluble resin is preferably contained in either one or both of the
aforementioned coating liquid and basic solution. Providing of the
colorant-receiving layer crosslinked and cured in the above manner is
preferable from the viewpoints of ink absorbancy and prevention of
cracking of the film.</p>
    <p num="0194">The mordant is made to be present such that the thickness, from 
the surface of the mordant, of the portion where the mordant is present is
10 to 60 % of the thickness of the receptor layer. The mordant portion
may be formed using a desired method such as (1) a method in which a
coated layer containing the aforementioned fine particle, water-soluble
resin and crosslinking agent is formed and a mordant-containing solution
is applied to the coated layer and (2) a method in which the coating liquid
containing the aforementioned fine particle and water-soluble resin and a
mordant-containing solution are applied in an overlaying manner. Also,
the aforementioned inorganic fine particle, water-soluble resin,
crosslinking agent and the like may be contained in the mordant-containing
solution.</p>
    <p num="0195">The aforementioned process allows a lot of mordant to exist at a
predetermined portion of the colorant-receiving layer. Therefore, the
colorant of an inkjet is sufficiently mordanted and the color density, the
bleeding over time, the glossiness of a print portion and the water-resistance
and ozone resistance of characters and images after printing
are improved and therefore, the above process is preferred. A part of the
mordant may be contained in a layer formed first on the support. In this
case, a mordant added afterwards may be the same as or different from the
above mordant.</p>
    <p num="0196">In the invention, the colorant-receiving layer coating liquid (coating
liquid A) containing at least the fine particle (for example, vapor-phase
method silica) and the water-soluble resin (e.g., polyvinyl alcohol) may be
prepared, for example, in the following manner.</p>
    <p num="0197">Specifically, the fine particle, such as vapor-phase method silica, 
and a dispersant are added to water (the content of the silica fine particle
in water is 10 to 20 mass %) and dispersed under the condition of being
rotated at speeds as high as, for example, 10000 rpm (preferably 5000 to
20000 rpm) for 20 minutes (preferably 10 to 30 minutes) using a high
rotation wet colloid mill (for example, "Clearmix" manufactured by M
Technique Co., Ltd.) An aqueous polyvinyl alcohol (PVA) solution is
added (such that the mass of PVA is about 1/3 of that of the
aforementioned vapor-phase silica) to the dispersion and dispersed under
the same rotation conditions as above, whereby the coating liquid for the
colorant-receiving layer can be prepared. It is preferable to adjust the
solution to pH 9.2 using aqueous ammonia or to use a dispersant to
prepare a stable coating liquid. The resulting coating liquid, which is in a
uniform sol state, is applied to the support using the following application
method and dried, whereby a porous colorant-receiving layer having a
three-dimensional network structure can be formed.</p>
    <p num="0198">As a dispersing machine used to obtain the water dispersion,
various conventionally-known dispersing machines, such as a high
rotation dispersing machine, medium stirring type dispersing machine
(e.g., a ball mill and sand mill), ultraviolet dispersing machine, colloid mill
dispersing machine and high pressure dispersing machine may be used.
The medium stirring type dispersing machine, the colloid mill dispersing
machine and the high pressure dispersing machine are preferable for
dispersing the formed dimer fine particle in an efficient manner.</p>
    <p num="0199">Also, as the solvent used in each step, water, an organic solvent or
a mixture of these solvents may be used. Examples of the organic solvent 
which may be used for this application include alcohols such as methanol,
ethanol, n-propanol, i-propanol and methoxypropanol, ketones such as
acetone and methyl ethyl ketone, tetrahydrofuran, acetonitrile, ethyl
acetate and toluene.</p>
    <p num="0200">Also, as the aforementioned dispersant, a cationic polymer may be
used. Examples of the cationic polymer are the same as those for the
mordant. Also, as the dispersant, a silane coupling agent is preferably
used.</p>
    <p num="0201">The amount of the aforementioned dispersant to be added to the
fine particle is preferably 0.1% to 30% and more preferably 1% to 10%.</p>
    <p num="0202">The application of the colorant-receiving layer coating liquid may
be carried out using a known coating method using an extrusion die coater,
air doctor coater, blade coater, rod coater, knife coater, squeeze coater,
reverse roll coater or bar coater.</p>
    <p num="0203">At the same time when or after the colorant-receiving layer coating
liquid (coating liquid A) is applied, the basic solution (coating liquid B) is
added to the coated layer. The coating liquid B may be added before the
applied coated layer shows the decreasing rate of drying. Namely, the
inkjet recording sheet is appropriately produced by introducing the basic
solution (coating liquid B) before the coated layer shows the decreasing
rate of drying after the colorant-receiving layer coating liquid (coating
liquid A) is applied. This coating liquid B may be made to contain a
mordant.</p>
    <p num="0204">Here, the aforementioned term "before the coated layer shows the
decreasing rate of drying" generally indicates a period of several minutes 
from just after the colorant-receiving layer coating liquid is applied.
During this period, a "constant drying rate" phenomenon that the content
of a solvent (dispersion medium) in the coated layer decreases in
proportion to time occurs. The time during which this "constant drying
rate" is shown is described in, for example, Chemical Engineering
Handbook (Maruzen, October 25 (1980), pp.707-712).</p>
    <p num="0205">As mentioned above, after the coating liquid A is applied, the coated
layer is dried until it shows the decreasing rate of drying. This drying is
carried out usually at 40 to 180°C for 0.5 to 10 minutes (preferably 0.5 to
5 minutes). This drying time preferably falls in the above range in general
though it, of course, differs depending on the amount to be applied.</p>
    <p num="0206">Examples of a method of adding the coating liquid B before the
aforementioned first coated layer shows the decreasing rate of drying
include (1) a method in which the coating liquid B is further applied to the
coated layer, (2) a method in which the coating liquid B is sprayed by, for
example, a spraying method and (3) a method, in which the support having
the coated layer formed thereon is dipped in the coating liquid B.</p>
    <p num="0207">As a coating method for applying the coating liquid B in the
aforementioned method (1), known coating methods using a curtain flow
coater, extrusion die coater, air doctor coater, blade coater, rod coater,
knife coater, squeeze coater, reverse roll coater or bar coater may be
utilized. However, it is preferable to utilize a method in which the coater
is not directly brought into contact with the first coated layer which has
been already formed like the case of an extrusion die coater, curtain flow
coater and bar coater. </p>
    <p num="0208">After the coating liquid B is added, it is heated generally at 40 to
180°C for 0.5 to 30 minutes to carry out drying and curing. Among these
conditions, it is preferable to heat at 40 to 150°C for 1 to 20 minutes.</p>
    <p num="0209">Also, in the case of adding the aforementioned basic solution
(coating liquid B) simultaneously when the colorant-receiving layer coating
liquid (coating liquid A) is applied, the coating liquid A and the coating
liquid B are applied (overlaying coating) to the support at the same time
such that the coating liquid A is brought into contact with the support and
then dried and cured whereby the colorant-receiving layer can be formed.</p>
    <p num="0210">The aforementioned simultaneous application (overlaying coating)
may be carried out using a coating method using an extrusion die coater or
curtain flow coater. The coated layer formed after the simultaneous
application is dried. The drying at this time is usually performed by
heating the coated layer at 40 to 150°C for 0.5 to 10 minutes and
preferably at 40 to 100°C for 0.5 to 5 minutes.</p>
    <p num="0211">When the aforementioned simultaneous application (overlaying
coating) is carried out using, for example, an extrusion die coater, two
coating liquids discharged simultaneously are overlaid with each other in
the vicinity of the discharge port of the extrusion die coater, namely, before
these solutions are transferred to the support, and applied to the support
in an overlaid manner in this state. The two layer coating liquids overlaid
before being applied tend to enter into a crosslinking reaction at the
boundary between the both solutions when transferring to the support.
For this, the discharged two liquids are mixed so that the viscosity tend to
increase in the vicinity of the discharged port of the extrusion die coater 
and there is the case where the coating operation is hindered. Therefore,
when performing the simultaneous application as described above, a
barrier layer liquid (intermediate layer liquid) is preferably interposed
between the aforementioned both liquids simultaneously, when the
coating liquid A and the coating liquid B are applied, to perform
simultaneous application of a triple layer.</p>
    <p num="0212">The barrier layer liquid may be selected without particular
limitation. An aqueous solution containing trace amounts of a water-soluble
resin and water may be given as an example. The aforementioned
water-soluble resin is used in consideration of coatability for the purpose
of fanctioning a thickener and the like. Examples of the water-soluble
resin include cellulose type resins (e.g., hydroxypropylmethyl cellulose,
methyl cellulose and hydroxyethylmethyl cellulose), polyvinylpyrrolidone
and polymers such as gelatin. It is noted that the barrier layer liquid may
contain the aforementioned mordant.</p>
    <p num="0213">After the colorant-receiving layer is formed on the support,
calendering treatment is performed by making the support pass between
roll nips while applying heat and pressure, using a super calender or gloss
calender, whereby the colorant-receiving layer can be improved in surface
smoothness, glossiness, transparency and film strength. However,
because the calendering treatment sometimes causes the aperture ratio to
decrease (namely, because it sometimes causes a reduction in ink
absorbancy), it is necessary that a condition are set under which the
decrease of aperture ratio is reduced to carry out the treatment.</p>
    <p num="0214">The temperature of the roll when performing the calendering 
treatment is preferably 30 to 150°C and more preferably 40 to 100°C.</p>
    <p num="0215">The line pressure between the rolls when performing the
calendering treatment is preferably 50 to 400 kg/cm and more preferably
100 to 200 kg/cm.</p>
    <p num="0216">The thickness of the aforementioned colorant-receiving layer must
be determined in relation to the aperture ratio in the layer because it is
required for the colorant-receiving layer to have an absorbing capacity
sufficient to absorb all liquid droplets. In the case where, for example, the
amount of ink is 8 nL/mm<sup>2</sup> and the aperture ratio is 60 %, a film having a
thickness of about 15 µm or more is required.</p>
    <p num="0217">Taking this point into account, the thickness of the colorant-receiving
layer is preferably 10 to 50 µm in the case of inkjet recording.</p>
    <p num="0218">The pore diameter of the colorant-receiving layer is preferably
0.005 to 0.030 µm and more preferably 0.01 to 0.025 µm in terms of
median diameter.</p>
    <p num="0219">The aforementioned aperture ratio and pore median diameter may
be measured using a mercury porosimeter ("Pore Sizer 9320-PC2"
(Trademark), manufactured by Shimadzu Corporation).</p>
    <p num="0220">Also, the colorant-receiving layer preferably has high transparency.
As to the standard of the transparency, the haze value when the
colorant-receiving layer is formed on a transparent film support is
preferably 30 % or less and more preferably 20 % or less.</p>
    <p num="0221">The above haze value may be measured using a haze meter (HGM-2DP,
manufactured by Suga Test Instrument Co. Ltd.).

A polymer fine particle dispersion may be added to the structural layers 
(e.g., the colorant-receiving layer and the back layer) of the inkjet
recording sheet of the invention. This polymer fine particle dispersion is
used with the intention of improving film qualities such as dimensional
stability, prevention of curling, prevention of adhesion and prevention of
cracking of the film. There are descriptions concerning the polymer fine
particle dispersion in JP-A Nos. 62-245258, 62-1316648 and 62-110066.
In this case, if a polymer fine particle dispersion having a low glass
transition temperature (40°C or less) is added to the aforementioned
mordant-containing layer, cracking and curling of the layer can be
prevented. Also, even the addition of a polymer fine particle dispersion
having a high glass transition temperature to the back layer can prevent
curling.</p>
    <heading>EXAMPLES</heading>
    <p num="0222">The present invention will be explained in more detail by way of
examples, which are not intended to be limiting of the invention. In the
examples, all designations of "parts" and "%" indicate "mass parts" and
"mass percentage (mass %)", respectively, unless otherwise noted and the
designation of "polymerization degree" indicates "mass average
polymerization degree".</p>
    <heading>(Production of a support)</heading>
    <p num="0223">Wood pulp consisting of 100 parts of LBKP was beaten down to a
Canadian Freeness of 300 ml by using a double disk refiner, to which was
then added 0.5 parts of epoxidated behenic acid amide, 1.0 parts of
anionic polyacrylamide, 0.1 parts of polyamidopolyamineepichlorohydrin 
and 0.5 parts of cationic polyacrylamide, wherein each amount is
expressed by absolute dry mass ratio to the pulp, to thereby produce using
a Fourdrinier paper machine, base paper weighing 170 g/m<sup>2</sup>.</p>
    <p num="0224">In order to regulate the surface size of the above base paper, 0.04%
of a fluorescent whitening agent ("Whitex BB", manufactured by Sumitomo
Chemical Co., Ltd.) was added to an aqueous 4% polyvinyl alcohol solution.
The above base paper was impregnated with the resulting solution such
that the amount of the solution was 0.5 g/m<sup>2</sup> converted into absolute dry
mass and the solution was dried, followed by further performing
calendering treatment to obtain substrate paper adjusted to a density of
1.05 g/cc.</p>
    <p num="0225">The wire side (backface side) of the resulting substrate paper was
processed by corona discharge treatment and then coated with high
density polyethylene using a melt extruder such that the thickness of
polyethylene was 19 µm to form a resin layer with a matted surface
(hereinafter the resin layer side is referred to as a "backside"). The resin
layer on this backside was further processed by corona discharge
treatment. Then, a dispersion in which aluminum oxide ("Alumina Sol
100", manufactured by Nissan Chemical Industries, Ltd.) and silicon
dioxide ("Snowtex O", manufactured by Nissan Chemical Industries, Ltd.)
were dispersed as antistatic agents in a mass ratio of 1:2 was applied to
the resin layer such that the dry mass was 0.2 g/m<sup>2</sup>.</p>
    <p num="0226">Furthermore, the felt side (surface) on the side on which no resin
layer was formed was processed by corona discharge treatment. Then,
low density polyethylene containing 10% of anatase type titanium dioxide, 
a trace amount of ultramarine blue and 0.01% (based on polyethylene) of a
fluorescent whitening agent was extruded at a MFR (melt flow rate) of 3.8
by using a melt extruder such that the thickness was 29 µm to form a
highly glossy thermoplastic resin layer on the surface side of the substrate
paper (hereinafter this highly glossy surface is referred to as a "front
surface"), thereby making a support.</p>
    <heading>(Example 1)</heading>
    <heading>
      <i>Preparation of a colorant-receiving layer coating liquid A</i>
    </heading>
    <p num="0227">
      <sl>
        <li>(1) A vapor-phase method silica fine particle, (2) ion exchange water and (3)
"PAS-M-1" in the composition described below were mixed and dispersed
using high speed rotating type colloid mill ("Clearmix", manufactured by M
technique Co., Ltd.) at a rotation of 10000 rpm for 20 minutes. Then, a
solution containing (4) polyvinyl alcohol, (5) boric acid, (6) polyoxyethylene
lauryl ether and (7) ion exchange water described below was added to the
above mixture, which was dispersed again at a rotation of 10000 rpm for
20 minutes to prepare a colorant-receiving layer coating liquid A.</li>
      </sl>
    </p>
    <p num="0228">The mass ratio (PB ratio: (1):(4)) of the silica fine particle to the
water-soluble resin was 4.5:1 and the pH of the colorant-receiving layer
coating liquid A was 3.5, showing that the resulting solution was acidic.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">&lt;Composition of the colorant-receiving layer coating liquid A&gt;</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(1) Vapor-phase method silica fine particle (inorganic fine particle) ("Reolosil QS 30", manufactured by Tokuyama, average primary particle diameter: 7 nm)</entry><entry align="left">10 parts</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(2) Ion exchange water</entry><entry align="left">51.7 parts</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(3) "PAS-M-1" (aqueous 60% solution) (dispersant, manufactured by Nittobo)</entry><entry align="left">0.83 parts </entry></row><row><entry align="left">(4) Polyvinyl alcohol (water-soluble resin), 8% aqueous solution ("PVA 124", manufactured by Kuraray Co., Ltd., saponification value: 98.5%, degree of polymerization: 2400)</entry><entry align="left">27.8 parts</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(5) Boric acid (crosslinking agent)</entry><entry align="left">0.4 parts</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(6) Polyoxyethylene lauryl ether (surfactant) ("Emulgen 109P", manufactured by Kao Corporation, (aqueous 10% solution), HLB value: 13.6)</entry><entry align="left">1.2 parts</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(7) Ion exchange water</entry><entry align="left">33.0 parts</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <heading>
      <i>Preparation of an inkjet recording sheet</i>
    </heading>
    <p num="0229">The front surface of the aforementioned support was processed by
corona discharge treatment. Thereafter, the colorant-receiving layer
coating liquid A obtained above was applied to the front surface of the
support using an extrusion die coater such that the amount to be applied
was 200 ml/m<sup>2</sup> (coating step). The coated layer was dried using a hot air
drier at 80°C (air-speed: 3 to 8 m/sec) until the solid concentration of the
coated layer was 20%. This coated layer showed the decreasing rate of
drying during this period. Just after the drying was finished, the
resulting support was immersed in a mordant solution B having the
composition described below for 30 minutes to stick 20 g/m<sup>2</sup> of the
mordant solution to the coated layer (step of adding the mordant solution)
and further the mordant solution B was dried at 80°C for 10 minutes
(drying step). By this treatment, the inkjet recording sheet (1) provided
with the colorant-receiving layer having a dried film thickness of 32 µm
according to the invention was produced. <tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">&lt;Composition of the mordant solution B&gt;</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(1) Boric acid (crosslinking agent)</entry><entry align="left">0.65 parts</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(2) Polyallylamine "PAA-10C", aqueous 10% solution (mordant, manufactured by Nittobo)</entry><entry align="left">25 parts</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(3) Compound (a) described below (compound according to the invention)</entry><entry align="left">2.5 parts</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(4) Ion exchange water</entry><entry align="left">59.7 parts</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(5) Ammonium chloride (surface pH regulator)</entry><entry align="left">0.8 parts</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(6) Polyoxyethylene lauryl ether (surfactant) ("Emulgen 109P", manufactured by Kao Corporation, aqueous 2% solution), HLB value: 13.6)</entry><entry align="left">10 parts</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(7) Megafac "F1405", aqueous 10% solution (fluorine type surfactant, manufactured by Dainippon Ink and Chemicals, Incorporated)</entry><entry align="left">2.0 parts</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <heading>(Examples 2 to 7)</heading>
    <p num="0230">Inkjet recording sheets (2) to (7) according to the invention were
produced in the same manner as in Example 1, except that the compound
(a) was changed to each of the following compounds (b) to (g) in the
composition of the mordant solution B of Example 1. <img id="img-00730001" orientation="unknown" wi="128" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00730001.tif" inline="no" he="46"/><img id="img-00730002" orientation="unknown" wi="129" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00730002.tif" inline="no" he="38"/><img id="img-00730003" orientation="unknown" wi="130" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00730003.tif" inline="no" he="44"/><img id="img-00730004" orientation="unknown" wi="53" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00730004.tif" inline="no" he="36"/></p>
    <heading>(Example 8)</heading>
    <p num="0231">Inkjet recording sheet (8) according to the invention was produced
in the same manner as in Example 1, except that 0.4 parts of the following
additive (1) was further added to the composition of the mordant solution
B of Example 1. <img id="img-00740001" orientation="unknown" wi="50" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00740001.tif" inline="no" he="28"/></p>
    <heading>(Example 9)</heading>
    <p num="0232">Inkjet recording sheet (9) according to the invention was produced
in the same manner as in Example 1, except that one part of
guanylthiourea (fastness improver) was further added to the composition
of the mordant solution B of Example 1.</p>
    <heading>(Example 10)</heading>
    <p num="0233">Inkjet recording sheet (10) according to the invention was produced
in the same manner as in Example 1, except that 0.83 parts of "PAS-M-1"
was altered to 0.6 parts of dimethyldiallylammonium chloride ("Shallol
DC-902P", manufactured by Dai-ichi Kogyo Seiyaku Co., Ltd., aqueous
50% solution) in the composition of the colorant-receiving layer coating
liquid A of Example 1.</p>
    <heading>(Example 11)</heading>
    <p num="0234">Inkjet recording sheet (11) according to the invention was produced
in the same manner as in Example 1, except that 0.63 parts of basic
aluminum chloride (Al<sub>2</sub>(OH)<sub>5</sub>Cl, "PAC #1000, manufactured by Taki
Chemical Co., Ltd., aqueous 40% solution) was further added to the
composition of the colorant-receiving layer coating liquid A of Example 1.</p>
    <heading>(Example 12)</heading>
    <p num="0235">Inkjet recording sheet (12) according to the invention was produced 
in the same manner as in Example 1 except that 0.6 parts of zirconyl
acetate (aqueous 30% solution) was further added in the composition of
the colorant-receiving layer coating liquid A of Example 1.</p>
    <heading>(Example 13)</heading>
    <p num="0236">Inkjet recording sheet (13) according to the invention was produced
in the same manner as in Example 1, except that 0.2 parts of lanthanum
nitrate was further added to the composition of the colorant-receiving layer
coating liquid A of Example 1.</p>
    <heading>(Example 14)</heading>
    <p num="0237">Inkjet recording sheet (14) according to the invention was produced
in the same manner as in Example 1, except that 10.0 parts of the vapor-phase
method silica fine particle was changed to 10.0 parts of an alumina
fine particle (aluminum oxide, average primary particle diameter: 10 nm,
manufactured by Japan Aerogyl) and the amount of boric acid was altered
to 0.1 parts from 0.4 parts in the composition of the colorant-receiving
layer coating liquid A of Example 1.</p>
    <heading>(Comparative Example 1)</heading>
    <p num="0238">A comparative inkjet recording sheet (15) was produced in the same
manner as in Example 1 except that 2.5 parts of the compound (a) was not
used in the composition of the mordant solution B.</p>
    <heading>(Comparative Example 2)</heading>
    <p num="0239">A comparative inkjet recording sheet (16) was produced in the same
manner as in Example 1, except that 2.5 parts of the compound (a) was
changed to 2.5 parts of HOCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>SCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>SCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>OH in the
composition of the mordant solution B. </p>
    <heading>(Comparative Example 3)</heading>
    <p num="0240">A comparative inkjet recording sheet (17) was produced in the same
manner as in Example 1, except that 25 parts of an aqueous 10 %
polyallylamine "PAA-10C" solution was changed to 25 parts of an aqueous
10% poly(N-(vinylbenzyl)triethylammonium chloride solution in the
composition of the mordant solution B.</p>
    <heading>(Comparative Example 4)</heading>
    <p num="0241">A comparative inkjet recording sheet (18) was produced in the same
manner as in Example 1, except that 25 parts of an aqueous 10%
polyallylamine "PAA-10C" solution was changed to 25 parts of an aqueous
10% diallylamine hydrochloride/sulfur dioxide copolymer (PAS-92,
manufactured by Nittobo) solution in the composition of the mordant
solution B.</p>
    <heading>(Test for evaluation)</heading>
    <p num="0242">Each of the inkjet recording sheets (1) to (14) according to the
invention and comparative inkjet recording sheets (15) to (18) was
subjected to the following evaluation tests. The results of the evaluation
are shown in Table 1.</p>
    <heading>(1) Ozone resistance</heading>
    <p num="0243">Using an inkjet printer ("PM-900C", manufactured by Seiko Epson),
solid images of magenta and cyan were respectively printed on each inkjet
recording sheet, which was then stored for 24 hours under an atmosphere
containing ozone in a concentration of 2.5 ppm. Each concentration of
magenta and cyan before and after the sheet was stored was measured by
a reflection density meter ("Xrite 938, manufactured by Xrite) to calculate 
each residual rate of magenta and cyan densities.</p>
    <p num="0244">Based on the calculated values, the case where the residual rate
was 80% or more was rated as A, the case where the residual rate was 70
to 80% was rated as B, the case where the residual rate was 60% to 70%
was rated as C and the case where the residual rate was less than 60% was
rated as D to evaluate.</p>
    <heading>(2) Light fastness</heading>
    <p num="0245">Using an inkjet printer ("PM-900C", manufactured by Seiko Epson),
solid images of magenta and cyan were respectively printed on each inkjet
recording sheet. Thereafter, a cycle was repeated for 168 hours, wherein:
the sheet was illuminated with a lamp of a Xenon Weather-Ometer Ci65A
(Manufactured by ATLAS), through a filter, which cut ultraviolet light of
365 nm or less, for 3.8 hours, under conditions of a temperature of 25 °C
and a relative humidity of 32%; and then allowed to stand with the lamp
extinguished for one hour, under conditions of a temperature of 20 °C and
a relative humidity of 91%.</p>
    <p num="0246">The image density of each color before and after this test was
measured using a reflection density meter ("Xrite 938", manufactured by
Xrite) to calculate the residual rate of each color density.</p>
    <p num="0247">Based on the calculated value, the case where the residual rate was
90% or more was rated as A, the case where the residual rate was 80 to
90% was rated as B, the case where the residual rate was 70% to 80% was
rated as C and the case where the residual rate was less than 70% was
rated as D to evaluate.</p>
    <heading>(3) Bleeding over time</heading>
    <p num="0248">Using an inkjet printer ("PM-900C, manufactured by Seiko Epson),
a lattice-like line pattern (line width: 0.28 mm) in which magenta ink and
black ink are positioned adjacent to each other was printed on the inkjet
recording sheet. The recording sheet was allowed to stand for 3 hours
after printed and then stored for 3 days kept under a relative humidity of
90% by a thermohygrostat. Then, the line width of the black portion was
measured to evaluate according to the following standard.</p>
    <heading>(Standard)</heading>
    <p num="0249">
      <sl>
        <li>AA: Almost no occurrence of bleeding over time was found and the
sheet was good. (Line width: 0.28 to 0.30 mm)</li>
        <li>BB: Little bleeding over time was found, but was a practically
acceptable level. (Line width: 0.31 to 0.35 mm)</li>
        <li>CC: Significant bleeding over time was found and was a
practically unacceptable level. (Line width: 0.35 mm)</li>
      </sl>
      <tables>
        <table>
          <tgroup cols="6">
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry align="center" namest="1"/>
                <entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2">Ozone resistance</entry>
                <entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="4">Light fastness</entry>
                <entry align="center" namest="6">Bleeding With time</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="center"/>
                <entry align="center">Magenta</entry>
                <entry align="center">Cyan</entry>
                <entry align="center">Magenta</entry>
                <entry align="center">Cyan</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Example 1</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Example 2</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Example 3</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Example 4</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Example 5</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Example 6</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Example 7</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Example 8</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Example 9</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Example 10</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Example 11</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Example 12</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Example 13</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Example 14</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Comparative Example 1</entry>
                <entry align="center">D</entry>
                <entry align="center">C</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Comparative Example 2</entry>
                <entry align="center">D</entry>
                <entry align="center">C</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Comparative Example 3</entry>
                <entry align="center">C</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">C</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Comparative Example 4</entry>
                <entry align="center">C</entry>
                <entry align="center">B</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">A</entry>
                <entry align="center">C</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </tables>
    </p>
    <p num="0250">It has been clarified from the results shown in Table 1 that the
inkjet recording sheets (1) to (14) containing the phenolic compound and
the organic mordant according to the invention have high ozone resistance
since the residual rate of the density of the formed image is high even after
these recording sheets are stored for a long period of time under an 
atmosphere containing high concentration of ozone. It has been also
clarified that the residual rate of the density of the formed image is high
even after the image is irradiated with xenon and even after the cycle test
in which the sheet is allowed to stand under a high moisture condition,
showing that these recording sheets are superior in light fastness,
particularly in the light fastness of a developed magenta color and further
these recording sheets are superior in resistance to bleeding over time.
Also, in the case of the inkjet recording sheets (8) and (9) using a hindered
amine type compound and a thiourea type compound together, inkjet
recording sheets which are more superior in ozone resistance and light
fastness could be obtained. Moreover, in the case of inkjet recording
sheets (11) to (13) using a metal compound together, the bleeding of an
image over time could be further increased.</p>
    <p num="0251">On the contrary, in the case of the inkjet recording sheets (15) to
(18) that use no combination of the phenolic compound and organic
mordant according to the invention, the light fastness, the ozone
resistance and the resistance to bleeding over time could not be satisfied at
the same time.</p>
    <p num="0252">According to the invention, an inkjet recording sheet which has
particularly good ink-absorbancy, is free from bleeding over time and is
improved in ozone resistance and light fastness can be provided.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>An inkjet recording sheet comprising a support, and on the support,
a colorant-receiving layer including:
<claim-text><claim-text>a phenolic compound; and</claim-text><claim-text>at least one organic mordant selected from the group consisting of
polyallylamine and derivatives thereof, and polyvinylamine and derivatives
thereof.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The inkjet recording sheet of claim 1, wherein the phenolic
compound comprises phenolic hydroxy groups and further comprises at
least one substituent group selected from the group consisting of carboxyl
groups, sulfo groups and salts thereof.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The inkjet recording sheet of claim 1, wherein the colorant-receiving
layer comprises from 0.01 g/m2 to 5 g/m2 of the phenolic
compound.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The inkjet recording sheet of claim 1, wherein a weight average
molecular weight of the organic mordant is from 500 to 100,000.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The inkjet recording sheet of claim 1, wherein the colorant-receiving
layer further comprises fine particles and a water-soluble resin.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The inkjet recording sheet of claim 5, wherein the fine particles
comprise at least one of silica fine particles, colloidal silica, alumina fine
particles and pseudo-boehmite.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>The inkjet recording sheet of claim 5, wherein the fine particles
comprise at least 50 mass % relative to a total mass of solid components of
the colorant-receiving layer.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The inkjet recording sheet of claim 5, wherein the water-soluble
resin comprises at least one water-soluble resin selected from a group
consisting of polyvinyl alcohols and derivatives thereof, cellulose resins,
resins having an ether bond, resins having a carbamoyl group and resins
having a carboxyl group.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>The inkjet recording sheet of claim 5, wherein the water-soluble
resin comprises from 9 to 40 mass % relative to a total mass of solid
components of the colorant-receiving layer.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>The inkjet recording sheet of claim 5, wherein the fine particles in
the colorant-receiving layer comprise a mass (x), the water-soluble resin in
the colorant-receiving layer comprises a mass (y), and a mass ratio thereof
(x/y) is from 1.5 to 10.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>The inkjet recording sheet of claim 5, wherein the colorant-receiving
layer further comprises a crosslinking agent, which can crosslink
the water-soluble resin.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>The inkjet recording sheet of claim 11, wherein the crosslinking
agent comprises a crosslinking agent selected from a group consisting of
boron compounds, aldehyde-based compounds, ketone-based compounds,
active halogen compounds, active vinyl compounds, N-methylol
compounds, melamine compounds, epoxy compounds, isocyanate-based
compounds, aziridine-based compounds, carbodiimide-based compounds,
ethylenimino-based compounds, halogenated carboxyaldehyde-based
compounds, dioxane-based compounds, compounds that include a metal,
polyamine compounds, hydrazide compounds, low-molecular weight
compounds that include at least two oxazoline groups, polymers that
include at least two oxazoline groups, multivalent acid anhydrides, acid
chlorides, bissulfonate compounds and active ether compounds.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>The inkjet recording sheet of claim 11, wherein an amount of the
crosslinking agent used comprises from 1 to 50 mass % of an amount of
the water-soluble resin used.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>The inkjet recording sheet of claim 1, wherein the colorant-receiving
layer further comprises a fastness improver.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>The inkjet recording sheet of claim 1, wherein the colorant-receiving
layer further comprises a surfactant and a high boiling-point
organic solvent.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>The inkjet recording sheet of claim 1, wherein a pH on a surface of
the colorant-receiving layer is from 3 to 8.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>The inkjet recording sheet of claim 1, wherein a thickness of the
colorant-receiving layer is from 10 to 50 µm.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="18">
      <claim-text>The inkjet recording sheet of claim 1, wherein the colorant-receiving
layer further comprises pores which have a median diameter of
from 0.005 to 0.030 µm.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="19">
      <claim-text>The inkjet recording sheet of claim 1, wherein the support is
transparent, and a haze value of the colorant-receiving layer formed
thereon is no more than 30 %.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="20">
      <claim-text>The inkjet recording sheet of claim 1, wherein the colorant-receiving
layer comprises a layer formed by a process including the steps
of:
<claim-text><claim-text>preparing a coating liquid containing at least fine particles and a
water-soluble resin;</claim-text><claim-text>preparing a basic solution having a pH value of at least 8;</claim-text><claim-text>adding a crosslinking agent to at least one of the coating liquid and
the basic solution;</claim-text><claim-text>applying the coating liquid to form a coated layer;</claim-text><claim-text>drying the coated layer;</claim-text><claim-text>crosslinking and curing the coated layer by adding the basic
solution to the coated layer at a time that is at least one of (1)
simultaneous with the step of applying the coating liquid to form the
coated layer, and (2) before the coated layer exhibits a decreasing rate of
drying during the step of drying the coated layer.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
