<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1231064-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1231064" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="26609194" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020814">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1231064-A2" status="new" fvid="23514282">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1231064</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20020814</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02002899-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02002899</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020208</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001033560-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001033560</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010209</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001384679-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001384679</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20011218</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/175       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/175       20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41J   2/175C2</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41J   2/175C3A</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Flüssigkeitsbehälter, elastisches Element für Flüssigkeitsbehälter und Aufzeichnungsgerät</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Liquid container, elastic member for liquid container, and recording apparatus</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Récipient de liquide, élément élastique pour récipient de liquide et dispositif d'enregistrement</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>CANON KK</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>CANON KABUSHIKI KAISHA</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>CANON KABUSHIKI KAISHA</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>3-30-2 Shimomaruko</street>
              <city>Ohta-ku, Tokyo</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HATASA NOBUYUKI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KOHNO TAKESHI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KOSHIKAWA HIROSHI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NANJO TATSUO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SHIMIZU EIICHIRO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YAMAMOTO HAJIME</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HATASA, NOBUYUKI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KOHNO, TAKESHI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KOSHIKAWA, HIROSHI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NANJO, TATSUO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SHIMIZU, EIICHIRO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YAMAMOTO, HAJIME</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Hatasa, Nobuyuki, Canon Kabushiki Kaisha</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>3-30-2, Shimomaruko, Ohta-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Kohno, Takeshi, Canon Kabushiki Kaisha</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>3-30-2, Shimomaruko, Ohta-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Koshikawa, Hiroshi, Canon Kabushiki Kaisha</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>3-30-2, Shimomaruko, Ohta-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Nanjo, Tatsuo, Canon Kabushiki Kaisha</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>3-30-2, Shimomaruko, Ohta-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Shimizu, Eiichiro, Canon Kabushiki Kaisha</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>3-30-2, Shimomaruko, Ohta-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Yamamoto, Hajime, Canon Kabushiki Kaisha</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>3-30-2, Shimomaruko, Ohta-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Leson, Thomas Johannes Alois, Dipl.-Ing.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Tiedtke-Bühling-Kinne &amp;amp; Partner GbR, TBK-Patent, Bavariaring 4</street>
              <city>80336 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A liquid container (2) for an ink jet recording
apparatus includes a connection opening connectable
with an outside; an elastic member provided in the
connection opening, the elastic member being adapted
to be penetrated by a cylindrical member (7) for fluid
communication with the outside; the elastic member
including a compressed region (18) and a substantially non-compressed
region (19) in a state without the cylindrical
member penetrated, disposed in this order in a
direction of insertion of the cylindrical member,
wherein the compressed region and the non-compressed
region are capable of being compressed when they are
penetrated by the cylindrical member.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="97" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="80"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>FIELD OF THE INVENTION AND RELATED ART:</heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a
replaceable liquid container, an elastic member for
plugging the connective hole which connects the inside
and outside of the container, and an ink jet recording
apparatus equipped with a replaceable liquid
container.</p>
    <p num="0002">As a replaceable liquid container in
accordance with the prior arts, the ink container for
an ink jet recording apparatus, which is disclosed in
Japanese Laid-open patent Application 5-162333, has
been known. The drawings disclosed in this patent
application are present in this specification, as
Figures 44, 45, and 46, to depict an example of a
conventional replaceable liquid container, or the
replaceable liquid container in accordance with the
prior arts.</p>
    <p num="0003">As shown in Figures 44 - 46, in the case of
the first example of the conventional liquid
container, an ink drawing member 72 is held in the
space formed by the recess 81a of the top portion 62A
of the liquid container shell, and the recess 83 of
the retaining portion of the bottom portion of the 
liquid container shell, the ink drawing member 72 is
placed in the recess 81a, and the top and bottom
portions L2A and 62B are joined in a manner to
compress the ink drawing member 72. The members in
other examples of a conventional liquid container, and
in the embodiments of the present invention, which are
equivalent to the ink drawing member 72 in this first
example of a conventional liquid container, will be
referred to as "elastic member" to better describe
them regarding their characteristics; a name "ink
drawing member" is used in the description of the
first example of a conventional liquid container,
after the name used in the specification of the
aforementioned patent application.</p>
    <p num="0004">Figure 44 is a perspective view of the ink
drawing member 72 used for the first example of a
conventional liquid container. This ink drawing
member 72 has an ink drawing portion 72f through which
the ink drawing needle on the main assembly side of a
recording means is inserted into the liquid container,
a positioning portion with a diameter larger than that
of the ink drawing portion 72f, an ink pouch
(unshown), and a connective portion 72g.</p>
    <p num="0005">Referring to figure 44, the diameter Y of the
ink drawing portion 72f of the ink drawing member 72
is greater than that of the portion of the recess of
the retaining portion of the bottom portion 62B of the 
liquid container shell. Thus, when the top and bottom
portions 62A and L28 are joined, the ink drawing
portion 72f of the ink drawing member 72 is compressed
only, or mainly, in its radius direction. After
assembly, the liquid container is structured as shown
in Figure 46.</p>
    <p num="0006">The positioning portion 72e with the diameter
accurately positions the ink drawing member 72
relative to the top and bottom portions 62A and 62B of
the liquid container shell, and prevents the ink
drawing member 72 from shifting.</p>
    <p num="0007">Figures 47 and 48 show the second example of
a conventional replaceable liquid container for an ink
jet recording apparatus. Figure 47 is a sectional
view of the ink container, at the plane which divides
the ink container into two symmetrical portions, and
shows the details thereof. Figure 48 is a schematic
sectional view of the ink outlet portion of the ink
container, more specifically, a plug for the
connective portion, which connects the inside and
outside of the ink container, and its adjacencies.</p>
    <p num="0008">Referring to Figures 47 and 48, an ink
container 100 has an ink storage chamber 101 and a
waste ink storage chamber 102. One end of the ink
storage chamber 101 is provided with two rubber plugs,
through which the ink drawing needle (unshown) is put.
Similarly, one end of the waste ink storage chamber 
102 is provided with one rubber plug 104. These
rubber plugs are parts of the connective portion.
Except for the portion facing the ink passage portion
3 through which the ink drawing needle is put, each
rubber plug 104 is confined by the wall of the rubber
plug holding recess 105 and a rubber plug pressing
member 107.</p>
    <p num="0009">The waste ink storage chamber 102 has two
storage portions (top and bottom portions in Figure
47) connected to each other at one end of the chamber.
The aforementioned portion, through which the ink
drawing needle for the waste ink storage portion is
put, corresponds in position to the bottom storage
portion. In other words, the waste ink delivery
needle connected to the waste ink delivery path of an
ink jet recording apparatus is put through, so that
the waste ink discharged through an ejection
performance recovery process or the like is allowed to
flow into the bottom storage portion of the waste ink
storage chamber 102. Virtually the entire space of
the waste ink storage chamber 102 is occupied by an
absorbent member 108. Thus, after flowing into the
bottom storage portion of the waste ink storage
chamber 102, the waste ink is absorbed by the
absorbent member 108. As the waste ink flows into the
waste ink storage chamber 102, the waste ink gradually
soaks the absorbent member 108, and reaches the 
portion of the absorbent member 108 in the top storage
portion, soaking this portion as well. Eventually, it
begins to seep out of the absorbent member 108. The
top storage portion of the waste ink storage chamber
102 is provided with a partitioning wall 102A, which
is located close to the end of the absorbent member
108. Thus, as long as the amount of the waste ink
does not exceed the waste ink retaining capacity of
the absorbent member 108, the aforementioned waste ink
which seeps out of the absorbent member 108 does not
spill over into the space on the right side of the
partitioning wall 102A, that is, the portion of the
top storage portion which does not contain the
absorbent member 108. As the cumulative amount of the
waste ink exceeds the capacity of the absorbent
member, the waste ink which seeps out of the absorbent
member 108 spills over into the space on the right
side of the partitioning wall 102A, for the first
time, and accumulates in the space. Eventually, the
top surface of the body of the waste ink in the space
on the right side of the partitioning wall 102A
reaches a waste liquid detection electrode (unshown)
located at a predetermined level. As a result, it is
detected that the waste ink storage chamber 102 is
filled up with the waste ink. Then, a user is
prompted to replace the ink container 100. Further,
the waste ink storage chamber 102 is provided with an 
air vent 109, which is located in the top rear corner.
The waste ink storage chamber 102 is allowed to breath
through this air vent.</p>
    <p num="0010">Referring to Figure 48, before the placement
of the rubber plug 104 in the recess 105, the external
diameter of the rubber plug 104 is greater than the
internal diameter of the recess 105. Thus, the rubber
plug 104 is placed in the recess 105 in the direction
indicated by an arrow mark B, while being kept
compressed in its radius direction (indicated by an
arrow mark A in Figure 48) with the use of a
predetermined apparatus.</p>
    <p num="0011">In the case of the ink drawing member 72 in
the first example of a conventional ink container,
shown in figure 44, which is disclosed in the
aforementioned patent application, however, its
positioning portion 72e functions only to accurately
position the ink drawing member 72, and the ink
drawing portion 72f remains compressed.</p>
    <p num="0012">Further, the connective portion 72g simply
connects the ink drawing portion 72f and ink pouch.
In other words, only the ink drawing portion 72f
contributes to the connection between the ink
container and the main assembly of a recording
apparatus.</p>
    <p num="0013">The ink drawing portion 72f is compressed and
confined by the top and bottom portions k2A and 62B of 
the ink container shell during the manufacture of the
liquid container. Therefore, even when the
cylindrical needle is not penetrating the ink drawing
portion 72f, compression pressure is always present in
the ink drawing portion 72f. Thus, when the
cylindrical needle is within the elastic member, the
compression pressure in the ink drawing portion 72f is
a total of the compression pressure when the
cylindrical needle is not in the imp 72f and the
compression pressure proportional to the volume of the
cylindrical needle.</p>
    <p num="0014">Generally speaking, the greater the
compression pressure, and the longer the duration of
the compression pressure, the greater the progression
of creep (phenomenon that an elastic substance kept
under compression pressure for a certain length time
fails to revert to its original state; in other
words, it becomes permanently deformed).</p>
    <p num="0015">In other words, when the cylindrical needle
is pulled out after remaining in the ink drawing
member 72 for a long time, the ink drawing member 74
is likely to fail to revert to the original state,
allowing the liquid within the liquid container to
drip through the connective hole.</p>
    <p num="0016">Referring to Figure 49, in the case of the
second example of a liquid container in accordance
with the prior arts, and the second example of an ink 
jet recording apparatus in accordance with the prior
arts, if the diameter of an ink delivery needle 127,
which is put through the ink passage portion 129 of a
liquid container 130, is large, an elastic member 128
is expanded in the direction in which the ink delivery
needle 127 advances, and also, in the radius direction
of the elastic member 128 (Figure 49(a). The volume
by which the elastic member 128 is expanded is equal
to the volume of the portion of the ink delivery
needle 127 within the elastic member 128. Then, even
after the ink delivery needle 127 is withdrawn from
the elastic member 128, the elastic member 128 does
not revert to its original condition.</p>
    <p num="0017">More concretely, on the needle entry side,
the elastic member 128 remains indented around the
path of the ink delivery needle 127, whereas on the
side opposite to the needle entry side, the conical
hole formed around the ink delivery needle 127 as the
internal portion of the elastic member 128 was pushed
out and partially dragged out of the elastic member
128 remains virtually intact (Figure 49(b)). In this
state, the sealing performance of the elastic member
is at a low level. Thus, there is a possibility that
the ink in the liquid container is allowed to drip
from the ink delivery hole 131, and contaminates the
area around the removed liquid container.</p>
    <p num="0018">Further, when the elastic member 128 is in 
the above described state, the interface which is
formed between the internal portion of the elastic
member 128 and ink delivery needle 127 as the liquid
container is remounted in the main assembly of a
recording apparatus is smaller than other wise.
Therefore, there is a possibility that ink will drip
from the ink delivery hole 131 and contaminate the
recording apparatus main assembly, and the area around
the liquid container.</p>
    <p num="0019">Figure 50 is a plan view of a rubber plug for
the ink passage portion of a liquid container, after
having been penetrated a number of times by the ink
delivery needle of the recording apparatus main
assembly. It shows the ribs formed in the rubber
plug.</p>
    <p num="0020">When a liquid container in accordance with
the prior arts is mounted in the main assembly of a
recording apparatus in accordance with the prior arts,
the ink delivery needle itself of the recording
apparatus main assembly enters the liquid container by
ripping through the elastic member 128, that is, the
rubber plug, fitted in the ink delivery hole. If, for
some reason or another, the user of the recording
apparatus repeatedly mounts and dismounts the liquid
container a number of times, the ink delivery needle
127 randomly tears the elastic member 128, resulting
in tears 128a - 128c shown in Figure 50, each time the 
liquid container is mounted; in other words, the
elastic member 128 is damaged.</p>
    <p num="0021">If these tears become connected, or a small
piece or pieces of the elastic member 128 become
severed from the elastic member 128, it becomes
impossible for the elastic member 128 to maintain a
predetermined amount of compression pressure. In the
worst case, the hatched portion 128d in the drawing
falls out and leaves a hole. In particular, when an
ink jet recording apparatus is equipped with an ink
delivery needle with a large diameter, the tear made
in the elastic member 128 by the ink delivery needle
is wider, allowing the ink to drip from the ink
delivery hole. Also in this case, as the liquid
container is repeatedly mounted into, or dismounted
from, the recording apparatus, the progression of the
damage to the elastic member 128 results in the
formation of a hole through the elastic member 128,
making it impossible for the elastic member 128 to
block the ink flow.</p>
    <p num="0022">The above described problems are likely to
occur to a commercial ink jet recording apparatus
enabled to handle a large sheet of paper, for the
following background. That is, in the case of a
commercial ink jet recording apparatus, in order to
inexpensively produce a large amount of prints, a
print job is automatically carried out at night, 
generally without the presence of an operator, after
the replacement of the ink container in the apparatus
with an ink container completely filled with ink.
Then, the partially empty ink container having been
replaced by the ink container completely filled with
ink, for the nigh job, is remounted into the recording
apparatus during the daytime when more hands are
available.</p>
    <heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION:</heading>
    <p num="0023">Thus, the primary object of the present
invention is to provide a liquid container, the inside
and outside of which become connected as a cylindrical
needle is put through a predetermined portion of the
wall of the liquid container, and which can be mounted
into, or dismounted from, the main assembly of a
recording apparatus, without allowing the ink therein
to leak, even after it is left alone for a long period
of time, or a cylindrical needle is left penetrating
the liquid container for a long period time, as well
as a recording apparatus compatible with such a liquid
container.</p>
    <p num="0024">The second object of the present invention is
to secure a sufficient amount of contact surface
between the elastic member of a liquid container and a
cylindrical ink delivery needle, by preventing the 
phenomenon that as a cylindrical needle is pushed
through the sealing member of a liquid container, the
elastic member is deformed in such a manner that the
portion of the elastic member around the needle, on
the needle entry side of the sealing member, is pulled
into the elastic member, whereas the portion of the
elastic member around the needle, on the side opposite
to the needle entry side, conically peels away from
the needle, and thereby, to provide a liquid
container, the inside and outside of which become
connected as a cylindrical needle is put through a
predetermined portion of the wall of the liquid
container, and which can be mounted into, or
dismounted from, the main assembly of a recording
apparatus, without allowing the ink therein to leak,
as well as a recording apparatus compatible with such
a liquid container.</p>
    <p num="0025">The third embodiment of the present invention
is to provide a liquid container the inside and
outside of which become connected as a cylindrical
needle is put through a predetermined portion of the
wall of the liquid container, and which can be mounted
into, or dismounted from, the main assembly of a
recording apparatus, without allowing the ink therein
to leak, even after the liquid container is connected
to the cylindrical needle a substantial number of
times, as well as a recording apparatus compatible 
with such a liquid container.</p>
    <p num="0026">Thus, the present invention for accomplishing
the above described three objects, that is, for
solving the three problems, the present invention
essentially comprises three additional inventions.
According to an aspect of the present invention, there
is provided a liquid container for an ink jet
recording apparatus, comprising a connection opening
connectable with an outside; an elastic member
provided in said connection opening, said elastic
member being adapted to be penetrated by a cylindrical
member for fluid communication with the outside; said
elastic member including a compressed region and a
substantially non-compressed region in a state without
said cylindrical member penetrated, disposed in this
order in a direction of insertion of said cylindrical
member, wherein said compressed region and said non-compressed
region are capable of being compressed when
they are penetrated by said cylindrical member.</p>
    <p num="0027">With this structure, the deterioration of
elasticity of the elastic member in the non-compressed
region with time is smaller than that in the elastic
member in the compressed region. Therefore, the
elastic member in the non-compressed region is
relatively free of the phenomenon (creep phenomenon)
in which when the cylindrical member is kept
penetrating in the compressed and non-compressed 
region of the elastic member for a long term, the
permanent strain is produced such that elastic member
does not restore the original state even after the
cylindrical member is removed. Therefore, even after
the removal of the cylindrical member after long term
penetration, the elastic member in the non-compressed
region can avoid improper sealing of the connection
opening. In addition, by the provision of the non-compressed
region of the elastic member, the absolute
area with which the elastic member is contacted to the
cylindrical member, can be increased. Therefore, the
sealing property of the connection opening against the
pressure change inside or outside of the liquid
container is improved.</p>
    <p num="0028">With this structure, it may preferably be
that a plane, perpendicular to the direction of
insertion of the cylindrical member, of said
compressed region of said elastic member is wider than
a plane, perpendicular to the direction of insertion,
of said non-compressed region of said elastic member
in the state without said cylindrical member
penetrated. In addition, it may preferably be that a
length, measured in the direction of insertion of the
cylindrical member, of said compressed region of said
elastic member, is longer than a length, measured in
the direction, of said non-compressed region of said
elastic member in the state without said cylindrical 
member penetrated.</p>
    <p num="0029">Additionally, it may preferably be that said
compressed region and said non-compressed region of
said elastic member are portions of a single member,
in the state without the cylindrical member
penetrated. In this case, it may preferably be that
one of opposite end surfaces of said elastic member
with respect to the direction of the insertion of said
cylindrical member has a protruded form, and the other
has a recessed form to provide a substantially uniform
thickness, and wherein said non-compressed region has
a configuration protruded toward said recessed form in
the state without the cylindrical member penetrated.
Furthermore, it may preferably be that the cylindrical
member is inserted at the end having the protruded
form.</p>
    <p num="0030">Moreover, it may preferably be that there is
further provided a housing, provided in said
connection opening, for housing said elastic member,
said housing having an inner diameter which is
substantially equal to an outer diameter of said
elastic member, wherein said elastic member is
compressed toward a center of said elastic member by a
fixing member compressing the end of the elastic
member having the protruded form. With this
structure, the compressive force is produced within
the column configuration portion only when the 
cylindrical member is inserted into the column
configuration portion of the elastic member, and
therefore, permanent strain of the column
configuration portion of the elastic member with time
does not easily occur as compared with the portion of
elastic member which is always placed in a compressed
state. Therefore, even if the cylindrical member is
removed after long term continuous penetration of the
cylindrical member in the elastic member, the leakage
of the liquid does not easily occur through the
connection opening.</p>
    <p num="0031">In addition, it may preferably be that when
the end of said elastic member having the protruded
form is compressed to the fixing member having an
opening through which the cylindrical member is
penetrated, the elastic member is not pressed into the
opening of said fixing member. In this case, it may
preferably be that the end having the protruded form
has a conical portion at a top of the protruded form,
or that the end having the protruded form has a flat
surface substantially perpendicular to the direction
of insertion of the cylindrical member or a stepped-down
surface. With such structures, the direction in
which the elastic member is pressed out by the
cylindrical member when the elastic member is
penetrated by the elastic member, can be limited to
the direction of the diameter of the elastic member, 
and therefore, the depression of the elastic member
attributable to the insertion of the cylindrical
member can be more suppressed.</p>
    <p num="0032">According to another aspect of the present
invention, there is provided a liquid container for an
ink jet recording apparatus, comprising a connection
opening connectable with an outside; an elastic member
plugged in said connection opening; a housing for
housing said elastic member, said elastic member being
adapted to be penetrated by a cylindrical member for
fluid communication with the outside; a slit provided
in said elastic member and extended from an end at
which said cylindrical member is insertable in a
direction of insertion of said cylindrical member,
wherein said elastic member is compressed inwardly in
said housing.</p>
    <p num="0033">With this structure, the cylindrical needle
enters along the slit, and therefore, the elastic
member can be pierced in a constant state. Therefore,
the possible damage to the elastic member upon the
insertion of the cylindrical needle can be avoided,
thus assuring the hermetical sealing of the connection
opening.</p>
    <p num="0034">In the structure, it may preferably be that
said elastic member is in the form of a dome having a
protruded form on one side and a recessed form on the
other side in the direction of insertion of the 
cylindrical member, the dome having a substantially
uniform thickness, and said elastic member is provided
with a column configuration portion of the recessed
form side, wherein the slit is within the column
configuration portion. With the dome-like
configuration of the elastic member, the state in
which the elastic member is compressed toward the
center thereof can be produced in the elastic member
in the housing, when the elastic member is pressed by
the fixing member. Therefore, the close contact
between the elastic member and the cylindrical member
when the cylindrical member is penetrated through the
elastic member is improved, thus enhancing the
reliability of the hermetical sealing of the
connection opening. The column configuration portion
of the dome configuration projects in the direction in
which the cylindrical member is inserted, and
therefore, when the cylindrical member is inserted
into the elastic member, protrusion or the like, and
therefore, the depression of the elastic member due to
the insertion of the cylindrical member can be
prevented. Therefore, as compared with the prior art
structure, the contact area between the cylindrical
member and the elastic member can be large.
Additionally, the provision of the slit extending in
the direction of the insertion of the cylindrical
member, the cylindrical member can be guided by the 
slit. Therefore, the possible damage to the elastic
member upon the insertion of the cylindrical member,
can be avoided, thus assuring the hermetical sealing
of the connection opening.</p>
    <p num="0035">In this case, it may preferably be that only
one such slit is provided. With the structure, the
elastic member can be penetrated always at a constant
position. Additionally, it may preferably be that
said slit does not penetrates all through said elastic
member. With this structure, the proper sealing of
the connection opening can be maintained in the
significant ambience condition changes during the
distribution process from the manufacturing of the
container to the beginning of the use of the
container. Additionally, it may preferably be that a
length of slit, measured in a direction perpendicular
to the direction of insertion of the cylindrical
member satisfies 2L&gt; πD, where D is a diameter of the
cylindrical member. With this structure, a
cylindrical needle is penetrated through the elastic
member along the slit, the slit is prevented from
enlarging.</p>
    <p num="0036">According to another aspect of the present
invention, there is provided a liquid container for an
ink jet recording apparatus, comprising a connection
opening connectable with an outside; an elastic member
provided in said connection opening, said elastic 
member being adapted to be penetrated by a cylindrical
member for fluid communication with the outside; said
elastic member including a compressed region and a
substantially non-compressed region in a state without
said cylindrical member penetrated, disposed in this
order in a direction of insertion of said cylindrical
member, wherein said compressed region is in the form
of a dome having a protruded form on one side and a
recessed form on the other side in the direction of
insertion of the cylindrical member, wherein a top
portion of said protruded form has a flat surface
substantially perpendicular to the direction of
insertion of the cylindrical member or a stepped-down
surface, wherein said non-compressed region is
provided with a column configuration portion of the
recessed form side, wherein the slit is within the
column configuration portion, wherein said compressed
region and said non-compressed region are capable of
being compressed when they are penetrated by said
cylindrical member. wherein said elastic member has a
slit provided in said elastic member and extended from
an end at which said cylindrical member is insertable
in a direction of insertion of said cylindrical
member, and the slit is within the column
configuration portion, wherein said elastic member is
compressed inwardly in said housing.</p>
    <p num="0037">According to a further aspect of the present 
invention, there is provided a liquid container for an
ink jet recording apparatus, comprising a connection
opening connectable with an outside; an elastic member
provided in said connection opening, said elastic
member being adapted to be penetrated by a cylindrical
member for fluid communication with the outside, said
elastic member including a compressed region and a
substantially non-compressed region in a state without
said cylindrical member penetrated, disposed in this
order in a direction of insertion of said cylindrical
member, wherein said compressed region is in the form
of a dome having a protruded form on one side and a
recessed form on the other side in the direction of
insertion of the cylindrical member, wherein a top
portion of said protruded form has a flat surface
substantially perpendicular to the direction of
insertion of the cylindrical member or a stepped-down
surface, wherein said non-compressed region is
provided with a column configuration portion of the
recessed form side, wherein said compressed region and
said non-compressed region are capable of being
compressed when they are penetrated by said
cylindrical member, wherein said elastic member has a
slit provided in said elastic member and extended from
an end at which said cylindrical member is insertable
in a direction of insertion of said cylindrical
member, and the slit is within the column 
configuration portion, wherein said elastic member is
compressed inwardly in said housing.</p>
    <p num="0038">In these two aspects, with the dome-like
configuration of the elastic member, the state in
which the elastic member is compressed toward the
center thereof can be produced in the elastic member
in the housing, when the elastic member is pressed by
the fixing member. Therefore, the close contact
between the elastic member and the cylindrical member
when the cylindrical member is penetrated through the
elastic member is improved, thus enhancing the
reliability of the hermetical sealing of the
connection opening. In addition, by the provision of
the column configuration portion, the depression of
the elastic member due to the insertion of the
cylindrical member can be avoided, and therefore, the
contacted area between the cylindrical member and
elastic member can be larger than in the conventional
structure. Additionally, the provision of the slit
extending in the direction of the insertion of the
cylindrical member, the cylindrical member can be
guided by the slit.</p>
    <p num="0039">Additionally, in the second aspect of the
present invention, it may preferably be that said
fixing member is provided with an absorbing material
for absorbing a droplet. In this case, it may
preferably be that said fixing member is provided with 
grooves extending radially from said connection
opening. With this structure, a small amount of
droplets which are produced when the liquid container
is disengaged from the cylindrical member (in the case
that liquid accommodated in the liquid container is
ink, they are droplets of ink), can be efficiently
guided to the absorbing material by the capillary
force. Therefore, the user of the ink jet recording
apparatus, the recording device per se and the
articles placed around the recording device can be
protected effectively from contamination.</p>
    <p num="0040">In the second, third and forth aspects, it
may preferably be that there is further provided a
fixing member for pressing and fixing said elastic
member, said fixing member being provided with an
absorbing material for absorbing a droplet and being
provided with grooves extending radially from said
connection opening, wherein at least one of said
grooves extends along said slit. With this structure,
the fine grooves on the surface of the elastic member
and the grooves of the fixing member are continued, so
that liquid droplets deposited on the surface of the
elastic member (in the case of the liquid being ink,
they are ink droplets) can be efficiently guided to
the absorbing material. In the second and third
aspects, it may preferably be that there is further
provided a fixing member for pressing and fixing said 
elastic member, wherein a free end of the cylindrical
member to be inserted into seven elastic member is
tapered, and said affixing member has an opening
contacted to the elastic member to guide insertion of
the cylindrical member into said elastic member,
wherein the opening has a length, measured in the
direction of insertion of the cylindrical member, is
larger than a length of the tapered portion of the
cylindrical member. With this structure, it can be
avoided that free end of the cylindrical member
reaches the surface of the elastic member while the
tapered portion at the free end of the cylindrical
member is still in contact with the inside diameter of
the opening of the fixing member for permitting the
insertion of the cylindrical member. As a result, it
is possible to guide the connecting needle to the
center of the elastic member. In this case, it may
preferably be that the plane perpendicular to the
direction of insertion of the cylindrical member has a
circular flat plane having a diameter larger than the
diameter of the opening provided in the fixing member.
With this feature, the compression stress toward the
center of the drastic member upon the assembling
operation, can be related by the contact surface
between the flat surface of the fixing member and the
flat surface of the elastic member, and therefore,
uniform contacts and therefore uniform compressions 
stresses can be accomplished.</p>
    <p num="0041">In the second and third aspects, it may
preferably be that a lubricant exists on a surface of
said elastic member. Additionally, it may preferably
be that a lubricant exists on a surface of said
elastic member open to an opening of a fixing member
for pressing and fixing said elastic member, the
cylindrical member being inserted through the opening
of the fixing member; that a lubricant exists on
contact surfaces between said elastic member and a
fixing member for pressing and fixing said elastic
member; that a lubricant exists on contact surfaces
between inside of said housing and said elastic
member; that a lubricant exists in a slit provided in
said elastic member and extended in the direction of
insertion of the cylindrical member; or that a
lubricant exists on a surface of a fixing member for
pressing and fixing said elastic member; that a
lubricant on said elastic member comprises a glycol
material.</p>
    <p num="0042">With any of such a features, the friction
between the elastic member and the leading edge
portion of the cylindrical member is reduced, and the
cylindrical member can be assuredly guided to the
slit, and it is easy to insert the cylindrical needle
into the elastic member by a powerless user.
Articulate, it is preferable to the lubricant is 
applied in the slit extended in the insertion of the
cylindrical member into the elastic member.</p>
    <p num="0043">By the existence of the lubricant on the
surface of the fixing member, or the contact surface
between the fixing member and said elastic member, it
can be avoided or suppressed that movement within the
elastic member per se upon mounting of the elastic
member, or upon insertion of the cylindrical member,
occurs, or that upon the removal of the cylindrical
member, the material of the elastic member per se is
moved you to the friction between the elastic member
and the fixing member. By applying the lubricant to
the contact surfaces between the housing and the
elastic member, the elastic member can be easily
inserted.</p>
    <p num="0044">In the first aspect of the present invention
described above, it may preferably be that there is
further provided a fixing member for pressing and
fixing said elastic member, wherein a connecting
portion configuration between said elastic member and
said housing is substantially circular by the pressing
of said fixing member. With this structure, the
compressive force is easily concentrated on the center
on elastic member, which is preferable.</p>
    <p num="0045">In the second aspect of the present
invention, it may preferably be that a plurality of
such slits are provided and are crossed at a 
substantial center of said elastic member. When the
plurality of slits are provided, it is preferable that
slits are crossed with each other substantially at the
center of the elastic member, since then the elastic
member can be properly inserted into the cylindrical
member, even if the inserting direction of the
cylindrical member is not particularly regulated.</p>
    <p num="0046">In the third aspect of the present invention,
it may preferebly be that the slits are generally
linear or circular. The arcuate configuration is
particularly preferable when the opening diameter of
the cylindrical member cannot be large from
standpoints of dimensions of the other parts.</p>
    <p num="0047">In addition, in the second aspect, it may
preferably be that a length measured in a direction
perpendicular to the direction of insertion satisfied
1.5πD&gt; L, where D is a diameter of said cylindrical
member. If the length of the slit, measured in the
direction perpendicular to the direction of insertion
of the cylindrical needle, is too large, the material
of the elastic member at the intersection and the
other material thereof are made separate, and
therefore, the sealing property against the depression
of the elastic member is deteriorated, and therefore,
the relationship 1.5πR&gt; L is preferable. According to
a further aspect of the present invention, there is
provided a liquid container comprising connection 
opening connectable with an outside, wherein said
liquid container is brought into fluid communication
with the outside by insertion of a cylindrical member
through said connection opening; an elastic member
plugged in said connection opening; and a guide for
guiding the cylindrical member into a range within
0.5D from a center of the elastic member, where D is a
diameter of said cylindrical member. With this
structure, the possibility of the damage to the
elastic member can be further reduced.</p>
    <p num="0048">According to a yet further aspect of the
present invention, there is provided a recording
apparatus using a liquid container as described above,
comprising a mounting means for detachably mounting
said liquid container, and the cylindrical member
provided in the mounting means, said cylindrical
member penetrates through said elastic member in said
connection opening of said liquid container.</p>
    <p num="0049">The recording apparatus preferably includes a
recording apparatus using a liquid container as
described above, further comprising an ink jet head
for effecting recording by ejecting droplets of liquid
supplied from said liquid container.</p>
    <p num="0050">In this case, the ink jet head preferably
includes means for ejecting the droplets of liquid by
application of thermal or vibration energy to the
liquid in models. </p>
    <p num="0051">These and other objects, features, and
advantages of the present invention will become more
apparent upon consideration of the following
description of the preferred embodiments of the
present invention, taken in conjunction with the
accompanying drawings.</p>
    <heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS:</heading>
    <p num="0052">
      <sl>
        <li>Figure 1 is a schematic drawing of an example
of an ink supplying system in an ink jet recording
apparatus which uses a liquid container in accordance
with the present invention.</li>
        <li>Figure 2 is an exploded perspective view of
the liquid container in the first embodiment of the
present invention, shown in Figure 1, and shows the
structural components thereof.</li>
        <li>Figure 3 is a sectional view of the liquid
container in the first embodiment of the present
invention, shown in Figure 1, at a plane inclusive of
the axial line of the container.</li>
        <li>Figure 4 is an external view of the portion
of the elastic member shown in Figure 2, which is
placed, in the compressed state, in the recess of the
elastic member of the liquid container: (a) is a
perspective view; (b) is a plan view; and (c) is a
side view. </li>
        <li>Figure 5 is an external view of the portion
of the elastic member shown in Figure 2, which is
placed, in the virtually uncompressed state, in the
recess of the elastic member of the liquid container:
(a) is a perspective view; (b) is a plan view; and
(c) is a side view.</li>
        <li>Figure 6 is an enlarged sectional view of the
connective portion of the liquid container, shown in
Figure 3, and shows the structural components thereof
prior to the assembly of the liquid container.</li>
        <li>Figure 7 is an enlarged sectional view of the
connective portion of the liquid container, shown in
Figure 3, and shows the structural components thereof
during the assembly of the liquid container.</li>
        <li>Figure 8 is an enlarged sectional view of the
connective portion of the liquid container, shown in
Figure 3, and shows the components thereof after the
completion of the liquid container, that is, after the
placement of the elastic member in the recess of the
elastic member holding member of the liquid container.</li>
        <li>Figure 9 is an enlarged sectional view of the
connective portion of the liquid container, shown in
figure 3, after a connective needle has been inserted
into the liquid container.</li>
        <li>Figure 10 shows a modified shape for the
portion of the elastic member which is placed, in the
compressed state, in the recess of the elastic member 
holding member of the liquid container, and also for
the portion of the elastic member which is placed, in
the virtually uncompressed state, in the recess of the
elastic member holding member o the liquid container.</li>
        <li>Figure 11 is a drawing for describing the elastic
member in the second embodiment of the present
invention, different in shape from the one in the
first embodiment, which is placed at the connective
hole of the liquid container shown in Figure 1: (a) is
an external perspective view; (b) is a plan view; and
(c) is a side view.</li>
        <li>Figure 12 is a drawing for showing the state
of the elastic member shown in Figure 11, prior to its
placement in the recess of the elastic member holding
member of the liquid contain2r.</li>
        <li>Figure 13 is a drawing for showing the state
of the elastic member shown in figure 11, after the
elastic member is compressed toward its axial line in
order to place it in the recess of the elastic member
holding member of the liquid container.</li>
        <li>Figure 14 is a drawing for showing the state
of the elastic member shown in figure 11, after its
placement in the recess.</li>
        <li>Figure 15 is a drawing for showing the state
of the elastic member in the liquid container, when a
connective needle begins to be inserted into the
elastic member. </li>
        <li>Figure 16 is a drawing for showing the state
of the elastic member in the liquid container, after
the completion of the insertion of the connective
needle into the liquid container through the elastic
member.</li>
        <li>Figure 17 is a drawing for showing a modified
version of the elastic member shown in Figure 11.</li>
        <li>Figure 18 is a drawing for showing the
configuration of the elastic member used for the
connective hole of the liquid container in the third
embodiment of the present invention, shown in Figure
1: (a) is a perspective view as seen from diagonally
above the side from which the connective needle is
inserted; (b) is a perspective view as seen from
diagonally below the side opposite to the side from
which the connective needle is inserted; (c) is a plan
view as seen directly above the side from which the
connective needle is inserted; (d) is a side view; and
(e) is a sectional view as seen from the direction A,
at a plane inclusive of the axial line of the elastic
member.</li>
        <li>Figure 19 is a drawing for showing the state
of the elastic member shaped as shown in Figure 18,
after its placement in the recess of the connective
hole of the liquid container shown in Figures 2 and 3.</li>
        <li>Figure 20 is a drawing for showing the state
of the elastic member shaped as shown in Figure 18, 
while the elastic member is pressed into the r2cess.</li>
        <li>Figure 21 is a drawing for showing the state
of the elastic member shaped as shown in Figure 18,
after its placement in the recess of the connective
hole of the liquid container shown in Figures 2 and 3.</li>
        <li>Figure 22 is a drawing for showing the state
of the elastic member (which is not provided with a
conical recess) shaped as shown in Figure 18, after
its placement in the recess of the connective hole of
the liquid container shown in Figures 2 and 3.</li>
        <li>Figure 23 is a drawing for describing the
relationship between the taper angle (angle of
inclined wall) of the conically recessed portion of
the elastic member, in the state shown in Figure 21,
and the taper angle of the leading end portion of the
connective needle.</li>
        <li>Figure 24 is a drawing for showing the
behavior (elastic deformation) of the elastic member
shaped as shown in Figure 18, while the connective
needle is inserted into the elastic member in the
recess of the elastic member holding member of the
liquid container.</li>
        <li>Figure 25 is a drawing for showing the state
of the elastic member shaped as shown in Figure 18,
after the connective needle is completely inserted
into the elastic member in the recess of the elastic
member holding member of the liquid container. </li>
        <li>Figure 26 is a drawing for showing a modified
shape for the elastic member shown in Figure 18.</li>
        <li>Figure 27 is a drawing for describing another
shape, as the fourth embodiment of the present
invention, for the elastic member for the connective
hole of the liquid container in figure 1: (a) is a
perspective view as seen from above the side from
which the connective needle is inserted; (b) is a plan
view as seen directly above the side from which the
connective needle is inserted; (c) is a side View as
Seen from the direction A in (b); (d) is a vertical
sectional view as seen from the direction parallel to
the direction B; and (e) is a vertical sectional view
as seen from the direction perpendicular to the
direction B.</li>
        <li>Figure 28 is a drawing for showing the first
stage of the insertion of the connective needle into
the elastic member, shaped as shown in Figure 27,
after the placement of the elastic member at the
connective hole of the liquid container shown in
Figure 1.</li>
        <li>Figure 29 is a drawing for showing also the
first stage of the insertion of the connective needle
into the elastic member, shaped as shown in Figure 27,
after the placement of the elastic member at the
connective hole of the liquid container shown in
Figure 1. </li>
        <li>Figure 30 is a drawing for showing the second
stage of the insertion of the connective needle into
the elastic member, shaped as shown in Figure 27,
after the placement of the elastic member at the
connective hole of the liquid container shown in
Figure 1.</li>
        <li>Figure 31 is a drawing for showing the final
stage of the insertion of the connective needle into
the elastic member, shaped as shown in Figure 27,
after the placement of the elastic member at the
connective hole of the liquid container shown in
Figure 1.</li>
        <li>Figure 32 is a drawing for showing the
configuration of the elastic member in the fourth
embodiment of the present invention, for the
connective hole of the liquid container shown in
Figure 1: (a) is a side view; (b) is a bottom view
(view as seen from the side opposite to the side from
which the connective needle is inserted); (c) is a
perspective view as seen from diagonally above the
side from which the connective needle is inserted; and
(d) is a perspective view as seen from diagonally
below the side opposite to the side from which the
connective needle is inserted.</li>
        <li>Figure 33 is a drawing for showing also the
elastic member in the fourth embodiment of the present
invention: (a) is a bottom view (view as seen from the 
side opposite to the side from which the connective
needle is inserted); and (b) is a sectional view at
the plane A-A in (a).</li>
        <li>Figure 34 is a drawing for showing the state
of the elastic member shown in Figures 32 and 33,
after the placement of the elastic member in the
recess connected to the connective hole.</li>
        <li>Figure 35 is a drawing for showing the state
of the elastic member shown in Figures 32 and 33,
while the elastic member is pressed into the recess by
the retaining member.</li>
        <li>Figure 36 is a drawing for showing the state
of the elastic member shown in Figures 32 and 33,
after the completion of the placement of the elastic
member in the recess.</li>
        <li>Figure 37 is a drawing for showing the
behavior (elastic deformation) of the elastic member,
shown in Figures 32 and 33, in the recess, while the
connective needle is inserted into the liquid
container.</li>
        <li>Figure 38 is a drawing for showing a
variation of the connective hole of the retaining
member of the liquid container shown in Figure 37.</li>
        <li>Figure 39 is a drawing for showing the state
of the elastic member, shown in Figures 32 and 33, in
the recess, after the completion of the insertion of
the connective needle into the liquid container. </li>
        <li>Figure 40 is a drawing for showing a
variation of the slit of the elastic member shown in
Figures 32 and 33.</li>
        <li>Figure 41 is a drawing for showing another
variation of the slit of the elastic member shown in
Figures 32 and 33.</li>
        <li>Figure 42 is a bottom plan view of the liquid
container equipped with the elastic member shaped as
shown in Figures 32 and 13, depicting the preferable
structural arrangement for the connective hole in the
bottom wall of the liquid container, and its
adjacencies.</li>
        <li>Figure 43 is a schematic perspective view of
an ink jet recording apparatus as an example of a
recording apparatus compatible with a liquid container
in accordance with the present invention.</li>
        <li>Figure 44 is a perspective view of the ink
drawing member for the replaceable liquid container in
accordance with the prior arts, disclosed in Japanese
Laid-open patent Application 5-162333.</li>
        <li>Figure 45 is a drawing for showing the
location of the ink container in accordance with the
prior arts, in which the ink drawing member shown in
Figure 44 is placed.</li>
        <li>Figure 46 is a sectional view of the
essential portion of the liquid container, inclusive
of the portion in which the ink drawing member shown 
in Figure 44 is placed.</li>
        <li>Figure 47 is a sectional view of an example
of a replaceable liquid container in accordance with
the prior arts.</li>
        <li>Figure 48 is a drawing for showing how a
rubber plug for the ink passage portion of the ink
container, which connects the inside and outside of
the ink container, is mounted.</li>
        <li>Figure 49 is a drawing for describing the
problem regarding the structural arrangement, shown in
Figures 47 and 48, of the connective hole of the
liquid container in accordance with the prior arts.</li>
        <li>Figure 50 is a drawing for describing also
the problem regarding the structural arrangement,
shown in Figures 47 and 48, of the connective hole of
the liquid container in accordance with the prior
arts.</li>
      </sl>
    </p>
    <heading>DESCRIPTION OF PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS:</heading>
    <p num="0053">Hereinafter, the preferred embodiments of the
present invention will be described with reference to
the appended drawings.</p>
    <p num="0054">The first object of the present invention is
to provide a liquid container, which can be mounted
into, or dismounted from, the main assembly of an ink 
jet recording apparatus, without leaking the liquid
therein, even after it is left alone for a long period
of time, or it is left alone, with a cylindrical
needle penetrating it, for a long period of time. The
concrete examples of such a liquid container is
disclosed in the description of the first embodiment
of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0055">The second object of the present invention is
to pr2vent the phenomenon that as a cylindrical needle
is pushed through the sealing member of a liquid
container, the elastic member is deformed in such a
manner that the portion of the elastic member around
the needle, on the needle entry side of the sealing
member, is pulled into the elastic member, whereas the
portion of the elastic member around the needle, on
the side opposite to the needle entry side, conically
peels away from the needle, and thereby, to provide a
liquid container, which can be mounted into, or
dismounted from, the main assembly of a recording
apparatus, without allowing the ink therein to leak.
The concrete examples of such a liquid container are
disclosed in the description of the second and third
embodiments of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0056">The third embodiment of the present invention
is to provide a liquid container which can be mounted
into, or dismounted from, the main assembly of a
recording apparatus, without allowing the ink therein 
to leak, even after the liquid container is connected
to the cylindrical needle a substantial number of
times. The concrete examples of such a liquid
container are disclosed in the description of the
fourth and fifth embodiments of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0057">The gist of the present invention is related
to the connective portion of a liquid container, by
which the liquid container is connected to an ink jet
recording apparatus, and is applicable to all the ink
containers disclosed in the first to fifth embodiments
of the present invention. Thus, the ink supplying
system shown in Figure 1 is common through all the
embodiments.</p>
    <p num="0058">Further, the present invention is applicable
an ink supplying system other than the system shown in
Figure 1, as long as the ink supplying system employs
a connective system comprising a connective needle
(cylindrical member) and an elastic member.</p>
    <p num="0059">Figure 1 is a schematic drawing of an example
of an ink supplying system for an ink jet recording
apparatus which uses a liquid container in accordance
with the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0060">The ink supplying system shown in Figure 1
comprises: a liquid container for storing ink 1; an
ink jet head 3 which ejects the ink 1, in the form of
droplets, onto recording medium (unshown), for
recording an image; a liquid supplying tube 4 which is 
a tube for supplying the ink from the liquid container
2 to the ink jet head 3; a liquid drawing needle 7
(cylindrical member) which is inserted into the first
joint 5 of the bottom portion 2a of the liquid
container 2 in order to connect the liquid supplying
tube 4 and liquid container 2; an ambient air drawing
tube 8 for introducing ambient air into the liquid
container by an amount equivalent to the amount by
which ink is drawn out of the liquid container 2
through the liquid drawing needle 7; and an ambient
air introducing needle 9 (cylindrical member) which is
inserted into the second joint 6 of the bottom portion
2a of the liquid container 2, at the same time as the
ink drawing needle 7 is inserted into the
aforementioned first joint 5, in order to connect the
ambient air drawing tube 8 and liquid container 2.
The connective needles 7 and 9 are liquid supplying
tubes with a pointed tip.</p>
    <p num="0061">The ink ejection surface 3a (surface which
has ink ejection orifices) of the ink jet head 3 is
positioned at a level above the lowest point of the
liquid drawing path connected to the liquid container
2, generating negative pressure in the liquid path in
the ink jet head 3. With the presence of this
negative pressure, the meniscus in each ink ejection
orifice remains stable.</p>
    <p num="0062">In this liquid supplying system, as ink is 
ejected from the ink jet head 3, the ink within the
liquid container 2 is drawn out of the liquid
container 2, and is delivered to the ink jet head 3
through the liquid drawing needle 7 and liquid
delivery tube 4. The liquid container 2 is virtually
in the form of a box, and does not deform in response
to the drawing of the ink 1 within the liquid
container 2. Therefore, as the ink 1 is drawn,
atmospheric air enters the liquid container 2 by the
amount equivalent to the amount by which the ink I is
drawn, through the air drawing tube 8 and air drawing
needle 9, making it possible to continuously supply
the ink jet head 3 with ink, while always maintaining
a predetermined amount of negative pressure within the
liquid paths in the ink jet head 3. The ink in the
nozzle is pushed (ejected) out of the nozzle by the
thermal energy from an unshown heat generating element
disposed in the nozzle, adjacent to the ink ejection
orifice of the nozzle, or by the vibratory energy of
an unshown vibratory element disposed in the nozzle,
adjacent to the ink ejection orifice of the nozzle.
Each time the ink is ejected, the nozzle is refilled
with ink by the capillary force of the nozzle. As
this ink ejection cycle, that is, a combination of the
process in which ink is ejected from the nozzle and
the process in which the nozzle is refilled with ink,
is repeated, ink is drawn out of the liquid container 
2 as necessary.</p>
    <p num="0063">First, the liquid container, which is common
through the first to fifth embodiments of the present
invention, will be described with reference to Figure
2 and 3.</p>
    <p num="0064">Figure 2 is an exploded perspective view of
the liquid container shown in Figure 1, and shows the
structural components of the liquid container. Figure
3 is a sectional view of the liquid container shown in
Figure 3, at a plane inclusive of the axial line of
the liquid container.</p>
    <p num="0065">As shown in Figures 2 and 3, the liquid
container 2 common through the first to fifth
embodiments of the present invention comprises the ink
1, a liquid holding portion 12, a compressed elastic
member 18, an uncompressed elastic member 19, an
elastic member retaining member, and an elastic member
storing portion 17.</p>
    <p num="0066">Naturally, the compressed elastic member 18
and uncompressed elastic member 19 are not in the
compressed state when they are not in the elastic
member storing portion 17.</p>
    <p num="0067">Referring to Figure 2, the liquid storing
portion 12 in this embodiment is a container in which
the ink 1 is directly stored. It comprises an opening
13, through which the liquid drawing connective needle
17 and air introducing connective needle 9 (Figure 1) 
are inserted into the internal space of the liquid
storing portion 12, which is shield from the ambience
by the elastic member storing portion 17, through the
compressed elastic member 18 and uncompressed elastic
member 19.</p>
    <p num="0068">The liquid storing portion 12 is formed by
direct blow molding or injection molding. Its size
may be varied according to the amount by which liquid
needs to be contained therein.</p>
    <p num="0069">The opening 13 of the liquid storage portion
12 is covered with the elastic member storing portion
17, which is attached to the liquid storage portion 12
with the use of ultrasonic welding or gluing. The
elastic member storing portion 17 is provided with a
pair of recesses 17a in which the compressed elastic
member 18 and uncompressed elastic member 19 are
housed.</p>
    <p num="0070">In order to prevent the compressed elastic
members 18 and uncompressed elastic members 19 housed
in the recesses 17a from becoming dislodged from the
recesses 17a, the elastic member retaining member 15
is attached to the elastic member storing portion 17
by ultrasonic welding, gluing, or the like, completing
the liquid container 2.</p>
    <p num="0071">Referring to Figure 3, as the liquid
container 2 is assembled as described above, the
internal space of the liquid storage portion 12 
becomes sealed, forming a sealed chamber, which
constitutes a liquid chamber for storing one of the
various inks used by an ink jet recording apparatus to
record one of the various colors.</p>
    <p num="0072">When the liquid container 2 is in an ink jet
recording apparatus (Figure 1), the liquid chamber lk
constitutes the top side of the ink container 2. The
opening 13 of the liquid containing portion 12 is
covered with the elastic member storing portion 17,
which is attached to the liquid containing portion 12.
The elastic member storing portion 17 is provided with
a first connective hole 5 and a second connective hole
6 through which the liquid drawing connective needle 7
and air introducing connective needle 9 are placed
into the liquid chamber 16. One end of the first
connective hole 5 is covered with a combination of the
compressed elastic member 18 and uncompressed elastic
member 19, and one end of the second connective hole 6
is covered with another combination of the compressed
elastic member 18 and uncompressed elastic member 19.
The connective needles 7 and 9 are put through the
corresponding combinations of the compressed elastic
member 18 and uncompressed elastic member 19,
establishing a pair of passages between the inside and
outside of the liquid chamber 16.</p>
    <heading>(Embodiment 1)</heading>
    <p num="0073">Next, referring to Figures 2 - 9, the first 
embodiment of the present invention will be described.</p>
    <p num="0074">In this embodiment, the compressed elastic
member 18 is used as an elastic member which is
subjected to compressive force as it is placed into
the liquid container 2. In comparison, the
uncompressed elastic member 19 is not subjected to
compressive force as it is placed into the liquid
container 2. It is subjected to compressive force for
the first time as the connective needles (cylindrical
members) are inserted.</p>
    <p num="0075">In the following descriptions of the
embodiments of the present invention, "uncompressed
state" means such a state of the elastic member that
the compression pressure generated in the elastic
member by the external force is not present in the
elastic member.</p>
    <p num="0076">Figure 4 is an external view of the
compressed elastic member 18 shown in Figure 2: Figure
4(a) is a perspective external view; Figure 4(b) is a
plan view; and Figure 4(c) is a side view. Figure 5
is an external view of the uncompressed elastic member
19; Figure 5(a) is a perspective external view; Figure
5(b) is a plan view; and Figure 5(c) is a side view.</p>
    <p num="0077">Figure 6 is a sectional view of the liquid
container 2 shown in Figure 3, before the connective
holes 5 and 6 are covered with the combinations of the
compressed elastic member 18 and uncompressed elastic 
member 19. Figure 7 is a sectional view of the liquid
container 2 shown in Figure 3, after only the
compressed elastic members 18 have been housed in the
recesses 17a of the elastic member storing portion 17.
Figure 8 is a sectional view of the liquid container 2
shown in Figure 3, after the combination of the
compressed elastic member 18 and uncompressed elastic
member 19 has been housed in the recesses 17a of the
elastic member storing portion 17 to cover the
connective holes 15 and 16.</p>
    <p num="0078">Figure 9 shows the state of the liquid
container 2 after the insertion of the connective
needle 7. Figures 6 - 9 only show how the elastic
members are mounted to cover the connective hole 5,
and how the elastic members are penetrated by the
connective needle 7. However, the state of the liquid
container 2 after the insertion of the connective
needle 9 through the elastic members 18 and 19, how
the elastic members are mounted to cover the
connective hole 6, and how the elastic members 18 and
19 are penetrated by the connective needle 9, are the
same as those shown in Figures 69.</p>
    <p num="0079">Referring to Figures 4 and 5, the compressed
elastic member 18 and uncompressed elastic member 19,
as plugs for connective holes 5 and 6, respectively,
which characterize this first embodiment, are
approximately cylindrical. prior to their placement 
into the recesses of the elastic member storing
portion 17, the diameter of the compressed elastic
member 18 is greater than that of the uncompressed
elastic member 19.</p>
    <p num="0080">Next, referring to Figures 6 - 8, how the
compressed elastic member 18 and uncompressed elastic
member 19 shaped as shown in Figures 4 and 5 are
placed into the recesses of the elastic member holding
portion 17 to cover the connective holes 5 and 6 shown
in Figures 2 and 3, will be described.</p>
    <p num="0081">In Figure 6, a referential code 17a
designates a recess, in which the combination of the
compressed elastic member 18 and uncompressed elastic
member 19 is placed to cover the connective hole 5
which leads to the liquid chamber 16. The internal
diameter d1 of the recess 17a is virtually the same
the external diameter w2 of the uncompressed elastic
member 19.</p>
    <p num="0082">In comparison, the external diameter w1 of
the compressed elastic member 18, prior to its
placement in the recess 17a, is greater than the
internal diameter d1 of the recess 17a. Before the
placement of the compressed elastic member 18 and
uncompressed elastic member 19 in the recesses 17a, no
force is active in the compressed elastic member 18
and uncompressed elastic member 19.</p>
    <p num="0083">Next, referring to Figure 7, the uncompressed 
elastic member 19 is placed in the recess 17a of the
elastic member holding portion 17. Since the internal
diameter d1 of the recess 17a and the external
diameter w2 of the uncompressed elastic member 19 are
virtually identical, the uncompressed elastic member
19 is not compressed as it is placed in the recess
17a.</p>
    <p num="0084">Next, the compressed elastic member 18 is
placed in the recess 17a of the elastic member holding
member 17. Unlike the uncompressed elastic member 19,
the external diameter w1 of the compressed elastic
member 18 prior to its placement in the recess 17a
(contoured by a double-dot chain line in Figure 7) is
greater than the internal diameter d1 of the recess
17a.</p>
    <p num="0085">Thus, without some modifications, the
compressed elastic member 18 cannot be placed in the
recess 17a. Therefore, the compressed elastic member
18 is placed in the recess 17a after it is compressed
in the radius direction (direction indicated by an
arrow mark A in Figure 7) until its external diameter
d1 is reduced to a diameter w1 (contoured by a solid
line in Figure 7), which is the same as, or slightly
smaller than, the internal diameter d1 of the recess
17a.</p>
    <p num="0086">Then, in order to prevent the compressed
elastic member 18 and uncompressed elastic member 19 
from becoming dislodged from the recess 17a, the
retaining member 15 is attached to the elastic member
holding member 17 as shown in Figure 8. In this
state, the resiliency of the compressed elastic member
18 generates such force that acts in the direction to
expands the compressed elastic member 18 in the radius
direction of the compressed elastic member 18
(direction indicated by an arrow A in Figure 8). This
force is confined by the wall of the recess 17a. As a
result, reactive force acts toward the center of the
compressed elastic member 18 as indicated by an arrow
mark B in Figure 8.</p>
    <p num="0087">In consideration of the fact that giving the
compressed elastic member 18 and 19 a cylindrical
external shape (making cylindrical the interfaces
between the peripheral surfaces of the elastic members
and the side wall of the recess 17a) makes it easier
for the compressive force to concentrate to the
centers of the elastic members 18 and 19, the most
desirable configuration for the elastic members 18 and
19 is a cylindrical one as shown in Figures 4 and 5.
However, as long as a predetermined amount of
compressive force is generated in the elastic members
18 and 19, the elastic members 18 and 19 do not need
to be cylindrical; for example, they may be in the
form of a square pillar, as shown in Figure 10.</p>
    <p num="0088">When the uncompressed elastic member 19 is in 
the state shown in Figure 8, no compressive force is
active in the uncompressed elastic member 19.</p>
    <p num="0089">In comparison, when the compressed elastic
member 18 is in the position shown in Figure 8, the
compressed elastic member 18 remains in the compressed
state whether the connective needle is in the
compressed elastic member 18 or not.</p>
    <p num="0090">Figure 9 shows the state of the liquid
container 2 after the penetration of the connective
needle 7 through the compressed elastic member 18 and
uncompressed elastic member 19.</p>
    <p num="0091">Compressive force is active in the compressed
elastic member 18, as shown in Figure 8, even before
its penetration by the connective needle 7.</p>
    <p num="0092">Therefore, as the connective needle 7 is put
through the compressed elastic member 18, the
compressive force within the compressed elastic member
18 is increased by an amount proportional to the
volume of the portion of the connective needle 7
within the compressed elastic member 18.</p>
    <p num="0093">In comparison, as the connective needle 7 is
put through the uncompressed elastic member 19, the
uncompressed elastic member 19, the external diameter
of which is virtually the same as the diameter d1 of
the recess 17a, expands in the radius direction of the
recess 17a, being therefore subjected to the reactive
force from the wall of the recess 17a. In other 
words, compressive force is active in the uncompressed
elastic member 19 only when the connective needle 7 is
in the uncompressed elastic member 19, and the amount
of this compressive force in the uncompressed elastic
member 19 is proportional to the volume of the portion
of the connective needle 7 in the uncompressed elastic
member 19. As is evident from the above description,
the amount of the compressive force generated in the
uncompressed elastic member 19 is smaller than that in
the compressed elastic member 18. The compressive
stress is present in the uncompressed elastic member
19 only when the connective needle 7 is in the
uncompressed elastic member 19.</p>
    <p num="0094">Therefore, during the period from when the
liquid container 2 is manufactured to when the liquid
container 2 is discarded, the cumulative length of the
time in which the compression pressure is present in
the uncompressed elastic member 19 is shorter than the
cumulative length of time in which the compression
pressure is present in the compressed elastic member
18.</p>
    <p num="0095">Generally speaking, the greater the amount of
the compressive pressure to which an elastic substance
is subjected, and the longer the time an elastic
substance is subjected to compressive pressure, the
greater the amount of creep (degree of the gradual and
permanent deformation of a body produced by a 
continued application of stress; degree of permanent
deformation). In the case of the structure of the
liquid container 2 in this embodiment of the present
invention, the amount of the permanent compression
deformation of the uncompressed elastic member 19 is
smaller than that of the compressed elastic member 18.
If the compressed elastic member 18 and uncompressed
elastic member 19 are left undisturbed for a long
time, with connective needle 7 penetrating them, creep
occurs to both members 18 and 19. However, the amount
of the creep which occurs to the uncompressed elastic
member 19 is extremely small being virtually nil. In
other words, it is assured that even after the
uncompressed elastic member 19 is left undisturbed for
a long time with the needle 7 left in the uncompressed
elastic member 19, as soon as the needle 7 is pulled
out of the uncompressed elastic member 19, the
uncompressed elastic member 19 regains its original
configuration; in other words, it reclaims the space
which the needle 7 had been occupying in the
uncompressed elastic member 19, preventing ink from
dripping from the connective hole 5.</p>
    <p num="0096">The effectiveness of the present invention is
not affected by whether or not the ink jet head 3 and
liquid container 2 are disposed apart from each other,
or whether or not there is a space between the
compressed elastic member 18 and uncompressed elastic 
member 19. However, when there is a space between the
compressed elastic member 18 and uncompressed elastic
member 19, the air within the space expands or
contracts in response to the changes in ambience.
This expansion or contraction of the air within the
space affects the internal pressure of the compressed
elastic member 18 and uncompressed elastic member 19.
Thus, it is desired that there is no space between the
compressed elastic member 18 and uncompressed elastic
member 19 as in this embodiment.</p>
    <p num="0097">Further, the effectiveness of the present
invention is not affected by the number of the
compressed elastic member 18 or uncompressed elastic
member 19, the position of the compressed elastic
member 18 or uncompressed elastic member 19 relative
to the opening of the retaining member 1S, the order
in which the compressed elastic member 18 and
uncompressed elastic member 19 are placed with respect
to the opening of the retaining member 15, or how the
compressed elastic member 18 and uncompressed elastic
member 19 are combined. However, for the
effectiveness of the present invention, it is
preferable that the uncompressed elastic member 19 is
disposed on the side from which the needle 7 comes out
first, that is, on the liquid holding portion side.
With this structural arrangement, the reversion of the
uncompressed elastic member 19 begins in the early 
stage of the removal of the liquid container 2, and
ends before the connective needle 7 will have
completely come out of the compressed elastic member
18.</p>
    <p num="0098">The changes shown in Figure 9, which occur to
the elastic members 18 and 19 as the connective needle
7 is put through the elastic members 18 and 19, are
the same as those which occur to the elastic members
18 and 19 as the connective needle 9 is put through
the elastic members 18 and 19.</p>
    <heading>(Embodiment 2)</heading>
    <p num="0099">Next, referring to Figures 11 - 17, the second embodiment of the present invention
will be described. The structural components in this
embodiment, which are identical to those shown in
Figures 1 - 3, are given the same referential codes as
those given to the corresponding structural components
in Figures 1 - 3, so that a part of the description of
the first embodiment can be used as the description of
some of the structural components in this embodiment.</p>
    <p num="0100">Figure 11 is a schematic drawing for
describing the configuration of the elastic member
placed in the recess of the elastic member holding
member 17 of the liquid container: Figure 11(a) is an
external perspective view of the elastic member;
Figure 11(b), a plan view of the elastic member; and
Figure 11(c) is a side view of the elastic member.</p>
    <p num="0101">Figures 12 - 14 show the various stages 
through which the elastic member 40 shown in Figure 11
is placed in the recess 17a of the elastic member
holding member 17 of the liquid container, and the
retaining member 15 is fixed to the elastic member
holding member 17. Figure 12 shows the elastic member
42 before its placement in the recess 17a, and Figure
13 shows the elastic member 42 which has been
compressed toward its center in order to place it in
the recess 17a of the elastic member holding member
17. Figure 14 shows the elastic member 42 after the
completion of its placement.</p>
    <p num="0102">Figure 15 shows the state of elastic member
42 when the connective needle begins to be inserted
into the elastic member 42, and Figure 16 shows the
state of the elastic member 42 when the insertion of
the connective needle 7 through the elastic member 42
has been completed.</p>
    <p num="0103">In Figures 11 - 17, the placement of the
elastic member 42 and the insertion of the connective
needle are depicted with reference to the connective
hole 5. The placement of the elastic member 42 in a
manner to plug the connective hole 6, and the
insertion of the connective needle through the elastic
member 42 placed in a manner to plug the connective
hole 6, are as shown in Figures 11 - 17 with reference
to the connective hole 5.</p>
    <p num="0104">Referring to Figure 11, the elastic member 42 
in this embodiment essentially comprises two portions:
cylindrical main portion 42a and smaller cylindrical
portion 42b smaller in diameter than the cylindrical
main portion 42a. The smaller cylindrical portion 42b
projects from the center of one of the end surfaces of
the cylindrical main portion 42a.</p>
    <p num="0105">Figure 12 shows the state of the elastic
member 42 before its placement in the recess 17a of
the elastic member holding member 17, in which the
elastic member 42 is to be placed in a manner to plug
the connective hole 5 which leads to the liquid
chamber 16. The external diameter w1 of the
cylindrical main portion 42a is greater than the
internal diameter d1 of the recess 17a, and the
external diameter w2 of the smaller ,cylindrical
portion 42b is smaller than the internal diameter d2
of the connective hole 5.</p>
    <p num="0106">Referring to Figure 13, which shows one of
the stages through which the elastic member 42 is
placed in the recess 17a of the liquid container 2,
the external diameter w1 of the cylindrical main
portion 42a of the elastic member 42 is greater than
the internal diameter d1 of the recess 17a.

Therefore, the elastic member 42 cannot be properly
placed in the recess 17a unless the elastic member 42
is modified in a certain way.</p>
    <p num="0107">Thus, pressure is applied to the cylindrical 
main portion 42a in the direction indicated by an
arrow mark A in Figure 13 so that the elastic member
42, the shape of which is contoured by a double-dot
chain line in Figure 13 is compressed into the shape
contoured by the solid line in Figure 13; in other
words, the external diameter w1 of the cylindrical
main portion 42a becomes the same as, or smaller than,
the internal diameter d1 of the recess 17a (external
diameter w1' of the cylindrical main portion 42a after
its compression). Then, the elastic member 42 is
placed in the recess 17a in the direction indicated by
an arrow mark B in the drawing, while being kept in
the above described compressed state.</p>
    <p num="0108">Thereafter, the retaining member 15 is fixed
to the elastic member holding portion 17, realizing
the liquid container 2 shown in Figure 14. In this
state, the resiliency of the cylindrical main portion
42a acts in the direction to expand the cylindrical
main portion 42a in the radius direction of the
cylindrical main portion 42a (direction indicated by
an arrow A in Figure 8), applying pressure upon the
wall of the recess 17a.</p>
    <p num="0109">This pressure is confined by the wall of the
recess 17a. As a result, reactive force from this
pressure acts toward the center of the cylindrical
main portion 42a as indicated by an arrow mark in
Figure 14. </p>
    <p num="0110">In consideration of the fact that giving the
main portion 42a a cylindrical external shape (making
cylindrical the interfaces between the peripheral
surfaces of the elastic members and the side wall of
the recess 17a) makes it easier for the reactive force
from the compression pressure to concentrate to the
centers of the main portion 42a, the most desirable
configuration for the main portion 42a is a
cylindrical one as shown in Figures 11. However, as
long as a predetermined amount of compression pressure
is generated in the main portion 42a, the main portion
42a does not need to be cylindrical; for example, it
may be in the form of a square pillar, as shown n
Figure 47.</p>
    <p num="0111">Figure 15 shows the elastic deformation of
the elastic member 42 at the beginning of the
insertion of the connective needle 7. As a relatively
thick connective needle 7 begins to be inserted into
the elastic member 42, the elastic member 42 deforms
as shown in Figure 15. if it were not for the small
cylindrical portion 42b, the elastic member 42 would
deform into the connective hole 5 in such a manner
that the portion of the elastic member around the
needle, on the needle entry side of the sealing
member, is pulled into the elastic member, whereas the
portion of the elastic member around the needle, on
the side opposite to the needle entry side, conically 
peels away from the needle. In this embodiment,
however, the connective hole 5 is occupied with the
small cylindrical portion 42b, being disposed on the
side toward which the connective needle 7 is inserted,
that is, being in the connective hole 5 into which the
elastic member 42 would be otherwise dislodged. This
presence of the small cylindrical portion 42b in the
connective hole 5, and the rigidity of the small
cylindrical portion 42b, makes it less likely for the
elastic member 42 in this embodiment to be dislodged
into the connective hole 5, compared to an elastic
member without the small cylindrical portion 42b.
Therefore, the elastic member 42 is prevented from
becoming permanently indented (Figure 49(b)). Thus,
the connective needle 7 can be desirably put through
the elastic member 42 as shown in Figure 16; it is
possible to prevent the size of the contact area
between the connective needle 7 and elastic member 42
from being reduced by the conical peeling of the
elastic member 42, and the formation of the permanent
indentation, in the direction in which the connective
needle is inserted.</p>
    <p num="0112">Further, the provision of the small
cylindrical portion 42b increases the size of the
contact area between the connective needle 7 and the
elastic member 42, increasing the effectiveness of the
elastic member 42 in sealing between itself and 
connective needle 7. In other words, the sealing
performance of the elastic member 42 is less likely to
be affected by the changes in the internal and/or
external pressure of the liquid container.</p>
    <p num="0113">In other words, the liquid container, which
can be mounted or dismounted without allowing the
liquid therein to leak, can be realized by securing
the sufficient amount of contact surface between the
elastic member 42 and connective needle 7 by
preventing the phenomenon that the elastic member is
deformed in such a manner that the portion of the
surface of the elastic member surrounding the entry
point of the connective needle is swallowed into the
elastic member itself, and that the internal portion
of the elastic member, the position of which coincides
with the passage of the connective needle, conically
peels away from the connective needle, on the side
opposite to the entry point of the connective needle.
As described before, the prevention of the above
description is the second object of the present
invention.</p>
    <p num="0114">The effects of the second embodiment, which
are similar to those of the first embodiment, are as
follows. In other words, even when the connective
needle 7 is pulled out of the liquid container after
it was left in the elastic member 42 for a long period
of time, the connective hole 5 remains satisfactorily 
sealed. When the elastic member 42 is in the state
shown in Figure 14, the cylindrical main portion 42a
is in the compressed state. In comparison, in the
small cylindrical portion 42b, compression stress is
present only when the connective needle 7 is in the
small cylindrical portion 42b. Therefore, referring
to Figure 16, in the case of the cylindrical main
portion 42a in which compression pressure is present
even before the insertion of the connective needle 7,
as the connective needle 7 is inserted into the
cylindrical main portion 42a, the compression pressure
in the cylindrical main portion 42a is increased by
the amount proportional to the volume of the portion
of the connective needle 7 in the cylindrical main
portion 42a.</p>
    <p num="0115">In comparison, in the case of the smaller
cylindrical portion 42b, the diameter of which is
virtually the same as the internal diameter d2 of the
recess 17b, as the connective needle 7 is inserted
into the smaller cylindrical portion 42b, the
connective needle 7 generates such force that acts in
the direction to expand the smaller cylindrical
portion 42b in the radius direction of the recess 17b.
However, the smaller cylindrical portion 42b is
confined in the recess 17a.</p>
    <p num="0116">Therefore, it is prevented by the wall of the
recess 17a from expanding in the radius direction of 
the recess 17a. As a result, it is compressed,
generating compression pressure therein. In other
words, compression pressure is present in the smaller
cylindrical portion 42b only after the insertion of
the connective needle 7 into the smaller cylindrical
portion 42b, and the amount of this compression
pressure is approximately proportional to the volume
of the portion of the connective needle 7 in the
smaller cylindrical portion 42b.</p>
    <p num="0117">Thus, effects similar to those obtained by
the first embodiment are also obtained by the second
embodiment. The deterioration of the elasticity of
the smaller cylindrical portion 42b, which occurs with
elapse of time, is smaller than that of the
cylindrical main portion 42a. This is for the
following reason. If the elastic member 42 is left
undisturbed for a long period of time, with the
connective needle 7 penetrating it, creep occurs to
the elastic member 42; in other words, the elastic
member 42 fails to completely revert to its original
shape and volume after the removal of the connective
needle 7. This phenomenon, or creep, is less likely
to occur to the smaller cylindrical portion 42b.
Therefore, even when the connective needle 7 is pulled
out of the elastic member 42 after being left therein
for a long period of time, the connective hole 5
remains properly sealed by the cylindrical portion 
42b.</p>
    <heading>(Embodiment 3)</heading>
    <p num="0118">Next, referring to Figures 18 - 25, the third
embodiment of the present invention will be described.
Any structural component in this embodiment which is
the same as one of the structural components in the
first embodiment shown in Figures 1 - 3, will be given
the same referential code as the one given to the same
component, so that the description of the same
component in the first embodiment can be used as a
reference.</p>
    <p num="0119">Figure 18 is a drawing for describing the
configuration of the elastic member for the connective
hole of the liquid container shown in Figure 1: (a) is
a perspective view as seen from diagonally above the
side from which the connective needle is inserted; (b)
is a perspective view as seen from diagonally above
the side opposite 2 to the side from which the
connective needle is inserted; (c) is a plan view as
seen from the side from which the connective needle is
inserted; (d) is a side view; and (e) is a sectional
view as Seen from the direction A in (c).</p>
    <p num="0120">As shown in Figures 18(a) - 18(2), the
elastic member 43 in this embodiment is approximately
semispherical (dome-shaped), bulging toward the
direction from which the connective needle is
inserted. The top portion of the elastic member 43, 
that is, the portion equivalent to the top of a dome,
is conically recessed forming a conically recessed
portion 43a. On the other hand, the concaved bottom
side, or the side opposite to the side from which the
connective needle is inserted, is provided with a
cylindrical portion 43b, which is located at the
bottom, or the center, of the concaved surface.</p>
    <p num="0121">Figures 19 and 20 show how the elastic member
43 shown in Figure 18 is placed in the recess 17a of
the elastic member holding portion 17 in a manner to
plug the connective holes 5 and 6 of the liquid
container shown in Figures 2 and 3, and how the
retaining member 15 is attached to the elastic member
holding portion 17 to k2ep the elastic member 43 in
the recess 17a. Figure 19 shows the state of the
elastic member 43 after its placement in the recess
17a in a manner to cover the connective holes 5 and 6,
and Figure 20 shows the elastic member 43 which is
being pressed down by the retaining member 15. Figure
21 shows the state of the elastic member 43 after the
completion of its placement in the recess 17a.</p>
    <p num="0122">Although these drawings show only the
connective hole 5 as the hole to be covered with the
elastic member 43, the connective hole 6 also is
covered with the elastic member 43 (different from the
one covering the hole 5).</p>
    <p num="0123">Referring to Figure 19, the recess 17a is 
where the elastic member 43 is placed to plug the
connective hole 5 leading to the liquid chamber 16.
The internal diameter of the recess 17a is virtually
the same as the external diameter of the elastic
member 43. If the external diameter of the elastic
member 43 is slightly smaller than the internal
diameter of the recess 17a, it is easier to place the
elastic member 43 in the recess 17a.</p>
    <p num="0124">Even if the external diameter of the elastic
member 43 is greater than the internal diameter of
the recess 17a, this does not cause any problem (it
is not difficult to place the elastic member 43 in
the recess 17a unless the diameter of the elastic
member 43 is disproportionately larger than the
internal diameter of the recess 17a), since the shape
of the elastic member 43 can be easily changed by the
application of force. The elastic member 42 is a
monolithic member, and in the form of a dome with a
predetermined curvature.</p>
    <p num="0125">Referring to Figure 20, as the retaining
member 15 is attached to the liquid container, the
elastic member 43 is pressed down by the pressing
portion 23 of the retaining member 15. The length of
the ridge line of the budging side of the dome- shaped
elastic member 43 is greater than the internal
diameter of the recess 17a. Therefore, not only does
the pressure applied to the elastic member 43 by the 
retaining member 15 act in the direction to press the
elastic member 43 down, but also in the direction to
spread the elastic member 43 in the radius direction
of the recess 17a.</p>
    <p num="0126">However, the elastic member 43 is confined in
the recess 17a, being prevented from spreading in the
radius direction, by the wall of the recess 17a.</p>
    <p num="0127">As a result, pressure is generated in the
elastic member 43 in the direction to concentrate to
the center of the elastic member 43.</p>
    <p num="0128">As for the external configuration of the
elastic member 43, from the standpoint of directing
the internal pressure of the elastic member 43 toward
its center, the cross section of the elastic member 43
perpendicular to its axial line is desired to be
circular as shown in Figure 18. However, it does not
need to be circular as long as a predetermined amount
of internal pressure can be concentrated to the center
of the elastic member 43. for example, it may be
square as shown in Figure 26.</p>
    <p num="0129">Next, referring to Figure 21, after the
completion of the placement of the elastic member 43
in the recess 17a, the compression pressure, which is
generated in the direction to concentrate to the axial
line of the elastic member 43 by the pressure from the
pressing portion 23 of the retaining member 15 and the
wall of the recess 17a, is present only in the very 
portion of the elastic member 43, which was dome-shaped
prior to the placement of the elastic member 43
in the recess 17a. In comparison, there is no
compression pressure in the cylindrical portion 43b of
the elastic member 43, since the external diameter W
of the cylindrical portion 43b is smaller than the
internal diameter d of the connective hole 5.</p>
    <p num="0130">If the surface of the top portion of the
elastic member 43, or the portion through which the
connective needle 7 is put, is not conically recessed
as shown in Figure 20, in other words, if it is
consistent with the curvature of the dome- shaped
portion of the elastic member 43, it will bulge into
the hole of the retaining member 15 as shown in Figure
22, as it is pressed down by the retaining member 15,
since the top portion of the elastic member 43 does
not come into contact with the retaining member 15,
being therefore not pressed down by the retaining
member 15.</p>
    <p num="0131">Referring to Figure 22, if an attempt is made
to insert the connective needle 7 into the elastic
member 43 through the connective hole 5 when the
elastic member 43 is in the state shown in Figure 22,
the portion 43d (hatched portion) of the elastic
member 43, which has bulged into the hole of the
retaining member 15, is not allowed to move in the
radius direction. Therefore, the portion 43d of the 
elastic member 43 is pushed back into the portion of
the elastic member 43 in the recess 17a, making it
likely for this portion of the elastic member 43 to be
conically indented following the movement of the
connective needle 7 into the elastic member 43.</p>
    <p num="0132">This is why the top portion of the dome-shaped
elastic member 43, that is, the portion
correspondent to the hole of the retaining member 15-1
is conically indented, eliminating the portion of the
elastic member 43 which otherwise would be pushed into
the portion of the elastic member 43 in the recess 17a
by the connective needle 7.</p>
    <p num="0133">With the provision of this structural
arrangement, the elastic member 43 does not bulge in
the form of a dome (portion 43d) into the hole of the
retaining member 15 as shown in Figure 22.</p>
    <p num="0134">Instead, the top portion of the elastic
member 43 becomes virtually flat or slightly indented
as represented by a portion 43a in Figure 21, as the
retaining member 15 is pressed down onto the elastic
member 43. Therefore, it does not occur that as the
connective needle 7 is inserted into the elastic
member 43, the portion of the elastic member 43 around
the entry point of the connective needle into the
elastic member 43 is conically pulled into the elastic
member 43 by the connective needle 7.</p>
    <p num="0135">Regarding the configuration of the top 
portion of the dome-shaped elastic member 43, as long
as it does not cause the elastic member 43 to bulge
into the hole of the retaining member 15 as shown in
Figure 22, it does not need to be conically indented,
although the effectiveness of the elastic member 43 in
this embodiment varies depending on the configuration.
Further, the portion 43d bulging above the contact
surface between the retaining member 15 and elastic
member 43 may be simply cut off to make this portion
of the elastic member 43 flat.</p>
    <p num="0136">If the angle of the taper of the conically
indented portion 43a of the elastic member 43
(inclination of the side wall) is made virtually the
same as the angle a of the taper of the tip of the
connective needle 7, there will be virtually no object
which resists the tip of the connective needle 7 as
the connective needle 7 is inserted into the conically
indented portion 43a of the elastic member 43 through
the connective hole 5 when the elastic member 43 is in
the state shown in Figure 21. Therefore, the
connective needle 7 can be smoothly inserted.</p>
    <p num="0137">The portion 43a of the elastic member 43
through which the connective needle 7 is inserted is
conically indented. Therefore, the force applied to
the elastic member 43 by the connective needle 7 in
the direction parallel to the axial direction of the
elastic member 43 as the connective needle 7 is pushed 
into the elastic member 43 is diverted in the radius
direction of the elastic member 43 by a substantially
larger amount than it is diverted in the axial
direction of the elastic member 43, making it less
likely for the portion of the elastic member 43 around
the connective needle 7 to be conically pulled into
the elastic member 43 itself by the movement of the
connective needle 7 into the elastic member 43. In
other words, the provision of the conically indented
portion 43a prevents the connective needle entry
portion of the elastic member 43 from being pulled
into the elastic member 43 itself. Figure 24 shows
the behavior (elastic deformation) of the elastic
member 43 which occurs to the elastic member 43 during
the insertion of the connective needle 7. As shown in
Figure 24, as an attempt is made to insert a
relatively thick connective needle 7 into the elastic
member 43, the elastic member 43 d2forms.</p>
    <p num="0138">However, the elastic member 43 is provided
with the cylindrical portion 43b, the diameter W of
which is smaller than the diameter of the connective
hole 5, and which is located on the downstream side in
terms of the direction in which the connective needle
7 is inserted. Further, the cylindrical portion 43b
is confined in the connective hole 5, the diameter of
which is smaller than the diameter d1 of the recess
17a. </p>
    <p num="0139">Therefore, the portion of the elastic member
43 around the connective needle 7 is not likely to
follow the connective needle 7 as the connective
needle 7 is pushed through the elastic member 43.</p>
    <p num="0140">Therefore, the portion of the elastic member
43 around the exit point of the connective needle 7
from the elastic member 43 is not likely be conically
peels away from the connective needle 7 (Figure
49(b)). In other words, according to this embodiment,
the amount by which the contact area between the
connective needle 7 and elastic member 43 is reduced
by the occurrence of the conical peeling and conical
indentation is much smaller compared to an elastic
member in accordance with the prior arts.</p>
    <p num="0141">The provision of the cylindrical portion
increases the contact area between the connective
needle 7 and elastic member 43, improving the elastic
member 43 in its ability to prevent the liquid within
the liquid container from being leaked by the changes
in the internal or ambient pressure of the liquid
container.</p>
    <p num="0142">To sum up, according to this second
embodiment of the present invention, the portion of
the elastic member 43 around the connective needle
entry point is prevented from being pulled into the
elastic member 43 itself, and also, the hole created
in the elastic member 43 by the connective needle 7 is 
prevented from conically widening, on the leading end
side of the elastic member 43 in terms of the
direction in which the connective needle 7 is
inserted. Therefore, the contact area formed between
the connective needle 7 and elastic member 43 as the
connective needle 7 is inserted into the elastic
member 43 is substantially larger than that formed
between the connective needle 7 and a conventional
elastic member as the connective needle 7 is inserted
into the conventional elastic member. Therefore, it
is assured that the ink jet head 3 and liquid
container 2 can be connected or disconnected without
leaking liquid.</p>
    <p num="0143">The effects of the third embodiment, some of
which are peculiar to the third embodiment, and the
other of which are the same as those of the first
embodiment, are as follows. In other words, the third
embodiment also assures that the connective hole 5
remains properly sealed even when the connective
needle 7 is pulled out after it is left in the elastic
member 43 for a long period of time. When the elastic
member 43 is in the state shown in Figures 21 and 22,
no compression pressure is present in the cylindrical
portion 43b of the elastic member 43. In comparison,
the dome-shaped portion of the elastic member 43 is
always in the compressed state, whether or not the
connective needle is in it. </p>
    <p num="0144">Figure 25 shows the state of the elastic
member 43 after the complete penetration of the
connective needle 7 through the elastic member 43.</p>
    <p num="0145">As is shown in Figure 25, in the case of the
dome- shaped portion of the elastic member 43 in which
compression pressure is present even before the
insertion of the connective needle 7, as the
connective needle 7 is inserted into the dome- shaped
portion of the elastic member 43, the compression
pressure in the dome-shaped portion of the elastic
member 43 is increased by the amount proportional to
the volume of the portion of the connective needle 7
in the dome-shaped portion of the elastic member 43.
In comparison, in the case of the cylindrical portion
43b, the diameter of which is smaller than the
internal diameter of the connective hole 5, as the
connective needle 7 is inserted into the cylindrical
portion 43b, the cylindrical portion 43b expands in
the radius direction of the connective hole 5, and
presses upon the wall of the connective hole 5. As a
result, it is compressed, generating compression
pressure therein. In other words, compression
pressure is present in the cylindrical portion 43b
only after the insertion of the connective needle 7
into the cylindrical portion 43b, and the amount of
this compression pressure is approximately
proportional to the volume of the portion of the 
connective needle 7 in the cylindrical portion 43b.</p>
    <p num="0146">As is evident from the above description, the
compression pressure generated in the dome-shaped
portion of the elastic member 43 is greater than that
generated in the cylindrical portion 43a of the
elastic member 43.</p>
    <p num="0147">Further, compression stress is present in the
cylindrical portion 43b only when the connective
needle 7 is inserted into, or in, the cylindrical
portion 43b. Therefore, during the period from when
the liquid container 2 is manufactured to when the
liquid container 2 is discarded, the cumulative length
of the time in which the compression pressure is
present in the dome-shaped portion of the elastic
member 43 is longer than the cumulative length of time
in which the compression pressure is present in the
cylindrical portion 43b.</p>
    <p num="0148">Thus, effects similar to those obtained by
the first embodiment are also obtained by the third
embodiment. The deterioration of the elasticity of
the cylindrical portion 43b, which occurs with elapse
of time, is smaller than that of the dome- shaped
portion of the elastic member 43. This is for the
following reason. If the elastic member 43 is left
alone for a long period of time, with the connective
needle 7 penetrating it, creep occurs to the elastic
member 43; in other words, the elastic member 43 fails 
to completely revert to its original shape and volume
after the removal of the connective needle 7. This
phenomenon, or creep, is less likely to occur to the
cylindrical portion 43b. Therefore, even when the
connective needle 7 is pulled out of the elastic
member 43 after being left therein for a long period
of time, the connective hole 5 remains properly sealed
by the cylindrical portion 43b.</p>
    <p num="0149">Incidentally, the changes, which occur to the
elastic member for the connective hole 6 as the
connective needle 9 is inserted into the elastic
member, are the same as those shown in Figures 23 -
25, which occur to the elastic member 43 as the
connective needle 7 is inserted into the elastic
member 43.</p>
    <heading>(Embodiment 4)</heading>
    <p num="0150">Next, referring to Figures 27 - 32, the
fourth embodiment of the present invention will be
described. Any structural component in this
embodiment which is the same as one of the structural
components in the first embodiment shown in Figures 1
- 3, will be given the same referential code as the
one given to the same component, so that the
description of the same component in the first
embodiment can be used as a reference.</p>
    <p num="0151">The external configuration of the elastic
member in the fourth embodiment, the relationship 
between this elastic member and recess 17a, and how
the elastic member is placed and kept in the recess
17a, are the same as those in the first embodiment.</p>
    <p num="0152">Figure 27 is a drawing for describing the
configuration of the elastic member for the connective
hole of the liquid container shown in Figure 1: (a) is
a perspective view as seen from diagonally above the
side from which the connective needle is inserted; (b)
is a plan view as Seen from directly above the side
from which the connective needle is inserted; (c) is a
side view; (d) is a sectional view as seen from the
direction A in (b); and (e) is a sectional view as
seen from the direction B in (b).</p>
    <p num="0153">Figures 27 - 31 show processes through which
the connective needle 7 is inserted through an elastic
member 44 after the elastic member 44 shaped as shown
in Figures 27 is placed in the recess 17a to plug the
connective hole 5 (or 6) shown in Figure 1. More
specifically, Figure 27 is a sectional view of the
elastic member 44, at the plane which coincides with a
slit 44c of the elastic member 44. The arrow mark in
Figure 27 represents the force acting on the slit 44c
before the penetration of the elastic member 44 by the
connective needle 7.</p>
    <p num="0154">Figure 3D shows the elastic deformation of
the elastic member 44 during the insertion of the
connective needle 7, and of the elastic member 44 
after the insertion of the connective needle 7.</p>
    <p num="0155">As shown in Figures 27(a) - 27(e), the
elastic member 44 is approximately cylindrical. It is
provided with the slit 44c (gapless cut), which is in
the surface on the side from which the connective
needle 7 is inserted. The slit 44c does not reach the
other side of the elastic member 44.</p>
    <p num="0156">Referring to Figures 28 and 29, the retaining
member 15 is fixed to the elastic member holding
portion 17 in a manner to cover the recess 17a.</p>
    <p num="0157">It is provided with a pressing portion 23 for
pressing the elastic member 44 in the direction
virtually perpendicular to the diameter direction of
the elastic member 44. After the elastic member 44 is
placed in the recess 17a, and the retaining member 15
is fixed to the elastic member holding member 17,
compression pressure is present in the elastic member
44. This compression pressure acts toward the center
of the elastic member 44, that is, in the direction
indicated by an arrow mark in Figure 29, in the
elastic member 44 .</p>
    <p num="0158">Next, referring to Figure 30, when the
connective needle 7 is inserted into the elastic
member 44, if the point of the surface of the elastic
member 44, with which the tip of the connective needle
7 comes into contact at first, is off the slit 44c,
the slit 44a moves to the connective needle 7 as the 
connective needle 7 is pressed upon the elastic member
44, since the aforementioned compression pressure,
which is acting toward the center of the elastic
member 44, deforms the elastic member 44 so that the
slit 44c moves to the connective needle 7. To state
inversely, the connective needle 7 is guided into the
slit 44c. Then, the connective needle 7 penetrates
the elastic member 44 after passing through the slit
44c, as shown in Figure 31.</p>
    <p num="0159">In other words, with the provision of the
above described structural arrangement, the connective
needle 7 is made to penetrate the elastic member 44
always through the same spot, that is, the slit 44c,
regardless of the initial contact point between the
connective needle 7 and elastic member 44, preventing
the damage to the elastic member 44 by the connective
needle 7. In addition, without the damage to the
elastic member 44, the compression force, which is
constantly acting toward the center of the elastic
member 44, in the elastic member 44 after the
placement of the elastic member 44 in the recess 17a,
remains intact, assuring that after the removal of the
connective needle 7, the slit 44c reverts to the
original state, or the state of being perfectly shut.
Therefore, the content of the liquid container 2, that
is, ink, is prevented from seeping out through the
elastic member 44. </p>
    <p num="0160">Incidentally, the elastic deformations which
occur to the elastic member 44 during the insertion of
the connective needle 9 through the elastic member 44
covering the connective hole 6 are the same as the
elastic deformations of the elastic member 44 which
occur to the elastic member 44 during the insertion of
the connective needle 7 through the elastic member 44
covering the connective hole 5, which are shown in
Figures 28 - 31.</p>
    <p num="0161">When the elastic member 44 is in the recess
17a, the mutually facing walls of the slit 44c of the
elastic member 44 remain pressed against each other by
the compression pressure generated by the resiliency
of the elastic member 44 and the wall of the recess
17a. Therefore, even after the extraction of the
connective needle 7, the slit 44c is kept perfectly
closed by the compression pressure in the elastic
member 44. for this reason, the slit 44c may be such
a slit that reaches from one end of the elastic member
44 to the other in terms of the connective needle
insertion direction.</p>
    <p num="0162">Further, after slipping into the slit 44c,
the connective needle 7 is always guided to a
predetermined point, that is, the connective hole 5,
by the slit 44c. Thus, the tiny rip which is caused
through the elastic member 44 by the penetration of
the connective needle 7 aligns with the slit 44c. 
Therefore, the damage the elastic member 44 in this
embodiment sustains from the insertion of the
connective needle 7 never reaches the amount of the
damage to the aforementioned elastic member in
accordance with the prior arts.</p>
    <p num="0163">The above described benefits of this
embodiment are more apparent when a material, which is
less likely to properly tear as the connective needle
advances through it, is used as the material for the
elastic member 44. For example, in the case of the
elastic member 44 formed of chlorinated butyl rubber
with a hardness of no more than 400, which is often
used as the material for the elastic member 44 because
of its gas- impermeability and also its compatibility
with ink, the mutually facing surfaces of the tiny rip
formed through the elastic member by the connective
needle are rough. Therefore, even when the rip looks
perfectly closed, there sometimes remain microscopic
gaps between the mutually facing surfaces of the rip,
allowing the liquid (ink) to leak. In comparison, in
the case of the elastic member 44 provided with the
above described slit 44c, it is unnecessary to worry
about this kind of problem.</p>
    <p num="0164">The possibility that the elastic member 44
might be damaged by the insertion of the connective
needle can be further reduced by making such a
structural arrangement that the connective needle 7 is 
guided by the hole of the retaining member 15 so that
the distance between the axial lines of the connective
needle 7 and elastic member 44 becomes no more than
0.5D (D: diameter of connective needle 7).</p>
    <p num="0165">Once the elastic member 44 is penetrated by
the connective needle 7, the elastic member 44 is
similar in structure to an elastic member, through
which the slit 43c has been cut all the way from the
top surface to the bottom surface with the use of a
stabbing blade or like during its manufacture. The
sealing performance of the elastic member 44 in this
condition is not as good as that of an elastic member,
the slit 43c of which does not reach all the way from
the top surface to the bottom surface. In other
words, an elastic member 44 with the blind slit 44c
can deal with wider ranges of ambient temperature and
pressure fluctuations. For this and following
reasons, it is desired that the slit 44c is not cut
from one end of the elastic member 44 to the other
during the manufacture of the elastic member 44. That
is, the period in which the ability of the elastic
member 44 to keep sealed the connective hole of a
liquid container which changes in the internal
pressure of its liquid chamber in response to the
changes in ambient temperature and pressure is most
important is the period from when the manufacturing of
a liquid container is completed to when the liquid 
container begins to be used by a user of an ink jet
recording apparatus (Figure 43), in particular, the
period in which the liquid container is transported.
It may be thought that the pressure and temperature
changes, to which the liquid container is subjected
after the liquid container begins to be used, are
ordinary ones, that is, those which occur in an
ordinary living or working environment. This is why
the slit 44c should not be cut all the way through the
elastic member 44 during the manufacture of the liquid
container.</p>
    <p num="0166">In order to prevent the slit 44c from being
widened by the complete penetration of the elastic
member 44 by the connective needle 7. The length L of
the slit 44c of the elastic member 44 is desired to
satisfy the following inequality (Figure 28):
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">2L &gt; πD</st32:df>
   D: diameter of connective needle 7.</p>
    <p num="0167">The connective needle entrance portion of the
connective hole 5 is tapered; the diameter X at the
top is greater than the diameter Y at the bottom edge.
Therefore, it is assured that even if the connective
needle 7 is slightly misaimed, it is guided to the
approximate center of the elastic member 44.</p>
    <p num="0168">Generally speaking, the connective needle 7
is tapered at the end. By making the distance M from
the tip of the connective needle 7 to the straight 
portion (portion with an external diameter of R) of
the connective needle 7, shorter than the distance N
from the edge of the connective needle entrance
portion of the connective hole 5, on the trailing side
in terms of the connective needle insertion direction,
which is Y in diameter, to the top surface of the
elastic member 44 (Figure 28), it is possible to
prevent the tip of the connective needle 7 from coming
into contact with the top surface of the elastic
member 44 while the tapered portion of the connective
needle 7 is still in contact with the edge of the
entrance portion of the connective hole 5, on the
trailing side in terms of the connective needle
insertion direction, which is Y in diameter. With
this arrangement, the connective needle 7 is guided to
the approximate center of the top surface of the
elastic member 44.</p>
    <p num="0169">The following is true with the above
described embodiment as well as the embodiments which
will be described later. The amount of the friction
between the elastic member 44 and tip of the
connective needle 7 varies depending on the materials
for the elastic member 44 and connective needle 7.
When this friction is high, a substantial amount of
force is necessary to mount an ink container in the
main assembly of an ink jet recording apparatus,
inconveniencing an incompetent user. </p>
    <p num="0170">When this friction is extremely high, it is
impossible to insert an ink container into the
predetermined position. In such a case, it is
possible that ink is not supplied to the ink jet head,
resulting in printing failure.</p>
    <p num="0171">In the worst case, the tip of the connective
needle 7 fails to be guided to the center portion of
the elastic member 44, that is, the position of the
slit 44c, after the connective needle 7 comes into
contact with the top surface of the elastic member 44.
As a result, the connective needle 7 enters the
elastic member 44 without going through the slit 44c,
tearing through the elastic member 44, which sometimes
reducing the ability of the elastic member 44 to keep
the connective hole 5 sealed.</p>
    <p num="0172">This problem can be avoided by coating the
top surface of the elastic member 44 with lubricant,
which reduces the aforementioned friction between the
top surface of the elastic member 44 and the tip of
the connective needle 7, making it possible for the
tip of the connective needle 7 to slide on the top
surface of the elastic member 44 to be guided into the
slit 44c.</p>
    <p num="0173">As the liquid lubricant usable for the above
described purpose, there are silicone oil, and
glycerine selected from among glycols. As the solid
lubricant, solidified liquid silicone or the like are 
available. The properties, in addition to lubricity,
which are required of the lubricant for the above
described purpose, are that it is not affected in its
properties by the environmental factors, for example,
temperature, humidity, and the like, that it does not
affect the properties of the object on which it is
coated or the object with which it comes into contact,
that it is not affected in properties by the object on
which it is coated or the object with which it comes
into contact, and also that it does not affect the
properties of the liquid within the liquid container,
or is not affected in properties by the liquid in the
liquid container. In this embodiment, glycerine was
used as the lubricant for satisfying the above
described requirements.</p>
    <p num="0174">Coating the top surface of the elastic member
44 with lubricant is most useful when it is impossible
to make a structural arrangement for realizing a
conical indentation of a sufficient size in the top
surface of the elastic member 44 as the elastic member
44 is placed in the recess 17a, or it is impossible to
make a structural arrangement for realizing a conical
indentation in the top surface of the elastic member
44.</p>
    <p num="0175">However, even when it is possible to make a
structural arrangement for realizing a conical
indentation of a sufficient size in the top surface of 
the elastic member 44 as the elastic member 44 is
placed in the recess 17a, coating the top surface of
the elastic member 44 with lubricant is still useful
in that it allows the connective needle 7 to be
smoothly inserted, since the fact that it reduces the
friction between the connective needle 7 and elastic
member 44 does not change.</p>
    <p num="0176">The top surface of the elastic member 44 and
the mutually facing internal surfaces of the slit 44c
can be coated with lubricant by coating the sharp
blade for cutting the slit 44c, with lubricant, when
cutting the slit 44c.</p>
    <p num="0177">Coating the mutually facing internal surfaces
of the slit 44c with lubricant reduces the amount of
the friction which occurs between the connective
needle 7 and the mutually facing internal surface of
the slit 44c, reducing therefore the possibility that
the connective needle 7 will pierce into the one of
the mutually facing surfaces of the slit 44c.</p>
    <p num="0178">Lubricant may be placed between the bottom
surface of the retaining member 15 and the top surface
of the elastic member 43, as indicated by a
referential code a in Figures 21 and 22. This reduces
the possibility that the elastic member 43 is shifted
by the friction, which occurs between the bottom
surface of the retaining member 15 and the top surface
of the elastic member 43, when the elastic member 43 
is placed in the recesses 17a, or when the connective
needle 7 is put through the elastic member 43 or
extracted from the elastic member 43. Further,
lubricant may be coated on the wall of the recess 17a,
in which the elastic member 43 is placed, as indicated
by a referential code b in Figures 20 and 21. This
reduces the friction between the elastic member 43 and
the wall of the recess 17a, making it easier for the
elastic member 43 to be placed in the recess 17a.</p>
    <heading>(Embodiment 5)</heading>
    <p num="0179">Next, referring to Figures 32 - 41, the
fifth embodiment of the present invention will be
described.</p>
    <p num="0180">Figure 32(a) is a side view of the elastic
member; Figure 32(b), a bottom view of the elastic
member (view as seen from the side opposite to the
side from which the connective needle is inserted);
Figure 32(c), a perspective view of the elastic member
as seen from diagonally ahove the side from which the
connective needle is inserted; and Figure 32(d) is a
perspective view of the elastic member as seen from
diagonally below the side opposite to the side from
which the connective needle is inserted. Figure 33(a)
is a bottom view of the elastic member (view as seen
from the side opposite to the side from which the
connective needle is inserted), and Figure 33(b) is a
sectional view of the elastic member at the plane A-A 
in Figure 33(a).</p>
    <p num="0181">Figures 34 - 36 show processes through which
the elastic member 45 shown in Figures 32 and 33 is
placed in the recess 17a and is secured therein with
the use of the retaining member 15. Figure 34 shows
the state of the elastic member 45 shows the state of
the elastic member 45 after its placement in the
recess 17a in a manner to cover the connective holes 5
and 6, and Figure 35 shows the elastic member 45 which
is being pressed down by the retaining member 15.
Figure 36 shows the state of the elastic member 45
after the completion of its placement in the recess
17a.</p>
    <p num="0182">Although these drawings show only the
connective hole 5 as the hole to be covered with the
elastic member 43, the connective hole 6 also is
covered with the elastic member 43 (different from the
one covering the hole 5) as shown in these drawings.</p>
    <p num="0183">Referring to Figure 34, a referential code
17a designates a recess, in which the elastic member
45 for plugging the connective hole 5 leading to the
liquid chamber 1k is placed. The internal diameter of
the recess 17a is virtually the same the external
diameter of the elastic member 45.</p>
    <p num="0184">If the external diameter of the elastic
member 45 is slightly smaller than the internal
diameter of the recess 17a, it is easier to place the 
elastic member 45 in the recess 17a. Even if the
external diameter of the elastic member 45 is greater
than the internal diameter of the recess 17a, this
does not cause any problem (it is not difficult to
place the elastic member 45 in the recess 17a unless
the diameter of the elastic member 45 is
disproportionately larger than the internal diameter
of the recess 17a), since the shape of the elastic
member 43 can be easily changed by the application of
force. The elastic member 45 is a monolithic member,
and in the form of a dome with a predetermined
curvature, as shown in Figures 32 and 33.</p>
    <p num="0185">Next, referring to Figure 20, as the
retaining member 15 is attached to the liquid
container, the elastic member 45 is pressed down by
the retaining member 15. The length of the ridge line
of the budging side of the dome-shaped elastic member
45 is greater than the internal diameter of the recess
17a. Therefore, not only does the pressure applied to
the elastic member 45 by the retaining member 15 act
in the direction to press the elastic member 45 down,
but also in the direction to spread the elastic member
45 in the radius direction of the recess 17a.

However, the elastic member 45 is confined in the
recess 17a, being prevented from expanding in the
radius direction, by the wall of the recess 17a. As a
result, pressure is generated in the elastic member 45 
in the direction to concentrate to the center of the
elastic member 45.</p>
    <p num="0186">In this state, the compression stress in the
elastic member 45 varies depending on which portion of
the elastic member 45 is pressed by the retaining
member 15. If the elastic member 45 is in the form of
a plane dome, as the retaining member 15 is pressed
down on the elastic member 45, the lip portion of the
hole of the retaining member 15 comes into contact
with the elastic member 45, indenting the elastic
member 45 is in the pattern of a ring. If the
diameter of the flat top surface 45b of the elastic
member 45 is greater than the diameter of the bottom
lip of the hole of the retaining member 15, the
compression stress which occurs at the contact surface
between the flat bottom surface of the retaining
member 15 and the flat top surface 45b of the elastic
member 45 can be better regulated than otherwise.</p>
    <p num="0187">Therefore, the contact pressure is more evenly
distributed across the area of the elastic member 45
which comes into contact with the retaining member 15,
and therefore, the compression stress which occurs
across the area of the elastic member 45 which comes
into contact with the retaining member 15 is less
likely to become uneven, than other wise.</p>
    <p num="0188">Providing the top portion of the dome-shaped
portion 45a of the elastic member 45 with a flat 
surface 45b as shown in Figures 32 and 33 prevents the
top portion of the dome-shape portion 45a of the
elastic member 45 from bulging upward as designated by
a referential code 43d in Figure 22.</p>
    <p num="0189">Also, it causes the elastic member 45 to form
an indentation (similar to the portion 43e in Figure
21), which serves as a guide for leading the
connective needle into the aforementioned slit, as the
elastic member 45 is pressed down by the retaining
member 15.</p>
    <p num="0190">However, the conical indentation which can be
realized with the provision of the above described
structural arrangement is shallower than the conical
indentation realized by providing the top portion of
the elastic member 43 with the slight but definitely
conical indentation 43a, in the third embodiment, as
shown in Figure 18.</p>
    <p num="0191">Therefore, attention should be paid to the
correlation between the angle of the side wall of the
conical indentation to be realized, and the angle a at
which the tip of the connective needle 7 is tapered.</p>
    <p num="0192">Referring to Figure 36 which shows the state
of the elastic member 45 in the recess 17a, only the
dome-shaped portion of the elastic member 45 has been
compressed toward its axial line by the pressing
portion 23 and the wall of the recess 17a.</p>
    <p num="0193">Figure 37 shows the behavior (elastic 
deformation) of the elastic member 45 during the
insertion of the connective needle 7. As shown in
Figure 37, as an attempt is made to insert a
relatively thick connective needle 7 into the elastic
member 45, the elastic member 45 deforms.</p>
    <p num="0194">However, the elastic member 45 is provided
with the cylindrical portion 45b, which is located on
the downstream side in terms of the direction in which
the connective needle 7 is inserted. In other words,
the space into which the portion of the elastic member
45, which came in contact with the connective needle
7, is dragged by the connective needle 7 if the
elastic member 45 were not provided with the
cylindrical portion 45b, has been occupied with the
cylindrical portion 45b.</p>
    <p num="0195">Further, the cylindrical portion 45b is
relatively rigid. Therefore, in comparison to the
provision of no cylindrical portion 45b, the provision
of the cylindrical portion 45b makes it less likely to
occur that as the end portion of the connective needle
7 is pushed past the elastic member 45, the internal
portion of the elastic member 45, which came into
contact with the connective needle 7 as the connective
needle 7 is inserted into the elastic member 45, is
dragged out of the elastic member 45 by the connective
needle 7, and conically peels away from the connective
needle 7 in a manner to create a conical hole (Figure 
49(b). Consequently, the connective needle 7 is
properly inserted as shown in Figure 39. In other
words, according to this embodiment, the contact area
formed between the connective needle 7 and the
internal portion of the elastic member 45 is prevented
from being reduced by the conical separation of the
internal portion of the elastic member 45 from the
connective needle 7. Further, the provision of the
cylindrical portion 45b increases the contact area
between the connective needle 7 and elastic member 45,
improving the elastic member 45 in its ability to
prevent the liquid within the liquid container from
being leaked by the changes in the internal or ambient
pressure of the liquid container.</p>
    <p num="0196">Further, the top portion of the dome-shaped
portion of the elastic member 45 may be provided with
a shallow recess with a flat bottom surface 45b,
instead of the aforementioned simple flat surface, so
that the flat bottom surface 45b can be coated with
lubricant with the use of a simply coating method such
as stamping. Obviously, even if the top portion of
the dome-shaped portion of the elastic member 45 is
provided with only a simple flat surface, instead of
the above described shallow recess with the flat
bottom surface, a simple coating method such as
stamping can be used.</p>
    <p num="0197">In the case of the elastic member 45, the 
flat top portion 45b of which is slightly recessed as
shown in Figure 32, the lubricant coated on the flat
top surface 45b is prevented from spreading to the
other portions of the connective hole, which makes it
possible to use lubricant with lower viscosity,
increasing the number of lubricant selections.</p>
    <p num="0198">Referring to Figures 33(c), the width L of
the slit of the elastic member 45 does not need to be
even from the top to bottom surfaces of the elastic
member 45. However, in order to prevent the
cylindrical portion 45d from being severed into two
pieces by the spreading of the slit after the complete
penetration of the elastic member 45, it is desired
that the external diameter D2 of the cylindrical
portion 45d, the diameter D of the connective needle
7, and the width L of the slit portion within the
cylindrical portion 45d, satisfy the following
inequity:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">D2 &gt; 2L/π &gt; D.</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0199">When the concerns regarding product structure
makes it impossible to make the diameter of the hole
of the retaining member 15 large, the elastic member
45 may be provided with an arcuate slit 45c, shown in
Figure 40, which satisfies the following inequity: 2L
&gt;πD. This is also true with the preceding
embodiments.</p>
    <p num="0200">For the same reason, the elastic member 45 
may be provided with a compound slit 42c made up of a
pair of mutually intersecting sub-slits, shown in
Figure 41, which also satisfies the following
inequity: 2L &gt; πD. However, as a liquid container is
repeatedly mounted and dismounted, the portion of the
elastic member 45 adjacent to the intersection of the
sub-slits is repeatedly damaged, and in the worst
case, it becomes detached from the surrounding portion
of the elastic member 45. In other words, this
compound slit 42c is inferior to a simple slit, in
terms of sealing performance; it is inferior in terms
of the caving resistance of the elastic member 45.</p>
    <p num="0201">Thus, when the compound slit 42c is used, it
is desired, for the following reason, that one of the
pair of sub-slits is made shorter than the other.</p>
    <p num="0202">That is, with such an arrangement, even if a
given portion of the elastic member 45 around the
intersection of the two sub-slits will become detached
from the elastic member 45 due to the repeated
mounting and dismounting of the liquid container, the
length of this portion will be relatively short, and
therefore, the caving of the elastic member 45, which
will result from such a detachment will be
insignificant. Therefore, the resultant decrease in
the sealing performance of the elastic member 45 will
be insignificant.</p>
    <p num="0203">Further, if the elastic member 45 must be 
provided with a compound slit, such as the above
described one, owing to unavoidable circumstances, the
direction in which the connective needle 7 enters the
elastic member 45 cannot be controlled.</p>
    <p num="0204">Therefore, it is desired that the intersection
of the sub-slits coincides with the axial line of the
elastic member 45.</p>
    <p num="0205">If the slit is too long in terms of the
direction perpendicular to the axial direction of the
elastic member 45, the portion of the elastic member
45 immediately next to the slit intersection becomes
detached from the surrounding portion of the elastic
member 45, causing the elastic member 45 to cave
around the slit intersection, which result in the
deterioration of the sealing performance of the
elastic member 45.</p>
    <p num="0206">Therefore, it is desired that the following
inequity is satisfied:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">1.5πD &gt; L.</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0207">Further, the portion of the connective hole 5
of the retaining member 15, on the elastic member
side, is desired to be gradually reduced in diameter
in terms of the connective needle insertion direction,
in order to assure that the connective needle 7 is
guided toward the slit 45c of the elastic member 45.</p>
    <p num="0208">Incidentally, the deformations of the elastic
member 45, shown in Figures 37 - 39, which occur 
during the insertion of the connective needle 7
through the elastic member 45 plugging the first
connective hole 5 are the same as those which occur
during the insertion of the connective needle 9
through the elastic member 45 plugging the second
connective hole 6.</p>
    <p num="0209">In the above described embodiments, in which
the elastic member comprised a dome-shaped main
portion, and a cylindrical portion attached to the
concaved side of the main portion, the cylindrical
portion was on the liquid chamber side.</p>
    <p num="0210">However, when the diameter of the connective
needle 7 is relatively small, the cylindrical portion
may be placed on the side from which the connective
needle 7 enters the elastic member.</p>
    <p num="0211">The elastic member with this positional
arrangement of the cylindrical portion is just as
effective as any of the elastic member without a
cylindrical portion, in accordance with the present
invention.</p>
    <p num="0212">The following structural arrangement is not
shown in Figures 2, 3, and 12 - 16, but is shown in
Figures 19 - 25, 28 - 31, and 34 - 39. The retaining
member 15 is made up of first and second sections.
The first section is fixed to the elastic member
holding member 17 in a manner to press the elastic
member, and the second section is fixed to the first 
section in a manner to cover an absorbent member 34.
The absorbent member 24 is fixed to the first section
of the retaining member 15 in a manner to surround the
hole (5) of the retaining member 15, through which the
connective needle 7 is put.</p>
    <p num="0213">The absorbent member 24 absorbs and retains
the small amount of liquid droplets formed when the
connective needles 7 and 9 are extracted from a liquid
container, preventing therefore a user of an ink jet
recording apparatus employing a liquid container in
accordance with this embodiment of the present
invention, the recording apparatus itself, the things
surrounding the recording apparatus, from being
contaminated with the liquid droplets (ink droplets)
which are formed when the liquid container is removed.</p>
    <p num="0214">When placing an absorbent member such as the
above described one at the connective hole of a liquid
container, the absorbent member is desired to be
configured as shown in Figure 42, which is a plan view
of the connective hole, and its adjacencies, in the
bottom portion of the liquid container in this
embodiment, as seen from the side from which the
connective needle is inserted.</p>
    <p num="0215">The sectional view of the portion of the
liquid container in Figure 42, at the plane D-D in
Figure 42, is similar Figures 29 and 36 (sectional
views). </p>
    <p num="0216">In this embodiment, when the liquid container
is provided with the above described absorbent member,
the retaining member 15 is provided with a plurality
of grooves 25, the depth direction of which coincides
with the radius direction of the elastic member, as
shown in Figure 42. With this structural arrangement,
the small amount of the liquid droplets (ink droplets)
which are formed when a liquid container is removed
from the connective needle are very effectively guided
to the absorbent member, by the capillary force,
better preventing therefore a user of an ink jet
recording apparatus, the recording apparatus itself,
and the things surrounding the recording apparatus,
from being contaminated with the liquid droplets (ink
droplets) which are formed when the liquid container
is removed.</p>
    <p num="0217">Further, at least one of the grooves 25 is
aligned with the slit 45c of the elastic member 45 to
connect the microscopic groove at the lip of the slit
45c and this groove 25. With this arrangement, the
liquid droplets (ink droplets) which have adhered to
the surface of the elastic member 45 are more
efficiently guided to the absorbent member.</p>
    <p num="0218">Next, a recording apparatus equipped with a
liquid supplying system (Figure 1) compatible with a
liquid container structured as described above will be
described. Figure 43 shows an ink jet recording 
apparatus as an example of an apparatus compatible
with a liquid container in accordance with the present
invention.</p>
    <p num="0219">The ink jet recording apparatus shown in
Figure 43 is a serial type recording apparatus. In
the apparatus, the reciprocal movement (primary
scanning) of the ink jet head 3, and the conveyance,
at a predetermined pitch, of a recording sheet S, such
as a sheet of ordinary paper, special purpose paper,
OHP film, or the like (secondary scanning), are
alternately repeated. In synchronism with these
movements, ink is selectively ejected from the ink jet
head 3 to adhere the ink to the recording sheet S so
that characters, signs, pictorial images, and/or the
like are formed on the recording sheet S.</p>
    <p num="0220">Referring to Figure 43, the ink jet head 3 is
removably mounted on the carriage 28, which is
supported by a pair of guide rails 26 and 27, being
enabled to slide on the guide rails 26 and 27, and
which is reciprocally moved on the guide rails 26 and
27 by an unshown driving means such as a motor. The
recording sheet S is conveyed by the conveying roller
29 in the direction intersectant with the moving
direction of the carriage 2 (for example, the
direction indicated by an arrow mark A, which is
perpendicular to the moving direction of the carriage
2), facing the ink ejection surface of the ink jet 
head 3 while being kept a predetermined distance away
from the ink ejection surface of the ink jet head 3.</p>
    <p num="0221">In order to eject plural inks different in
color, the ink jet head 3 has plural columns of
nozzles different in ink color. For each ink ejected
from the ink jet head 3, one ink container 2, which is
one of the main containers, is removably mounted in
the ink supplying unit 30.</p>
    <p num="0222">The ink supplying unit 30 and ink jet head 3
are connected with plural liquid supply tubes 4, the
number of which equals to the number of the inks
different in color. As each liquid container 2 is
mounted in the ink supplying unit 30, it becomes
possible for the ink therein to be supplied to the ink
nozzle column of the same color, independently from
the other ink containers and inks therein.</p>
    <p num="0223">The recording apparatus is provided with a
recovery unit 32, which is disposed within the
reciprocating range of the ink jet head 3, but outside
the path of the recording sheet S, that is, out side
the recording range of the ink jet head 3, being
enabled to face the ink ejection surface of the ink
jet head 3. The recovery unit 32 has: a cap for
covering the ink ejection surface of the ink jet head
3; a suctioning mechanism for forcefully suctioning
ink out of the ink jet head 3, with the ink ejection
surface of the ink jet head 3 covered with the cap; a 
cleaning blade for wiping away the contaminant on the
ink ejection surface; and the like.</p>
    <p num="0224">In the above, the embodiments of the present
invention were described with reference to a serial
type ink jet recording apparatus. However, the
present invention is also applicable to an ink jet
recording apparatus having a line type ink jet head in
which a single or plural rows of nozzles extend from
one end to the other of the recording range of the ink
jet head 3 in terms of the widthwise direction of a
recording medium.</p>
    <p num="0225">As described above, according to the first
embodiment of the present invention, a liquid
container for an ink jet recording apparatus comprises
a connective hole for connecting the inside and
outside of the container, and an elastic member placed
at the opening of the connective hole. The inside and
outside of the liquid container are connected as a
cylindrical needle is put through the elastic member.
The elastic member has first and second portions. In
terms of the direction in which the cylindrical needle
is inserted, the first and second portions are on the
trailing and leading sides, respectively. The first
portion remains compressed even before the insertion
of the cylindrical needle, whereas before the
insertion of the cylindrical needle, the second
portion is not in the compressed state, in practical 
terms.</p>
    <p num="0226">However, after the insertion of the
cylindrical needle, both the first and second portions
remains compressed. With the provision of this
structural arrangement, the amount of the
deterioration of the elasticity of the second portion
resulting from the elapse of time is smaller than that
of the first portion. In other words, the amount of
the creep (phenomenon that if an elastic member is
left alone, under a given pressure, for a long period
of time, the elastic member does not revert to its
original shape; it becomes permanently deformed) which
occurs to the second portion is far smaller than the
amount of the creep which occurs to the first portion.
Therefore, even when the cylindrical needle is
extracted after being left in the elastic member for a
long period time, the second portion of the elastic
member, to which virtually no creep, or permanent
deformation, occurs, keeps the connective hole
satisfactorily sealed. Further, the provision of the
second portion increases the size of the contact
surface between the elastic member and cylindrical
needle, improving the ability of the elastic member to
keep the connective hole sealed against the changes in
the internal and/or ambient pressure of the liquid
container.</p>
    <p num="0227">According to another aspect of the present 
invention, an elastic member is monolithic, and also
has first and second portions. The first portion
remains compressed even before the insertion of the
cylindrical needle, whereas before the insertion of
the cylindrical needle, the Second portion is not in
the compressed state, in practical terms. However,
after the insertion of the cylindrical needle, both
the first and second portions remains compressed. In
terms of the cylindrical needle insertion direction,
the first and second portions are on the trailing and
leading sides, respectively. Also in terms of the
direction in which the cylindrical needle is inserted,
the first portion bulges in the direction from which
the cylindrical needle is inserted, and concaves on
the side opposite to the bulging side. It is uniform
in thickness in terms of the cylindrical needle
insertion direction. The second portion is
cylindrical before the insertion of the cylindrical
needle. It projects from the concaved side of the
first portion.</p>
    <p num="0228">With the provision of this structural
arrangement, it is easy to compress, and keep
compressed, the elastic member toward its axial line.
Further, with the cylindrical portion of the elastic
member protruding in the cylindrical needle insertion
direction, it is not likely that when the leading end
portion of the cylindrical needle comes out of the 
other side of the elastic member, the internal portion
of the elastic member, which has come into contact
with the advancing cylindrical needle, is partially
dragged out of the elastic member, and conically peels
away from the cylindrical needle in a manner to create
a conical recess around the cylindrical needle; in
other words, it is possible to prevent the elastic
member from being conically caved around the
cylindrical needle by the insertion of the cylindrical
needle. Therefore, the elastic member in accordance
with this aspect of the present invention is greater
in the contact surface between the cylindrical needle
and elastic member than an elastic member in
accordance with the prior arts. The elastic member in
accordance with this aspect of the present invention
may be provided with a slit, which is cut in the
direction parallel to the direction in which the
cylindrical needle is advanced through the elastic
member. With the provision of this structural
arrangement, the cylindrical needle is guided by the
slit, being enabled to properly penetrate the elastic
member. Therefore, the elastic member is less likely
to be damaged by the insertion of the cylindrical
needle, assuring that the connective hole remains
satisfactorily sealed.</p>
    <p num="0229">Further, the external diameter of the
cylindrical portion of the elastic member is made 
smaller than the internal diameter of the connective
hole. With the provision of this structural
arrangement, compression force is generated only as
the cylindrical needle is inserted into the
cylindrical portion of the elastic member.

Therefore, the cylindrical portion of the elastic
member is less likely to permanently deform with the
elapse of time. Even when the cylindrical needle is
extracted from the elastic member after it has been
left alone in the elastic member for a long period of
time, liquid is not likely to drip from the connective
hole.</p>
    <p num="0230">Further, the top portion of the bulging
portion of the elastic member may be provided with a
conical recess, a simple flat surface perpendicular to
the cylindrical needle insertion direction, or a
shallow recess with a flat bottom surface
perpendicular to the cylindrical needle insertion
direction. With the provision of this structural
arrangement, it is possible to limit to the radius
direction of the elastic member, the direction in
which the internal portion of the elastic member is
pushed out as the cylindrical needle is inserted
through the elastic member.</p>
    <p num="0231">Therefore, the caving of the elastic member
which is caused by the insertion of the cylindrical
needle is more effectively prevented. </p>
    <p num="0232">Further, the recess in which the elastic
member is retained by the retaining member for
retaining the elastic member in the compressed state
is made virtually cylindrical. Therefore, as the
elastic member is pressed down in the retaining
member, the contact surface between the elastic member
and the recess wall becomes cylindrical, causing the
compression pressure generated in the elastic member
by the pressure from the retaining member, to
concentrate toward the axial line of the elastic
member, which is desirable from the standpoint of the
sealing performance of the elastic member.</p>
    <p num="0233">According to the second embodiment of the
present invention, a liquid container for an ink jet
recording apparatus has a connective hole for
connecting the inside and outside of the container, an
elastic member for keeping the connective hole sealed,
and a recess in which the elastic member is retained.
The elastic member is provided with a slit, which
extends inward of the elastic member, from the surface
of the elastic member, on the side from which the
cylindrical needle is inserted into the container, in
the direction in which the cylindrical needle is
inserted. The elastic member in the recess, which has
been compressed toward the center of the recess, is in
the compressed state. Thus, when a cylindrical needle
is inserted into the elastic member, it advances in 
the elastic member, following the slit. Consequently,
the cylindrical needles goes through virtually the
same path as the path made when the cylindrical needle
was previously put though the elastic member,
minimizing the damage which occurs to the elastic
member as the cylindrical needle is put through the
elastic member. This assures that the elastic member
keeps the connective hole satisfactorily sealed.</p>
    <p num="0234">In the case of the above structural
arrangement, the elastic member is made up of a dome-shaped
portion and a cylindrical portion. In terms of
the direction in which the cylindrical needle is
inserted, one side of the dome-shaped portion is
bulged, and the other side of the dome- shaped portion
is concaved. The dome-shaped portion is uniform in
the thickness in terms of the cylindrical needle
insertion direction. The cylindrical portion projects
from the concaved side of the dome-shaped portion.
The aforementioned slit is formed so that it is
positioned in the center of the elastic member, and
that its dimension in terms of the radius direction of
the elastic member does not exceed the diameter of the
cylindrical portion. As the elastic member placed in
the aforementioned recess is pressed down by the
retaining member, compression pressure is easily
generated in the dome-shaped portion and is directed
toward the axial line of the elastic member, 
increasing the amount by which contact pressure is
generated between the cylindrical needle and the
internal portion of the elastic member as the
cylindrical needle is inserted. This improves the
reliability of the elastic member in its ability to
keep the connective hole sealed. Next, the
cylindrical needle on the concaved side of the elastic
member projects in the cylindrical needle insertion
direction, making it difficult for the phenomenon that
when the leading end portion of the cylindrical needle
is pushed past the bottom surface of the elastic
member, the internal portion of the elastic member
around the needle path in the elastic member made by
the advancement of the elastic member through the
elastic member is partially dragged out of the elastic
member from the bottom surface of the elastic member,
by the cylindrical needle, and conically peels away
from the cylindrical needle in a manner to create a
conical recess around the cylindrical needle, to
occur. In other words, this structural arrangement
prevents the elastic member from becoming conically
caved due to the insertion of the cylindrical needle.
Therefore, the contact area between the cylindrical
needle and the elastic member in this embodiment is
greater than that between the cylindrical needle and
an elastic member in accordance with the prior arts.
Next, the elastic member is provided with a slit, 
which is cut in the direction in which the cylindrical
needle inserted. Therefore, the cylindrical needle is
guided through the elastic member by the slit, being
prevented from damaging the elastic member. In other
words, the elastic member in accordance with this
embodiment assures that the connective hole is kept
satisfactorily sealed.</p>
    <p num="0235">Providing the elastic member with only a
single slit assures that each time the cylindrical
needle is inserted in the elastic member, the
cylindrical needle follows virtually the same path as
that which the cylindrical needle followed when it was
previously inserted. The slit may be cut in such a
manner that it falls slightly short of reaching the
bottom surface of the elastic member. With this
arrangement, the connective hole is kept perfectly
sealed even when a liquid container is placed in the
adverse environment in terms of the leakage during the
period from the liquid container manufacture to the
beginning of its usage; in other words, this
arrangement makes a liquid container more tolerant to
environmental changes. Next, the relationship between
the length L of the slit in terms of the direction
perpendicular to the direction in which the
cylindrical needle is inserted, and the diameter D of
the cylindrical needle, is made to satisfy the
following inequity: 2L &gt; πD. With this arrangement, 
the slit does not tear (it does not widen) when the
cylindrical needle is put all the way through the
elastic member, following the slit.</p>
    <p num="0236">Further, an absorbent member is attached to
the retaining member to absorb liquid droplets. Also,
the wall of the connective hole of the retaining
member is provided with plural grooves, the depth
direction of which coincides with the radius direction
of the connective hole. With this arrangement, a
small amount of liquid droplets (ink droplets if the
liquid within the liquid container is ink) which are
formed when a liquid container is moved away from
the cylindrical needle, are efficiently guided to the
absorbent member by capillary force. Therefore, a
user of an ink jet recording apparatus, the recording
apparatus itself, and the things around the recording
apparatus, can be prevented from being contaminated by
ink.</p>
    <p num="0237">Further, the elastic member may be provided
with a compound slit made up of a pair of sub- slits,
which intersect each other, and the intersection of
which virtually coincides with the axial line of the
elastic member. With this arrangement, the
cylindrical needle is inserted into the elastic member
in a satisfactory manner even when the cylindrical
needle is not strictly regulated in terms of the
direction in which it is inserted. </p>
    <p num="0238">Regarding the elastic member with a compound
slit, if the shorter sub-slit is excessively long in
terms of the direction perpendicular to the
cylindrical needle insertion direction, the portion of
the elastic member immediately next to the
intersection of the sub-slits is isolated from the
surrounding portion of the elastic member, adversely
affecting the ability of the elastic member to resist
caving. Therefore, the relationship between the
length L of the sub-slit in terms of the direction
perpendicular to the cylindrical needle insertion
direction, and the diameter D of the cylindrical
needle, is desired to satisfy the following inequity:
1.5πD &gt; L.</p>
    <p num="0239">According to the third and fourth embodiments
of the present invention, a liquid container for an
ink jet recording apparatus comprises a connective
hole for connecting the inside and outside of the
container, and an elastic member placed at the opening
of the connective hole. The inside and outside of the
liquid container are connected as a cylindrical needle
is put through the elastic member. The elastic member
has first and second portions. In terms of the
direction in which the cylindrical needle is inserted,
the first and Second portions are on the trailing and
leading sides, respectively. The first portion
remains compressed even before the insertion of the 
cylindrical needle, whereas before the insertion of
the cylindrical needle, the second portion is not in
the compressed state, in practical terms. However,
after the insertion of the cylindrical needle, both
the first and second portions remains compressed. In
terms of the cylindrical needle insertion direction,
the first portion is dome-shaped, being bulged on the
side from which the cylindrical needle is inserted,
and concaved on the opposite side. The top portion of
the dome-shaped first portion is provided with a
simple flat surface, which is virtually perpendicular
to the cylindrical needle insertion direction, or is
provided with a shallow recess with a flat bottom
surface, which is virtually perpendicular to the
cylindrical needle insertion direction. The second
portion is a cylindrical, protruding from the concaved
side of the dome- shaped portion. Further, the
elastic member is provided with a slit, which extends
in the direction parallel to the cylindrical needle
insertion direction from the surface from which the
cylindrical needle is inserted. The slit is cut so
that it is positioned in the approximate center of the
elastic member, and its dimension in terms of the
radius direction of the elastic member does not exceed
the diameter of the cylindrical portion. Thus, when
the elastic member is in the recess, compression
pressure is present in the dome-shaped portion, and 
acts toward the axial line of the elastic member.</p>
    <p num="0240">Also with this structural arrangement, in
which the elastic member is provided with the dome-shaped
portion, such compression pressure that acts
toward the axial line of the elastic member is easily
generated in the elastic member, increasing the amount
by which contact pressure is generated between the
cylindrical needle and the internal portion of the
elastic member as the cylindrical needle is inserted.
This improves the reliability of the elastic member in
its ability to keep the connective hole sealed.
Further, the provision of the cylindrical portion
prevents the elastic member from conically caving.
Therefore, the contact area between the cylindrical
needle and the elastic member in this embodiment is
greater than that between the cylindrical needle and
an elastic member in accordance with the prior arts.
Further, with the provision of the slit, which is cut
in the direction in which the cylindrical needle
inserted, the cylindrical needle is guided by the slit
through the elastic member.</p>
    <p num="0241">In the third embodiment of the present
invention, the slit was virtually straight, or
arcuate. When the requirement regarding the product
design makes it necessary for the cylindrical portion
of the elastic member to be small in diameter, an
arcuate slit is advantageous. Further, 
according to the second and third embodiments of the
present invention, a liquid container is provided with
an elastic member retaining member, and the leading
end, in terms of the insertion direction, of a
cylindrical needle which is inserted into the elastic
member is tapered. The retaining member is provided
with a hole for guiding the entry of the cylindrical
needle into the elastic member. The lip of one end of
this hole is in contact with the elastic member, and
has a predetermined diameter. In terms of the
cylindrical needle insertion direction, the depth of
this hole is made greater than the length of the
tapered portion of the cylindrical needle. With this
arrangement, it is prevented that the tip of the
cylindrical needle reaches the top surface of the
elastic member while the tapered portion of the
cylindrical needle is still in contact with the wall
of the above described guiding hole. Therefore, the
connective needle is guided to the center of the
elastic member.</p>
    <p num="0242">In this case, it is desired that the
aforementioned flat surface perpendicular to the
direction in which the cylindrical needle enters the
elastic member is a circular surface with a diameter
greater than that of the guiding hole of the elastic
member retaining member. With this arrangement, the
compression stress, which is generated toward the 
axial line of the elastic member as the elastic member
is placed in the recess, can be regulated by the flat
bottom surface of the retaining member and the flat
top surface of the elastic member. In other words,
the compression stress is evenly distributed in the
elastic member.</p>
    <p num="0243">According to the first to third embodiments
of the present invention, the top surface of the
elastic member is coated with lubricant. With this
arrangement, the friction which occurs between the top
surface of the elastic member and the tip of the
cylindrical needle to be inserted into the elastic
member is smaller, assuring that the cylindrical
needle is guided to the slit, and also making it
easier for an incompetent use to insert the
cylindrical needle into the elastic member.

Lubricant may be placed in the slit itself cut in the
elastic member in the direction parallel to the
cylindrical needle insertion direction. This will
enhance the above described benefits of the coating of
the top surface of the elastic member with lubricant.</p>
    <p num="0244">Further, lubricant may be coated on the
surface of the retaining member, or may be placed in
the interface between the retaining member and elastic
member. With this arrangement, it is possible to
reduce the possibility that the elastic member is
shifted by the friction which occurs between the 
retaining member and the elastic member, when the
elastic member is placed in the recess, when the
cylindrical needle is inserted into the elastic
member, or when the cylindrical needle is extracted
from the elastic member.</p>
    <p num="0245">Further, lubricant may be placed in the
interface between the wall of the recess and the
elastic member. This arrangement makes it easier to
place the elastic member in the recess.</p>
    <p num="0246">Further, an absorbent member for absorbing
liquid droplets is attached to the retaining member
which presses down and holds the elastic member. Also
the wall of the guiding (connective) hole of the
retaining member is provided with plural grooves, the
depth direction of which coincides with the radius
direction of the guiding hole, and at least one of the
grooves is aligned with the slit. With this
arrangement, the microscopic groove created at the
surface of the elastic member by the formation of the
slit becomes connected with the groove of the
retaining member. Therefore, the liquid droplets (ink
droplets if the liquid in the liquid container is ink)
is more efficiently guided to the absorbent member.</p>
    <p num="0247">Further, according to the present invention,
a liquid container is provided with a connective hole
for connecting the insert and outside of the
container, the inside and outside of the liquid 
container becomes connected as the cylindrical needle
is put through the connective hole. This liquid
container is also provided with an elastic member for
plugging the connective hole, and a guide for guiding
the cylindrical needle with a diameter of D, in such a
manner that the axial line of the cylindrical needle
is positioned no more than 0.5D away from the axial
line of the elastic member, reducing further the
possibility that the elastic member will be damaged.</p>
    <p num="0248">While the invention has been described with
reference to the structures disclosed herein, it is
not confined to the details set forth, and this
application is intended to cover such modifications or
changes as may come within the purposes of the
improvements or the scope of the following claims. </p>
    <p num="0249">While the invention has been described with
reference to the structures disclosed herein, it is
not confined to the details set forth and this
application is intended to cover such modifications or
changes as may come within the purpose of the
improvements or the scope of the following claims.</p>
    <p num="0250">A liquid container for an ink jet recording
apparatus includes a connection opening connectable
with an outside; an elastic member provided in the
connection opening, the elastic member being adapted
to be penetrated by a cylindrical member for fluid
communication with the outside; the elastic member
including a compressed region and a substantially non-compressed
region in a state without the cylindrical
member penetrated, disposed in this order in a
direction of insertion of the cylindrical member,
wherein the compressed region and the non-compressed
region are capable of being compressed when they are
penetrated by the cylindrical member.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A liquid container for an ink jet recording
apparatus, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a connection opening connectable with an
outside;</claim-text><claim-text>an elastic member provided in said connection
opening, said elastic member being adapted to be
penetrated by a cylindrical member for fluid
communication with the outside;</claim-text><claim-text>said elastic member including a compressed
region and a substantially non-compressed region in a
state without said cylindrical member penetrated,
disposed in this order in a direction of insertion of
said cylindrical member, wherein said compressed
region and said non-compressed region are capable of
being compressed when they are penetrated by said
cylindrical member.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 1, wherein a
plane, perpendicular to the direction of insertion of
the cylindrical member, of said compressed region of
said elastic member is wider than a plane,
perpendicular to the direction of insertion, of said
non-compressed region of said elastic member in the
state without said cylindrical member penetrated.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 1, wherein a
length, measured in the direction of insertion of the
cylindrical member, of said compressed region of said
elastic member, is longer than a length, measured in
the direction, of said non-compressed region of said
elastic member in the state without said cylindrical
member penetrated.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 1, wherein
said compressed region and said non-compressed region
of said elastic member are portions of a single
member, in the state without the cylindrical member
penetrated.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 4, wherein one
of opposite end surfaces of said elastic member with
respect to the direction of the insertion of said
cylindrical member has a protruded form, and the other
has a recessed form to provide a substantially uniform
thickness, and wherein said non-compressed region has
a configuration protruded toward said recessed form in
the state without the cylindrical member penetrated.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 5, wherein the
cylindrical member is inserted at the end having the
protruded form.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 5, further
comprising a housing, provided in said connection
opening, for housing said elastic member, said housing
having an inner diameter which is substantially equal
to an outer diameter of said elastic member, wherein
said elastic member is compressed toward a center of
said elastic member by a fixing member compressing the
end of the elastic member having the protruded form.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 5, wherein
when the end of said elastic member having the
protruded form is compressed to the fixing member
having an opening through which the cylindrical member
is penetrated, the elastic member is not pressed into
the opening of said fixing member.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 8, wherein the
end having the protruded form has a conical portion at
a top of the protruded form.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 8, wherein the
end having the protruded form has a flat surface
substantially perpendicular to the direction of
insertion of the cylindrical member or a stepped-down
surface.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>A liquid container for an ink jet recording
apparatus, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a connection opening connectable with an
outside;</claim-text><claim-text>an elastic member plugged in said connection
opening;</claim-text><claim-text>a housing for housing said elastic member,
said elastic member being adapted to be penetrated by
a cylindrical member for fluid communication with the
outside;</claim-text><claim-text>a slit provided in said elastic member and
extended from an end at which said cylindrical member
is insertable in a direction of insertion of said
cylindrical member,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein said elastic member is compressed
inwardly in said housing.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 11, wherein
said elastic member is in the form of a dome having a
protruded form on one side and a recessed form on the
other side in the direction of insertion of the
cylindrical member, the dome having a substantially
uniform thickness, and said elastic member is provided
with a column configuration portion of the recessed
form side, wherein the slit is within the column
configuration portion.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>A liquid container for an ink jet recording
apparatus, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a connection opening connectable with an
outside;</claim-text><claim-text>an elastic member provided in said connection
opening, said elastic member being adapted to be
penetrated by a cylindrical member for fluid
communication with the outside; said elastic member
including a compressed region and a substantially non-compressed
region in a state without said cylindrical
member penetrated, disposed in this order in a
direction of insertion of said cylindrical member,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein said compressed region is in the form
of a dome having a protruded form on one side and a
recessed form on the other side in the direction of
insertion of the cylindrical member,
   wherein a top portion of said protruded form
has a flat surface substantially perpendicular to the
direction of insertion of the cylindrical member or a
stepped-down surface,
   wherein said non-compressed region is
provided with a column configuration portion of the
recessed form side, wherein the slit is within the
column configuration portion,
   wherein said compressed region and said non-compressed
region are capable of being compressed when
they are penetrated by said cylindrical member.
   wherein said elastic member has a slit
provided in said elastic member and extended from an
end at which said cylindrical member is insertable in
a direction of insertion of said cylindrical member,
and the slit is within the column configuration
portion,
   wherein said elastic member is compressed
inwardly in said housing.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>A liquid container for an ink jet recording
apparatus, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a connection opening connectable with an
outside;</claim-text><claim-text>an elastic member provided in said connection
opening, said elastic member being adapted to be
penetrated by a cylindrical member for fluid
communication with the outside, said elastic member
including a compressed region and a substantially non-compressed
region in a state without said cylindrical
member penetrated, disposed in this order in a
direction of insertion of said cylindrical member,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein said compressed region is in the form
of a dome having a protruded form on one side and a
recessed form on the other side in the direction of
insertion of the cylindrical member,
   wherein a top portion of said protruded form
has a flat surface substantially perpendicular to the
direction of insertion of the cylindrical member or a
stepped-down surface,
   wherein said non-compressed region is
provided with a column configuration portion of the
recessed form side,
   wherein said compressed region and said non-compressed
region are capable of being compressed when
they are penetrated by said cylindrical member,
   wherein said elastic member has a slit
provided in said elastic member and extended from an
end at which said cylindrical member is insertable in
a direction of insertion of said cylindrical member,
and the slit is within the column configuration
portion,
   wherein said elastic member is compressed
inwardly in said housing.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 11, wherein
only one such slit is provided.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 11, wherein
said slit does not penetrates all through said elastic
member.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 11, wherein a
length of slit, measured in a direction perpendicular
to the direction of insertion of the cylindrical
member satisfies 2L &gt; πD, where D is a diameter of the
cylindrical member.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="18">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 7, wherein
said fixing member is provided with an absorbing
material for absorbing a droplet.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="19">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 18, wherein
said fixing member is provided with grooves extending
radially from said connection opening.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="20">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 11, further
comprising a fixing member for pressing and fixing
said elastic member, said fixing member being provided
with an absorbing material for absorbing a droplet and
being provided with grooves extending radially from
said connection opening, wherein at least one of said
grooves extends along said slit.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="21">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 1, further
comprising a fixing member for pressing and fixing
said elastic member, wherein a free end of the
cylindrical member to be inserted into seven elastic
member is tapered, and said affixing member has an
opening contacted to the elastic member to guide
insertion of the cylindrical member into said elastic
member, wherein the opening has a length, measured in
the direction of insertion of the cylindrical member,
is larger than a length of the tapered portion of the
cylindrical member.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="22">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 21, wherein
the plane perpendicular to the direction of insertion
of the cylindrical member has a circular flat plane
having a diameter larger than the diameter of the
opening provided in the fixing member.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="23">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 1, wherein a
lubricant exists on a surface of said elastic member.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="24">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 1, wherein a
lubricant exists on a surface of said elastic member
open to an opening of a fixing member for pressing and
fixing said elastic member, the cylindrical member
being inserted through the opening of the fixing
member.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="25">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 1, wherein a
lubricant exists on contact surfaces between said
elastic member and a fixing member for pressing and
fixing said elastic member.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="26">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 1, wherein a
lubricant exists on contact surfaces between inside of
said housing and said elastic member.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="27">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 11, wherein a
lubricant exists in a slit provided in said elastic
member and extended in the direction of insertion of
the cylindrical member.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="28">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 1, wherein a
lubricant exists on a surface of a fixing member for
pressing and fixing said elastic member.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="29">
      <claim-text>An apparatus according to Claim 25, wherein a
lubricant on said elastic member comprises a glycol
material.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="30">
      <claim-text>A recording apparatus using a liquid
container as defined in Claim 1, comprising a mounting
means for detachably mounting said liquid container,
and the cylindrical member provided in the mounting
means, said cylindrical member penetrates through said
elastic member in said connection opening of said
liquid container.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="31">
      <claim-text>A recording apparatus using a liquid
container as defined in Claim 32, further comprising
an ink jet head for effecting recording by ejecting
droplets of liquid supplied from said liquid
container.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="32">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 1, further
comprising a fixing member for pressing and fixing
said elastic member, wherein a connecting portion
configuration between said elastic member and said
housing is substantially circular by the pressing of
said fixing member.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="33">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 11, wherein a
plurality of such slits are provided and are crossed
at a substantial center of said elastic member.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="34">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 13, wherein
the slits are generally linear or circular.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="35">
      <claim-text>A container according to Claim 11, wherein a
length measured in a direction perpendicular to the
direction of insertion satisfied 1.5πD &gt; L, where D is
a diameter of said cylindrical member.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="36">
      <claim-text>A liquid container comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>connection opening connectable with an
outside, wherein said liquid container is brought into
fluid communication with the outside by insertion of a
cylindrical member through said connection opening;</claim-text><claim-text>an elastic member plugged in said connection
opening; and</claim-text><claim-text>a guide for guiding the cylindrical member
into a range within 0.5D from a center of the elastic
member, where D is a diameter of said cylindrical
member.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
