<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1260611-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1260611" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="19001336" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021127">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1260611-A2" status="new" fvid="23610788">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1260611</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021127</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02253656-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02253656</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020523</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001157481-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001157481</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010525</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B23B  27/14        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B23B  27/14        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B23C   5/16        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B23C   5/20        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  14/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  14/06        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  30/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  30/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C  14/06F</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C  30/00B</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Schneidwerkzeug und Werkzeughalter</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Cutting tool and tool with holder</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Outil de coupe et porte-outil</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NGK SPARK PLUG CO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NGK SPARK PLUG COMPANY LIMITED</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>NGK Spark Plug Company Limited</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>14-18, Takatsuji-cho Mizuho-ku</street>
              <city>Nagoya, Aichi</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KATO HIDEKI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KATO, HIDEKI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Kato, Hideki, NGK Spark Plug Co., Ltd</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>14-18 Takatsuji-cho, Mizuho-ku</street>
              <city>Nagoya, Aichi</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Nicholls, Michael John</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>J.A. KEMP &amp;amp; CO. 14, South Square Gray's Inn</street>
              <city>LONDON WC1R 5JJ</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>IT</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A cutting tool 1 is a throwaway tip configured such that a hard coating is
formed on the surface of a substrate formed of, for example, a hard material of
cemented carbide (WC-Co-type cemented carbide) equivalent to JIS K10 and
polished into the shape of ISO SPGN120312. Specifically, the cutting tool 1 is a
plate-shaped positive tip whose rake face (the main surface side), which is the upper
face in Fig. 1, is wider than the opposite face. The substrate surface is coated with a
hard coating having a thickness in the range of from 1 µm to 5 µm, formed of a
TiAIN material, and having a Ti/Al ratio of 1. Particularly, coarse grains present in
the hard coating of this cutting tool and having a size not less than coating thickness
occupy an area percentage not greater than 5% by area; and the hard coating has a
surface roughness Ra of not greater than 0.1 µm and a surface roughness Rz of not
greater than 1 µm.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="72" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="77"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a cutting tool coated with a hard coating
exhibiting excellent adhesion resistance and excellent wear resistance and to a tool
with a holder incorporating the same.</p>
    <p num="0002">Conventionally, an arc-ion-type PVD process has been frequently employed
for PVD coating with a TiAlN material (coating through physical vapor deposition),
since high energy is required for ionization of a TiAl metal and the process has the
advantage, among others, that a coating layer of excellent adhesion is readily
obtained.</p>
    <p num="0003">However, in some cases, this process permits generation of coarse TiAl
grains which is caused by local concentration of arc derived from the non-uniform
surface condition of a TiAl target or non-uniform generation of arc, resulting in
deposition of coarse TiAlN grains.</p>
    <p num="0004">Some such coarse grains have a size of several micrometers to several tens of
micrometers. When such coarse grains are present on the surface of coating,
application to a cutting tool encounters the following problem: contact of the surface
with chips of a work material, mechanical vibration, or the like may cause coarse
grains to drop off. Exposure of a substrate as a result of dropping off of coarse
grains has sometimes caused unstable cutting performance (adhesion resistance and
wear resistance), and in the worst case impairment in cutting performance.</p>
    <p num="0005">In order to cope with the above problem, PVD apparatus manufacturers and
cutting tool manufacturers have investigated coating conditions and coating
processes that can eliminate coarse grains. At present, in order to reduce generation
of coarse grains, a load current to a target is decreased, a trap for eliminating coarse
grains is provided between a target and a substrate to be coated, or a similar method
is employed.</p>
    <p num="0006">However, the above-mentioned methods involve an impairment in
productivity and an increase in cost, since the coating deposition rate drops.</p>
    <p num="0007">Some coating provides improved surfaces in which generation of coarse
grains is prevented through employment of a multilayer structure consisting of TiN, 
AlN, etc., but fails to sufficiently exhibit inherent properties of the TiAlN film in
relation to heat resistance, wear resistance, etc., and thus performance thereof is not
satisfactory.</p>
    <p num="0008">As described in Japanese Patent No. 2901043, an improvement in
performance is attempted by eliminating coarse grains after coating to thereby
establish a surface having craters formed thereon.</p>
    <p num="0009">However, in this case, application to an actual tool also involves the
following problem. In some cases, the substrate may be exposed at a crater portion
of coating. When a work material is adhered to the crater portion through fusion, and
such a portion is exfoliated, a surrounding portion of the hard coating or the substrate
is chipped off together with the adhered portion. As a result, unusual wear is
initiated from the chipped portion, and thus satisfactory performance is not
necessarily exhibited. Further, since a process for eliminating coarse grains must be
carried out after coating, an impairment in productivity and an increase in cost result.</p>
    <p num="0010">The present invention has been accomplished in view of the foregoing, and an
object of the invention is to provide a cutting tool coated with a hard coating capable
of reliably and favorably exhibiting cutting performance, such as adhesion resistance
and wear resistance, as well as a tool with a holder incorporating the same.</p>
    <p num="0011">In order to achieve the above object, the present inventors have studied
conditions for allowing a TiAlN-type PVD film to reliably and favorably maintain
cutting performance and have found that through control of the size and amount of
coarse grains to certain respective ranges and through determination of surface
smoothness by use of surface roughness, wear resistance can be stabilized, thus
leading to achievement of the present invention.
<sl><li>(1) According to the invention, a cutting tool comprises a substrate and a
TiAlN-type hard coating formed on the substrate and is characterized in that the hard
coating has a thickness of 1 to 5 µm, and coarse grains present in the hard coating
and having a size not less than the thickness of the hard coating occupy an area
percentage not greater than 5% by area.
The thickness of the hard coating is specified as 1 µm to 5 µm for the
following reason. When the thickness is less than 1 µm, desired cutting performance
(i.e., high resistance to joining through fusion and wear resistance) is not exhibited. 
When the thickness is in excess of 5 µm, residual stress of coating increases, and
thus the coating undergoes self fracture with a resultant impairment in cutting
performance.The invention also specifies the size of coarse grains (whose amount is
specified in terms of % by area) as being not less than the thickness of the hard
coating on the substrate surface, for the following reason. When a grain having a
size not less than the coating thickness drops off during cutting, exposure of the
substrate becomes highly likely. When the substrate is exposed, joining through
fusion and exfoliation arise, resulting in occurrence of unusual wear. In other words,
when coarse grains have a size less than the thickness of the hard coating, dropping-off
of a coarse grain does not lead to exposure of the substrate, whereby an
impairment in cutting performance can be restrained. Therefore, the size of coarse
grains to be limited in amount is specified as being not less than the thickness of the
hard coating.Further, the area percentage of coarse grains present in the hard coating and
having a size not less than the thickness of the hard coating is specified as being not
greater than 5% by area, for the following reason. When the area percentage is in
excess of 5% by area, the possibility that cutting performance is impaired by
dropping-off of a grain increases. The area percentage is more preferably not greater
than 3% by area. Even in the case of grains having a size less than coating thickness,
smaller amounts are preferred.Since the invention is constructed as described above, an impairment in
cutting performance, which would otherwise arise from dropping-off of a coarse
grain, does not arise, whereby excellent cutting performance can be reliably
maintained over a long period of time.</li><li>(2) According to a second preferred aspect of the invention, in the cutting
tool as described above, the hard coating satisfies at least either a requirement for a
surface roughness Ra of not greater than 0.1 µm or a requirement for a surface
roughness Rz of not greater than 1 µm.
In the invention of this aspect, the surface smoothness of the hard coating
satisfies at least either a requirement for Ra not greater than 0.1 µm or a requirement
for Rz not greater than 1 µm. When the above-mentioned requirements for surface roughness are not
satisfied, in the course of a work material rubbing against coating surface, droppingoff
of a grain becomes highly likely, and frictional resistance increases. As a result,
joining of a work material through fusion (and subsequent exfoliation) becomes
likely to occur, possibly resulting in an impairment in cutting performance.Notably, Ra refers to the known average roughness along centerline Ra, and
Rz refers to the known 10-point average roughness Rz.</li><li>(3) According to a third preferred aspect of the invention, in the cutting tool
as described above, the substrate is formed of a hard material, such as cemented
carbide, cermet, ceramic, or high-speed steel.
The invention of this aspect is drawn to an embodiment of a material used to
form the substrate of the cutting tool. Use of such a material enables high cutting
performance.</li><li>(4) According to a fourth preferred aspect of the invention, in the cutting tool
as described above, the hard coating is a vapor deposition film formed through arc-ion-type
physical vapor deposition.
The invention of this aspect is drawn to an embodiment of a hard coating. A
vapor deposition film formed through arc-ion-type physical vapor deposition can
favorably form a dense hard coating on the surface of the substrate.</li><li>(5) According to a fifth preferred aspect of the invention, a tool with a holder
is characterized in that a cutting tool according to the invention as described above is
mounted on a holder.
The invention of this aspect contemplates a tool with a holder, configured
such that a cutting tool (e.g., a tip) is mounted on a holder.</li><li>(6) According to a sixth preferred aspect of the invention, in the tool with a
holder as described in the fifth aspect, the tool with a holder is used for milling or
grooving.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0012">The present invention contemplates a tool with a holder for milling or a tool
with a holder for grooving. By use of the tools with a holder, milling and grooving
can be favorably performed.</p>
    <p num="0013">A metallic component of the TiAlN-type hard coating in the present invention
is not limited to TiAl. So long as a coating of high hardness and high wear resistance 
can be formed, a composition may be such that a metallic component, such as a
metal belonging to Group 4a, 5a, or 6a, Si, Y, or a rare-earth element, is present in
the TiAl alloy while forming solid solution to some extent. No particular limitations
are imposed on the metallic component ratio between Ti and Al or those between
other metals. Further, a light element to be contained in addition to a metallic
component is not limited to nitrogen, but may be a composite which contains carbon,
oxygen, boron, or the like.</p>
    <p num="0014">Embodiments of the invention will now be described, by way of example
only, with reference to the accompanying drawings in which:
<sl><li>Fig. 1 is a perspective view showing a cutting tool of an embodiment;</li><li>Fig. 2 is a view for explaining an arc-ion-type PVD apparatus;</li><li>Fig. 3 - views showing a state in which the cutting tools of the embodiment
are mounted on a holder; (a): top view; and (b): front view; and</li><li>Figs. 4 - views showing the surfaces of cutting tools; (a): scanning electron
micrograph showing the surface of the cutting tool of the present invention; and (b):
scanning electron micrograph showing the surface of the conventional cutting tool.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0015">Examples of a cutting tool and a tool with a holder according to a mode for
carrying out the present invention will next be described.
<sl><li>a) First, a cutting tool of the present embodiment will be described.
As shown in Fig. 1, a cutting tool 1 of the present embodiment is a
throwaway tip configured such that a hard coating is formed on the surface of a
substrate 3 (see Fig. 2) formed of, for example, a hard material of cemented carbide
(WC-Co-type cemented carbide) equivalent to JIS K10 and polished into the shape
of ISO SPGN120312.Specifically, the cutting tool 1 is a plate-shaped positive tip whose rake face
(the main surface side), which is the upper face in Fig. 1, is wider than the opposite
face. The surface of the substrate 3 is coated with a hard coating having a thickness
ranging from 1 µm to 5 µm (e.g., 3 µm), formed of a TiAlN material, for example,
(Ti,Al)N, and having a Ti/Al ratio of 1.Particularly, according to the present embodiment, coarse grains present in
the hard coating and having a size not less than the thickness of the hard coating 
(e.g., coarse grains having a size not less than 3 µm) occupy not greater than 5% by
area of the surface of the hard coating; and the surface of the hard coating has a
surface roughness Ra of not greater than 0.1 µm and a surface roughness Rz of not
greater than 1 µm.Notably, the hard coating may satisfy at least either a requirement for a
surface roughness Ra of not greater than 0.1 µm or a requirement for a surface
roughness Rz of not greater than 1 µm.</li><li>b) Next, a method for manufacturing the cutting tool 1 will be described.
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>First, materials for the substrate 3; i.e., a WC powder and a Co powder, are
measured out in respective predetermined amounts, followed by wet mixing and
pulverization.</li><li>Next, to the pulverized material, paraffin is added in an amount of 2% by
weight. The resultant mixture is dried and granulated, thereby yielding a powder for
compaction.</li><li>The thus-obtained powder is pressed into a predetermined positive-tip
shape, followed by firing in a vacuum.</li><li>Next, the fired body is polished into the substrate 3 whose dimensions fall
within a predetermined dimensional tolerance range.</li><li>Next, the substrate 3 is coated with a TiAlN material by PVD coating;
specifically, by an arc-ion-type physical vapor deposition process, whereby a hard
coating is formed on the surface of the substrate 3 to thereby complete the cutting
tool 1.</li></ul>The above-mentioned arc-ion-type vapor deposition process will next be
described.An arc-ion plating device (an arc-ion-type PVD apparatus) 5 as shown in Fig.
2 is used, and the substrate 3 is placed on a turntable 9 within a vacuum chamber 7.
While reaction gas (e.g., N<sub>2</sub>) is being supplied into the vacuum chamber 7, bias
voltage (-) is applied to the substrate 3 via the turntable 9, and arc voltage (-) is
applied to an evaporation source (cathode) 11 which carries a metallic material (TiAl
alloy) for a hard coating. Thus, metal ions of Ti and Al from the cathode 11 are deposited on the
surface of the substrate 3, and the supplied reaction gas (N<sub>2</sub>) reacts with the deposited
metal ions, thereby forming a hard coating formed of (Ti,Al)N and having a Ti/Al
ratio of 1 on the surface of the substrate 3.According to the present embodiment, physical vapor deposition is performed
under the coating conditions (PVD Condition 1) specified below. Through
adjustment of coating time, the thickness of the hard coating is adjusted.
<sl><li>PVD Condition 1</li><li>Metallic material: TiAl alloy having a Ti/Al ratio of 1</li><li>Reaction gas pressure: 1.20 Pa</li><li>Substrate temperature: 500°C</li><li>Bias voltage: -150 V</li><li>Arc current: 100 A</li></sl>Notably, through adjustment of current and voltage to be applied, and gas
pressure, surface roughness can be adjusted.</li><li>c) Next, a tool with a holder on which the cutting tool 1 is mounted will be
described.
As shown in Fig. 3(a) and Fig. 3(b), a tool with a holder (milling cutter) 20 of
the present embodiment includes a substantially columnar cutter body (holder) 21
and is configured such that eight cutting portions 23 are circumferentially provided
on the outer circumference of the holder 21 on the side toward the front end (on the
side toward the machining face) of the holder 21.Specifically, six mounting portions 25 each in the form of a recess are
circumferentially provided on the outer circumference of the holder 21 on the side
toward the front end of the holder 21. In each of the mounting portions 25, the
cutting tool (tip) 1, an alloy steel cartridge 27 for retaining the cutting tool 1, an alloy
steel wedge 29, and a like member are disposed, thereby constituting the cutting
portion 23.In Fig. 3(b), in order to clarify the structure of the milling cutter, among six
cutting portions 23, two cutting portions 23 are illustrated such that the cutting tool 1
is not disposed, and one cutting portion 23 is illustrated such that the cutting tool 1
and the wedge 29 are not disposed. </li><li>d) As described above, the cutting tool 1 of the present embodiment is
configured such that the TiAlN-type hard coating formed on the surface of the
substrate 3 has a thickness of 1 to 5 µm, and coarse grains present in the hard coating
and having a size not less than the thickness of the hard coating occupy an area
percentage of not greater than 5% by area, thereby reducing the possibility that
resistance to joining through fusion and wear resistance are impaired by dropping-off
of a grain.
The cutting tool 1 of the present invention has a very smooth surface;
specifically, Ra is not greater than 0.1 µm, and Rz is not greater than 1 µm.
Accordingly, in the course of a work material rubbing against coating surface,
dropping-off of a grain becomes unlikely, and frictional resistance is low. As a
result, joining of a work material through fusion (and exfoliation) becomes unlikely
to occur, whereby high cutting performance is maintained.Thus, the present embodiment yields the following marked effect: an
impairment in cutting performance (resistance to joining through fusion and wear
resistance), which would otherwise arise from dropping-off of a coarse grain, does
not arise, whereby excellent cutting performance can be reliably maintained over a
long period of time.Therefore, use of the milling cutter 20 equipped with the above-described
cutting tools 1 allows stable cutting over a long period of time.</li><li>e) Next, an experiment example for verifying the effect of the present
embodiment will be described.
<sl><li>(1) Substrates which were manufactured by the previously described
manufacturing method of the present embodiment were subjected to coating under
the aforementioned PVD Condition 1 by use of the arc-ion physical vapor deposition
process, whereby a hard coating was formed on the surface of each substrate. In this
manner, cutting tools of Sample Nos. 2 to 4, which are to be subjected to experiment
and fall within the scope of the present invention, were yielded.
Another sample, which falls within the scope of the present invention, was
manufactured in the following manner. A substrate similar to that of the
embodiment was subjected to coating under the coating conditions specified below 
(PVD Condition 2) by use of an arc-ion-type PVD apparatus similar to that used in
the embodiment, whereby a cutting tool of Sample No. 7 was yielded.

   PVD Condition 2

   Reaction gas pressure: 1.33 Pa

   Substrate temperature: 500°C

   Bias voltage: -200 V

   Arc current: 150 AComparative Examples, which fall outside the scope of the present invention
(the coating thickness falls outside the scope), were manufactured in the following
manner. Substrate similar to those of the embodiment were subjected to coating
under the aforementioned PVD Condition 1 by use of an arc-ion-type PVD apparatus
similar to that used in the embodiment, whereby cutting tools of Comparative
Examples (Sample Nos. 1 and 5) were yielded.Another Comparative Example (coarse grains fall outside the scope of the
invention) was manufactured in the following manner. A substrate similar to that of
the embodiment was subjected to coating under the coating conditions specified
below (PVD Condition 3) by use of an arc-ion-type PVD apparatus similar to that
used in the embodiment, whereby a cutting tool of Comparative Example (Sample
No. 6) was yielded.

   PVD Condition 3

   Reaction gas pressure: 1.33 Pa

   Substrate temperature: 500°C

   Bias voltage: -200 V

   Arc current: 200 A</li><li>(2) The above-described cutting tool of an Example of the present invention
and a conventional cutting tool were examined for the thickness of a hard coating
and the amount of coarse grains present in the hard coating and having a size not less
than the thickness of the hard coating, by use of a scanning electron microscope.
Fig. 4 shows scanning electron micrographs (1000 times magnification). The
cutting tool which falls within the scope of the present invention; i.e., the cutting tool
of Sample No. 3 of the present invention shown in Fig. 4(a), exhibits presence of few
coarse grains on the surface thereof, indicating that the surface thereof is smooth. Measurement of Sample No. 3 showed that coarse grains having a size not
less than 3 µm occupy an area percentage of 3% by area.As compared with the cutting tool of the present invention, the conventional
cutting tool shown in Fig. 4(b) exhibits presence of a number of coarse grains on the
surface thereof, indicating that the surface thereof is rough.</li><li>(3) The cutting tools of the Examples of the present invention and those of
the Comparative Examples were measured for surface roughness Ra and surface
roughness Rz, which indicate surface smoothness of a hard coating, by use of a
surface roughness tester. The results are shown below in Table 1.</li><li>(4) The cutting tools of the Examples of the present invention and those of
the Comparative Examples were mounted on the holder of the milling cutter
mentioned previously and were evaluated for cutting performance in terms of
chipping resistance and thermal shock resistance, under conditions (i) and (ii)
described below. The results are also shown below in Table 1.</li></sl>A cutting tool exhibits the phenomenon that wear resistance or the like is
impaired as a result of joining through fusion and associated exfoliation described
previously. Microscopic observation of such an exfoliated portion indicates that
exfoliation can be considered as chipping. Thus, an experiment on chipping
resistance, which is considered as an indicator of resistance to joining through fusion
(thus an indicator of wear resistance), was carried out. Since the condition of
occurrence of chipping varies depending on thermal shock, an experiment on thermal
shock resistance was also carried out.
<sl><li>(i) Chipping Resistance
In the chipping resistance test, cutting was performed under the conditions
itemized below, and the number of shocks (the number of times cutting was
performed) until a cutting tool was chipped was measured.

   Cutting rate: 200 m/min

   Feed rate: 0.07 mm/blade

   Depth of cut: 1.5 mm

   Work material: SNCM439 (HB300), dry type</li><li>(ii) Thermal Shock Resistance In the thermal shock resistance test, cutting was performed under the
conditions itemized below, and the number of shocks (the number of times cutting
was performed) until a cutting tool was chipped was measured.In the case of the Examples of the present invention, since wet cutting is
performed, a wet state and a dry state are repeated in every cutting. Therefore, this
cutting operation served as the thermal shock resistance test.

   Cutting rate: 250 m/min

   Feed rate: 0.25 mm/blade

   Depth of cut: 1.5 mm

   Work material: SNCM439 (HB300), wet type <img id="img-00120001" orientation="unknown" wi="101" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00120001.tif" inline="no" he="229"/></li></sl></li></sl></p>
    <p num="0016">As is apparent from Table 1, the cutting tools (Sample Nos. 2 to 4 and 7)
which fall within the scope of the present invention are excellent in cutting
performance in terms of chipping resistance and thermal shock resistance (thus
resistance to joining through fusion and wear resistance) as compared with the
Comparative Examples, and thus in application thereof to actual cutting, stable
cutting can be performed over a long period of time. Particularly, the cutting tools
(Sample Nos. 2 to 4) which satisfy the preferred surface roughness requirement of
the present invention are enhanced further in cutting performance.</p>
    <p num="0017">Thus, the cutting tools of the present invention yield the following marked
effect: an impairment in cutting performance, which would otherwise arise from
dropping-off of a coarse grain, does not arise, whereby excellent cutting performance
can be reliably maintained over a long period of time.</p>
    <p num="0018">By contrast, the cutting tools of the Comparative Examples (Sample Nos. 1,
5, and 6) exhibit poor cutting performance in terms of chipping resistance and
thermal shock resistance.</p>
    <p num="0019">The present invention is not limited to the above-described embodiment, but
may be embodied in various other forms without departing from the spirit or scope of
the invention.
<sl><li>(1) For example, in addition to the aforementioned cemented carbide, various
other hard materials, such as cermet, ceramic, and high-speed steel, can be used as
material for the substrate of a cutting tool.</li><li>(2) Preferably, the aforementioned hard coating is formed through arc-ion-type
physical vapor deposition. However, other known processes (e.g., ARE-activated
reactive evaporation- process) can also be employed.</li><li>(3) The above embodiment is described while mentioning a milling cutter for
milling use as a tool with a holder. However, the present invention is also applicable
to a cutting tool for grooving use or a like cutting tool.</li></sl></p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A cutting tool comprising a substrate and a TiAlN-type hard coating formed
on the substrate, wherein the hard coating has a thickness in the range of from 1 to 5
µm, and coarse grains present in the hard coating and having a size not less than the
thickness of the hard coating occupy not greater than 5% by area.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A cutting tool according to claim 1, wherein the hard coating satisfies at least
one of: a requirement for a surface roughness Ra of not greater than 0.1 µm; and/or a
requirement for a surface roughness Rz of not greater than 1 µm.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A cutting tool according to claim 1 or 2, wherein the substrate is formed of a
hard material, such as cemented carbide, cermet, ceramic, or high-speed steel.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A cutting tool according to claim 1, 2 or 3, wherein the hard coating is a
vapor deposition film formed through arc-ion-type physical vapor deposition.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A tool with a holder, characterized in that a cutting tool according to any one
of the preceding claims is mounted on a holder.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A tool with a holder according to claim 5, which is for use in milling or
grooving.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
