<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1264577-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1264577" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="11457094" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021211">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1264577-A1" status="new" fvid="23604268">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1264577</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20021211</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02012181-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02012181</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020603</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="IT-SV20010020-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>IT</country>
          <doc-number>SV20010020</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010608</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61B   5/0452      20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61B   5/0456      20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61B   5/055       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61B   5/055       20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61B   8/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61B   8/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G01R  33/28        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G01R  33/28        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61B   5/055B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61B   8/00</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G01R  33/28</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61B5:0456</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Vorrichtung zur Kombination verschiedener diagnostischer bildgebender Verfahren</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Apparatus combining different diagnostic imaging modalities</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Appareil combinant differentes méthodes diagnostiques d'obtention d'images</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ESAOTE SPA</name>
            <address>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ESAOTE S.P.A.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Esaote S.p.A.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Via Ruffino Aliora 32</street>
              <city>15033 Casale Monferrato (AL)</city>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>BESSI LORENZO</name>
            <address>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>BIGLIERI EUGENIO</name>
            <address>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>PUGLIESE OSVALDO</name>
            <address>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SATRAGNO LUIGI</name>
            <address>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SCHIAVINI LUCIANO</name>
            <address>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>BESSI, LORENZO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>BIGLIERI, EUGENIO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>PUGLIESE, OSVALDO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SATRAGNO, LUIGI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SCHIAVINI, LUCIANO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>BESSI, LORENZO</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Via della Rondinella, 66/16</street>
              <city>50135 Firenze</city>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>BIGLIERI, EUGENIO</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Via Oreste Piacenza, 37</street>
              <city>15024 Masio (AL)</city>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>PUGLIESE, OSVALDO</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Via A.Sant'Elia, 192/2</street>
              <city>16153 Genova</city>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>SATRAGNO, LUIGI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Via Bertore, 8/10A</street>
              <city>16122 Genova</city>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>SCHIAVINI, LUCIANO</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Via Bianchessi, 9</street>
              <city>26013 Crema (CR)</city>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Karaghiosoff, Giorgio A. C/O Studio Karaghiosoff &amp;amp; Frizzi S.a.s</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Studio Karaghiosoff e Frizzi S.a.S. Via Pecorile 25/C</street>
              <city>17015 Celle Ligure (SV)</city>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A combined apparatus for imaging the inner part of a
body, particularly for diagnostic imaging thereof,
comprising at least means for imaging and displaying
images according to at least one type of beams, waves
or signals transmitted toward a body or a part thereof
to be examined, characterized in that it comprises a
combination of at least means for imaging and
displaying images according to two types of beams,
waves or signals transmitted by the body under
examination or a part thereof.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="111" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="99"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">The invention relates to a combined apparatus for
imaging the internal part of a body, particularly for
diagnostic imaging thereof, comprising at least means
for imaging and displaying images according to at least
one type of beams, waves or signals transmitted by a
body or a part thereof to be examined.</p>
    <p num="0002">Particularly, the invention relates to an
apparatus for imaging the internal part of a body,
particularly for diagnostic imaging thereof, comprising
at least means for generating at least one type of
waves or beams which are transmitted toward the body or
the part thereof to be internally imaged and means for
receiving said type of waves or beams transmitted by
the body under examination or by the part thereof or
deriving from the excitation of said part or body under
examination, from the reflection and/or transmission
and/or modification of waves, of the beams transmitted
against said body under examination or the part
thereof, there being provided means for univocally
relating the information of the waves or beams
retransmitted by the body under examination or the part
thereof, to a space position of an image unit element
(so-called pixel or voxel) and means for reconstructing
the image from the array of pixels or voxels obtained
thereby, which relate the information of the received
waves or beams to brightness and/or color 
characteristics of the individual pixels.</p>
    <p num="0003">Such apparatuses are well-known and include
ultrasound imaging apparatuses, Nuclear Magnetic
Resonance imaging apparatuses, X-Ray apparatuses, etc.</p>
    <p num="0004">In such type of prior art apparatuses, each
apparatus always uses a single type of wave or beam for
imaging. From the diagnostic point of view, human body
tissues and human body fluid flows provide better or
worse different responses in relation to the type of
imaging method in use. In order to image with
sufficient clearness and accuracy tissues or flows
which have an unfavorable imaging behavior, with
reference to a specific type of imaging method,
arrangements or constructions of imaging apparatuses
are often needed which increase the cost and hinder the
installation thereof. Hence, for instance, Nuclear
Magnetic Resonance imaging apparatuses generally
require large magnetic structures. Further, there
exists a tendency to provide a separate apparatus for
each type of imaging method with considerable purchase
costs. It shall be also considered that the physical
characteristics of the waves or beams used for imaging
have intrinsic limits as regards the capability of
imaging certain types of tissues or flows.</p>
    <p num="0005">According to an additional aspect, in the field of
Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging, there exists a
current tendency toward providing dedicated
apparatuses. The peculiar characteristic of these
apparatuses is a reduced size of the magnetic structure
which allows to considerably limit the weight and 
dimensions, hence both purchase and installation costs
thereof. These apparatuses are obviously constructed
in such a manner as to have small housings in which the
parts of the body to be examined are to be received.
Essentially, instead of housing the patient inside the
magnetic structure for a relevant part of his/her body,
the dedicated apparatuses may only accommodate small
regions of the patient body, like parts of a limb or
body, e.g. the region of the knee, elbow, shoulder,
etc. This type of Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging
apparatuses operates with low magnetic fields. In these
conditions, imaging of tissues which have unfavorable
characteristics with respect to the Nuclear Magnetic
Resonance imaging technique in use is even more
difficult. In order to obviate this, and obtain images
of a certain quality and usefulness, the drawbacks of
small magnetic structures and low fields are
compensated by using more complex and longer scanning
sequences, i.e. protocols.</p>
    <p num="0006">Combined apparatuses currently exist for imaging
and therapeutic applications, which use, for instance,
a Nuclear Magnetic Resonance technique for imaging
purposes, in combination with ultrasound probes for
therapeutic applications. In these applications, the
interference between ultrasound imaging means and
therapeutic means is not of substantial importance,
since the two techniques do not have to provide
mutually related images, whereas the image generally
has the only purpose to verify, for instance, the
position of the therapeutic tool and/or the effect of 
the therapeutic application on tissues.</p>
    <p num="0007">Particualrly relevant are actually imaging
apparatuses and method which allow to acquire 3D images
of the body under examination. The actual 3D imaging
methods combines a certain nuber of images acquired
along a certain number of adiacent scanning planes
intersecting the body under examination. Each sectional
image also called a slice is combined with the other
slices relating to their spatial relations in order to
organise the information as the section planes of the
body under examination along which the images have been
acquired, thus obtaining a three dimensional image data
set describing the object in a three dimensional data
array.</p>
    <p num="0008">WO 96/32056 discloses a system for multidimensional
imaging in which an ultrasound system and a
x-ray system are combined. This document does not deal
with the hardware integration of the two system but
limit its disclosure to the techniques for combinig the
data obtainmed by the two different imging systems. The
system disclosed in WO 96/32056 is a so called 3D
(three dimensional) imaging system.</p>
    <p num="0009">The invention has the object of providing an
apparatus for imaging the inner part of a body,
particularly for diagnostic imaging thereof and
especially for a so called 3D imaging, which obviates
the drawbacks of prior art apparatuses, while allowing
to obtain an improved imaging apparatus which has
better global imaging functions, a smaller global size,
a higher versatility and lower costs. </p>
    <p num="0010">The invention achieves the above purposes by
providing an apparatus as described hereinbefore,
wherein at least means for imaging and displaying
images according to two types of beams, waves or
signals transmitted toward the body under examination
or a part thereof are provided together within the same
apparatus.</p>
    <p num="0011">Especially, the apparatus according to the
invention includes means for generating, means for
receiving, means for univocally relating the
information of the waves or beams transmitted back from
the body under examination or the part thereof, with a
space position of an image unit element (so-called
pixel or voxel) and means for reconstructing the image
from the array of pixels or voxels obtained thereby,
which turn the information of the waves or beams
received into brightness and/or color characteristics
of the individual pixels, both for Nuclear Magnetic
Resonance imaging and for ultrasound imaging.</p>
    <p num="0012">Hence, the typical elements of an ultrasound
imaging apparatus and those of a Nuclear Magnetic
Resonance imaging apparatus are integrated in the same
apparatus.</p>
    <p num="0013">Typically, Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging
apparatuses have a magnetic structure which is composed
of a static field generating magnet and of several
coils designed to transmit radio-frequency signals for
exciting nuclear spins, as well as gradient coils and
receiving coils. The magnet, which may be of the
permanent, or resistive or superconducting type, 
defines a cavity for receiving the body under
examination or a substantial part thereof, in so-called
"total body" magnets, or a limited part of the body or
limb in so-called "dedicated" magnets. A patient
supporting element, e.g. a patient chair, table/chair
or table is associated to the magnetic structure. Total
body apparatuses include an electric cabinet which
contains all the electronic control and
processing/displaying devices. In dedicated
apparatuses, a control console is provided, which also
has display means. Said console contains the
electronics designed to control the magnetic structure,
generate nuclear spin exciting signals and gradients,
and to process the echo signals picked up by the
receiving coils. Moreover, said console contains the
electronics for image reconstruction from received
signals and for image processing, as well as for the
control of display means.</p>
    <p num="0014">Ultrasound imaging apparatuses generally include a
console having integrated or associated display means.
The console includes the electronics for controlling an
ultrasound probe upon transmission and reception,
provided with transmitting and receiving transducers;
the electronics for processing the received signals and
for reconstructing images; the electronics for
controlling the display. The connecting cable/s for one
or more ultrasound probes branch off from the console.</p>
    <p num="0015">The apparatus according to the invention comprises
at least one patient supporting means, such as a
patient chair, a table/chair, a table, or the like, 
with a part thereof being provided in the form of a
case for accommodating at least a part of the
electronic control and/or processing and/or displaying
circuits of the Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging
and/or ultrasound imaging apparatus.</p>
    <p num="0016">In a particular embodiment, this case consists of
a base block for supporting the patient chair,
table/chair and/or table, which has the shape of a
polyhedron, like a cabinet.</p>
    <p num="0017">Advantageously, the support means consist of a
table/chair with a central base block having the shape
of a parallelepiped or the like.</p>
    <p num="0018">The table/chair may have any construction, and
preferably has a table part shorter than a table and an
end extension part which may be displaced to several
different positions, to be used as a footrest, thereby
allowing a downward positioning of the lower part of
the legs, or as a table extension, thereby allowing to
also support the lower part of the legs on an extension
surface of the table part.</p>
    <p num="0019">The armrests may have an identical construction or
function.</p>
    <p num="0020">Particularly, the table may be like the one
described in the published patent application EP 913
122 of the owner hereof.</p>
    <p num="0021">In accordance with an additional characteristic, a
supervision, control and display console is associated
to the table, integrating: the means for controlling
the ultrasound apparatus, the display means and the
means for controlling them, the means for setting the 
operating options and the apparatus parameters,
possible mass storage means for storing image data
and/or hospital file databases.</p>
    <p num="0022">Advantageously, the console is associated to the
table by means of a support structure which is
articulated to the table structure and is provided with
joints for displacement in different relative positions
with reference to the table.</p>
    <p num="0023">The console has means for connecting, at least
partly, the probes and/or sensors of at least a part of
the imaging devices, whereas a communication line is
provided between the console and the block of circuits
dedicated to the control of said sensors and/or said
probes, which line connects said probes and/or said
sensors to the corresponding block of dedicated
circuits.</p>
    <p num="0024">An additional characteristics of the invention
provides that the electronics of the ultrasound imaging
device and/or the electronics of the nuclear magnetic
resonance imaging device is divided into a part that is
specifically designed for the processing of the
specific type of transmission/excitation signals and of
received signals, i.e. ultrasonic echoes or RF magnetic
resonance signals, and into a common image processing
and image displaying part, which may process both image
data from nuclear magnetic resonance imaging device and
image data from the ultrasounf imaging device, all data
being transmitted on transmission lines or buses.</p>
    <p num="0025">In this case, the outputs and inputs of the
control and processing units dedicated to each specific 
imaging device, i.e. to the ultrasound imaging device
and to the Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging device
have output and input sections from and toward the
control and display console, which encode data and
control signals according to identical structures,
protocols and transmission/reception parameters which
are supported by the communication unit, the so-called
communication bus. The electronic units of the console,
substantially including the control and adjustment
means and the image data processing means also have
corresponding input and output sections.</p>
    <p num="0026">The above has the advantage that it allows to
easily integrate the functions generally assigned to
two dedicated consoles - one for the ultrasound device
and the other for the Nuclear Magnetic Resonance device
in a single console, which has the specific control
means for the two types of imaging devices and the
image processing and displaying means. Hence, the cost
and size is further reduced as compared with prior art
separate apparatuses.</p>
    <p num="0027">The above is essentially based on the
acknowledgement that when a structured set of image
data, e.g. a two-dimensional or three-dimensional data
matrix, is constructed by specific and dedicated
processing, depending on the different types of signals
and by univocal correlation between the individual data
and the space location thereof, imaging occurs for the
different imaging means with processing procedures
which are substantially identical or anyway deriving at
least partly from identical algorithms. </p>
    <p num="0028">The advantages of this configuration of the
control, processing and display electronics also allow
to possibly provide the integrated apparatus of the
invention with additional units for imaging or
detecting other physiological parameters. The control
means of the additional devices for imaging or
detecting physiological parameters and the processing
and displaying means may be integrated without
affecting the structure of the apparatus, by simply
supplying the dedicated electronic units with
corresponding means for interfacing them with output
and input sections which encode data according to the
structure, the protocol and the parameters of the
selected communication bus.</p>
    <p num="0029">Hence, for instance, the integrated apparatus that
comprises ultrasound imaging devices and Nuclear
Magnetic Resonance imaging devices allows to integrate
easily and with no effort, and especially with no
changes to the existing structure, except software
configuration changes, an X-ray imaging device, and/or
an ECG electrocardiograph, or an EGG, EMG or other
imaging means.</p>
    <p num="0030">It shall be further noted that by structuring
detected data according to predetermined communication
and processing protocols by substantially identical or
common means, a high-level integration of the data
detected with the different methods is possible.</p>
    <p num="0031">The apparatus of the invention may further be
provided with a magnetic structure for Nuclear Magnetic
Resonance imaging which integrates therein at least a 
portion of the control and processing electronics,
thereby increasing the useful space in the housing
formed in the table structure or the like.</p>
    <p num="0032">Referring to the above, the configuration of the
control and processing electronics of the different
imaging types, allows a mutual integration of the
images obtained by said two different types. In fact,
when each processing electronics generates image data
matrixes having a compatible structure, the latter may
be displayed alternately, or in adjacent or overlaid
positions on the display screen, thanks to the
compatible structuration of data and to the common
section of image processing. The information obtained
by the different imaging types may be integrated in a
better and more detailed image, without having to
excessively enhance the individual imaging techniques
of the two different types to display particular poorly
visible tissues and flows providing lower responses
with one imaging type or the other.</p>
    <p num="0033">In the apparatus of the invention, the integration
may be further enhanced to deeper levels, by
structuring the dedicated control and processing
electronics in such a manner as to also use electronic
units having common functions. A particular example may
consist, for instance, of the analog to digital
conversion section shared by both types of devices. In
this cases the analog to digital unit converters of a
device may be also used for the other device.</p>
    <p num="0034">Here, in order to prevent any mutual interference
between the two or more imaging devices, a unit is 
provided to control the imaging procedures on a time-sharing
basis. Hence, while one of the imaging devices
is enabled, the other is temporarily disabled and vice
versa. By using scan speed up techniques, the times of
the different imaging steps may be reduced, while
ensuring that global imaging times for one and the
other imaging device type are relatively short and
substantially allow to display the detected images
essentially in real time or almost in real time.</p>
    <p num="0035">In accordance with a further improvement of the
invention, in order to allow the mutual integration of
the image data obtained with the different types of
imaging devices, advantages may be obtained by
providing means for univocal location of the space
position of the individual detected image planes with
respect to the body under examination or a part
thereof. In fact, both ultrasound devices and Nuclear
Magnetic Resonance devices image bodies through
predetermined slice planes. In order to compare
individual images obtained by the same imaging type or
by two different imaging types, it is necessary to
locate in an accurate and univocal manner the position
in space of said slice images with respect to the body
or to each other.</p>
    <p num="0036">To this end, the invention provides that the
receiving unit of at least one of the two imaging
devices have reference marks that can be univocally
located by the other imaging device. To this end, it is
very simple to provide the ultrasonic probe with one or
more marking elements whose material leaves a 
definitely and univocally identifiable trace in the
image obtained with the other imaging device, for
instance small containers of a predetermined shape,
filled with water.</p>
    <p num="0037">Moreover, this characteristic also allows to find
the precise orientation of the ultrasonic probe with
respect to the body under examination, hence the
precise orientation of the slice plane along which
imaging occurs.</p>
    <p num="0038">An ultrasound 3D or three-dimensional imaging
technique provides detection of a succession of images
over more adjacent different slice planes of the body
under examination or a part thereof. The ultrasonic
probe is displaced along the body or the part thereof
in at least one predetermined direction. The
displacement may be a translational or rotary motion of
the probe. Said displacement may occur either by
mechanical means, in the form of a probe supporting
structure which has probe connection means which are
supported in such a manner as to allow translation
thereof along one or more guides transverse to each
other, or said probe connection means may be of the
swinging type. Displacements may be controlled either
manually or by means of motors. Nevertheless, the probe
may also be supported and displaced manually, when this
is convenient. In this case, the different slice planes
along which ultrasound imaging occurs may not be
equally spaced and especially may also not be parallel
to each other due to orientation inaccuracies caused by
radial displacements. </p>
    <p num="0039">However, thanks to the marking elements of the
probe and to the indication thereof in the Nuclear
Magnetic Resonance images, both the precise position of
the probe and the exact orientation of the slice plane
may be detected. This may be also obtained by providing
more aligned marking elements parallel to the axis of
the ultrasound waves transmitted to the body under
examination, which indicate the orientations of said
axis with respect to at least one or more projections
on orthogonal planes which subtend the space. In this
case, Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging may still be
performed while the ultrasonic probe is enabled
because, if the marking elements provide strong
signals, the risk that artifacts may be generated while
locating the orientation of the image slice planes of
the probe is not relevant. During Nuclear Magnetic
Resonance imaging of the body, the probe may be
disabled again to prevent the formation of artifacts.</p>
    <p num="0040">Also, as a further improvement, since ultrasound
imaging apparatuses may already have probe position
detecting systems which use magnetic fields, it is
possible to avoid a real Nuclear Magnetic Resonance
imaging of the probe during ultrasound imaging of the
body, thereby using the magnetic structure of the
Nuclear Magnetic Resonance device as a magnetic sensor
for detecting the displacement of the probe which, in
this case, would be provided with magnetic or
magnetizable elements as marking elements.</p>
    <p num="0041">Obviously, all the above ultrasonic probe location
options may be included in the integrated apparatus of 
the invention and these may be provided in such a
manner as to enable operation and use thereof either
alternatively to and in combination with each other.</p>
    <p num="0042">Yet another characteristic of the invention
provides that the Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging
device is also adapted to three-dimensional imaging,
i.e. to detect images composed of a plurality of
adjacent slices of the body under examination or of a
limited portion thereof.</p>
    <p num="0043">An example of this device may be similar to the
one described and illustrated, for instance, in EP 654
675 and EP 430 322.</p>
    <p num="0044">Particularly, in dedicated machines, which have
small magnetic structures and are designed for imaging
delimited parts of the body under examination, real
time or almost real time Nuclear Magnetic Resonance
imaging techniques may be implemented in the apparatus
according to the invention.</p>
    <p num="0045">In this case, the electronic control means of the
Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging device may have
imaging sequences or combinations thereof which allow
to vary the Field of View, or FOV and/or definition
and/or contrast and/or signal-to-noise ratio by
limiting these parameters in an alternative or combined
fashion to drastically reduce global imaging times. The
controls may be such as to allow modification thereof
during the scan.</p>
    <p num="0046">Upon Nuclear Magnetic Resonance three-dimensional
scanning of the body under examination or a part
thereof, relative displacements must be provided 
between the magnetic structure and the body under
examination or the part thereof. In this case, the
means for displacing the magnetic structure and/or the
table may be provided with transducers or tracers for
detecting the distance from the table. This may be
achieved either by mechanical links between the table
and the magnetic structure, e.g. one or more guides
and/or rotary supports for the table and/or the
magnetic structure whereon both the table and the
magnetic structure are mounted, or by non contact
means, such as proximity sensors or the like.</p>
    <p num="0047">In combination with the integrated apparatus, the
invention also provides several different Nuclear
Magnetic Resonance imaging methods.</p>
    <p num="0048">According to a first method, ultrasound imaging
and Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging of the same
slice of the body under examination are performed in
any sequence and at immediately successive time
intervals;
<sl><li>the received signals for ultrasound pulses and
spin echoes are processed separately, whereby virtual
images are reconstructed, which are formed by separate
image data matrixes;</li><li>image data matrixes are transmitted to common
means for image processing and for controlling the
display means whereon ultrasound images, i.e. obtained
by ultrasound imaging, and Nuclear Magnetic Resonance
images are displayed in alternative, adjacent and/or
overlaid configurations.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0049">A further improvement provides the location of the 
slice planes whereat ultrasound imaging and Nuclear
Magnetic Resonance imaging were performed, and the
combination of the two images obtained thereby into a
single image, which contains the information obtained
by the two separate images.</p>
    <p num="0050">Yet another improvement of the method provides the
alternate detection of a succession of ultrasound
images and of a succession on Nuclear Magnetic
Resonance images along a succession of slices of the
body under examination;
<sl><li>the detection of the positions and orientations of
the slice planes along which imaging occurs and the
univocal correlation of position data to image data
along each slice plane; the reconstruction of three-dimensional
matrixes of image data;</li><li>the transmission of the image data of each three-dimensional
matrix of image data obtained with the two
imaging modes, to a common image processing and display
unit;</li><li>the combined display of the two images and/or the
alternate display and/or the adjacent display of the
two images.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0051">In accordance with a variant of the method, the
images relating to each slice plane may be displayed in
adjacent, alternate or combined positions, immediately
or after a very short time from each scan, thereby
obtaining a real-time adjacent, alternate and/or
combined display of the images detected by ultrasound
imaging means and by Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging
means, along each slice of the body under examination. </p>
    <p num="0052">Acording to a further feature of the invention,
the spacing distances between the slice planes along
which slice images are obtained, are different
depending for the two imaging types, namely magnetic
resonance or ultrasound imaging.</p>
    <p num="0053">The spacing distances between the slice planes
along which a slice image of the body under examination
or a part thereof is obtained, may be varied based on
the closeness of said slice planes to a particular
region or interest or non-interest of the body under
examination and to a different or equal extent for each
of the two imaging types.</p>
    <p num="0054">Furthermore it is possible to provide that for
each imaging type, the imaging parameters are changed
between a slice image and the next slice image or for
each imaging step with respect to the preceding one and
within the same slice image.</p>
    <p num="0055">In combination therewith, the method of the
invention may include the use of contrast agents for
ultrasound imaging applications.</p>
    <p num="0056">In combination therewith or as an alternative
thereto, the use of contrast agents for Nuclear
Magnetic Resonance imaging applications may be
provided.</p>
    <p num="0057">Advantageously, the method of the invention
includes the injection of contrast agents for
ultrasound imaging only and/or for Nuclear Magnetic
Resonance imaging only, or the injection of mixtures of
contrast agents for ultrasound imaging and/or for
Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging applications. </p>
    <p num="0058">Contrast agents for ultrasound imaging are made of
microbubbles, whereas contrast agents for Nuclear
Magnetic Resonance imaging are made of paramagnetic
molecules.</p>
    <p num="0059">In this case, in addition to a simple mixture
within the same carrier for said contrast agents, the
carrier itself may be provided with paramagnetic
characteristics so as to have contrast functions for
Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging.</p>
    <p num="0060">Paramagnetic molecules may be also encased in
microbubbles.</p>
    <p num="0061">The combined use of contrast agents for ultrasound
imaging and of those for Nuclear Magnetic Resonance
imaging has a considerable advantage. Typically, high
quality Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging sequences,
i.e. having a high resolution, a high contrast and an
optimized signal-to-noise ratio are relatively long,
whereby it is difficult to determine the moment in
which the contrast agents for Nuclear Magnetic
Resonance imaging reach the region under examination of
the body. The result of a long imaging sequence may be
that, when it ends, the contrast agent may be no longer
present in a sufficient amount in the region under
examination. In these conditions, a new injection of
the contrast agent, i.e. another invasive procedure on
the patient, is required.</p>
    <p num="0062">With the ultrasound imaging device, which operates
in a more rapid manner, the perfusion of the specific
contrast agent may be detected in a much easier manner,
whereby more accurate and specific information may be 
obtained on the instant in which the contrast agents
for Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging perfuse the
region under examination, thereby obviating the need to
repeat the invasive process of contrast agent
injection.</p>
    <p num="0063">Even more accurately, it is possible to determine
the instant in which perfusion of the region under
examination by contrast agents is complete, by
detecting physiological parameters of the heart cycle
of the patient and by using them to determine the flow
of body liquids within the secondary vascular system,
i.e. at the capillary level. This additional
characteristic of the method also allows implementation
of imaging methods like stress echo or the like.</p>
    <p num="0064">According to still other variants of the
invention, the integration of several different imaging
types into a single Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging
apparatus allows to provide a section for storing all
data relating to a patient, which comprises all the
information obtained by the different imaging and
physiological parameter detection methods. This allows
to automatically obtain a complete database of a
considerable number of examinations for each patient.</p>
    <p num="0065">In order that data obtained with other devices or
images may be integrated in said diagnostic database, a
data entry unit is provided in combination with said
integrated apparatus, which may comprise, in a combined
or alternative manner, means like a keyboard, a
scanner, or the like.</p>
    <p num="0066">The method according to the invention provides for 
the detection of a physiological parameter and the
control of the enabling functions for one or both
imaging types based on the curves or values of said
parameters. Particulalrly the detected physiological
parameter is an electrocardiogram and the imaging by
one or both the imaging types is enabled at identical
or different phases or times of the heart cycle.</p>
    <p num="0067">The characteristics of the invention and the
advantages derived therefrom will appear more clearly
from the following description of a few non limiting
embodiments, illustrated in the annexed drawings, in
which:
<sl><li>Figs. 1 and 2 are two perspective views, in two
different directions, and with the table in different
orientations, of an integrated ultrasound and Nuclear
Magnetic Resonance imaging apparatus.</li><li>Figs. 3 to 5 are different perspective views of
the apparatus as shown in Fig. 1, in which the magnetic
structure of the Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging
device is omitted, and the console is shown in
different operating and rest positions.</li><li>Fig. 6 shows a variant embodiment of the
integrated apparatus as shown in Figs. 1 to 5, in which
the magnetic structure is very small and has an
inverted U or C shape.</li><li>Figs. 7 and 8 show a variant of the integrated
apparatus, in which the magnetic structure of the
Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging device is mounted
with the table on a common guide for a controlled and
measurable relative displacement. </li><li>Fig. 9 shows a detail of a C-shaped receiving coil
which bears slide support means for reading the
position of an ultrasound imaging probe.</li><li>Fig. 10 is a front view as seen from the open side
of the receiving coil as shown in fig. 9.</li><li>Fig. 11 shows an ultrasound imaging probe having
marking elements adapted to generate a Nuclear Magnetic
Resonance detectable signal.</li><li>Fig. 12 shows a block diagram of the electronics
for ultrasound imaging signal processing, as well as
for controlling and processing and displaying the
images obtained by the integrated apparatus as shown in
the previous figures.</li><li>Fig. 13 is a schematic view of movable means for
supporting a part of the patient body relative to the
imaging volume, which are associated to the magnetic
structure of the dedicated Nuclear Magnetic Resonance
imaging device.</li><li>Fig. 14 shows a variant embodiment in which the
receiving coil is integrated in the dedicated magnetic
structure and has means for displacing the table
relative to said magnetic structure.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0068">With reference to Figures 1 and 2, an integrated
apparatus for ultrasound imaging and Nuclear Magnetic
Resonance imaging comprises a Nuclear Magnetic
Resonance imaging device and an ultrasound imaging
device. The Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging device
comprises a magnetic structure generally denoted as 1,
which includes a permanent, resistive or
superconducting magnet for generating a static field in 
a cavity 101 designed to receive a part of the patient
body; coils for transmitting radio-frequency pulses for
exciting nuclear spins, gradient coils for applying
selecting and phase and frequency encoding gradients
and receiving coils. All these elements are known per
se and are not shown in detail.</p>
    <p num="0069">In Figs. 1 and 2, the magnetic structure 1 is
contained in a separate case and has a peripherally
closed annular shape, with two opposite open sides. A
patient table 2, in the form of a table/chair is
associated to the magnetic structure 1. Particularly,
the table is shorter than the patient body and, in the
portion associated to the lower limbs, substantially
reaches the knee level, but is able to extend beyond it
by a footrest element 102 which may be displaced to
various positions, for instance to a lowered and tilted
position parallel to the ground with a footrest
function, or to a lowered and vertically tilted
position against the end side of the table or even to a
position in which it extends and completes the surface
of the table. A detailed construction example of a
table of this type is provided in the published patent
application EP 913 122.</p>
    <p num="0070">Particularly, the table is mounted on an
intermediate carriage which consists of a cabinet-like
element 202. At one of its end sides, particularly the
one associated to the lower limbs, the table has a
vertical leg 302, also in the form of a carriage, which
extends substantially all along the table, thereby
having the function of a pair of traditional legs. </p>
    <p num="0071">A control console 3 is associated to the patient
table 2, particularly but without limitation to the end
opposite to the one associated to the lower limbs.</p>
    <p num="0072">The control console 3 has an upper surface with
the different ultrasound imaging controls and
advantageously an ultra-slim display 103, e.g. a liquid
crystal display, which is articulated to the console 3
in such a manner as to allow it to be tilted to a
lifted operating position and to a rest position in
which it lays over the upper face of the console 3.</p>
    <p num="0073">The control console 3 is secured to a support
structure 4 formed by swinging arms 104 and supporting
and sliding beams 204, in such a manner that it can be
displaced relative to the vertical level, swung forward
and rearward, and translated transverse to the
longitudinal axis of the table 2.</p>
    <p num="0074">These displacements may be obtained by using any
support structure construction, depending on the
structure and on the aspect of the table. In the
embodiment as shown in the Figures, and with particular
reference to Figs. 3 to 5, the support structure 4 of
the console 3 has at least one transverse support guide
204 for transverse sliding, for example extending
telescopically or as a rod sliding in slide supports,
whereon at least two swinging arms 104 are mounted,
which are spaced in the axial direction of the guide
204, and are articulated by their opposite ends to the
case of the console 3. The guide 204 may be secured to
the lower side of the table 2 by one or more additional
vertical and/or longitudinal guides (with reference to 
the longitudinal axis of the table) and/or with rotary
joints according to a vertical axis. The two arms 104
may themselves be secured to the console case 3 to
pivot about it with the interposition of a rotary joint
for the rotation of the console 3 with respect to a
vertical axis. Also, the guide 204 may slide in the
transverse direction to such an extent as to allow the
console to slide independently on one side or the other
of the table 2. As an alternative to the illustrated
means, the console may be supported by a jointed arm
which may have one or more successive arm sections,
connected to each other by spherical or cardan joints,
and is fastened to the structure of the table. The
jointed arm may be fabricated as is known, for instance
for display supporting arms, or the like, with the
appropriate changes required by the conditions of
displacement of the console 3 relative to the table 2.
Advantageously, both the illustrated structure 3 and
the possibly provided jointed arm have cavities wherein
the wires for connecting the console 3 to other
electronic units associated to the imaging devices may
pass and be housed.</p>
    <p num="0075">Thanks to the above construction, the console 3
may be displaced to any position relative to the table
2. Particularly, there are provided an operating
position adjacent to one of the sides of the table 2
and a rest position, in which, after tilting the
display into the rest position, against the upper
surface of the console, the latter may be completely
displaced under the surface of the table. </p>
    <p num="0076">Thanks to this construction, besides ensuring the
highest operational convenience, the retractable
position of the console within the size of the table
allows to reduce the damaging risks, for instance,
while displacing the console, and to prevent any
hindrance to the freedom of movement of the personnel
when intervening on the patient.</p>
    <p num="0077">With reference to the above construction, the
ultrasound imaging device comprises a probe 5 which is
connected by a cable to the console or to the control
and processing electronics contained inside the
cabinet-like support 202 of the table 2.</p>
    <p num="0078">Here, in order to maintain a relatively limited
size of the console 3, the cabinet-like base 202 of the
table 2 is provided in the form of an electrical
cabinet for housing at least a part or all of the
processing electronics of at least the ultrasound
imaging device.</p>
    <p num="0079">According to an advantageous embodiment, the
electronics is appropriately divided between the
console 2 and the cabinet-like base 202. Particularly,
the base 202 contains the typical electronic circuits,
specifically dedicated to the control of the ultrasonic
probe for the transmission of ultrasonic waves,
focusing thereof and reception of reflected waves, the
reconstruction according to the focusing rule and the
processing of received signals as regards the
extraction of data useful for imaging and correlation
thereof to a precise space position and to a precise
and unique pixel of the image to be displayed. 
Moreover, these circuits may also comprise all the
sections for filtering and for processing the data
extracted from the received signals with various
processing modes, such as those known as B-Mode,
Harmonic Imaging, Doppler, Color Doppler and other data
processing and extraction modes. When devices for
detecting other data or physiological parameters, e.g.
an electrocardiogram are provided, the cabinet 202 may
also contain the control and processing units of these
devices and possibly the units for synchronizing the
signal of the electrocardiogram or other devices, for
instance with the electronics of the ultrasound imaging
device, such as in the apparatuses known as "stress
ultrasound imaging" or the like.</p>
    <p num="0080">On the other hand, the console 3 includes the
electronic circuits for controlling and setting the
ultrasound imaging modes, the circuits for image
processing and controlling the display means and the
means for setting the display and detection controls,
such as the selection of imaging modes, amongst the
modes mentioned above (B-Mode, Harmonic Imaging,
Doppler, Color Doppler, and other data processing and
extraction methods).</p>
    <p num="0081">Advantageously, according to a preferred
embodiment, the dedicated circuits of the cabinet 202
and those of the console 3 communicate with each other
via communication interfaces which encode the data to
be exchanged between the console 3 and the dedicated
control and processing circuits contained in the
cabinet with a common structure, for instance a so-called 
bidirectional communication bus.</p>
    <p num="0082">Mass storage means may be also associated to the
console 3 or the cabinet 202, such as hard disks, or
the like, means for reading or writing removable data
storage media, such as floppy disks, CR-Rom, CD-R, CD-RW
and/or flashcard memories or the like, and/or other
output peripherals, such as printers and/or other data
entry peripherals, such as scanners or the like.</p>
    <p num="0083">Advantageously, the console 3 has a microprocessor
unit, the functions thereof being implemented in
software form.</p>
    <p num="0084">This structure may be easily used to also
integrate, in the apparatus of the invention, a program
for processing, storage and centralized control of the
diagnostic data of the patient, obtained either through
the specific analyses performable by the integrated
apparatus or through other apparatuses, which may be
entered in the patient diagnostic data control program
through the various data entry means as mentioned
above.</p>
    <p num="0085">With reference now to the Nuclear Magnetic
Resonance imaging device, the latter generally
comprises, besides the magnetic structure 1, circuits
for generating the excitation sequences and for
capturing images and circuits for receiving nuclear
spin echoes, which contain the information, i.e. the
data for image reconstruction, as well as circuits for
reconstructing images, i.e. for extracting image data
from received signals and for relating said data to the
space location wherefrom it is transmitted, hence to an 
image pixel. Further, the device comprises, like the
ultrasound imaging device, circuits for controlling and
setting the modes of the Nuclear Magnetic Resonance
imaging device, and circuits for processing, display
and storage of reconstructed images.</p>
    <p num="0086">All the above circuits may be provided in a
separate console (not shown in detail). Nevertheless,
by using the same circuit configuration as the
ultrasound imaging device, the specific part for
controlling the magnetic structure and the associated
units like excitation coils, gradient coils, etc., and
the specific part designed to receive echo signals, to
reconstruct and extract image data and relate it to a
specific pixel of an array of image pixels, may be
housed wholly or partly in the case of the magnetic
structure 1 and/or wholly or partly in the cabinet 202,
whereas the image processing means, the display control
means, the Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging command
entry means are housed in a separated console (not
shown) and/or integrated in the console 3.</p>
    <p num="0087">Here, the processing and control electronics of
the Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging device should be
provided with a communication interface, i.e. a
bidirectional bus for communication with the console 3,
which is of the same type as the one used for the
control and processing electronics of the ultrasound
imaging device.</p>
    <p num="0088">By this arrangement, the means for image
processing and display control may be the same as used
in the ultrasound imaging device. </p>
    <p num="0089">Mass storage means, data entry means, like
scanners or the like, for entering data detected by
other separate devices and/or data transmission means,
like printers or the like may also be shared by the two
types of devices.</p>
    <p num="0090">If the ultrasound imaging device also comprises an
ECG unit, the latter may be also interfaced with the
Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging device, like the
ultrasound imaging device, through means for
synchronizing resonance imaging with the physiological
parameters detected by the ECG.</p>
    <p num="0091">According to an additional characteristic, the
console 3 may have image processing means which combine
images of the same section obtained by the ultrasound
imaging device and by the Nuclear Magnetic Resonance
imaging device. In this case, the advantage consists in
the possibility to mutually combine the information of
the image obtained by ultrasound imaging and that
obtained by Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging. Besides
obtaining better and more complete results, this
combination option may allow to use imaging modes of a
reduced duration and complexity for both devices, since
even the characteristics that are hardly visible
through an imaging method may be visible through the
other imaging method.</p>
    <p num="0092">The combination may be simply obtained by
displaying the two images obtained each with one of the
two imaging methods sequentially or side by side , or
by overlaying the two images, or even by a real
combination and mutual integration of the image data 
obtained by the two imaging modes.</p>
    <p num="0093">Since the simultaneous use of the two imaging
methods may cause adverse effects on one of the two
imaging modes, e.g. the presence of ultrasonic
transducer power may generate noise which cause the
formation of artifacts in the Nuclear Magnetic
Resonance imaging signals, the two devices are arranged
to be operated in fast alternate succession, on a time-sharing
basis. To this end, the console 3 has means for
entering time sharing parameters, and a control unit is
provided which, based on said parameters, controls the
alternate operation of said two imaging devices.</p>
    <p num="0094">Nevertheless, the two modes may be also used in
combination, for instance with the help of contrast
agents which are caused to burst or be destroyed by the
power provided by the ultrasonic probe, whereas imaging
is performed by Nuclear Magnetic Resonance in these
conditions of the contrast agents.</p>
    <p num="0095">A further embodiment of the invention provides an
ultrasound imaging device adapted for three-dimensional
imaging, particularly obtaining a succession of slice
images taken along different adjacent slice planes of
the body under examination or a part thereof. In this
case, the ultrasonic probe 5 may be displaced
essentially parallel to itself in a direction
transverse to the scan plane of the slice image. This
displacement may be a translational motion in a
rectilinear direction or an oscillation about an axis
which coincides with the origin of the scan plane.</p>
    <p num="0096">The probes or transducers may traditionally be 
displaced manually, or on slides, carriages or movable
supports either manually or by motor-driven actuators.
The displacement of probes 5 is generally detected with
various methods, to be used either separately and
alternately or in any combination.</p>
    <p num="0097">Referring to Figs. 9 to 11, a few arrangements are
shown of the integrated apparatus of the invention.
These arrangements are particularly advantageous with
reference to apparatuses which integrate dedicated
Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging devices, but may be
obviously easily implemented with appropriate obvious
modifications, to so-called total body or other similar
apparatuses.</p>
    <p num="0098">With reference to Figs. 9 and 10, as is known, the
low intensity of the transmitted MRI signals requires
the receiving coil 14 to have such a size as to be as
close as possible to the body part C under examination.
The receiving coil 14 has an outer case or carter 114
for covering and finishing the magnetic structure 14,
which is made of a material that does not interfere
with MRI, generally plastic.</p>
    <p num="0099">In this case, the receiving coil 14 is
advantageously arranged to be open on at least one
side, and is particularly made in the form of a sector
of a cylindrical shell or the like, to allow the
access, from said open side, of the ultrasonic probe 6
which, in the illustrated embodiment is of the type in
which scanning is performed by mechanical displacement
thereof along the anatomic part of the body C under
examination. To this end, the ultrasonic probe 6 is 
provided with at least one pair of carriages 18
disposed at opposite ends of two support elements or
arms 19 which are in turn disposed at opposite ends of
the ultrasonic probe 6. The carriages are slidably
engaged in a corresponding pair of guides 20 each
disposed on one of the two delimiting edges of the
opening of the part 114 for covering the receiving coil
14 and are oriented parallel to the axis of the
receiving coil 14. Obviously, the opposite arrangement
may be also provided, i.e. with the sliding carriages
18 being disposed on the edges of the opening, and the
guides 20 being provided at the ends of the arms 19.
Different slideable support means may be also provided.
Particularly, besides the carriages 18 and the guides
20, the arms may be provided with an additional guide
22 for the slides 23 associated to the body of the
probe 6 or to a support whereon the probe 6 may be
secured. The guides 22 are oriented perpendicular to
the axis of the receiving coil 14 and allow to bring
the ultrasonic probe to contact with the region of the
body C to be examined. Furthermore, the slides 23 may
be attached to the probe 6 or to a support (not shown)
in such a manner as to be able to rotate about an axis
perpendicular to the sliding direction thereof, and to
the sliding direction of the arms 19 along the guides
20.</p>
    <p num="0100">Various means 24, 25 may be further provided to
univocally define the mutual position between the
ultrasonic probe 6, the part of the body C under
examination and the receiving coil 14. Particularly, 
one or more light emitting elements may be fitted on
the receiving coil, whose incident beam on the body
surface has a light cone which indicates at least
roughly the imaging area. These means may be of any
type, i.e. may consist of a conventional light source
associated to appropriately calibrated optical
instruments or coherent light beams, such as laser
beams having a harmless frequency or the like. The
position and the displacements of the ultrasonic probe
6 may be read in several different manners, e.g. by
means of encoders for detecting the angles of rotation
and the number of revolutions completed by the driving
motors, as known per se. Other means and methods, as
known per se, are applicable, such as the combination
of means for reading the resistance between conductors
associated to the carriages 18 and to their respective
guides 20, or code reading means associated to the
guides 20 for reading codes disposed along the means 19
for supporting the probe 6, or vice versa there being
provided the possibility to use either analog or
digital optical means or electronic or
electromechanical means.</p>
    <p num="0101">In order to prevent any interference with the
magnetic structure of the Nuclear Magnetic Resonance
imaging device, said electric or optoelectronic tracer
means may be enabled or disabled in a synchronized
manner with the enabling and disabling of the
ultrasound imaging device. Obviously, these tracer
means may be also associated to the rotary support of
the probe 6 (not shown), whereby they indicate the 
angular position of the probe. Obviously, the means for
supporting the probe 6 may also be of a different type,
and allow additional degrees of freedom in probe
displacement.</p>
    <p num="0102">According to the variant as shown in Fig. 11, one
or more marking elements 26 may be provided on the body
part C under examination and/or on the probe 6, which
consist, for instance, of one or more bubbles of a
liquid adapted to provide a typical Nuclear Magnetic
Resonance response, for instance the so-called doped
water, i.e. water mixed with other materials, such as
oil.</p>
    <p num="0103">Water bubbles generate clearly visible and easily
recognizable spots in a Nuclear Magnetic Resonance
image. This also allows to univocally recognize,
possibly with the help of an image processing
procedure, the position of the ultrasonic probe,
regardless of whether it is simply hand held by the
user, or supported by a structure as shown in Fig. 9.
In this case, the arms 19 for slidably supporting the
ultrasonic probe 6 have such a configuration that the
ultrasonic probe 6 is positioned inside the cavity
defined by the receiving magnet 14. It is apparent that
the position of the probe 6 may be easily located by
imaging the marking elements 26. To this end, the
probe 6 need not be positioned in an area of the static
magnetic field having such homogeneity conditions as to
certainly provide diagnostically usable images, as
markings are well visible even in poorer imaging
accuracy conditions. </p>
    <p num="0104">The marking elements may be arranged to not only
indicate position, but even orientation of the
ultrasonic probe 6, for instance they may have an
elongated shape or consist of at least two bubbles or a
row of bubbles aligned in a predetermined direction.
Hence, the orientation of the alignment axis in the
image obtained by Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging
indicates the orientation of the scan plane of the
ultrasonic probe 6.</p>
    <p num="0105">An additional variant provides the use of magnetic
means for marking and detecting the probe 6. To this
end, the probe may be provided with elements 26
consisting of magnetic dipoles or Hall probes or
combinations thereof, which interfere with a magnetic
field. This method is already known to be used in
combination with ultrasound imaging apparatuses.
Advantageously, in the integrated apparatus of the
invention, the magnetic structure of the ultrasound
imaging device may be utilized as an element of the
magnetic device for detecting the position of the
ultrasonic probe 6 in combination with an appropriate
processing electronics, which may be alternately
connected to the circuits for controlling and
processing Nuclear Magnetic Resonance signals to the
magnetic structure when Nuclear Magnetic Resonance
imaging is disabled.</p>
    <p num="0106">These electronic circuits for detecting the
position of the ultrasonic probe 6, as well as those
associated to the different methods indicated above may
be at least partly or wholly housed in the case of the 
magnetic structure or in the cabinet 202.</p>
    <p num="0107">Referring now to Figs. 6, 13 and 14, a magnetic
structure may be provided which is displaced relative
to the patient table, hence to the body under
examination or the part thereof C to a predetermined
extent an in predetermined directions, the direction
and displacement modulus being detected in the same
manner as provided for the ultrasonic probe 6.</p>
    <p num="0108">In this case, the magnetic structure 1 or the
patient table 2, or both may be displaced relative to
each other.</p>
    <p num="0109">In the embodiment of Figs. 6 and 14, there is
provided at least one guide 34 on which the table 2
and/or the magnetic structure 1 and/or both are mounted
to be displaced on slides or carriages.</p>
    <p num="0110">Furthermore, the table 2 and/or the magnetic
structure 1 and/or both may be arranged to rotate at
least about a vertical axis.</p>
    <p num="0111">The position locating means may be manufactured in
the same manner as described for the ultrasonic probe 6
provided they are compatible with the magnetic
structure 1.</p>
    <p num="0112">With reference to Figs. 13 and 14, two different
arrangements are schematically shown, which are used to
allow the magnetic structure 1 to be displaced relative
to the body under examination, hence to the table 2, or
to allow the table 2, hence the body under examination
to be displaced relative to the magnetic structure 1,
with respect to three spatial directions.</p>
    <p num="0113">In this case the body under examination, the part 
thereof, the limb or the like is to be held in position
so as to allow the displacement of the magnetic
structure and the receiving coil with no mechanical
interference with the magnetic structure and especially
with the receiving coil. To this end, the magnetic
structure 1, and/or the receiving coil 14 are
associated to a support for the body, for the part
thereof, for the limb or the like, which is
displaceable relative to said structure and to said
receiving coil. Fig. 13 is a schematic view of an
embodiment of said support means, generally denoted by
the numeral 35. In this case, the means for relative
displacement of the magnetic structure 1 and of the
body under examination are adapted to allow motion
along orthogonal axes. Hence, even the movable support
means are arranged to ensure displacement with respect
to the magnetic structure along the same three
orthogonal axes.</p>
    <p num="0114">These support means may include a bearing member
36, such as a cradle, a surface, or the like which
passes through the receiving coil 14 and slides at the
outside ends of the magnetic structure on slides 36
mounted on guides 38 which are oriented parallel to the
axis of the receiving coil, which is in turn parallel
to a displacement axis. The guides 38 are supported on
carriages 39, which are designed to slide on guides 40
orthogonal to the former and supported by a stationary
member 101 of the case for the magnetic structure 1,
which cannot be moved relative to the magnetic
structure 1. The guide 40 is borne by guides 41, 
orthogonal to the guide 40 itself and to the guide 38
and is slidably engaged in the carriages 39. Hence, the
body part under examination is perfectly still, whereas
the magnetic structure moves together with the
receiving coil 14.</p>
    <p num="0115">According to an improvement, in order to allow at
least a rough imaging of the region of the body under
examination being imaged from time to time, one or more
light emitting elements may be mounted on the receiving
coil and/or on the magnetic structure, the cone of
light of the beam incident on the body surface
indicating the imaging portion. These means may be of
any type, i.e. a conventional light source associated
to appropriately calibrated optical instruments or
coherent light beams, such as laser beams having a
harmless frequency or the like. The Figure shows these
light pointing means mounted on the receiving coil 14
and generally denoted by the reference number 42.</p>
    <p num="0116">Obviously, some of the displacements in at least
one of the directions or all of them may be performed
by the table. In this case, the table is mounted on
guides, like the magnetic structure. The embodiment of
Fig. 14 schematically shows a variant, in which the
base 202 of the table 2 has a vertical guide 302 and is
mounted on orthogonal guides 402,, 501, which have a
predetermined starting position with respect to the
magnet structure 1. In this embodiment, the receiving
coil 14 is integrated in the magnetic structure 1.</p>
    <p num="0117">Here, projecting cantilever means 602 are
associated to the table 2 and carry the limb or the 
part of the body into the structure, thereby avoiding
the complex construction of Fig. 13.</p>
    <p num="0118">However, with reference to the embodiment of Fig.
6, the magnetic structure 1 has a very small size and
is mounted on a carriage, whereas one of the poles
thereof forms a portion of the support surface of the
seat table 2. Such a magnet construction is well-known
and forms the subject of a former published patent
application EP 1004269.</p>
    <p num="0119">The use of a construction of the magnetic
structure 1 and of the table 2 as shown in Figure 13 or
14, apparently allows to avoid the provision of
separate means for guiding and displacing the
ultrasonic probe 6 as described with reference to Figs.
9 to 11. In this case, the probe may be fitted in a
stationary position onto the receiving coil 14 or onto
the magnetic structure 1, when the coil is integrated
therein, and the displacement thereof occurs at the
same time as the relative displacement between the
magnetic structure 1 and the table 2. However, in this
case, it might be advantageous to provide support means
which allow to angularly displace the orientation of
the probe 6 and/or to translate it away from or closer
to the surface of the body under examination C.</p>
    <p num="0120">As an alternative to the above mentioned case, the
ultrasonic probe 6 may be separated from the receiving
coil or the magnetic structure, or may be integrated,
i.e. be a permanent part of the magnetic structure, by
being incorporated therein or in the case of the
receiving coil/s. </p>
    <p num="0121">Obviously, when the characteristics as illustrated
and described herein with reference to the different
Figures and variants are not in contrast with each
other, they may be provided in any combination,
regardless of the expressly described and illustrated
embodiments.</p>
    <p num="0122">Figure 12 shows a simplified block diagram of an
example of a circuit for an integrated apparatus of the
invention.</p>
    <p num="0123">The Figure shows the magnetic structure 1, the
patient table 2 and the console 3. The magnetic
structure 1 includes the means for generating the
static magnetic field and the various coils denoted as
50. A circuit 51 for controlling said means 50 and
extracting from the received signals the data to be
transformed into images, may be housed at least partly
or wholly inside the magnetic structure containing case
and/or at least partly or wholly in the structure of
the table 2, particularly in the base block/cabinet
202.</p>
    <p num="0124">The means 52 for controlling the relative position
between the table and the magnetic structure and for
processing the position reading may be disposed outside
or integrated in the case for the magnetic structure
and/or in the structure of the table 2, whereas both
the means for controlling the transducers of the
ultrasonic probe 6 and the means for receiving and
processing the received signals to extract therefrom
the data required for image reconstruction, generally
denoted as 53, are integrated in the structure of the 
table 2 and particularly in the base block.</p>
    <p num="0125">Possibly, the table structure 2 may integrate the
control and dedicated processing circuits signals of
devices for detecting further physiological parameters,
such as ECG, EMG, EGG, and the circuits for
synchronizing the ultrasound imaging and Nuclear
Magnetic Resonance imaging processes with said
parameters, which are shown with a dashed outline and
denoted as 54.</p>
    <p num="0126">The circuits 50, 51, 52, 53, 54 are connected to a
data encoding unit for bidirectional communication with
the console, a so-called bus, which is denoted as 55.</p>
    <p num="0127">The bidirectional bus 55 is controlled by a
microprocessor unit 56 of the console 3 and provides
the image data obtained by the two methods and any
additional parameter to the console 3. This data is
transmitted to an image processing and display unit 57,
hence to a display 58 or to another display device,
such as a printer or the like. Also, the data may be
stored into a mass storage memory, as a hard disk, or
the like or on a floppy disk, or other removable
memories such as a compactflash card, or recorded on a
CD. Memories are denoted as 59. The console also
includes memories 60, 61, 62, in which the software for
controlling the various imaging options for each type
of imaging mode are stored, e.g. for ultrasound imaging
with B-Mode, Harmonic Imaging, Doppler, Color Doppler,
etc., and/or for Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging
with the different possible scan sequences or other
typical adjustments or settings. The memory 62 
represents the software for controlling devices having
diagnostic purposes or for detecting any other
physiological parameters, such as, without limitation,
ECG, EMG, EGG devices.</p>
    <p num="0128">The numeral 63 denotes the interfaces of said
device with the patient.</p>
    <p num="0129">The numeral 64 denotes a memory for programming
therapeutic means or devices that may be used in
combination with ultrasound and/or Nuclear Magnetic
Resonance imaging means, and may use themselves
ultrasounds or other types or radiation or intervention
means, such as catheters, needles, ultrasonic means and
needles, or else.</p>
    <p num="0130">The numeral 65 denotes the ultrasonic probe and/or
the therapeutic application tools. Possibly, as shown
in 65' and 65'', the probe and/or said devices may be
directly connected to the control and processing
circuits contained in the structure of the table 2.</p>
    <p num="0131">The numerals 67 and 68 denote a scanner for
digitizing images or else obtained by separate devices
and additional data entry and/or control and/or display
devices, etc., respectively.</p>
    <p num="0132">Obviously, what has been described and illustrated
with reference to Fig. 12 shall be intended without
limitation. In fact, a global X-ray imaging or
tomographic imaging device may be selected as an
additional integrated device.</p>
    <p num="0133">The structure of the integrated apparatus as
described above allows to implement various imaging
processes. First, all typical imaging modes of 
ultrasound and Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging
apparatuses may be executed.</p>
    <p num="0134">Further, the information obtained with the two
imaging modes may be combined for comparison thereof,
to achieve a safer recognition of irregular or
pathological situations.</p>
    <p num="0135">The two ultrasound and Nuclear Magnetic Resonance
images may be also combined in such a manner as to
reconstruct a more detailed image by mutually
integrating the characteristics resulting from the two
images.</p>
    <p num="0136">The integrated apparatus in combination with the
means for displacing the ultrasonic probe and the
magnet relative to the region under examination allows
to obtain tomographic and three-dimensional images of
the body under examination or a part thereof, and hence
to reconstruct a three-dimensional image based on the
data obtained through the two different modes either by
comparison or by integration.</p>
    <p num="0137">Thanks to this method, the apparatus of the
invention allows to perform a three-dimensional scan in
a diversified manner for the two ultrasound and Nuclear
Magnetic Resonance imaging types. Hence, for instance,
according to a first variant, a three-dimensional
tomographic scan may be executed, i.e. through several
adjacent slice images of the body under examination or
a part thereof, in which the distance between the
individual slice images is different for the two
imaging modes. Especially, the slice images may be
closer to each other for the imaging mode which has 
shorter imaging times, whereas for the imaging mode
with longer imaging times, the slice images are
selected at a greater distance from each other.</p>
    <p num="0138">Therefore, image reconstruction may integrate the
data of an imaging method with that of the other method
to perform interpolation reconstruction between two
actually obtained adjacent slice images.</p>
    <p num="0139">Within a single region of the body under
examination in which imaging is to be performed in said
two modes, it is also possible to use the more rapid
imaging method in the lower interest peripheral areas
of said region under examination and to use both
imaging methods or only the other slower imaging method
in the higher interest area of the region under
examination.</p>
    <p num="0140">In this case, the more rapid imaging method may be
used to verify in real time that the region of interest
has been reached so that the other imaging method may
be enabled only in this condition, in combination with
the other method or alone.</p>
    <p num="0141">It shall be noted that, as mentioned in the
previous description, in order to prevent any
interference between the two imaging methods, and any
resulting artifacts, the two methods may be enabled
alternately in successive time intervals.</p>
    <p num="0142">Imaging with the two methods also allows to locate
the univocal space positions of the slice images
obtained by each of the methods, with reference to an
origin defined univocally at the beginning of the
imaging session. </p>
    <p num="0143">With reference to another variant of the method,
the latter may include the steps of changing in real
time, and during the imaging session, the imaging
parameters according to the two methods, in such a
manner as to change image quality characteristics, such
as definition, field of view, signal-to-noise ratio,
contrast.</p>
    <p num="0144">In order to achieve this, the method provides that
imaging parameters or imaging sequence settings are
stored in the memories designed to contain the software
for controlling the two imaging devices, which settings
cause variations of said image quality characteristics,
there being provided setting selectors which
specifically indicate the modified image quality
characteristics, rather than parameters or sequences.</p>
    <p num="0145">Further, Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging
methods may be implemented in combination with
ultrasound imaging methods which have relatively short
imaging times for a rough scan adapted to provide real-time
displayable images for both imaging methods.</p>
    <p num="0146">In this case, it is possible to reduce the
definition and/or the field of view and/or the contrast
and the signal-to-noise characteristics of the
resulting image. Regarding the generation of artifacts
caused by the use of less accurate scan modes, to the
advantage of speed, it is initially possible to perform
a comparative analysis between the images of the same
slice obtained through the two methods to check if a
certain structure represented in the image may or may
not be an artifact. In this manner, the identification 
of artifacts is assured without affecting imaging
speed.</p>
    <p num="0147">According to a further improvement of the method,
the combined imaging by the two imaging methods may be
performed in combination with the injection of contrast
agents in the region under examination.</p>
    <p num="0148">It is possible to inject either contrast agents
for ultrasounds (typically microbubbles) or contrast
agents for Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (typically
paramagnetic molecules). These contrast agents may be
injected separately and alternately, or together,
either separately or in the form of a mixture.</p>
    <p num="0149">Advantageously, the two types of contrast agents
may be combined together by using a single carrier for
the two. As an alternative, the carrier for the one may
have the contrast agent characteristics required for
the other imaging mode. Particularly, the micro-bubble
carrier may have the paramagnetic characteristics
required for Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging
contrast agents.</p>
    <p num="0150">Nuclear Magnetic Resonance contrast agents may be
also arranged to be contained inside micro-bubbles.</p>
    <p num="0151">When the two contrast agents are used in
combination, the advantage is obtained that one of the
two imaging methods, i.e. the more rapid method,
adapted to provide real-time images may be used to
identify with a higher accuracy the instant in which
the region under examination is reached by the
contrast agents for the other generally slower imaging
method. Typically, Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging 
requires longer times to display the resulting image,
whereby ultrasound imaging allows to monitor the
perfusion condition of the region under examination,
and prevents Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging of said
region from occurring when the specific contrast agents
are still not or no longer present in the region under
examination. These early or late imaging situations may
jeopardize the examination and require the repetition
thereof, while involving a repeated invasive operation
on the patient, as well as time loss and power and
material consumption.</p>
    <p num="0152">In combination with or as an alternative to said
contrast agents, substances may be used that are
adapted to determine a higher oxygen request in the
region under examination, hence an increase of blood
flow.</p>
    <p num="0153">Imaging by the two methods may be synchronized
with the heart cycle of the patient, by providing the
steps of detecting the electrocardiogram of the patient
and of defining the curve thereof, wherewith imaging
with one of the two imaging methods or with both
imaging methods is synchronized. Synchronization
with the heart cycle may be also adjusted in such a
manner that one of the two imaging types is
synchronized with a predetermined phase of the heart
cycle and the other with another phase.</p>
    <p num="0154">By synchronizing imaging with the heart cycle
according to the two different imaging methods the two
imaging types may be executed in identical
physiological conditions. This may be very useful when 
imaging is aimed at examining spontaneous flows, such
as the blood flow, or the like.</p>
    <p num="0155">The option to also provide other means for imaging
or detecting other physiological parameters, to be
integrated in the same apparatus allows to relate
images of the region under examination with other types
of examinations and to possibly establish relations
between the results thereof and the resulting images.
This may be useful to identify any possible artifact,
as well as any possible connection between the obtained
images and the detected values for the different
physiological parameters or other types of images.</p>
    <p num="0156">As an additional image type, an X-ray imaging
device may be integrated with the ultrasound and
Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging devices. In this
case, the XR device is also enabled in different
periods from those of the other two imaging devices and
the obtained, digitized and stored images may be used
to integrate, correct or evaluate the information
obtained by the other two imaging methods.</p>
    <p num="0157">Obviously, the invention is not limited to what
has been described and illustrated herein, but may be
greatly varied. Variations may particularly relate to
the combination of not expressly mentioned imaging
techniques or with not expressly mentioned means for
detecting physiological parameters, as well as to the
combination with other ultrasound and/or Nuclear
Magnetic Resonance imaging signal detection and
processing. The invention may be also greatly varied
and modified as regards construction. All the above 
without departure from the inventive teaching disclosed
above and claimed below.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A combined apparatus for imaging the inner part
of a body, particularly for diagnostic imaging thereof,
comprising at least means (1, 6, 14) for imaging and
displaying images according to at least two types of
beams, waves or signals transmitted toward a body or a
part thereof (C) to be examined, characterized in that
it comprises a Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (1) imaging
and displaying device and an ultrasound imaging and
displaying device (6) in an integrated configuration
within the same apparatus.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in claim 1,
characterized in that it includes means 1, 6)for
generating at least one type of waves or beams which
are transmitted toward the body (C) or the part thereof
to be internally imaged and means (14, 6) for receiving
said type of waves or beams transmitted by the body
under examination or by the part thereof or deriving
from the excitation of said part or body under
examination, from the reflection and/or transmission
and/or modification of waves, of the beams transmitted
against said body under examination or the part
thereof, there being provided means for univocally
relating the information of the waves or beams
retransmitted by the body under examination or the part
thereof, to a space position of an image unit element
(so-called pixel or voxel) and means for reconstructing
the image from the array of pixels or voxels obtained
thereby, which turn the information of the received
waves or beams into brightness and/or color
characteristics of the individual pixels of the image
both for Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging and for
ultrasound imaging.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in claims 1 or 2,
characterized in that it includes at a patient
supporting element (2), such as a patient chair, a
table/chair, a table, or the like, at least one control
and display console (3), shared by the different
imaging devices integrated therein and a case of the
magnetic structure while the said such patient
supporting element (2) and/or the case of the console
(3) and/or the case of the magnetic structure (1)
include chambers for housing completely or at least
partly the electronic control, processing and data
storage circuits.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in one or more of the
preceding claims, characterized in that the electronic
circuits of the nuclear magnetic resonance imaging
devices (1) and of the ultrasound imaging device are
divided into separate blocks, at least one block (50,
51, 52, 53, 54, 63, 65) being made of the circuits for
controlling, receiving and processing the beams, waves
or signals transmitted to the body under examination
and the signals coming from the body under examination,
i.e. at least one block of circuits specifically
designed to control and process the signals according
to a particular imaging type, the other block (56, 57,
58, 59, 60, 61, 62, 64, 67, 68) of circuits being made
of circuits for entering commands, generating and
processing images, and for displaying and/or storing
data, said circuit blocks including transmitting and
receiving circuits which encode the signals whereby the
two blocks communicate in an identical and compatible
manner (55).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in claim 4,
characterized in that it comprises a common console (3)
including common circuits (56, 57, 58, 59, 60, 61, 26,
64, 67, 68) for generating and/or processing and/or
displaying and/or storing the images and/or
physiological parameters obtained for each imaging type
integrated therein or provided in combination, the
console being provided with means for entering specific
commands for each type of imaging devices, which means
may be dedicated to the specific imaging device and/or
shared by all imaging devices.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in one or more of the
preceding claims, characterized in that it comprises at
least three imaging devices, each for a different
imaging method, and particularly for ultrasound,
Nuclear Magnetic Resonance, and X-Ray imaging.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in one or more of the
preceding claims, characterized in that it includes at
least one additional type of device for detecting and
measuring physiological parameters, for instance
alternatively or in combination, a device for detecting
an ECG and/or EGG and/or EMG electrocardiogram.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in one or more of the
preceding claims, characterized in that it has a
circuit for synchronizing the enabling/disabling
functions for the different imaging devices which may
be controlled by the console.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in claim 8,
characterized in that the synchronization circuit
enables the individual imaging devices in an alternate
manner and for intervals of a predetermined duration.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in claim 8 or 9,
characterized in that the circuit for synchronizing the
enabling/disabling functions for the imaging devices is
connected to the output of at least one of the devices
for detecting physiological parameters and particularly
to an electrocardiograph, to control the
enabling/disabling functions for the different imaging
devices or of devices for detecting any other
physiological parameters in such a manner as to
synchronize them with certain values or curves of at
least one of the physiological parameters, particularly
with one or more predetermined phases of the heart
cycle.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in one or more of the
preceding claims, characterized in that it includes at
least one Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging device (1)
and at least one ultrasound imaging device, the
ultrasound imaging device being provided with a probe
(6) for transmitting and receiving ultrasonic waves,
and there being provided a magnetic structure (101, 14)
adapted to also receive the ultrasonic probe, (6)
within or at the edges of the cavity for receiving the
body under examination or a part thereof (C), whereas
means (24, 25, 26) for univocally locating the position
and/or the orientation of the ultrasonic probe (6)
relative to the body or the part thereof under
examination (C) are also provided.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in claim 11,
characterized in that the means (26) for univocally
locating the position and/or orientation of the
ultrasonic probe (6) consist of marking elements
provided on the probe itself, which are univocally
visible in the Nuclear Magnetic Resonance image.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in claim 12,
characterized in that the probe (6) has a plurality of
marking elements (26), aligned at least in pairs in one
of three orthogonal spatial directions.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in claim 12 or 13,
characterized in that the marking elements (26) have an
elongated shape with the longitudinal axis being
aligned in at least one of three orthogonal spatial
directions.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in one or more of the
preceding claims, characterized in that the means for
locating the position and/or orientation of the
ultrasonic probe consist of magnetized elements and/or
magnetic sensors, such as Hall probes or the like,
which are secured or associated to the ultrasonic probe
(6) and to the magnetic structure of the Nuclear
Magnetic Resonance imaging device (1).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in one or more of the
preceding claims, characterized in that the magnetic
structure includes a receiving coil (14) associated
thereto and said magnetic structure or receiving coil
(14) has combinations of guides or slides (18, 19, 20,
21) for displacing the ultrasonic probe (6) in at least
one direction, preferably two directions, which are
associated to tracer means (22, 23) for reading the
position along the directions of the ultrasonic probe
(6).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in claim 16,
characterized in that the tracer means (22, 23) consist
of optoelectronic position reading means, of bar codes
readers for indicating the position along a translation
or displacement path and/or of electronic or electrical
position reading means.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="18">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in one or more of the
preceding claims, characterized in that the magnetic
structure (1) may be displaced in at least one
direction relative to the body under examination or a
part thereof (C), there being provided means (42) for
locating the relative position between the magnetic
structure (1) and the body under examination (C).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="19">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in claim 18,
characterized in that the magnetic structure (1) may be
displaced relative to the table, chair or table/chair
(2) or vice versa, and is mounted on combinations of
guides and carriages (34, 402) which are linked to the
table, chair or table/chair (2).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="20">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in claim 19,
characterized in that tracer means for locating the
relative position and/or orientation between the table
(2), chair or table/chair and the magnetic structure
(1) are associated to the combination of guides or
carriages (34, 402) for displacing the magnetic
structure (1) and/or the table, chair or table/chair
(2).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="21">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in one or more of the
preceding claims, characterized in that the magnetic
structure (1) and/or the table, chair or table/chair
(2) may be freely displaced relative to each other,
there being provided tracer or sensor means, for
instance relative position detecting proximity sensors.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="22">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in claim 21,
characterized in that, as an alternative to the tracer
means or in combination therewith, there may be
provided means for locating the relative position
between the magnetic structure (1) and the body under
examination or a part thereof (C) which are removable
and may be positioned on said body under examination or
a part thereof.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="23">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in one or more of the
preceding claims, characterized in that the magnetic
structure (1) and/or the receiving coil (14) have means
(35, 36, 37, 38, 39, 40, 41) for supporting the body
under examination or a part thereof (C), which may be
displaced relative to said magnetic structure (1)
and/or to the receiving coil (14).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="24">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in one or more of the
preceding claims, characterized in that the receiving
coil (14) has an annular or substantially cylindrical
shape, the ultrasonic probe (6) being housed in the
case thereof, and said receiving coil (14) being
displaceable with the magnetic structure (1) in at
least one direction relative to the body under
examination or a part thereof (C).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="25">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in one or more of the
preceding claims, characterized in that the magnetic
structure (1) is dedicated and has a very small size as
compared with the chair, table, or table/chair (2), a
portion of the patient supporting surface of said
chair, table, or table/chair (2) being formed by at
least a portion of said magnetic structure (1, 101).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="26">
      <claim-text>An imaging method which uses the integrated
apparatus as claimed in one or more of the preceding
claims, characterized in that it includes alternate
imaging according to at least two imaging types in
successive intervals.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="27">
      <claim-text>A method as claimed in claim 26, characterized
in that the two imaging types are ultrasound imaging
and Nuclear Magnetic Resonance imaging.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="28">
      <claim-text>A method as claimed in claim 26 or 27,
characterized in that it includes dedicated processing
of the two image types, reconstruction of a set of
image data, conversion of said image data into data
encoded according to a predetermined communication
protocol, transmission of said image data to an image
processing and displaying station which is shared or
essentially shared by the two different imaging types,
and which processes and displays the images obtained by
said two imaging types, in adjacent, subsequent,
overlaid and/or combined positions, thereby
constructing a single image from the information of
said two images obtained by the two different imaging
types.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="29">
      <claim-text>A method as claimed in one or more of the
preceding claims 26 to 28, characterized in that it
provides successive imaging of slices of the body under
examination or a part thereof, univocal location of the
position and orientation in space for each slice image
and reconstruction of a three-dimensional image formed
by the individual slice images.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="30">
      <claim-text>A method as claimed in one or more of the
preceding claims 26 to 29, characterized in that it
provides successive imaging of the body under
examination or a part thereof by the at least two
imaging types and reconstruction of two three-dimensional
images by said two imaging types and/or
display of the two images in an overlaid position
and/or combination of the two three-dimensional images
into a common three-dimensional image formed by the
information of both three-dimensional images obtained
by the two imaging types.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="31">
      <claim-text>A method as claimed in one or more of the
preceding claims 26 to 30, characterized in that it
provides that the slice images for the two imaging
types are obtained along coincident slice planes of the
body under examination or a part thereof.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="32">
      <claim-text>A method as claimed in one or more of the
preceding claims 26 to 31, characterized in that it
provides that the slice images for the two imaging
types are obtained along non-coincident slice planes of
the body under examination or a part thereof.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="33">
      <claim-text>A method as claimed in one or more of the
preceding claims 26 to 32, characterized in that it
provides the injection of contrast agents for
ultrasound images, and ultrasound imaging thereof.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="34">
      <claim-text>A method as claimed in one or more of the
preceding claims 26 to 33 characterized in that it
provides the injection of contrast agents for Nuclear
Magnetic Resonance images, and imaging thereof.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="35">
      <claim-text>A method as claimed in one or more of the
preceding claims 26 to 34, characterized in that it
provides the injection of contrast agents for
ultrasound images and for Nuclear Magnetic Resonance
images, whereas the moment in which the Nuclear
Magnetic Resonance contrast agents reach the region of
interest for imaging purposes is determined by
detecting the moment in which the region of interest is
reached by ultrasound imaging of ultrasound contrast
agents, or vice versa.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="36">
      <claim-text>A method as claimed in one or more of the
preceding claims 26 to 35, characterized in that it
provides a variation of the imaging parameters for one
and/or for the other of the two imaging types, for a
higher or lower image quality or longer or shorter
imaging times based on the coincidence of an image
plane with regions of higher or lower interest for the
one and/or the other imaging type.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
