<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1225285-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1225285" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="9907328" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020724">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1225285-A2" status="new" fvid="23523984">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1225285</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20020724</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02250469-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02250469</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020123</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="GB-0101710-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>GB</country>
          <doc-number>0101710</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010123</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">E04D  11/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">E04D  11/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">E04D  13/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">E04D  13/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">E04D  13/12        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">E04D  13/12        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H02G   3/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H02G   3/04        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H02G   9/00        20060101C I20070602RMGB        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H02G   9/04        20060101A I20070602RMGB        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">E04D  11/00</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">E04D  13/00</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">E04D  13/12</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H02G   3/04E</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H02G   3/26C</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verbesserungen an oder in Bezug auf Anlagen</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Improvements in or relating to installations</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Améliorations concernant des installations</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SWINTEX</name>
            <address>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SWINTEX LIMITED</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>SWINTEX LIMITED</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Derby Works Manchester Road</street>
              <city>Bury Lancashire BL9 9NX</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HOUGHTON HARRY VINCENT</name>
            <address>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HOUGHTON, HARRY VINCENT</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>HOUGHTON, HARRY VINCENT</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>56 Shorefield Mount, Egerton</street>
              <city>Bolton BL7 9EW</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Wilson Gunn M'Caw</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>41-51 Royal Exchange, Cross Street</street>
              <city>Manchester M2 7BD</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>An article, particularly a cable tray 1, for installation on a flat roof 12
of a building. The article has an underside 10 and a side wall 11 extending
upwards from the underside. A first part of a piece of fabric 9 extends over
at least a part of the underside of the article and a second part of the piece
of fabric extends over at least part of the side wall of the article. The fabric
acts as a cushion reducing the risk of damage to a surface on which an
article is installed. The fabric also acts as a wick operative to draw
moisture away from between an article and a surface on which it is
installed. The fabric may comprise hydrophilic material, such as polyester,
and may be non-woven. The article may be moulded and the fabric
incorporated into the article during moulding.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="162" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="92"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to articles for installation on a flat roof
of a building, a method of installing an article on a surface, particularly but
not exclusively a flat roof of a building, and to such installations.</p>
    <p num="0002">Flat roofed buildings typically comprise a waterproof membrane.
These membranes are expensive and typically expected to last for at least
twenty years.</p>
    <p num="0003">It is often desirable for articles to be installed on a flat roof of a
building, such as cable trays for supporting cables running over a flat roof to
a telecommunications antenna. Traditional lightweight cable trays are
usually installed on a flat roof by bolting them to concrete flag stones laid
loose on the roof. Heavier moulded cable trays, such as those described in
the applicant's UK patent application nos. 0024988.8 and 0024990.4 which
include means for receiving ballast, are usually laid directly onto a flat roof.</p>
    <p num="0004">A problem with cable tray and other installations on flat roofs is that
they can lead to premature failure of the roof membrane. It has been found
that there are two main reasons for this.</p>
    <p num="0005">Firstly, placing an object onto a flat roof can puncture the roof
membrane, especially if the object has well defined edges or corners and/or
if the object is walked upon. Cable tray installations may serve as
walkways.</p>
    <p num="0006">Secondly, water can become trapped between an article placed on a 
flat roof and the roof. This can cause water to remain in contact with the
roof beneath the article for much longer periods than for exposed areas of
the roof. Prolonged presence of water is favourable to biological growth
activity which is generally prejudicial to the life expectancy of a roof
membrane. Weakening of a roof membrane caused by biological growth
activity also increases the risk of the membrane being punctured.</p>
    <p num="0007">It is an object of the present invention to overcome, or at least
reduce, these problems.</p>
    <p num="0008">According to a first aspect of the present invention there is provided
an article for installation on a flat roof of a building, the article comprising
an underside on which it is intended to be supported and a side wall
extending at an angle to the underside wherein a first part of a piece of
fabric extends over at least part of the underside of the article and a second
part of the piece of fabric extends over at least part of the side wall of the
article.</p>
    <p num="0009">According to a second aspect of the present invention there is
provided a method of installing an article on a surface comprising the steps
of interposing a first part of a piece of fabric between the article and the
surface so that a second part of the piece of fabric extends out from
between the article and the surface, and supporting the second part of the
piece of fabric so that it extends away from the surface.</p>
    <p num="0010">According to a third aspect of the present invention there is provided 
an installation comprising an article on a surface wherein a first part of a
piece of fabric extends between the article and the surface and a second
part of the piece of fabric extends out from between the article and the
surface and away from the surface.</p>
    <p num="0011">Provision of the fabric confers two major benefits. The fabric acts as
a cushion reducing the risk of damage to a surface on which an article is
installed. The fabric also acts as a wick operative to draw moisture away
from between an article and a surface. Provision of a part of the fabric
extending away from the surface enhances the wicking and drying functions
of the fabric by providing an increased area from which moisture can
evaporate and reducing the risk of the entire piece of fabric being
underwater, for example on a waterlogged roof. Thus the fabric can
enhance the drying rate of a waterlogged roof.</p>
    <p num="0012">Preferably the article is supported on a generally horizontal surface.
The second part of the fabric preferably extends generally upwardly from
the surface, more preferably to at least 10mm and still more preferably to at
least 20mm above the surface.</p>
    <p num="0013">The fabric preferably has good wicking properties and as such
preferably comprises some hydrophilic material. Polyester is hydrophilic and
the fabric preferably comprises some polyester fibres. The fabric is
preferably non-woven, such fabrics generally being cheaper than woven or
knitted fabrics which could, however, equally be used. The fabric 
preferably extends completely over the underside of the article. As the
preferred thickness of fabric to provide adequate cushioning properties may
be greater than required to provide adequate wicking properties the first
part of the piece of fabric may be thicker than the second part.</p>
    <p num="0014">The fabric is preferably fastened to or comprised in the article. This
enables an article and associated fabric to be shipped and installed as a
single item. The fabric may be fastened to the article by an adhesive and/or
by fasteners, for example staples. The fabric could be incorporated into the
article.</p>
    <p num="0015">In a preferred embodiment the article is a moulded article and the
fabric is incorporated into the article during moulding. In one example
articles are moulded from a plastics material, for example recycled partially
plasticised PVC, using the process known as compression moulding. This
involves placing molten or partially molten plastics material into a mould tool
which is subsequently closed by a press. To incorporate the fabric during
moulding the fabric is placed into the mould tool so that it is between
molten plastics material in the tool and the part of the tool wall
corresponding to the part of the outside of the finished moulded article at
which the fabric is to be located. The fabric may be temporarily held in
position in the mould tool by suitable fasteners, for example pins or clips.
The mould tool is then closed in the usual way to form the article. When it
solidifies the plastics material becomes adhered to the fabric so that the 
fabric is incorporated into the outside surface of the moulded article.</p>
    <p num="0016">Where the fabric is incorporated into an article during moulding it is
important that the fabric is chosen so that it exhibits adequate cushioning
and wicking properties after moulding. Where synthetic fibres are
comprised in the fabric it is important that those fibres have a melting point
which is greater than that of the material used to form the article. For
example where the article is formed from plasticised PVC polyester fabrics
are suitable. Plasticised PVC moulding temperatures are typically between
140 and 190°C. The melting point of suitable polyester fabrics is typically
between 225 and 265°C.</p>
    <p num="0017">It has been found that some fabrics improve their wicking
characteristics when moulded into an article. Non-woven polyester fabrics
comprised of fibres of between about 12 and 30 Decitex and particularly
between 15 and 25 Decitex are preferred. The mass of the fabric is
preferably between 150 and 500g/m<sup>2</sup>, more preferably between 250 and
400g/m<sup>2</sup>. The thickness of the fabric is preferably in the range 3.5 to 7mm
prior to moulding. It is preferable that the fabric has undergone carding,
cross-folding of multilayers and needle teasing to achieve a layer bond.</p>
    <p num="0018">Two preferred fabrics are manufactured by Lantor (UK) Limited and
sold under grade references 4906 and 4918. Grade reference 4906 is
particularly preferred.</p>
    <p num="0019">To illustrate the properties of these fabrics comparative tests were 
performed. Three similarly sized strips of each of fabric grades 4906, 4918
and other grades were prepared. One strip of each fabric was moulded
onto a PVC moulding using the compression moulding process described
above and allowed to condition for twenty four hours. All the strips were
then mounted upright so that one end of each strip was simultaneously
immersed to 15mm of its length in water. The two non-moulded strips of
each fabric type were mounted with their machine directions extending in
upright and generally horizontal directions respectively. The moulded strips
were mounted with their machine direction extending in an upright direction.
After thirty seconds the height to which the water had risen on each
moulded strip was noted. After 60 seconds the height to which the water
had risen on each non-moulded strip was also noted. The results of the test
are shown below.
<img id="img-00060001" orientation="unknown" wi="144" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00060001.tif" inline="no" he="60"/></p>
    <p num="0020">The wicking properties of some fabric types considerably improved
following moulding, both in terms of the height reached by the water and
the time taken to reach that height. The considerable and unexpected 
improvement in wicking properties of some of the fabrics makes them
especially suited for use in the manufacture of articles according to the
invention.</p>
    <p num="0021">Further details about some of the tested fabric types are given below:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Fabric Type (Lantor grade reference)</entry><entry align="left">mass/gm<sup>-2</sup></entry><entry align="left">approximate thickness/ mm (before moulding)</entry><entry align="left">fibre Decitex</entry></row><row><entry align="left">4906</entry><entry align="left">329</entry><entry align="center">5.6</entry><entry align="left">17 (polyester)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">4912</entry><entry align="left">400</entry><entry align="center">5.0</entry><entry align="left">70% 5.3 (polyester)</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">30% 4.4 (polyester)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">4918</entry><entry align="left">339</entry><entry align="center">6.5</entry><entry align="left">28 (polyester)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0022">A single layer of fabric of preferred type is usually found sufficient to
significantly reduce the risk of puncture of a roof membrane. Should
additional cushioning be required, however, one or more additional layers of
fabric may be included, preferably only to the underside of the article. Any
additional layers may be bonded to the first layer, for example by placing
pellets of a warm melt polyurethane adhesive between layers of fabric prior
to incorporation of the fabric in the article by moulding.</p>
    <p num="0023">In one embodiment a first layer of hydrophilic fabric extends over the
underside and side wall of an article and a second layer of hydrophobic
fabric extends over the first layer of fabric on the underside of the article
and, optionally, partially over the first layer of fabric on the sidewall.</p>
    <p num="0024">The provision of an outer layer of hydrophobic fabric on the outside
of the underside of the article is thought to reduce penetration of water
between the underside of the article and a surface on which it is supported, 
whilst still permitting a wicking action to occur. Any water that is trapped
under the article will be physically forced through the outer hydrophobic
layer and wicked away by the hydrophilic layer.</p>
    <p num="0025">The hydrophilic layer preferably extends further up the side wall of
the article than the hydrophobic layer.</p>
    <p num="0026">The hydrophobic layer employed may be a much thinner layer than
the hydrophilic layer. Suitable preferred materials for use in this fabric layer
are polypropylene and polyethylene although others can also be used. As
this hydrophilic layer does not come into intimate contact with the molten or
partially molten material of the moulding and is in intimate contact with the
cooled tooling surface, the melt temperature characteristics are not found to
be as critical as those of the hydrophilic layer. The presence of this
hydrophobic layer encourages the movement of water away from intimate
contact with the roof surface and into the layer of the wicking fabric. Any
water present will be repelled in the hydrophobic layer and preferentially
drawn into the hydrophilic layer.</p>
    <p num="0027">Use of a fabric, in accordance with the invention, significantly
reduces biological growth. This may be further reduced by incorporating a
biocide/fungicide in the fabric.</p>
    <p num="0028">Although particularly concerning cable trays the invention applies
equally to other articles, for example cantiledge weights and ballast blocks.</p>
    <p num="0029">Although the invention is particularly concerned with compression 
moulded articles it applies equally to articles made by other techniques.
One example is reactional moulding where a granular material such as
crumbed motor tyres is coated with a polyurethane or similar liquid binder
material prior to introduction into a mould where the binder material is
allowed to set. If a fabric is placed into a mould used for reactional
moulding there is a risk that the fabric will become impregnated with the
binder material, reducing its wicking performance. This problem can be
reduced by providing a barrier layer in the fabric, for example a plastics film
such as a polyethylene or polyester film. The barrier layer is preferably
placed adjacent one side of the fabric and the fabric disposed so that the
barrier layer is directed towards the inside of the mould. A barrier layer
prevents or largely reduces the likelihood of the fabric being impregnated by
the binder material during moulding.</p>
    <p num="0030">A barrier layer may also be similarly used between the fabric layer
and a plasticised PVC moulding if it is desirable to reduce or prevent
possible migration of plasticisers in either direction between roof membrane
materials and the moulding. In such situations polyethylene or more
preferably polyester films between 12.5 and 150.0 microns are effective,
but films between 12.5 and 50.0 microns are most cost effective. Bonding
of the polyester film to the moulding can be assisted using warm melt
adhesive pellets as previously described.</p>
    <p num="0031">In order that the invention may be more clearly understood an 
embodiment thereof will now be described by way of example with
reference to the accompanying drawing, the single figure of which shows a
transverse cross-sectional view through a cable tray installation.</p>
    <p num="0032">Referring to the figure a cable tray 1 is compression moulded from
recycled partially plasticised PVC. The cable tray 1 defines a partially
enclosed region 2 for receiving ballast. Webs 3 extending in the partially
enclosed region 2 define a surface for supporting cables 4. Upper side
walls 5 extend upwardly from the surface for supporting cables and a cover
6 extends between the upper side walls 5. Projections 7 on the underside of
the cover 6 are received into channels 8 running along the top edge of each
upper side wall 5.</p>
    <p num="0033">When the cable tray 1 is moulded a piece of non-woven polyester
fabric 9 of mass approximately 329g/m<sup>2</sup>, thickness approximately 5.0mm
and composed of fibres of approximately 17 Decitex incorporating a biocide
is placed into the region of the mould tool corresponding to the underside
10 and lower side walls 11 of the cable tray. Plastics material is then
placed into the tool, onto the fabric, and the tool closed to form the cable
tray. As the tray is formed the fabric 9 adheres to the plastics material so
that it extends over the outside of the underside 10 and lower side walls 11
of the cable tray 1. The fabric 9 extends about 60mm up the lower side
walls 11 of the cable tray 1.</p>
    <p num="0034">The cable tray 1 is supported on a flat roof 12 of a building. The roof 
12 incorporates a waterproof membrane.</p>
    <p num="0035">The fabric 9 covered underside 10 of the cable tray contacts the
surface of the flat roof 10. The fabric 9 provides some cushioning between
the roof 12 and the remainder of the cable tray 1 and considerably reduces
the risk of the cable tray 1 puncturing the roof membrane compared to a
similar cable tray without fabric.</p>
    <p num="0036">The fabric 9 has good wicking properties. Any water between the
cable tray 1 and the surface of the roof 12 will tend to be absorbed by the
fabric 9 and travel along the fabric 9 extending up the lower side walls 11
of the cable tray 1, from where it can evaporate. This considerably reduces
the risk of water becoming trapped between the cable tray 1 and roof 12
for an extended period compared to a similar cable tray without fabric. This
results in a lower incidence of biological growth activity. As the fabric 9
extends up the lower side walls 11 of the cable tray water can evaporate
from the fabric 9 even when there is standing water on the roof 12,
provided, of course, that this does not exceed the height of the fabric 9
above the roof 12. The fabric extending up the lower side walls tends to be
washed by rain removing accumulated dirt particles from the fabric and
maintaining its wicking properties.</p>
    <p num="0037">The above embodiment is described by way of example only. Many
variations are possible without departing from the invention.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>1. An article for installation on a flat roof of a building, the article
comprising an underside on which it is intended to be supported and
a side wall extending at an angle to the underside wherein a first part
of a piece of fabric extends over at least part of the underside of the
article and a second part of the piece of fabric extends over at least
part of the side wall of the article.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>2. An article as claimed in claim 1, wherein the fabric extends over the
side wall of the article such that when the underside of the article is
supported on a surface the fabric extends at least 10mm above the
surface.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>3. An article as claimed in either claim 1 or 2, wherein the fabric
comprises some hydrophilic material.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>4. An article as claimed in claim 3, wherein the fabric comprises some
polyester fibres.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>5. An article as claimed in any preceding claim, wherein the fabric is
non-woven.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>6. An article as claimed in any preceding claim, wherein the fabric
extends completely over the underside of the article.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>7. An article as claimed in any preceding claim, wherein the fabric is
fastened to or comprised in-the article.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>8. An article as claimed in any preceding claim, wherein the article is a
moulded article and the fabric is at least partially incorporated into, or
attached to, the article during moulding.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>9. An article as claimed in claim 8, wherein the fabric is selected so that
its wicking properties improve after being incorporated into, or
attached to, the article.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>10. An article as claimed in either claim 8 or 9 moulded from a plastics
material.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>11. An article as claimed in any of claims 8 to 10. wherein any synthetic
fibres comprised in the fabric have a melting point which is greater
than that of the material used to form the article.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>12. An article as claimed in any of claims 8 to 11, wherein the fabric is
non-woven and comprises fibres of between 12 and 30 Decitex.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>13. An article as claimed any of claims 8 to 12, wherein the thickness of
the fabric is in the range 3.5 to 7mm prior to moulding.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>14. An article as claimed in any preceding claim, wherein the mass of the
fabric is between 150 and 500g/m2.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>15. An article as claimed in any preceding claim, wherein a first layer of
hydrophilic fabric extends over the underside and side wall of the
article and a second layer of hydrophobic fabric extends over the first
layer of fabric on the underside of the article.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>16. An article as claimed in any preceding claim, wherein the fabric
includes a biocide and/or fungicide.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>17. An article as claimed in any preceding claim, wherein the article is a
cable tray.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="18">
      <claim-text>18. A method of installing an article on a surface comprising the steps
of interposing a first part of a piece of fabric between the article and
the surface so that a second part of the piece of fabric extends out
from between the article and the surface, and supporting the second
part of the piece of fabric so that it extends away from the surface.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="19">
      <claim-text>19. A method as claimed in claim 18, wherein the second part of the
fabric is supported so that it extends generally upwardly at least
10mm from the surface.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="20">
      <claim-text>20. A method as claimed in either claim 18 or 19, wherein the fabric
comprises some hydrophilic material.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="21">
      <claim-text>21. A method as claimed in claim 20, wherein the fabric comprises some
polyester fibres.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="22">
      <claim-text>22. A method as claimed in any of claims 18 to 21, wherein the fabric is
non-woven.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="23">
      <claim-text>22. A method as claimed in any of claims 18 to 22, wherein the fabric is
fastened to or comprised in the article.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="24">
      <claim-text>24. A method as claimed in any of claims 18 to 23, wherein the fabric is
comprised of fibres of between 12 and 30 Decitex.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="25">
      <claim-text>25. A method as claimed in any of claims 1 to 24 comprising the steps of
moulding the article and at least partially incorporating the fabric into,
or attaching the fabric to, the article during moulding.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="26">
      <claim-text>26. A method as claimed in claim 25, wherein the fabric is selected so
that its wicking properties improve after being incorporated into, or
attached to, the article.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="27">
      <claim-text>27. A method as claimed in either claim 25 or 26, wherein the thickness
of the fabric is in the range 3.5 to 7mm prior to moulding.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="28">
      <claim-text>28. An installation comprising an article on a surface wherein a first part
of a piece of fabric extends between the article and the surface and a
second part of the piece of fabric extends out from between the
article and the surface and away from the surface.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="29">
      <claim-text>29. An installation comprising an article as claimed in any of claims 1 to
17 on a surface.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
