<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1244182-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1244182" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="18934378" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020925">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1244182-A1" status="new" fvid="23564833">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1244182</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20020925</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02290627-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02290627</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020312</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001077654-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001077654</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010319</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01R  12/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01R  12/16        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01R  13/00        20060101CLI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01R  13/646       20060101ALI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01R  13/658       20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01R  13/658       20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H01R  23/68D2</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H01R  23/72K</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Elektrischer Verbinder</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Electrical connector</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Connecteur électrique</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>J S T MFG CO LTD</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>J.S.T. MFG. CO., LTD.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>J.S.T. Mfg. Co., Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>4-8 Minamisenba 2-chome, Chuo-ku</street>
              <city>Osaka, 542-0081</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HIROAKI KUKITA</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HIROFUMI YAMAGATA</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HIROAKI, KUKITA</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HIROFUMI, YAMAGATA</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Hiroaki, Kukita, J.S.T. Mfg. Co., Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Toyko Eng. Ctr., 4-4-36, Tarumachi, Kohoku-ku</street>
              <city>Yokohama-shi, Kanagawa, 222-0001</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Hirofumi, Yamagata, J.S.T. Mfg. Co., Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Toyko Eng. Ctr., 4-4-36, Tarumachi, Kohoku-ku</street>
              <city>Yokohama-shi, Kanagawa, 222-0001</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Dronne, Guy</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Cabinet Beau de Loménie, 158, rue de l'Université</street>
              <city>75340 Paris Cedex 07</city>
              <country>FR</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A contact (24) and a conductor plate (26;27) are held in the
housing (21) so that portions of the contact (24) except its end portion
(24a) and the plate (26;27) can be put in a parallel relation to each other.
Also, a contact (34) is held in the housing (31) so that when connectors
(2,3) are fitted to each other, portions of the contact (34) except its end
portion (34a) and the plate (26;27) can be put in a parallel relation with
each other. Further, the end portions (24a,34a) are so shaped that the
distance between the signal line formed by the contacts (24,34) and the
plate (26;27) can be kept substantially uniform. This can provide a
stabilized impedance of the signal line formed by the contacts being
contacted with each other.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="153" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="108"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <b>Background of the Invention</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to an electrical connector for
electrically interconnecting two boards or equivalent.</p>
    <p num="0002">In recent years, with increase in the number of input and output
lines, such as signal lines and electric power lines, to the boards built in
electrical equipment such as computers, multicore electrical connectors
are often used as a board-to-board electrical connector for interconnecting
the two boards. In addition, since fast signals may be included in the
input and output to and from the boards, some of the electrical connectors
take measurements against noises through the use of the transmission
line structure formed by the signal lines and the ground planes.</p>
    <p num="0003">In the electrical connector having a pair of male and female
connectors for instance, the pair of male and female connectors are each
provided with terminals having contacts for signal line and for conductor
plates for ground plane. When the terminals of one connector and the
related terminals of the other connector are fitted to each other, the
contacts of the terminals of the respective connectors are brought into
contact with each other to form the signal lines and also the conductor
plates are brought into contact with each other to form the ground planes.</p>
    <p num="0004">However, this conventional type of electrical connector has a
disadvantage that the distances between the signal lines and the ground
planes undergo drastic changes in the region where the respective
contacts are brought into contact with each other and the respective
conductor plates are brought into contact with each other. If the
distances between the signal lines and the ground planes in the
transmission lines undergo drastic changes, then the impedances of the
transmission lines will not be kept stable, i.e., the impedance
characteristics will be varied by the frequencies. If the impedances of the
transmission lines are not kept stable, then there will arise the problem
that even when the electrical connector is designed to produce a desired 
impedance at a certain frequency, the electrical connector thus designed
will not produce the desired impedance at different frequencies from the
certain frequency and, as a result, losses will increase at the different
frequencies.</p>
    <p num="0005">It is the object of the present invention to provide an electrical
connector that can provide stabilized impedances of transmission lines in
the electrical connector.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>Brief Summary of the Invention</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0006">An electrical connector of the present invention comprises a first
connector having a first contact; and a second connector having a second
contact which is brought into contact with the first contact when the
second connector is fitted to the first connector, wherein a conductor plate,
which extends in a substantially parallel relation to the first contact and
the second contact when the first connector and the second connector are
fitted to each other, is provided in at least either of the first connector and
the second connector; and wherein an end portion of the first contact and
an end portion of the second contact, which are to be contacted with each
other, are so shaped that the distance between the contact portions of the
first and second contacts and the conductor plate can be made
substantially equal to the distance between portions of the first and
second contacts except their contact portions and the conductor plate.</p>
    <p num="0007">According to the electrical connector thus constructed, since the
end portion of the first contact and the end portion of the second contact
which are to be contacted with each other are so shaped that the distance
between the contact portions of the first and second contacts and the
conductor plate can be made substantially equal to the distance between
portions of the first and second contacts except their contact portions and
the conductor plate, the distance between the signal line formed by the
first and second contacts being contacted with each other when the first
connector and the second connector are fitted to each other and the
conductor plate (the ground plane) can be kept substantially uniform. As 
a result of this, the impedance of the transmission line can be stabilized.</p>
    <p num="0008">In the electrical connector mentioned above, the first connector is
provided with two first contacts which are put in a parallel relation with
each other and spaced at a substantially equal distance to the conductor
plate when the first connector and the second connector are fitted to each
other, and wherein the second connector is provided with two second
contacts which are put in a parallel relation with each other and spaced at
a substantially equal distance to the conductor plate when the first
connector and the second connector are fitted to each other.</p>
    <p num="0009">According to the electrical connector thus constructed, since the
two signal lines are formed which are put in a parallel relation with the
ground plane (the conductor plate) and spaced at a substantially equal
distance to the ground plane, transmission of differential signals can be
provided.</p>
    <p num="0010">In the electrical connector mentioned above, a plurality of
conductor plates provided in at least either of the first connector and the
second connector are spaced in a confronting relation to each other; the
first connector is provided with one or more first contacts which are
placed between each pair of conductor plates when the first connector
and the second connector are fitted to each other; and the second
connector is provided with one or more second contacts which are placed
between each pair of conductor plates when the first connector and the
second connector are fitted to each other.</p>
    <p num="0011">According to the electrical connector thus constructed, since the
conductor plate is placed between each pair of the signal lines formed by
the first and second contacts being contacted with each other, the signals
transmitted through the respective signal lines can be prevented from
interfering with each other.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>Brief Description of the Drawings</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0012">
      <sl>
        <li>FIG. 1 is a perspective view in section of an electrical connector of
the invention; </li>
        <li>FIG. 2 is a perspective view of one connector of the electrical
connector of which perspective view in section is shown in FIG. 1;</li>
        <li>FIG. 3 is a perspective view of the other connector of the electrical
connector of which perspective view in section is shown in FIG. 1;</li>
        <li>FIG. 4 is a diagram illustrating the distance relation between the
signal line and the ground planes; and</li>
        <li>FIG. 5 is a rough sketch showing the contacts of another form.</li>
      </sl>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <b>Detailed Description of the Preferred Embodiments</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0013">In the following, a certain preferred embodiment of the present
invention will be described with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
    <p num="0014">An electrical connector 1 according to the embodiment shown in
FIGS. 1-3 comprises a pair of male and female connectors 3 and 2.</p>
    <p num="0015">The connector 2 comprises a housing 21, a group of terminals 22
mainly used for slow signals, and a group of terminals 23 mainly used for
fast signals, as shown in FIG. 2.</p>
    <p num="0016">The housing 21 is formed in one piece which comprises a
terminal-group holding portion 21a for holding the group of terminals 22
and a terminal-group holding portion 21b for holding the group of
terminals 23. The terminal-group holding portion 21a has a concave
portion 21c formed therein. On the other hand, the terminal-group
holding portion 21b has three concave portions 21d, 21e and 21f formed
therein.</p>
    <p num="0017">The group of terminals 22 comprises a total of eight contacts 22a,
22b, 22c, 22d, 22e, 22f, 22g and 22h which are identical in shape and are
aligned in two columns and four rows. The group of terminals 22 is held
in the concave portion 21c provided in the terminal-group holding portion
21a of the housing 21.</p>
    <p num="0018">The group of terminals 23 is held in the terminal-group holding
portion 21b of the housing 21 and comprises two contacts 24 and 25 and
three conductor plates 26, 27 and 28.</p>
    <p num="0019">The contact 24 is a conductor having an end portion 24a which is 
shaped to extend toward the conductor plate 26, first, and then extend
away therefrom, as mentioned later. The contact 24 is held in the
housing 21 so as to be accommodated in the concave portion 21d
provided in the terminal-group holding portion 21b.</p>
    <p num="0020">The contact 25 is a conductor having an end portion 25a identical
in shape to the end portion 24a of the contact 24. The contact 25 is held
in the housing 21 so as to be accommodated in the concave portion 21e
provided in the terminal-group holding portion 21b and to extend in a
parallel relation with the contact 24.</p>
    <p num="0021">When the connector 2 and the connector 3 are fitted to each other,
the end portion 24a of the contact 24 and the end portion 25a of the
contact 25 are brought into contact with an end portion 34a of a contact
34 mentioned later and an end portion 35a of a contact 35 mentioned
later, respectively, to form signal lines S1 and S2 through which signals are
transmitted from a printed circuit board (not shown) mounting the
connector 2 thereon to a printed circuit board (not shown) mounting the
connector 3 thereon or vice versa, as shown in FIG. 1.</p>
    <p num="0022">The conductor plates 26, 27 and 28, which are to form the ground
planes, have a flat-plate form. The conductor plate 26 is held in the
housing 21 so as to be accommodated in the concave portion 21d
provided in the terminal-group holding portion 21b and to extend in a
parallel relation with portions of the contact 24 except it's end portion 24a.
The conductor plate 27 is held in the housing 21 so as to be
accommodated in the concave portion 21e provided in the terminal-group
holding portion 21b and to extend in a parallel relation with portions of the
contact 25 except its end portion 25a. Further, the conductor plate 28 is
held in the housing 21 so as to be accommodated in the concave portion
21f provided in the terminal-group holding portion 21c and to extend in a
parallel relation with the conductor plates 26 and 27.</p>
    <p num="0023">As a result of the contacts 24 and 25 and the conductor plates 26,
27 and 28 being held in the housing 21 in the manner mentioned above,
the portions of the contact 24 except its end portion 24a, the portions of 
the contact 25 except its end portion 25a and the conductor plates 26, 27
and 28 are aligned to extend in parallel with each other.</p>
    <p num="0024">The connector 3 comprises a housing 31, a group of terminals 32
mainly used for slow signals, and a group of terminals 33 mainly used for
fast signals, as shown in FIG. 3.</p>
    <p num="0025">The housing 31 is formed in one piece which comprises a
terminal-group holding portion 31a for holding the group of terminals 32
and a terminal-group holding portion 31b for holding the group of
terminals 33. The terminal-group holding portion 31a has a convex
portion 31c formed therein. On the other hand, the terminal-group
holding portion 31b has a frame portion 31d, and projecting portions 31e
and 31f provided in the terminal-group holding potion 31b.</p>
    <p num="0026">The group of terminals 32 comprises a total of eight contacts 32a,
32b, 32c, 32d, 32e, 32f, 32g and 32h which are identical in shape and are
aligned in two columns and four rows. The group of terminals 32 is held
in side surfaces of the convex portion 31c provided in the terminal-group
holding portion 31a of the housing 31.</p>
    <p num="0027">The group of terminals 33 is held in the terminal-group holding
portion 31b of the housing 31 and comprises two contacts 34 and 35.</p>
    <p num="0028">The contact 34 is a conductor having an end portion 34a which is
shaped to extend away from the projecting portion 31e provided in the
housing 31, first, and then extend toward it. The contact 34 is held in
the housing 31 to be placed in between the projecting portions 31e and
31f provided in the terminal-group holding portion 31b so that when the
connectors 2 and 3 are fitted to each other, the contact 34 can extend in
parallel with the conductor plate 26 of the connector 2 and also the
distance between the portions of the contact 34 except its end portion 34a
and the conductor plate 26 of the connector 2 can be made substantially
equal to the distance between the portions of the contact 24 except its
end portion 24a and the conductor plate 26.</p>
    <p num="0029">The contact 35 has an end portion 35a identical in shape to the
end portion 34a of the contact 34. The contact 35 is held in the housing 
to be placed in the opposite side to the projecting portion 31e with respect
to the projecting portion 31f provided in the terminal-group holding
portion 31b so that when the connectors 2 and 3 are fitted to each other,
the contact 35 can extend in parallel with the conductor plate 27 of the
connector 2 and also the distance between the portions of the contact 35
except its end portion 35a and the conductor plate 27 of the connector 2
can be made substantially equal to the distance between the portions of
the contact 25 except its end portion 25a and the conductor plate 27. It
should be noted that the contacts 34 and 35 may be made to be identical
to the contacts 24 and 25 of the connector 2, in order to reduce the
production costs.</p>
    <p num="0030">When the connector 2 and the connector 3 are fitted to each other,
the end portion 34a of the contact 34 is brought into contact with the end
portion 24a of the contact 24, to form the signal line S1, and the end
portion 35a of a contact 35 is brought into contact with the end portion
25a of the contact 25 of the connector 2, to form the signal line S2.</p>
    <p num="0031">In the following, reference is given to the fitting of the connectors
2 and 3.</p>
    <p num="0032">The convex portion 31c provided in the housing 31 of the
connector 3 is accommodated in the concave portion 21c provided in the
terminal-group holding portion 21 of the connector 2, such that the group
of terminals 22 of the connector 2 and the group of terminals 32 of the
connector 3 are brought into contact with each other.</p>
    <p num="0033">The terminal-group holding portion 21b of the connector 2 is
accommodated in the frame portion 31d of the terminal-group holding
portion 31b of the connector 3. Then, the projecting portion 31e
provided in the housing 31 of the connector 3 and the contact 34 of the
connector 3 are accommodated in the concave portion 21d provided in the
terminal-group holding portion 21b of the connector 2 so that they can be
placed between the conductor plate 26 and contact 24 of the connector 2.
As a result of this, the end portion 24a of the contact 24 of the connector
2 and the end portion 34a of the contact 34 of the connector 3 are 
brought into contact with each other. The projecting portion 31f provided
in the housing 31 of the connector 3 and the contact 35 of the connector
3 are accommodated in the concave portion 21e provided in the
terminal-group holding portion 21b of the connector 2 so that they can be
placed between the conductor plate 27 and contact 25 of the connector 2.
As a result of this, the end portion 25a of the contact 25 of the connector
2 and the end portion 35a of the contact 35 of the connector 3 are
brought into contact with each other.</p>
    <p num="0034">In the following, reference is given to the shape of the contact 24
of the connector 2 and of the contact 34 of the connector 3.</p>
    <p num="0035">The end portion 24a of the contact 24 and the end portion 34a of
the contact 34 are so shaped that when the connectors 2 and 3 are fitted
to each other, the distance between the signal line S1 and the conductor
plate 26 and the distance between the signal line S1 and the conductor
plate 27 are kept substantially uniform. It should be noted that what is
intended to be meant by the phrase that "the distance between the signal
line S1 and the conductor plate 26 and the distance between the signal
line S1 and the conductor plate 27 are kept substantially uniform" is that
even if the distances undergo changes, such changes are the degree to
which the impedance of the transmission line formed by the signal line S1
and the ground planes (the conductor plates 26 and 27) is kept at a stable
level.</p>
    <p num="0036">For example, as shown in FIG. 4, the end portion 24a of the
contact 24 and the end portion 34a of the contact 34 are shaped to satisfy
the following relation:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">Abs(L1-L2)/L1≦0.2</st32:df><st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">(Preferably, Abs(L1-L2)/L1≦0.1)</st32:df><st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">(Further preferably, Abs(L1-L2)/L1≦0.05)</st32:df>
where L1 is the distance between the signal line S1, except its part where
the contacts 24 and 34 are in contact with each other, and the conductor
plate 26; 27, and L2 is the distance between the signal line S1 at its part
where the contacts 24 and 34 are in contact with each other and the 
conductor plate 26; 27. It is to be noted that Abs(L1-L2) represents the
absolute value of a value obtained by subtracting L2 from L1.</p>
    <p num="0037">Also, the contact 24 of the connector 2 and the contact 35 of the
connector 3 are shaped to form substantially the same relation as the
contact 24 of the connector 2 and the contact 34 of the connector 3 relate
to each other.</p>
    <p num="0038">According to the electrical connector of the present invention
described above, since the end portion 24a of the contact 24, the end
portion 25a of the contact 25, the end portion 34a of the contact 34, and
the end portion 35a of the contact 35 are shaped as mentioned above, the
distance between the signal line S1 and the ground planes (the conductor
plates 26, 27) and the distance between the signal line S2 and the ground
planes (the conductor plates 27, 28) are each kept substantially uniform
and thus the impedance of the transmission line is stabilized. As a result
of this, when the electrical connector is designed to produce a desired
impedance at a certain frequency, it can also produce the desired
impedance at different frequencies from the certain frequency, and as
such can avoid increase of losses at the different frequencies from the
designed frequency caused by the impedance being kept unstable.</p>
    <p num="0039">In addition, since the conductor plate 27 is placed between the
signal line S1 formed by the contacts 24 and 34 being contacted with each
other and the signal line S2 formed by the contacts 25 and 35 being
contacted with each other, the signals transmitted through the respective
signal lines can be prevented from interfering with each other.</p>
    <p num="0040">While the preferred embodiment of the present invention has been
illustrated above, it will be understood that the present invention should
not be limited to the embodiment illustrated above and various changes
and modifications in design may be made in the invention within the scope
of the claims. For example, while the two fast-signal signal lines are
formed in the embodiment illustrated above, any adequate number of
signal lines may selectively be formed. Also, the conductor plates 26, 27
and 28 may be provided in the connector 3, rather than in the connector 2. 
Alternatively, the conductor plates may be provided in both of the
connectors 2 and 3 so that when the connectors 2 and 3 are fitted to each
other, the conductor plates provided in the both of the connectors 2 and 3
can be brought into contact with each other to form the ground planes.</p>
    <p num="0041">In addition, as long as the end portions of the contacts are so
shaped that when the connectors 2 and 3 are fitted to each other, the
distance between the signal line S1 formed by the contact 24 of the
connector 2 and the contact 34 of the connector 3 and the ground planes
(the conductor plates) and the distance between the signal line S2 formed
by the contact 25 of the connector 2 and the contact 35 of the connector
3 and the ground planes (the conductor plates) are each kept substantially
uniform, no particular limitation is imposed on the shape of the end
portions of the contacts. For example, a pair of contacts 4 and 5 may be
formed into a complementary shape, as shown in FIG. 5.</p>
    <p num="0042">Further, instead of the structure wherein a single contact is held
between each pair of conductor plates, two contacts aligned in parallel
with each other at a substantially equal distance to the conductor plates
may alternatively be held therebetween. This alternation can provide an
advantage of enabling the transmission of differential signals.</p>
    <p num="0043">Further, it is needless to say that the present invention is
applicable to various types of electrical connectors as well as to the
board-to-board electrical connector.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>An electrical connector (1) comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a first connector (2) having a first contact (24); and</claim-text><claim-text>a second connector (3) having a second contact (34) which is
brought into contact with the first contact (24) when the second connector
(3) is fitted to the first connector (2),</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein a conductor plate (26;27), which extends in a
substantially parallel relation to the first contact (24) and the second
contact (34) when the first connector (2) and the second connector (3)
are fitted to each other, is provided in at least either of the first connector
and the second connector; and
   wherein an end portion (24a) of the first contact (24) and an end
portion (34a) of the second contact (34), which are to be contacted with
each other, are so shaped that the distance between the contact portions
of the first and second contacts and the conductor plate (26;27) can be
made substantially equal to the distance between portions of the first and
second contacts except their contact portions and the conductor plate.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The electrical connector according to Claim 1, wherein the first
connector (2) is provided with two first contacts (24,25) which are put in a
parallel relation with each other and spaced at a substantially equal
distance to the conductor plate (26;27) when the first connector (2) and
the second connector (3) are fitted to each other, and wherein the second
connector (3) is provided with two second contacts (34,35) which are put
in a parallel relation with each other and spaced at a substantially equal
distance to the conductor plate (26;27) when the first connector and the
second connector are fitted to each other.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The electrical connector according to Claim 1, wherein a plurality
of conductor plates (26,27,28) provided in at least either of the first
connector (2) and the second connector (3) are spaced in a confronting
relation to each other;
   wherein the first connector (2) is provided with one or more first
contacts (24,25) which are placed between each pair of conductor plates
when the first connector and the second connector are fitted to each
other; and
   wherein the second connector (3) is provided with one or more
second contacts (34,35) which are placed between each pair of conductor
plates when the first connector and the second connector are fitted to
each other.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
