<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1243277-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1243277" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="25208661" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020925">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1243277-A1" status="new" fvid="23567126">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1243277</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20020925</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02251914-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02251914</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020318</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="US-81214801-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>81214801</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010319</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61L   2/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61L   2/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61L   2/14        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61L   2/18        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61L   2/18        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61L   2/20        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61L   2/20        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61L   2/24        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  19/08        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  19/08        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H05H   1/24        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H05H   1/24        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61L   2/14</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61L   2/18</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61L   2/20</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61L   2/24</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H05H   1/24</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Sterilisationssystem mit Verwendung eines Schaltmoduls zum Pulsieren der an einem Plasma angelegten Niederfrequenz-Energie</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Sterilization system employing a switching module adapted to pulsate the low frequency power applied to a plasma</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Système de stérilisation utilisant un module de commutation adapté pour pulser l'énergie basse fréquence appliquée à un plasma</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ETHICON INC</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ETHICON, INC.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>ETHICON, INC.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>U.S. Route 22</street>
              <city>Somerville, NJ 08876</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>AGAMOHAMADI MITCH</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>CHOPERENA ALFREDO M</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>LEMUS ANTHONY</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>PLATT ROBERT C</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>AGAMOHAMADI, MITCH</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>CHOPERENA, ALFREDO M.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>LEMUS, ANTHONY</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>PLATT, ROBERT C.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>AGAMOHAMADI, MITCH</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1105 E. Grove Avenue</street>
              <city>Orange, CA 92865</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>CHOPERENA, ALFREDO M.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>31342 Via Las Palmas</street>
              <city>San Juan Capistrano, CA 92675</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>LEMUS, ANTHONY</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>24610 Via Vallarta</street>
              <city>Yorba Linda, CA 92887</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>PLATT, ROBERT C.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>5 Saint Croix</street>
              <city>Laguna Niguel, CA 92677</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Fisher, Adrian John</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>CARPMAELS &amp;amp; RANSFORD 43 Bloomsbury Square</street>
              <city>London WC1A 2RA</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>IT</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A sterilization system and method applies low frequency power to a plasma
within a vacuum chamber to remove gas or vapor species from an article. The
sterilization system includes a switching module adapted to pulsate the low frequency
power applied to the plasma and a low frequency power feedback control system for
controllably adjusting the low frequency power applied to the plasma. A power
monitor is adapted to produce a first signal indicative of the low frequency power
applied to the plasma within the vacuum chamber. A power control module is
adapted to produce a second signal in response to the first signal from the power
monitor, and a power controller is adapted to adjust, in response to the second signal,
the low frequency power applied to the plasma to maintain a substantially stable
average low frequency power applied to the plasma while the article is being
processed.</p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Background of the Invention</u>
    </heading>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Field of the Invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0001">The invention relates to systems and methods for controlling gas discharge
plasmas in sterilization systems that employ gas discharge plasmas.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Description of the Related Art</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0002">Plasmas produced using radio frequency (RF) generators in particular have
proven to be valuable tools in processes for the sterilization of medical devices. For
example, in U.S. Patent Nos. 4,643,876 and 4,756,882, which are incorporated by
reference herein, Jacobs, et al. disclose using hydrogen peroxide as a precursor in a
low temperature sterilization system that employs RF plasma. The combination of
hydrogen peroxide vapor and a RF plasma provides an efficient method of sterilizing
medical devices without using or leaving highly toxic materials or forming toxic byproducts.
Similarly, Jacob, U.S. Patent No. 5,302,343, and Griffiths, et al., U.S.
Patent No. 5,512,244, teach the use of RF plasmas in a sterilization process.</p>
    <p num="0003">However, there are problems associated with the use of an RF plasma in a
sterilization process. The RF plasma may leave residual hydrogen peroxide on the
sterilized article. The residual amount of hydrogen peroxide remaining on the
sterilized article depends upon the RF power applied to the article, the amount of time
exposed to the RF plasma, and the material of the article. For example, while some
plastics (e.g., polyurethane) absorb hydrogen peroxide, other materials (e.g., Teflon)
absorb relatively little, thereby yielding less residual hydrogen peroxide after
sterilization. </p>
    <p num="0004">In addition, inherent inefficiencies in the energy conversion from the low
frequency (<i>e.g</i>., 60 Hz) line voltage to the RF (e.g., approximately 1 MHz - 1 GHz)
voltage used to generate the RF plasma limit the power efficiency of such systems to
typically less than 50%. Energy efficiency is further reduced by typically 5 - 20% by
virtue of the losses from the required impedance matching network between the RF
generator and the load. Such low energy efficiency significantly increases the cost
per watt applied to the sterilized articles. The required instrumentation for using RF
electrical energy (<i>e.g</i>., RF generator, impedance matching network, monitoring
circuitry) is expensive, which also increases the cost per watt applied to the sterilized
articles.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Summary of the Invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0005">One aspect of the present invention is a sterilization system that applies low
frequency power to a plasma within a vacuum chamber to remove gas or vapor
species from an article. The low frequency power has a frequency less than or equal
to approximately 200 kHz. The sterilization system comprises a switching module
adapted to pulsate the low frequency power applied to the plasma. The sterilization
system further comprises a low frequency power feedback control system for
controllably adjusting the low frequency power applied to the plasma. The low
frequency power feedback control system comprises a power monitor adapted to
produce a first signal indicative of the low frequency power applied to the plasma
within the vacuum chamber. The low frequency power feedback control system
further comprises a power control module adapted to produce a second signal in
response to the first signal from the power monitor, and a power controller adapted to
adjust, in response to the second signal, the low frequency power applied to the
plasma to maintain a substantially stable average low frequency power applied to the
plasma while the article is being processed.</p>
    <p num="0006">Another aspect of the present invention is a method of controllably adjusting a
low frequency power applied to a plasma within a vacuum chamber of a sterilization
system to remove gas or vapor species from an article. The low frequency power has
a frequency less than or equal to approximately 200 kHz. The method comprises
pulsating the low frequency power applied to the plasma and monitoring the low 
frequency power applied to the plasma within the vacuum chamber. The method
further comprises generating a first signal indicative of the low frequency power
applied to the plasma. The method further comprises adjusting the low frequency
power applied to the plasma in response to the first signal to maintain a substantially
stable average low frequency power applied to the plasma while the article is being
processed.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Brief Description of the Drawings</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0007">Figure 1 schematically illustrates a preferred embodiment of a sterilization
system compatible with the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0008">Figure 2A schematically illustrates a preferred embodiment of a cylindrically-shaped
electrode with open ends and perforated sides.</p>
    <p num="0009">Figure 2B schematically illustrates an alternative embodiment of a
cylindrically-shaped electrode with open ends and louvered sides.</p>
    <p num="0010">Figure 2C schematically illustrates an alternative embodiment of a
cylindrically-shaped electrode with open ends and solid sides.</p>
    <p num="0011">Figure 2D schematically illustrates an alternative embodiment of an electrode
comprising one or more colinear cylindrically-shaped segments with open ends and
solid sides.</p>
    <p num="0012">Figure 2E schematically illustrates an alternative embodiment of an electrode
with a partial cylindrical shape, open ends, and solid sides.</p>
    <p num="0013">Figure 2F schematically illustrates an alternative embodiment of a
cylindrically-symmetric and longitudinally-asymmetric electrode with open ends and
solid sides.</p>
    <p num="0014">Figure 2G schematically illustrates an alternative embodiment of one or more
asymmetric electrodes with open ends and solid sides.</p>
    <p num="0015">Figure 2H schematically illustrates an alternative embodiment of an electrode
system with a first electrode that is cylindrically-shaped with open ends and solid
sides, and a second electrode comprising a wire substantially colinear with the first
electrode. </p>
    <p num="0016">Figure 2I schematically illustrates an alternative embodiment of a generally
square or rectangular electrode within a generally square or rectangular vacuum
chamber.</p>
    <p num="0017">Figure 3, which is broken into Figures 3A and 3B, schematically illustrates an
embodiment of a low frequency power module compatible with the phase angle
control method of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0018">Figure 4, which is broken into Figures 4A and 4B, schematically illustrates an
embodiment of a low frequency power module compatible with the amplitude control
method of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0019">Figure 5A schematically illustrates the phase angle control method of
controlling the low frequency power applied to the plasma.</p>
    <p num="0020">Figure 5B schematically illustrates the amplitude control method of
controlling the low frequency power applied to the plasma.</p>
    <p num="0021">Figure 6, which is broken into Figures 6A and 6B, schematically illustrates an
embodiment of a low frequency power module comprising a switching module
compatible with the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0022">Figure 7 schematically illustrates the output from a switching module
compatible with the present invention which pulsates an incoming sinusoidal voltage
with a frequency of 60 Hz to form a series of voltage pulses with widths W and
spaced by times T.</p>
    <p num="0023">Figure 8A schematically illustrates a rippled DC voltage generated by full-wave-rectifying
and filtering the line voltage prior to pulsating the voltage via the
switching module.</p>
    <p num="0024">Figure 8B schematically illustrates the rippled DC voltage of Figure 8A after
being pulsated by the switching module utilizing unipolar switching.</p>
    <p num="0025">Figure 8C schematically illustrates the rippled DC voltage of Figure 8A after
being pulsated by the switching module utilizing bipolar switching.</p>
    <p num="0026">Figure 9 schematically illustrates one embodiment of a switching module
which generates a unipolar pulsation.</p>
    <p num="0027">Figure 10 schematically illustrates a preferred embodiment of a method of
sterilization compatible with the present invention. </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Detailed Description of the Preferred Embodiment</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0028">Production of gas discharge plasmas using low frequency (LF) voltages avoids
the various problems inherent in the state of the art sterilization devices and processes
which form and use plasmas produced by radio frequency (RF) voltages. First, LF
plasma processing leaves less residual reactive species remaining on the sterilized
articles than does RF plasma processing. Second, generation of the LF plasma is
highly energy efficient because little or no frequency conversion from the line voltage
is needed. For example, by using no frequency conversion with a line voltage
frequency of 60 Hz, the energy efficiency of the sterilization system can reach
approximately 85-99%. Use of LF voltages also does not require an impedance
matching network, thereby avoiding the associated energy losses. Third, due to the
simplified instrumentation and higher energy efficiency of LF generation, the cost per
watt applied to the sterilized articles using LF plasmas can be as low as one-tenth the
cost per watt of using RF plasmas. Fourth, the simplified instrumentation used for
generating LF plasmas has proven to be more reliable and robust, and requiring less
complicated diagnostic instrumentation.</p>
    <p num="0029">Figure 1 schematically illustrates one preferred embodiment of the present
invention comprising a sterilization system 10. The sterilization system 10 comprises
a vacuum chamber 12, a vacuum pump 14, a vacuum pump line 15, a vacuum pump
valve 16, a reactive agent source 18, a reactive agent line 19, a reactive agent valve
20, a low frequency (LF) power module 22, an LF voltage conduit 24, a vent 26, a
vent line 27, a vent valve 28, a process control module 30, an electrode 32, and a
reactive agent monitor 34. Persons skilled in the art recognize that other
embodiments comprising sterilization systems of different configurations than that
illustrated in Figure 1 are compatible with the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0030">In the preferred embodiment of the present invention, the articles (not shown
in Figure 1) to be sterilized are packaged in various commonly employed packaging
materials used for sterilized products. The preferred materials are spunbonded
polyethylene packaging material commonly available under the trademark "TYVEK"
or composites of "TYVEK" with a polyethylene terephthalate packaging material
commonly available under the trademark "MYLAR". Other similar packaging 
materials may also be employed such as polypropylene. Paper packaging materials
may also be used. With paper packaging, longer processing times may be required to
achieve sterilization because of possible interactions of the reactive agent with paper.</p>
    <p num="0031">The vacuum chamber 12 of the preferred embodiment is sufficiently gas-tight
to support a vacuum of approximately less than 40 Pa (0.3 Torr). Coupled to the
vacuum chamber 12 is a pressure monitor (not shown) which is also coupled to the
process control module to provide a measure of the total pressure within the vacuum
chamber. Also coupled to the vacuum chamber 12 is the reactive agent monitor 34
which is capable of detecting the amount of the reactive agent in the vacuum
chamber 12. In the exemplary embodiment of the present invention, the reactive
agent is hydrogen peroxide, and the reactive agent monitor 34 measures the
absorption of ultraviolet radiation at a wavelength characteristic of hydrogen
peroxide. Other methods of reactive agent detection compatible with the present
invention include, but are not limited to, pressure measurement, near infrared
absorption, and dew point measurement. The reactive agent monitor 34 is also
coupled to the process control module 30 to communicate the detected amount of the
reactive agent to the process control module 30.</p>
    <p num="0032">In the preferred embodiment of the present invention, inside and electrically
isolated from the vacuum chamber 12 is the electrode 32, which is electrically
conductive and perforated to enhance fluid communication between the gas and
plasma species on each side of the electrode 32. The electrode 32 of the preferred
embodiment generally conforms to the inner surface of the vacuum chamber 12,
spaced approximately one-half to two inches from the wall of the vacuum chamber
12, thereby defining a gap region between the vacuum chamber 12 and the electrode
32. The electrode 32 is coupled to the LF power module 22 via the LF voltage
conduit 24. In the preferred embodiment, with the vacuum chamber 12 connected to
electrical ground, application of an LF voltage between the vacuum chamber 12 and
the electrode 32 creates an LF electric field which is stronger in a first region 31
which includes the gap region and the vicinity of the edges of the electrode 32. The
LF electric field is weaker in a second region 33 where the sterilized articles are
placed. Generally, in other embodiments, the LF electric field can be generated by 
applying an LF voltage between the electrode 32 and a second electrode in the
vacuum chamber 12. In such embodiments, the first region 31 includes the gap
region between the two electrodes, and the vicinity of the edges of one or both of the
electrodes. The preferred embodiment in which the vacuum chamber 12 serves as the
second electrode is one of the many different ways to generate the gas plasma.</p>
    <p num="0033">In the preferred embodiment illustrated in Figure 2A, a cylindrically-shaped
electrode 32 provides fluid communication between the gas and plasma on each side
of the electrode 32 through the open ends of the electrode 32 as well as through the
perforations in the side of the electrode 32. These open ends and perforations permit
gaseous and plasma species to freely travel between the first region 31 between the
electrode 32 and the walls of the vacuum chamber 12 and the second region 33 where
the sterilized articles are placed. Similarly, as illustrated in Figures 2B - 2I, other
configurations of the electrode 32 provide fluid communication between the first
region 31 and the second region 33. Figure 2B schematically illustrates a
cylindrically-shaped electrode 32 with open ends and louvered openings along its
sides. Figure 2C schematically illustrates a cylindrically-shaped electrode 32 with
open ends and solid sides. Figure 2D schematically illustrates an electrode 32
comprising a series of colinear cylindrically-shaped segments with open ends and
solid sides. Figure 2E schematically illustrates an electrode 32 with a partial
cylindrical shape, open ends and solid sides. Figure 2F schematically illustrates a
cylindrically-symmetric and longitudinally-asymmetric electrode 32 with open ends
and solid sides. Figure 2G schematically illustrates an asymmetric electrode 32 with
open ends and solid sides. More than one electrode can be used to generate the
plasma. Figure 2H schematically illustrates an electrode system with a first electrode
32 that is cylindrically-shaped with open ends and solid sides, and a second electrode
32' comprising a wire substantially colinear with the first electrode 32. The LF
voltage is applied between the first electrode 32 and the second electrode 32'. In this
embodiment, the first region 31 is the region between the first electrode 32 and the
second electrode 32', and the second region 33 is between the first electrode 32 and
the vacuum chamber 12. Figure 2I schematically illustrates a generally square or
rectangular electrode within a generally square or rectangular vacuum chamber. The 
various configurations for generally cylindrical electrodes schematically illustrated in
Figures 2A-2H can also be applied to the generally square or rectangular electrode of
Figure 2I. Each of these embodiments of the electrode 32 provide fluid
communication between the first region 31 and the second region 33.</p>
    <p num="0034">The vacuum pump 14 of the preferred embodiment is coupled to the vacuum
chamber 12 via the vacuum pump line 15 and the vacuum valve 16. Both the
vacuum pump 14 and the vacuum pump valve 16 are coupled to, and controlled by,
the process control module 30. By opening the vacuum valve 16, gases within the
vacuum chamber 12 are pumped out of the vacuum chamber 12 through the vacuum
pump line 15 by the vacuum pump 14. In certain embodiments, the vacuum valve 16
is capable of being opened to variable degrees to adjust and control the pressure in
the vacuum chamber 12.</p>
    <p num="0035">The reactive agent source 18 of the preferred embodiment is a source of fluid
coupled to the vacuum chamber 12 via the reactive agent line 19 and the reactive
agent valve 20. The reactive agent valve 20 is coupled to, and controlled by, the
process control module 30. The reactive agent source 18 of the preferred
embodiment comprises reactive agent species. In the preferred embodiment, the
reactive agent species comprises a germicide which is a sterilant or a disinfectant,
such as hydrogen peroxide. In addition, the germicide supplied by the reactive agent
source 18 can be in gas or vapor form. By opening the reactive agent valve 20,
reactive agent atoms and molecules from the reactive agent source 18 can be
transported into the vacuum chamber 12 via the reactive agent line 19. In certain
embodiments, the reactive agent valve 20 is capable of being opened to variable
degrees to adjust the pressure of the reactive agent in the vacuum chamber 12. In the
exemplary embodiment of the present invention, the reactive agent species of the
reactive agent source 18 comprising hydrogen peroxide molecules.</p>
    <p num="0036">The vent 26 of the preferred embodiment is coupled to the vacuum chamber
12 via the vent line 27 and the vent valve 28. The vent valve 28 is coupled to, and
controlled by, the process control module 30. By opening the vent valve 28, vent gas
is vented into the vacuum chamber 12 via the vent line 27. In certain embodiments,
the vent valve 28 is capable of being opened to variable degrees to adjust the pressure 
of the air in the vacuum chamber 12. In the exemplary embodiment of the present
invention, the vent 26 is a High Efficiency Particulate-filtered Air (HEPA) vent
which provides filtered air as the vent gas. Other vent gases compatible with the
present invention include, but are not limited to, dry nitrogen, and argon.</p>
    <p num="0037">The process control module 30 is coupled to various components of the
sterilization system 10 to control the sterilization system 10. In an exemplary
embodiment of the present invention, the process control module 30 is a
microprocessor configured to provide control signals to the various other components
in response to the various signals received from other components.</p>
    <p num="0038">The LF power module 22 of the preferred embodiment is coupled to the
electrode 32 via the LF voltage conduit 24, and is coupled to, and controlled by, the
process control module 30. The LF power module 22 is adapted to apply a low
frequency voltage between the electrode 32 and the vacuum chamber 12 so as to
generate a plasma in the vacuum chamber 12. Figure 3, which is broken into Figures
3a and 3b, schematically illustrates an embodiment of the LF power module 22
compatible with the phase angle control method of controlling the low frequency
power applied to the plasma. As illustrated in Figure 3, the LF power module 22
comprises an over-power relay 40, a pair of metal oxide varistors 42, a step-up
transformer 50, a flyback current shunt element 62, an inductor 64, a capacitor 66,
and a LF power feedback control system 70. The LF power feedback control system
70 illustrated in Figure 3 comprises a power controller 60, a current monitor 80, a
voltage monitor 90, and a power monitor 100 coupled to the current monitor 80 and
the voltage monitor 90. Line voltage (typically 200 - 240 VAC, 50/60 Hz) is
provided to the step-up transformer 50 via the closed over-power relay 40 which is
coupled to the LF power feedback control system 70.</p>
    <p num="0039">In the embodiment illustrated in Figure 3, the metal oxide varistors (MOVs)
42 are used to suppress transient voltage impulses. Each MOV 42 is a multiple-junction
solid-state device capable of withstanding large magnitude impulses with a
low amount of let-through voltage. The MOVs 42 serve as fast acting "variable
resistors" with a low impedance at higher-than-normal voltages and a high impedance
at normal voltages. MOVs are manufactured for specific voltage configurations and 
for a variety of impulse magnitudes. Persons skilled in the art are able to select
MOVs 42 consistent with the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0040">The output voltage of the step-up transformer 50 is preferably between
approximately 100 and 1000 V<sub>rms</sub>, more preferably between approximately 200 and
500 V<sub>rms</sub>, and most preferably between approximately 250 and 450 V<sub>rms</sub>. The output
voltage of the step-up transformer 50 is transmitted to the power controller 60, which
provides the LF voltage to the electrode 32 and vacuum chamber 12 via the flyback
current shunt element 62, the inductor 64, the capacitor 66, and the LF power
feedback control system 70. The flyback current shunt element 62 provides a path
for fly-back current and to tune the circuit, and in the preferred embodiment the
flyback current shunt element 62 is a load resistor of approximately 1500 ohms. In
other embodiments, the flyback current shunt element 62 can be a snubber. The
inductance of the inductor 64 is chosen to limit noise spikes in the LF current, and is
typically approximately 500 mH. The capacitance of the capacitor 66 is chosen to
maximize the efficiency of power transfer to the LF plasma by matching the resonant
frequency of the series LC circuit to the frequency of the applied LF voltage. For a
60 Hz voltage and an inductance of 500 mH, a capacitance of approximately 13.6 µ<i>F</i>
provides the resonant condition for which the impedance of the series LC circuit is
approximately zero, thereby maximizing the transmitted LF power. Persons skilled in
the art are able to select appropriate values for these components depending on the
frequency of the applied LF voltage in a manner compatible with the present
invention.</p>
    <p num="0041">Figure 4, which is broken into Figures 4a and 4b, schematically illustrates an
embodiment of the LF power module 22 compatible with the amplitude control
method of controlling the low frequency power applied to the plasma. As illustrated
in Figure 4, the LF power module 22 comprises an over-power relay 40, a pair of
metal oxide varistors 42, a step-up transformer 55, and a LF power feedback control
system 70. The LF power feedback control system 70 illustrated in Figure 4
comprises a high voltage (HV) DC power supply 51, a voltage-controlled oscillator
(VCO) 52, a voltage-controlled amplifier (VCA) 53, a HV operational amplifier 54, a
current monitor 80, a voltage monitor 90, and a power monitor 100 coupled to the 
current monitor 80 and the voltage monitor 90. Line voltage is provided to the HV
DC power supply 51 via the closed over-power relay 40 which is coupled to the LF
power feedback control system 70. The output of the HV DC power supply 51 is
preferably between approximately 100 and 1000 VDC, more preferably between
approximately 200 and 500 VDC, and most preferably between approximately 250
and 450 VDC.</p>
    <p num="0042">In the embodiment illustrated in Figure 4, the VCO 52 generates a sinewave
output with a constant amplitude and fixed low frequency less than or equal to
approximately 200 kHz (which includes DC voltages and currents), the low frequency
selected by supplying an appropriate set-point voltage to the VCO 52. Alternative
embodiments can utilize other waveforms, e.g., triangular or square waveforms. The
LF output of the VCO 52 is supplied to the VCA 53, which serves as a power
controller to maintain a substantially stable average LF power applied to the plasma.
In response to a feedback signal from the power control module 110, the VCA 53
amplifies the LF output of the VCO 52 to generate an amplified LF voltage with an
amplitude between approximately 0 and 12 VAC. The amplified LF voltage from the
VCA 53 is supplied to the HV operational amplifier 54 which in response generates a
high voltage LF output with an amplitude determined by the amplitude of the
amplified LF voltage from the VCA 53. Appropriate HV operational amplifiers are
commercially available (e.g., Apex Microtechnology, Tuscon, AZ, part number
PA93), and persons skilled in the art are able to select a HV operational amplifier
compatible with the present invention. Typically, the amplitude of the high voltage
LF output from the HV operational amplifier 54 is approximately 100 to 150 VAC.
In order to generate larger amplitude LF voltages to be applied to the plasma, the high
voltage LF output from the HV operational amplifier 54 can be further amplified by
the step-up transformer 55, as illustrated in Figure 4. Alternatively, the step-up
transformer 55 may be omitted if the HV operational amplifier 54 is capable of
generating a high voltage LF output with the desired amplitude to be applied to the
plasma.</p>
    <p num="0043">In both the phase angle control embodiment illustrated in Figure 3 and the
amplitude control embodiment illustrated in Figure 4, the LF power feedback control 
system 70 of the LF power module 22 further comprises a power control module 110
coupled to the power monitor 100, which is coupled to the current monitor 80 and
voltage monitor 90. The current monitor 80 measures the LF current through the
electrode 32 and the vacuum chamber 12. In the preferred embodiment of the present
invention, the current monitor 80 includes a current sensor 82 which provides a
voltage output indicative of the measured real-time, cycle-by-cycle LF current, a first
converter 84 which produces a DC voltage in response to the RMS of the voltage
output of the current sensor 82, and a first voltage amplifier 86 which amplifies the
DC voltage from the first converter 84 to produce a real-time current signal. In
addition, the current monitor 80 also includes an over-current detector 88, which
monitors the DC voltage from the first converter 84 in real-time and sends an error
signal to the power control module 110 if the LF current exceeds a pre-set value,
caused for example by a plasma instability between the electrode 32 and the vacuum
chamber 12. Under such an occurrence, the LF voltage is turned off momentarily.
This occurrence can result in a few cycles being lost, however the LF power is
stabilized so that the average power is not affected by more than a predetermined
tolerance.</p>
    <p num="0044">The voltage monitor 90 measures the LF voltage between the electrode 32 and
the vacuum chamber 12. In the preferred embodiment of the present invention, the
voltage monitor 90 includes a step-down transformer 92 which produces a voltage
output indicative of the measured real-time, cycle-by-cycle LF voltage, a second
converter 94 which produces a DC voltage in response to the RMS of the voltage
output of the step-down transformer 92, and a second voltage amplifier 96 which
amplifies the DC voltage from the second converter 94 to produce a real-time voltage
signal. In other embodiments, the voltage output from the step-down transformer 92
and the voltage output of the current sensor 82 are multiplied together and directed to
a single converter which creates a voltage signal corresponding to the power applied
to the plasma.</p>
    <p num="0045">In the preferred embodiment, the power monitor 100 further comprises a
multiplier that receives the DC voltages from the current monitor 80 and the voltage
monitor 90, and multiplies these two voltages to produce a real-time power signal 
proportional to the LF power applied to the plasma between the electrode 32 and the
vacuum chamber 12, the real-time power signal being generated in response to the
real-time current and real-time voltage signals, and transmitted to the power control
module 110. In other embodiments, the power monitor 100 monitors the LF power
applied to the plasma by utilizing a signal indicative of the real-time impedance of
the plasma with either the real-time current or real-time voltage signals. In still other
embodiments, the power monitor 100 monitors the LF power applied to the plasma by
utilizing other real-time signals which indirectly indicate the LF power applied to the
plasma; e.g., a real-time signal proportional to the brightness of the glow discharge
generated by the plasma. Persons skilled in the art can select an appropriate power
monitor 100 compatible with the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0046">The power control module 110 of the preferred embodiment includes a fault
detector, such as an over-power detector 112 which monitors the real-time power
signal from the power monitor 100 and opens the over-power relay 40 if the LF power
exceeds a pre-set value, thereby extinguishing the LF plasma. After such an
occurrence, the control of restart can be given to the user or to software. The power
control module 110 of the preferred embodiment further comprises an additional fault
detector, such as a thermal switch 114 which detects overheating, and a power control
processor 120.</p>
    <p num="0047">In the preferred embodiment, the power control processor 120 controls and
monitors the status of the LF power feedback control system 70. The power control
processor 120 is coupled to a user interface 122 which provides user input regarding
a selected power magnitude setting and a selected power on/off setting. The power
control processor 120 is also coupled to the power monitor 100, the thermal switch
114, and the over-current detector 88. In the preferred embodiment, the power
magnitude setting can be selected from two power levels. When the LF power is
turned on, the preferred embodiment of the power control processor 120 ensures that
a "soft start" condition is maintained in which the inrush current is minimized. In
addition, the user interface 122 receives signals from the power control processor 120
indicative of the status of the sterilization system 10, which is communicated to the
user. </p>
    <p num="0048">In the phase angle control embodiment illustrated in Figure 3, the power
control processor 120 is also coupled to the power controller 60. In this embodiment,
the power control processor 120 transmits a signal to the power controller 60 in
response to signals from the user interface 122, power monitor 100, over-current
detector 88, and thermal switch 114 in order to maintain a substantially stable LF
power applied to the LF plasma while avoiding error conditions. In the amplitude
control embodiment illustrated in Figure 4, the power control processor 120 is
coupled to the VCA 53. In this embodiment, the power control processor 120
transmits a signal to the VCA 53 in response to signals from the user interface 122,
power monitor 100, over-current detector 88, and thermal switch 114 in order to
maintain a substantially stable LF power applied to the LF plasma while avoiding
error conditions. In both embodiments illustrated in Figure 3 and Figure 4, the power
control processor 120 typically maintains the LF power applied to the LF plasma
within a tolerance of approximately 0 - 5% of the specified power level.</p>
    <p num="0049">Note that not all of the components listed and described in Figure 3 and
Figure 4 are required to practice the present invention, since Figure 3 and Figure 4
merely illustrate particular embodiments of the LF power module 22. These
components include components for automation, safety, regulatory, efficiency, and
convenience purposes. Other embodiments compatible with the present invention
can eliminate some or all of these components, or can include additional components.</p>
    <p num="0050">In response to the signal from the power control processor 120, the power
controller 60 of the embodiment illustrated in Figure 3 controls the LF power applied
between the electrode 32 and the vacuum chamber 12 by utilizing phase angle
control. Under phase angle control, the duty cycle of the LF power is modified by
zeroing the voltage and current applied between the electrode 32 and the vacuum
<i>chamber 12 for a portion Δ of the cycle period. Such phase angle control is often</i>
used to maintain constant power from electric heaters or furnaces. Figure 5A
schematically illustrates the voltage and current for a 100% duty cycle (<i>i.e.</i>, Δ = <i>0)</i>
and for a reduced duty cycle (<i>i.e.</i>, Δ ≠ 0). <i>During normal operations, the power</i>
controller 60 maintains a constant LF power applied to the plasma by actively
adjusting the duty cycle of the LF power in response to the feedback real-time signal 
received from the power control module 110 in response to the measured LF power.
When a fault event is detected by the over-current detector 88 or thermal switch 114,
the power control processor 120 reduces the LF power by reducing the duty cycle of
the LF power, and it transmits a signal to the user interface 122 to provide
notification of the fault event. Persons skilled in the art are able to select appropriate
circuitry to modify the duty cycle of the LF power consistent with the present
invention.</p>
    <p num="0051">Alternatively, the LF power can be controlled by utilizing amplitude control,
as in the embodiment illustrated in Figure 4. Under amplitude control, the LF power
is modified by adjusting the amplitude of the voltage and current applied between the
electrode 32 and the vacuum chamber 12. Figure 5B schematically illustrates the
voltage and current corresponding to a first LF power setting and a second LF power
setting less than the first LF power setting. During normal operations, the VCA 53
maintains a constant LF power applied to the plasma by actively adjusting the
amplitude of the LF power in response to the feedback real-time signal received from
the power control module 110 in response to the measured LF power. Persons skilled
in the art are able to select appropriate circuitry to modify the amplitude of the LF
power consistent with the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0052">The electronics for RF sterilizers are complicated by the need of such systems
to attempt to closely match the output impedance of the RF generator with the plasma
impedance at all times in order to maximize power efficiency and to avoid damage to
the RF generator. Plasma impedance varies widely during plasma formation, being
very high until the plasma is fully formed, and very low thereafter. When first
igniting a plasma, the RF generator cannot match the high plasma impedance which
exists prior to the full formation of the plasma, so a large fraction of the power output
is reflected back to the RF generator. RF generators have protection systems which
typically limit the RF generator output during periods of high reflected power to
avoid damage. However, to ignite the plasma, the voltage output of the RF generator
must exceed the threshold voltage required for plasma ignition. The threshold
voltage is dependent on the chamber pressure, reactive agent, and other operating
geometries and parameters and is approximately 300 V<sub>rms</sub> in the preferred 
embodiment. In an RF system, once ignition has been achieved, and the plasma
impedance is thereby reduced, the magnitude of the applied RF voltage must be
reduced to a sustaining voltage, e.g., approximately 140 V<sub>rms</sub>, to avoid excessive
power delivery. Because the higher RF voltages required for plasma ignition produce
excessively high reflected power before full plasma formation, RF generators require
complicated safeguards to prevent damage during the plasma ignition stage.</p>
    <p num="0053">Conversely, the complexity of the power system and rate of ignition failures
are significantly reduced for LF sterilizers since the LF sterilizers may operate using
applied voltages above the threshold voltage and have much less restrictive output
impedance matching requirements. For frequencies below approximately 1 kHz,
during the times at which the applied LF voltage equals zero, as seen in Figure 5A,
the LF plasma is extinguished and there is no LF plasma in the vacuum chamber.
The LF plasma must then be re-ignited twice each cycle. By only operating in one
voltage regime, LF sterilizers have simpler and more reliable electrical systems than
do RF sterilizers. These electrical systems are easier to service and diagnose, thereby
reducing the costs associated with repair. In addition, the higher peak plasma
densities resulting from LF sterilizers likely result in increased dissociative
recombination on the articles, thereby reducing the amount of residual reactive
species remaining on the articles after the sterilization procedure.</p>
    <p num="0054">In certain embodiments, localized gas heating causes reductions of the plasma
impedance, which then generate arcing or other plasma instabilities. This condition
is more likely to occur where current densities are larger. However, this effect is
reduced, and stability is increased, for frequencies higher than the 50/60 Hz of the
incoming line voltage. As schematically illustrated in Figure 6, which is broken into
Figures 6a and 6b, certain embodiments of the LF power module 22 may also include
a switching module 130 to provide higher frequencies by pulsating the LF power
applied to the plasma. While Figure 6 is based on the embodiment illustrated in
Figure 3, a switching module 130 can also be used by making a similar modification
to the embodiment of Figure 4. While Figure 6 shows the switching module 130
inserted between the first MOV 42 and the step-up transformer 50, persons skilled in 
the art appreciate that other embodiments can have the switching module 130 at other
locations within the LF power module 22.</p>
    <p num="0055">Figure 7 schematically illustrates the output from a switching module 130
compatible with the present invention. As shown in Figure 7, an incoming sinusoidal
voltage with a frequency of 60 Hz is pulsated by the switching module 130 to form a
series of voltage pulses with widths W and spaced by times T. Persons skilled in the
art appreciate that other waveforms may also be inputted into the switching module
130. For example, in order to minimize or eliminate periods in which the applied
voltage is less than the threshold voltage V<sub>T</sub> required for plasma ignition, a rippled
DC voltage can be generated by full-wave-rectifying and filtering the line voltage
prior to pulsating the voltage via the switching module 130, as illustrated in Figure
8a. In one embodiment, such a rippled DC voltage can be generated by inserting a
AC-to-DC converter in the device schematically illustrated by Figure 6 between the
over power relay 40 and the MOV 42. Persons skilled in the art can identify other
embodiments which can generate such a rippled DC voltage.</p>
    <p num="0056">For illustrative purposes, the output of the switching module 130 illustrated in
Figure 7 has a frequency of approximately 1000 Hz. Persons skilled in the art
appreciate that other frequencies are compatible with the present invention. The
output frequency of the switching module is preferably less than or equal to
approximately 200 kHz (which includes DC voltages and currents), more preferably
between approximately 1 kHz to 100 kHz, and most preferably between
approximately 20 kHz to 50 kHz. In addition, the switching module 130 can be
configured to provide an output with unipolar pulsation, as illustrated in Figure 8b, or
with bipolar pulsation, as illustrated in Figure 8c. Bipolar pulsation reduces the
possibility of electrode sputtering by the plasma and can provide a more stable
plasma. Figure 9 schematically illustrates one embodiment of a switching module
130 which generates a unipolar pulsation by utilizing a bridge rectifier 131, a power
MOSFET 132, a MOSFET driver 133, a snubber 134, a opto-isolator 135, and a
function generator 136. The snubber 134 is used to shunt the energy stored in the
leakage inductance of the step-up transformer 50 so it does not damage the power
MOSFET 132. An example of an opto-isolator 135 compatible with the present 
invention is the 4N26 phototransistor optocoupler, sold by Texas Instruments of
Dallas, Texas. An example of a power MOSFET 132 compatible with the present
invention is the "Super-247," serial number IRFPS37N50A, sold by International
Rectifier of El Segundo, California. An example of a MOSFET driver 133
compatible with the present invention is the SN75372 dual MOSFET driver, sold by
Texas Instruments of Dallas, Texas.</p>
    <p num="0057">In certain embodiments, such as that illustrated in Figure 9, the LF power
applied to the plasma can also be adjusted by the switching module 130 by adjusting
pulse widths W or times T between pulses. In certain embodiments, the function
generator 136 can be replaced by a pulse width modulation (PWM) controller that
automatically controls the applied LF power. While the period (W+T) is the inverse
of the selected pulsating frequency, the ratio of W/T can be varied to control the
average LF power applied to the plasma. In such embodiments, the switching module
130 can receive appropriate signals from the power control processor 120 to
appropriately select the pulse widths W and/or times T.</p>
    <p num="0058">Figure 10 schematically illustrates a preferred method of sterilization using
the apparatus schematically illustrated in Figure 1. The sterilization process shown in
Figure 10 is exemplary, and persons skilled in the art recognize that other processes
are also compatible with the present invention. The preferred process begins by
sealing 200 the article to be sterilized into the vacuum chamber 12. The vacuum
chamber is then evacuated 210 by engaging the vacuum pump 14 and the vacuum
valve 16 under the control of the process control module 30. The vacuum chamber
12 is preferably evacuated to a pressure of less than approximately 1320 Pa (10 Torr),
more preferably between approximately 25 to 270 Pa (0.2 to 2 Torr), and most
preferably between approximately 40 to 200 Pa (0.3 to 1.5 Torr).</p>
    <p num="0059">In an exemplary process, upon reaching a desired pressure in the vacuum
chamber 12, the process control module 30 signals the LF power module 22 to
energize the electrode 32 within the vacuum chamber 12. By applying a LF voltage
to the electrode 32, the LF power module 22 ionizes the residual gases in the vacuum
chamber 12, thereby creating 220 a gas discharge LF plasma inside the vacuum
chamber 12. This gas discharge LF plasma is formed from the residual gases in the 
vacuum chamber 12, which are primarily air and water vapor. Because this gas
discharge LF plasma is created 220 before the reactive agent is injected into the
vacuum chamber 12, this gas discharge LF plasma is typically called the "pre-injection"
plasma. The vacuum valve 14 is controllably opened and closed to
maintain a preset vacuum pressure during the pre-injection plasma step 220. The
pre-injection plasma heats the surfaces inside the vacuum chamber 12, including the
articles, thereby aiding the evaporation and removal of condensed water and other
absorbed gases from the vacuum chamber 12 and the articles. A similar pre-injection
plasma is described by Spencer, et al. in U.S. Patent Nos. 5,656,238 and 6,060,019,
which are incorporated by reference herein. In an exemplary process, the pre-injection
plasma is turned off after approximately 0 to 60 minutes. Other
embodiments that are compatible with the present invention do not include the
creation of the pre-injection plasma, or use multiple pre-injection plasmas. In still
other embodiments, the vacuum chamber 12 can be vented after the articles are
exposed to the pre-injection plasma.</p>
    <p num="0060">In the preferred process, upon reaching a desired chamber pressure, the
vacuum valve 16 is closed, and the reactive agent valve 20 is opened under the
control of the process control module 30, thereby injecting 230 reactive agent from
the reactive agent source 18 into the vacuum chamber 12 via the reactive agent line
19. In the preferred embodiment, the reactive agent comprises hydrogen peroxide,
which is injected in the form of a liquid which is then vaporized. The injected liquid
contains preferably from about 3% to 60% by weight of hydrogen peroxide, more
preferably from about 20% to 60% by weight of hydrogen peroxide, and most
preferably from about 30% to 60% by weight of hydrogen peroxide. The
concentration of hydrogen peroxide vapor in the vacuum chamber 12 may range from
0.125 to 20 mg of hydrogen peroxide per liter of chamber volume. The higher
concentrations of hydrogen peroxide will result in shorter sterilization times. Air or
inert gas such as argon, helium, nitrogen, neon, or xenon may be added to the
chamber with the hydrogen peroxide to maintain the pressure in the vacuum chamber
12 at the desired level. This injection 230 of reactive agent may occur as one or more
separate injections. </p>
    <p num="0061">Due to this injection 230 of reactive agent, the chamber pressure of the
preferred process rises to approximately 2000 Pa (15 Torr) or more. After
approximately 6 minutes into the injection stage 230, the reactive agent is permitted
to diffuse 240 completely and evenly throughout the vacuum chamber 12. After
approximately 1 - 45 minutes of diffusing 240, the reactive agent is substantially in
equilibrium inside the vacuum chamber 12. This diffusing 240 allows the reactive
species to diffuse through the packaging material of the articles, and come into close
proximity, if not contact, with the surfaces of the articles, thereby sterilizing the
articles. In other embodiments, the diffusion of the reactive agent can be immediately
followed by a vent of the vacuum chamber 12.</p>
    <p num="0062">The vacuum chamber 12 is then partially evacuated 250 by pumping out a
fraction of the reactive agent from the vacuum chamber 12 by controllably opening
the vacuum valve 16 under the control of the process control module 30. Once the
vacuum pressure within the vacuum chamber 12 has reached the desired pressure, the
vacuum valve 16 is controllably adjusted to maintain the desired pressure, and the
process control module 30 signals the LF power module 22 to energize the electrode
32 within the vacuum chamber 12. In the preferred embodiment in which the
reactive agent comprises hydrogen peroxide, the pressure of the hydrogen peroxide in
the vacuum chamber 12 is preferably less than approximately 1320 Pa (10 Torr),
more preferably between approximately 25 and 270 Pa (0.2 to 2 Torr), and most
preferably between approximately 40 and 200 Pa (0.3 to 1.5 Torr). By applying a LF
voltage to the electrode 32, the LF power module 22 generates 260 a reactive agent
LF plasma inside the vacuum chamber 12 by ionizing the reactive agent. The article
is exposed to the reactive agent LF plasma for a controlled period of time. In the
preferred embodiment, an additional cycle 275 is performed. Other embodiments
may omit this additional cycle 275, or may include further cycles.</p>
    <p num="0063">In both RF and LF plasmas, the components of the reactive agent plasma
include dissociation species of the reactive agent and molecules of the reactive agent
in excited electronic or vibrational states. For example, where the reactive agent
comprises hydrogen peroxide as in the preferred embodiment, the reactive agent
plasma likely includes charged particles such as electrons, ions, various free radicals 
(e.g., OH, O<sub>2</sub>H), and neutral particles such as ground state H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> molecules and
excited H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> molecules. Along with the ultraviolet radiation produced in the reactive
agent plasma, these reactive agent species have the potential to kill spores and other
microorganisms.</p>
    <p num="0064">Once created, the charged particles of the reactive agent plasma are
accelerated by the electric fields created in the vacuum chamber 12. Because of the
fluid communication between the first region 31 and the second region 33, some
fraction of the charged particles created in the first region 31 are accelerated to pass
from the first region 31 to the second region 33 which contains the articles.</p>
    <p num="0065">Charged particles passing from the first region 31 to the second region 33
have their trajectories and energies affected by the electric potential differential of the
sheath regions between the plasma and the walls of the vacuum chamber 12 and the
electrode 32. These sheath regions are created by all electron-ion plasmas in contact
with material walls, due to charged particles impinging from the plasma onto the
walls. Electrons, with their smaller mass and hence greater mobility, are lost from the
plasma to the wall before the much heavier and less mobile ions, thereby creating an
excessive negative charge density surrounding the walls and a corresponding voltage
differential which equalizes the loss rates of the electrons and the ions. This voltage
differential, or sheath voltage, accelerates electrons away from the wall surface, and
accelerates positive ions toward the wall surface.</p>
    <p num="0066">The sheath voltage varies for different plasma types, compositions, and
methods of production. For RF plasmas, the sheath voltage is typically 40% - 80% of
the RF voltage applied to the electrode 32. For example, for a root-mean-squared
(RMS) RF voltage of 140 V<sub>rms</sub> applied to the electrode 32 once the RF plasma is
established, the corresponding sheath voltage is approximately 55 - 110 V. An ion
entering the sheath region surrounding the electrode 32 will then be accelerated to an
energy of 55 - 110 eV. This acceleration of positive ions by the sheath voltage is the
basic principle behind semiconductor processing by RF plasmas.</p>
    <p num="0067">As described above, for the LF plasmas of the preferred embodiment of the
present invention, the voltage applied to the electrode 32 may be equal to or greater
than the ignition threshold voltage, which is typically 300 V. In addition, for LF 
plasmas, the sheath voltage is typically a higher percentage of the applied voltage
than for RF plasmas, so the sheath voltage of the preferred embodiment of the present
invention is then much higher than the sheath voltage for an RF plasma system. This
higher sheath voltage thereby accelerates the charged particles of the LF plasma to
much higher energies. Therefore, because the charged particles are accelerated to
higher energies, the charged particles of the LF plasma of the preferred embodiment
travel farther and interact more with the articles than do the charged particles of RF
plasma sterilizers.</p>
    <p num="0068">Since the LF electric field changes polarity twice each cycle, the direction of
the electric field acceleration on the charged particles reverses twice each cycle. For
charged particles in the first region 31, this oscillation of the direction of the
acceleration results in an oscillation of the position of the charged particles.
However, because of the fluid communication between the first region 31 and the
second region 33, some fraction of the charged particles are able to pass to the second
region 33 containing the articles from the first region 31 before the direction of the
electric field acceleration reverses.</p>
    <p num="0069">The fraction of the charged particles created in the reactive agent LF plasma
which enter the second region 33 is a function of the frequency of the applied electric
field. The charged particles have two components to their motion -- random thermal
speed and drift motion due to the applied electric field. The thermal speed, measured
by the temperature, is the larger of the two (typically approximately 10<sup>7</sup> - 10<sup>8</sup> cm/sec
for electrons), but it does not cause the charged particles to flow in any particular
direction. Conversely, the drift speed is directed along the electric field, resulting in
bulk flow of charged particles in or opposed to the direction of the applied electric
field. The magnitude of the drift speed is approximately proportional to the
magnitude of the applied electric field, and inversely proportional to the mass of the
charged particle. In addition, the magnitude of the drift speed is dependent on the gas
species and chamber pressure. For example, for typical operating parameters of gas
discharge plasma sterilizers, including an average electric field magnitude of
approximately 1 volt/cm, the drift speed for an electron formed in a gas discharge
plasma is typically approximately 10<sup>6</sup> cm/sec. </p>
    <p num="0070">A charged particle enters the second region 33 containing the articles only if it
reaches the second region 33 before the polarity of the applied electric field changes,
which would reverse the acceleration of the charged particle away from the electrode
32. For example, for an applied RF electric field with a frequency of 13.56 MHz, the
period of the electric field is approximately 7.4 x 10<sup>-8</sup> sec, so an electron only moves
a distance of approximately 3.7 x 10<sup>-3</sup> cm during the half-cycle or half-period before
the direction of the electric field changes and the electron is accelerated away from
the electrode 32. Due to their much larger masses, ions move much less than do
electrons. Where the first region 31 between the vacuum chamber 12 and the
electrode 32 is approximately 2.54 cm wide, as in the preferred embodiment, only a
fraction of the charged particles created by an RF plasma would actually reach the
second region 33 containing the articles.</p>
    <p num="0071">Conversely, for an applied LF electric field with a frequency of 60 Hz, the
period of the electric field is approximately 16.7 x 10<sup>-3</sup> sec, so an electron can move
approximately 8.35 x 10<sup>3</sup> cm before it is accelerated away from the electrode 32.
Therefore, the use of LF voltages to create the plasma in the sterilization system 10 of
the preferred embodiment results in more activity in the second region 33, as
compared to a plasma generated using RF voltages. This higher activity in LF
sterilizers likely contributes to the increased efficiency for the removal of residual
reactive species from the sterilized articles as compared to RF sterilizers.</p>
    <p num="0072">The plasma decay time, defined as a characteristic time for the plasma to be
neutralized after power is no longer applied, provides an approximate demarcation
between the LF and RF regimes. The plasma decay time is not known precisely, but
it is estimated to be approximately 10<sup>-4</sup> - 10<sup>-3</sup> sec for the plasma densities used in
sterilizer systems, such as the preferred embodiment of the present invention. This
plasma decay time corresponds to the time a charged particle exists before it is
neutralized by a collision with a surface or another plasma constituent, and is
dependent on the plasma species generated and the geometries of the various
components of the sterilization system 10. As described above, the LF regime is
characterized by a plasma which is extinguished and re-ignited twice each cycle, i.e.,
the half-period of the applied LF voltage is greater than the plasma decay time. 
Therefore, the sterilization system 10 is continually run at an applied voltage above
the ignition threshold voltage of the plasma in order to re-ignite the plasma. The
estimated approximate range of plasma decay times of 10<sup>-4</sup> - 10<sup>-3</sup> sec for many of the
plasmas compatible with the present invention then translates to an upper limit on the
low frequency regime of approximately 1 - 10 kHz. However, under certain
circumstances, higher frequencies can be tolerated.</p>
    <p num="0073">Alternatively, the upper limit of the low frequency regime may be defined as
the frequency at which the electron drift speed is too slow for an electron to traverse
the 2.54-cm-wide first region 31 during a half-period of the applied LF voltage.
Under typical operating geometries, this upper limit of the low frequency regime
would be approximately 200 kHz. For other geometries, the upper limit of the low
frequency regime can be correspondingly different.</p>
    <p num="0074">In the preferred method, the LF power module 22 remains energized for
approximately 2 - 15 minutes, during which the plasma removes excess residual
reactive species present on surfaces within the vacuum chamber 12, including on the
articles. There is a brief rise of the vacuum pressure upon generating 260 the plasma,
however, the majority of the residual removal step 270 is conducted at an
approximately constant vacuum pressure of 50 to 70 Pa (0.4 to 0.5 Torr). The
residual removal step 270 is ended by the process control module 30, which turns off
the LF power module 22, thereby quenching the plasma.</p>
    <p num="0075">After the residual removal step 270, the vacuum chamber 12 is vented 280 by
the process control module 30 which opens the vent valve 28, thereby letting in vent
gas from the vent 26 through the vent line 27 and the vent valve 28. In the preferred
process, the vacuum chamber 12 is then evacuated 290 to a pressure of approximately
40 to 105 Pa (0.3 to 0.8 Torr) to remove any remaining reactive agent which may be
present in the vacuum chamber 12. The vacuum chamber 12 is then vented again
300 to atmospheric pressure, and the sterilized articles are then removed 310 from the
vacuum chamber 12.</p>
    <p num="0076">The LF plasma provides a reduction of the amount of residual reactive agent
molecules remaining on the articles after the sterilization procedure is complete.
Where the reactive agent comprises hydrogen peroxide, the amount of residual 
hydrogen peroxide remaining on the sterilized articles is preferably less than
approximately 8000 ppm, more preferably less than approximately 5000 ppm, and
most preferably less than approximately 3000 ppm. In a comparison of the amount of
residual hydrogen peroxide remaining after a LF plasma sterilization as compared to a
RF plasma sterilization, nine polyurethane test samples were exposed to hydrogen
peroxide during a simulated sterilization cycle in both a LF sterilizer and a RF
sterilizer. Each sample was prepared by washing with Manuklenz® and drying prior
to sterilization to avoid any cross contamination. The nine samples were then
distributed uniformly across the top shelf of a standard industrial rack.</p>
    <p num="0077">A full LF sterilization cycle, which matched nearly exactly the conditions of a
standard RF sterilizer cycle, was used to perform the comparison. The full LF
sterilization cycle included a 20-minute exposure to a pre-injection plasma, a first 6-minute
hydrogen peroxide injection, a vent to atmosphere, a 2-minute diffusion, a
first 2-minute post-injection plasma, a second 6-minute hydrogen peroxide injection,
a vent to atmosphere, a 2-minute diffusion, a second 2-minute post-injection plasma,
and a vent to atmosphere. Two full LF sterilization cycles were performed and
compared to 
two full RF sterilization cycles. As seen in Table 1, all parameters other than the
post-injection plasma power were maintained as constant as possible from run to run.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">LF Run 1</entry><entry align="left">LF Run 2</entry><entry align="left">RF Run 1</entry><entry align="left">RF Run 2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Pre-injection plasma power</entry><entry align="left">727 W</entry><entry align="left">779 W</entry><entry align="left">751 W</entry><entry align="left">752 W</entry></row><row><entry align="left">First post-injection plasma power</entry><entry align="left">783 W</entry><entry align="left">874 W</entry><entry align="left">757 W</entry><entry align="left">756 W</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Second post-injection plasma power</entry><entry align="left">755 W</entry><entry align="left">893 W</entry><entry align="left">758 W</entry><entry align="left">758 W</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Chamber temp.</entry><entry align="left">45° C nom.</entry><entry align="left">45° C nom.</entry><entry align="left">45° C nom.</entry><entry align="left">45° C nom.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Injection system temp.</entry><entry align="left">65-75° C</entry><entry align="left">65-75° C</entry><entry align="left">65-75° C</entry><entry align="left">65-75° C</entry></row><row><entry align="left">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> concentration</entry><entry align="left">17 mg/l</entry><entry align="left">17 mg/l</entry><entry align="left">17 mg/l</entry><entry align="left">17 mg/l</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Chamber pressure during plasma</entry><entry align="left">50 Pa (0.4 Torr)</entry><entry align="left">50 Pa (0.4 Torr)</entry><entry align="left">50 Pa (0.4 Torr)</entry><entry align="left">50 Pa (0.4 Torr)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables>
Variations in the pre-plasma power were ± 3.5%, so the sample temperature was
approximately constant from run to run. The samples were then removed and the
residual analysis was performed.</p>
    <p num="0078">The LF sterilizer used to generate the LF plasma was operated at 60 Hz, and
<i>with an inductor of 500 mH and a capacitor of 13.6 µF. LF plasma power was</i>
determined by multiplying the voltage across the LF plasma by the current, then
averaging on an oscilloscope. The fluctuation level of the LF power was
approximately 10%. Table 2 illustrates the results of the comparison.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">LF Run 1</entry><entry align="left">LF Run 2</entry><entry align="left">RF Run 1</entry><entry align="left">RF Run 2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Average post-injection plasma power</entry><entry align="left">769 W</entry><entry align="left">884 W</entry><entry align="left">757 W</entry><entry align="left">757 W</entry></row><row><entry align="left">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> residuals (ppm)</entry><entry align="left">1973 ± 144</entry><entry align="left">1864 ± 75</entry><entry align="left">2682 ± 317</entry><entry align="left">2510 ± 203</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0079">Exposure to a LF post-injection plasma reduced the residual reactive species
more effectively than did exposure to a RF post-injection plasma of comparable
power. LF Run 1 had approximately 23% less residual hydrogen peroxide than either
RF Run 1 or RF Run 2, even though all had approximately the same post-injection
plasma power. The LF processes therefore resulted in less residual hydrogen peroxide
than did the corresponding RF process. </p>
    <p num="0080">The comparison of the two LF sterilization cycles illustrates that increased
plasma power results in a reduction of the hydrogen peroxide residuals. Furthermore,
the variation between samples, as indicated by the standard deviation of the residual
measurements, was significantly reduced in the LF process, thereby indicating an
increased uniformity as compared to the RF process.</p>
    <p num="0081">Although described above in connection with particular embodiments of the
present invention, it should be understood the descriptions of the embodiments are
illustrative of the invention and are not intended to be limiting. Various modifications
and applications may occur to those skilled in the art without departing from the true
spirit and scope of the invention as defined in the appended claims.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A sterilization system that applies low frequency power to a plasma
within a vacuum chamber to remove gas or vapor species from an article, the low
frequency power having a frequency less than or equal to approximately 200 kHz, the
sterilization system comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a switching module adapted to pulsate the low frequency power
applied to the plasma;</claim-text><claim-text>a low frequency power feedback control system for controllably
adjusting the low frequency power applied to the plasma, the low frequency
power feedback control system comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a power monitor adapted to produce a first signal indicative of the low
frequency power applied to the plasma within the vacuum chamber;</claim-text><claim-text>a power control module adapted to produce a second signal in
response to the first signal from the power monitor; and</claim-text><claim-text>a power controller adapted to adjust, in response to the second signal,
the low frequency power applied to the plasma to maintain a substantially
stable average low frequency power applied to the plasma while the article is
being processed.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The sterilization system as described in Claim 1, wherein the
switching module utilizes unipolar switching to pulsate the low frequency power
applied to the plasma.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The sterilization system as described in Claim 1, wherein the
switching module utilizes bipolar switching to pulsate the low frequency power
applied to the plasma.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The sterilization system as described in Claim 1, wherein the
switching module is further adapted to adjust pulse widths of the low frequency
power applied to the plasma in response to signals from the power control module,
thereby controlling the average low frequency power applied to the plasma.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The sterilization system as described in Claim 1, wherein the
switching module is further adapted to adjust times between pulses of the low
frequency power applied to the plasma in response to signals from the power control
module, thereby controlling the average low frequency power applied to the plasma.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The sterilization system as described in Claim 1, wherein the low
frequency power feedback control system further comprises a current monitor that is
adapted to produce a third signal indicative of a current applied to the plasma, and a
voltage monitor that is adapted to produce a fourth signal indicative of a voltage
applied across the plasma.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>The sterilization system as described in Claim 6, wherein the power
monitor is adapted to produce the first signal in response to the third signal and the
fourth signal.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The sterilization system as described in Claim 6, wherein the current
monitor comprises a current sensor, a first converter, and a first voltage amplifier.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>The sterilization system as described in Claim 8, wherein the current
monitor further comprises an over-current detector coupled to the power control
module.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>The sterilization system as described in Claim 6, wherein the voltage
monitor comprises a step-down transformer, a second converter, and a second voltage
amplifier.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>The sterilization system as described in Claim 1, wherein the power
control module comprises a power control processor.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>The sterilization system as described in Claim 11, wherein the power
control module further comprises a fault detector.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>The sterilization system as described in Claim 12, wherein the fault
detector is selected from the group consisting of an over-power detector and a thermal
switch.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>The sterilization system as described in Claim 11, wherein the power
control processor is coupled to the power controller, the power monitor, and the
current monitor.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>The sterilization system as described in Claim 1, wherein the power
control module is coupled to a user interface adapted to receive user input and to
transmit the user input to the power control module.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>The sterilization system as described in Claim 1, wherein the power
controller is adapted to adjust a duty cycle of the low frequency power applied to the
plasma in response to the second signal from the power control module.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>The sterilization system as described in Claim 1, wherein the power
controller is adapted to adjust an amplitude of the low frequency power applied to the
plasma in response to the second signal from the power control module.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="18">
      <claim-text>The sterilization system as described in Claim 1, wherein the low
frequency power has a frequency less than or equal to approximately 200 kHz .</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="19">
      <claim-text>The sterilization system as described in Claim 1, wherein the low
frequency power has a frequency from approximately 1 kHz to approximately 100
kHz.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="20">
      <claim-text>A method of controllably adjusting a low frequency power applied to a
plasma within a vacuum chamber of a sterilization system to remove gas or vapor
species from an article, the low frequency power having a frequency less than or
equal to approximately 200 kHz, the method comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>pulsating the low frequency power applied to the plasma;</claim-text><claim-text>monitoring the low frequency power applied to the plasma within the
vacuum chamber;</claim-text><claim-text>generating a first signal indicative of the low frequency power applied
to the plasma; and</claim-text><claim-text>adjusting the low frequency power applied to the plasma in response to
the first signal to maintain a substantially stable average low frequency power
applied to the plasma while the article is being processed.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="21">
      <claim-text>The method as described in Claim 20, wherein the pulsating of the low
frequency power applied to the plasma is unipolar.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="22">
      <claim-text>The method as described in Claim 20, wherein the pulsating of the low
frequency power applied to the plasma is bipolar.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="23">
      <claim-text>The method as described in Claim 20, wherein the adjusting of the low
frequency power applied to the plasma comprises adjusting pulse widths of the low
frequency power applied to the plasma.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="24">
      <claim-text>The method as described in Claim 20, wherein the adjusting of the low
frequency power applied to the plasma comprises adjusting times between pulses of
the low frequency power applied to the plasma.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="25">
      <claim-text>The method as described in Claim 20, wherein the monitoring of the
low frequency power applied to the plasma comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>monitoring a current applied to the plasma and generating a second
signal indicative of the current; and</claim-text><claim-text>monitoring a voltage applied across the plasma and generating a third
signal indicative of the voltage.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="26">
      <claim-text>The method as described in Claim 25, wherein the generating of the
first signal is in response to the second signal and the third signal.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="27">
      <claim-text>The method as described in Claim 20, wherein the adjusting of the low
frequency power applied to the plasma comprises adjusting a duty cycle of the low
frequency power applied to the plasma.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="28">
      <claim-text>The method as described in Claim 20, wherein the adjusting of the low
frequency power applied to the plasma comprises adjusting an amplitude of the low
frequency power applied to the plasma.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="29">
      <claim-text>The method as described in Claim 20, wherein the low frequency
power has a frequency less than or equal to approximately 200 kHz.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="30">
      <claim-text>The method as described in Claim 20, wherein the low frequency
power has a frequency from approximately 1 kHz to approximately 100 kHz.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
