<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1229076-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1229076" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="18890826" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020807">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1229076-A1" status="new" fvid="23516714">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1229076</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20020807</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02001948-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02001948</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020201</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001025918-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001025918</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010201</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A43B  17/00        20060101CLI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A43B  17/14        20060101ALI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   9/00        20060101ALI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   9/00        20060101CLI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/098       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/56        20060101ALI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  23/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  23/06        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  23/08        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08K   5/098+L23/04</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  23/08A1+B2</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L23:06</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L23:08A1</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Elastomerzusammensetzung für vernetzte Olefinschäume und ihre Verwendung</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Elastomic composition for preparing olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam and use thereof</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Compositions élastomérées pour la preparation de mousses oléfiniques et leur utilisation</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MITSUI CHEMICALS INC</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MITSUI CHEMICALS, INC.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Mitsui Chemicals, Inc.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>2-5, Kasumigaseki 3-chome, Chiyoda-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>CHOI KYUNG-MAN</name>
            <address>
              <country>KR</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SUEDA TAKANORI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YASAKA NAOTO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YOO CHONG-SUN</name>
            <address>
              <country>KR</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YOON JEONG-SIK</name>
            <address>
              <country>KR</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>CHOI, KYUNG-MAN</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SUEDA, TAKANORI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YASAKA, NAOTO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YOO, CHONG-SUN</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YOON, JEONG-SIK</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>CHOI, KYUNG-MAN</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Kukje-Packyang Apt. 7-1106, 791 DangKam-3-dong</street>
              <city>Pusanjin-ku, Pusan</city>
              <country>KR</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>SUEDA, TAKANORI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Mitsui Chemicals, Inc., 3, Chigusakaigan</street>
              <city>Ichihara-shi, Chiba</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>YASAKA, NAOTO</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Mitsui Chemicals, Inc., 3, Chigusakaigan</street>
              <city>Ichihara-shi, Chiba</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>YOO, CHONG-SUN</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Galak Apt. 203-804, HaDan-1-dong-Saha-ku</street>
              <city>Pusan</city>
              <country>KR</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>YOON, JEONG-SIK</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Kukje-Packyang Apt. 7-804, 791 DangKam-3-dong</street>
              <city>Pusanjin-ku, Pusan</city>
              <country>KR</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>HOFFMANN - EITLE</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Patent- und Rechtsanwälte Arabellastrasse 4</street>
              <city>81925 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>IT</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>The elastomeric composition for preparing an olefinic
elastomer crosslinked foam according to the present invention
contains an ethylene/α-olefin copolymer (A) having a specific
density and MFR, an organic peroxide (D), a crosslinking
assistant (E), a foaming agent (F), an organic metal compound
(G), andas necessary, a high pressure low density polyethylene
(B) having a specific MFR, and an ethylene/vinyl acetate
copolymer (C) having a specific amount of vinyl acetate and
a specific MFR. An olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam of
the present invention can be obtained by crosslinking and
foaming the above composition. Further, another olefinic
elastomer crosslinked foam of the present invention can be
obtained by a secondary compression of the above crosslinked
foam. The footwear part of the present invention is made of
these crosslinked foams. The present invention provides an
elastomeric composition for preparing an olefinic elastomer
crosslinked foam that can provide an olefinic elastorner
crosslinked foam having an Asker C hardness of 20 to 80, a
low specific gravity, a low compression set, and excellent
tear strength and impact resilience; and a crosslinked foam
made of this. Furthermore, the present invention provides
footwear parts made of the above crosslinked foam.</p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <heading>Field of the Invention</heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to an elastomeric
composition for preparing an olefinic elastomer crosslinked
foam and use thereof, and more specifically, an elastomeric
composition for preparing an olefinic elastomer crosslinked
foam that can provide an olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam
having an Asker C hardness of 20 to 80, a low specific gravity,
a low compression set (CS), and an excellent tear strength
and impact resilience, and to an olefinic elastomer crosslinked
foam made of this.</p>
    <heading>Description of the Related Art</heading>
    <p num="0002">Techniques using crosslinked foams to obtain a resin
having a low specific gravity, i.e. a light weight, a high
flexibility and a high mechanical strength are broadly applied
to interior and exterior building materials, automotive parts
such as interior materials or door glass runs, wrapping
materials, articles of daily use, etc. Such techniques are
used because mere foaming a resin for weight reduction leads 
to a reduction of mechanical strength, but, in contrast,
binding molecular chains by crosslinking reaction of a resin
enables weight reduction by foaming while avoiding reduction
of mechanical strength.</p>
    <p num="0003">In addition, resin crosslinked foams are also used for
soles (mainly, midsoles) of athletic shoes etc. This is
because materials are needed that are light and have a high
mechanical strength enough to avoid deformation due to
long-term use and withstand harsh use conditions.</p>
    <p num="0004">Conventionally, crosslinked foams of an ethylene/vinyl
acetate copolymer are used for soles and is publicly known.
However, such crosslinked foams, which are molded using an
ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymer composition, have a high
specific gravity and are insufficient in terms of a low
compression set, and therefore when used for a sole for example,
a problem arises that the sole is heavy and is compressed by
long-term use, so that mechanical strength such as impact
resilience is lost.</p>
    <p num="0005">National Publication of International Patent Application
No. 9-501447 and Japanese Patent Laid-Open No. 11-206406
describe a crosslinked foam using an ethylene/α-olefin
copolymer, and a crosslinked foam using a mixture of an
ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymer and an ethylene/α-olefin
copolymer, respectively. Some improvements in terms of a low 
specific gravity and a low compression set are attained, but
adequate performance has not been obtained in these inventions.</p>
    <p num="0006">Therefore, there is a need for an elastomeric composition
for preparing an olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam that can
provide an olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam having an Asker
Chardness of 20 to 80, a low specific gravity, a low compression
set (CS) and an excellent tear strength and impact resilience,
and a crosslinked foam made of this.</p>
    <p num="0007">The present invention intends to solve the above problems
accompanying the prior art, and an object of the present
invention is to provide an elastomeric composition for
preparing an olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam that can
provide an olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam having an Asker
C hardness of 20 to 80, a low specific gravity and a low
compression set (CS) and furthermore having excellent tear
strength and impact resilience, and a crosslinked foam made
of this.</p>
    <p num="0008">Another object of the present invention is to provide
a footwear part made of the above olefinic elastomer
crosslinked foam, such as a sandals and a sole, midsole, and
innersole of shoes.</p>
    <heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0009">The elastomeric composition for preparing an olefinic
elastomer crosslinked foam of the present invention comprises
an ethylene/α-olefin copolymer (A) having a density (ASTM D
1505) of 880 to 920 kg/m<sup>3</sup>, and a melt flow rate (ASTM D 1238,
190°C, 2.16 kg load), MFR<sub>2.16</sub> of 0.1 to 10 g/10 min; an organic
peroxide (D); a crosslinking assistant (E); a foaming agent
(F); and an organic metal compound (G) which is a compound
of metal selected from Groups 2 to 12 of the periodic table
and having at least two groups containing unsaturated carbon
bond and at least one atom selected from oxygen, sulfur and
nitrogen per one molecule.</p>
    <p num="0010">This elastomeric composition may further comprise, based
on 100 parts by weight of the ethylene/α-olefin copolymer (A) ,
5 to 100 parts by weight of a high pressure low density
polyethylene (B) having a melt flow rate (ASTM D 1238, 190°C,
2.16 kg load) of 0.1 to 50 g/10 min, and/or 5 to 1,900 parts
by weight of an ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymer (C) having
a vinyl acetate content of 10 to 30% by weight and a melt flow
rate (ASTM D 1238, 190°C, 2.16 kg load) of 0.1 to 50 g/10 min.</p>
    <p num="0011">The α-olefin in the above ethylene/α-olefin copolymer
(A) is usually an α-olefin having 3 to 10 carbon atoms.</p>
    <p num="0012">There may be used, as the above ethylene/α-olefin
copolymer (A), a mixture of two or more ethylene/α-olefin
copolymers having a molecular weight distribution (Mw/Mn) 
determined by gel permeation chromatography (GPC) of 1.5 to
4, and a ratio (MFR<sub>10</sub>/MFR<sub>2.16</sub>) of a melt flow rate (ASTM D 1238,
190°C, 2.16 kg load), MFR<sub>2.16</sub> to a melt flow rate (ASTM D 1238,
190°C, 10 kg load), MFR<sub>10</sub>, of 5 to 20.</p>
    <p num="0013">The above mixture of two or more of the ethylene/α-olefin
copolymers is preferably produced by blending or multistage
polymerization so that the molecular weight distribution
(Mw/Mn) determined by GPC can be within a range of 2.3 to 6.</p>
    <p num="0014">The above organic metal compound (G) generally has at
least two CH<sub>2</sub>=CH-CO-O- or CH<sub>2</sub>=C (CH<sub>3</sub>) -CO-O- groups per molecule .</p>
    <p num="0015">The above organic metal compound (G) is preferably an
organic zinc compound.</p>
    <p num="0016">The organic zinc compound is preferably zinc diacrylate
or zinc dimethacrylate.</p>
    <p num="0017">The above organic metal compound (G) is contained in the
above elastomeric composition in a proportion of 0.05 to 5
parts by weight based on 100 parts by weight of the total amount
of the ethylene/α-olefin copolymer (A) , the high pressure low
density polyethylene (B) and the ethylene/vinyl acetate
copolymer (C). However, since components (B) and (C) are
optional components, the amount of these components may be
0 part by weight.</p>
    <p num="0018">The olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam of the present
invention is obtained by crosslinking and foaming the above 
elastomeric composition for preparing an olefinic elastomer
crosslinked foam of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0019">The olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam of the present
invention may be a crosslinked foam obtained by a secondary
compression of the crosslinked foam of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0020">The secondary compression is usually performed under
conditions of a temperature of 130°C to 200°C, a load of 30
to 300 kgf/cm<sup>2</sup> for 5 to 60 minutes.</p>
    <p num="0021">These crosslinked foams desirably have a specific gravity
(JIS K 7222 (g/cm<sup>3</sup>)) of 0.05 to 0.25, a surface hardness (Asker
C hardness) of 20 to 80, and a gel fraction of 70% or more.</p>
    <p num="0022">The footwear part of the present invention is made of
the above olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam of the present
invention.</p>
    <p num="0023">Examples of the footwear parts include midsoles,
innersoles, soles, etc.</p>
    <heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
    <p num="0024">Now, the elastomeric composition for preparing an
olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam of the present invention
and a use thereof are described in detail.</p>
    <p num="0025">The elastomeric composition for preparing an olefinic
elastomer crosslinked foam of the present invention is an
uncrosslinked unfoamed composition which is to be crosslinked 
and foamed by heating, and it comprises an ethylene/α-olefin
copolymer (A), an organic peroxide (D), a crosslinking
assistant (E), a foaming agent (F), an organic metal compound
(G) , and as necessary, a high pressure low density polyethylene
(B) and an ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymer (C).</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Ethylene/α-olefin copolymer (A)</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0026">Ethylene/α-olefin copolymer (A) used in the present
invention is a low crystalline random copolymer composed of
ethylene and an α-olefin containing 3 to 10 carbon atoms, and
has a density (ASTM D 1505) of 880 to 920 kg/m<sup>3</sup> and a melt
flow rate (ASTM D 1238, 190°C, 2.16 kg load), MFR<sub>2.16</sub>, of 0.1
to 10 g/10 min, preferably 0.5 to 10 g/10 min, and more preferably
0.5 to 5 g/10 min.</p>
    <p num="0027">Moreover, the molecular weight distribution (Mw/Mn) of
ethylene/α-olefin copolymer (A) determined by gel permeation
chromatography (GPC) is preferably within a range of 1.5 to
4. By using an ethylene/α-olefin copolymer (A) having a
molecular weight distribution (Mw/Mn) within the above range,
a composition which is capable for giving an elastomer
crosslinked foam excellent in terms of high mechanical
strength and low compression set can be obtained.</p>
    <p num="0028">The above molecular weight distribution (Mw/Mn) was
determined using GPC-150C (Millipore) as follows. </p>
    <p num="0029">As a separation column, TSK GNH HT having a diameter of
72 mm and a length of 600 mm was used, the column temperature
was set at 140°C, and o-dichlorobenzene (Wako Pure Chemical
Industries, Ltd.) and 0.025% by weight BHT (Takeda Chemical
Industries, Ltd.) as an antioxidant were of used as a mobile
phase. 500 µl of the sample having a concentration of 0.1%
by weight, was poured into the column and transferred by the
mobile phase fed at a rate of 1.0 ml/min. A differential
refractometer was used as a detector. Using an EPR having
a known Mw and Mn as a standard sample, the molecular weight
was determined.</p>
    <p num="0030">The α-olefin to be copolymerized with ethylene is
preferably an α-olefin having 3 to 10 carbon atoms, and
examples of such α-olefins include propylene, 1-butene,
1-pentene, 1-hexene, 1-heptene, 1-octene, 1-nonene, 1-decene,
4-methyl-1-pentene, etc., andof these, propylene, 1-butene,
1-hexene, 4-methyl-1-pentene and 1-octene are particularly
preferable. These α-olefins are used singly or in combination
of two or more.</p>
    <p num="0031">The ethylene/α-olefin copolymer (A) contains a unit
derived from ethylene at an amount of usually 85 to 99 mole %,
preferably 85 to 98 mole %, and a unit derived from an α-olefin
(preferably, those having 3 to 10 carbon atoms) at an amount
of usually 1 to 15 mole %, preferably 2 to 15 mole %. </p>
    <p num="0032">The composition of the ethylene/α-olefin copolymer (A)
is generally determined by measuring <sup>13</sup>C-NMR spectrum of the
sample obtained by homogenously dissolving about 200 mg of
the ethylene/α-olefin copolymer in 1 ml of hexachlorobutadiene
in a 10 mm  sample tube under conditions of a temperature
of 120°C, a frequency of 25.05 MHz, a spectrum width of 1,500
Hz, a pulse-repetition time of 4.2 sec, and a pulse width of
6 µsec.</p>
    <p num="0033">In addition to the above units, the ethylene/α-olefin
copolymer (A) may contain units derived from other
polymerizable monomers to the extent that they do not impair
the objects of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0034">Examples of preferable ethylene/α-olefin copolymers (A)
include an ethylene/propylene random copolymer, an
ethylene/1-butene random copolymer, an
ethylene/propylene/1-butene random copolymer, an
ethylene/1-hexene random copolymer, an
ethylene/4-methyl-1-pentene random copolymer, an
ethylene/1-octene random copolymer, etc. These copolymers
may be used in combination of two or more.</p>
    <p num="0035">As for the flow properties of the ethylene/α-olefin
copolymer (A) used in the present invention, the ratio
(MFR<sub>10</sub>/MFR<sub>2.16</sub>) of a melt flow rate (ASTM D 1238, 190°C, 2.16 
kg load), MFR<sub>2.16</sub>, to a melt flow rate (ASTM D 1238, 190°C,
10 kg load), MFR<sub>10</sub>, is preferably within a range of 5 to 20.</p>
    <p num="0036">Furthermore, as the ethylene/α-olefin copolymer (A) , two
or more ethylene/α-olefin copolymers having different
composition and molecular weight can also be used in
combination. For example, the following composition is
preferably used, that is, one comprising: 5 to 95 parts by
weight of an ethylene/α-olefin copolymer (A-1) having a density
(ASTM D 1505) of 880 kg/m<sup>3</sup> to less than 900 kg/m<sup>3</sup>, a melt flow
rate (ASTM D 1238, 190°C, 2.16 kg load) of 0.1 to 50 g/10 min,
and a molecular weight distribution (Mw/Mn) determined by GPC
of 1.5 to 4; and 5 to 95 parts by weight of an ethylene/α-olefin
copolymer (A-2) having a density (ASTM D 1505) of 900 to 920
kg/m<sup>3</sup>, a melt flow rate (ASTM D 1238, 190°C, 2.16 kg load)
of 0.1 to 50 g/10 min, and a molecular weight distribution
(Mw/Mn) determined by GPC of 1.5 to 4 (the total amount of
both copolymers is 100 parts by weight). Two or more types
of these copolymers (A-1) and (A-2) can also be used.</p>
    <p num="0037">The molecular weight distribution (Mw/Mn) of the above
mixture of two or more of the ethylene/α-olefin copolymers
determined by GPC is preferably within a range of 2.3 to 6.</p>
    <p num="0038">The above ethylene/α-olefin copolymer (A) can be produced
by a previously known method involving the use of a vanadium,
titanium or metallocene catalyst. </p>
    <p num="0039">To obtain a composition composed of component (A-1) and
component (A-2), either a method of blending these components
or a method of polymerizing different compositions by
multistage polymerization may be selected.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">High pressure low density polyethylene (B)</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0040">High pressure low density polyethylene (B) that is
optionally used in the present invention, is a polyethylene
resin produced by radical polymerization of ethylene or both
ethylene and an α-olefin having 3 to 10 carbon atoms, using
a publicly known tubular reactor or an autoclave reactor, in
the presence of a radical polymerization catalyst under high
pressure.</p>
    <p num="0041">The α-olefin to be copolymerized with ethylene is an
α-olefin having 3 to 10 carbon atoms, and examples of such
α-olefins include propylene, 1-butene, 1-pentene, 1-hexene,
1-heptene, 1-octene, 1-nonene, 1-decene, 4-methyl-1-pentene,
etc., and of these, propylene, 1-butene, 1-hexene,
4-methyl-1-pentene and 1-octene are preferable. These
α-olefins are used singly or in combination of two or more.</p>
    <p num="0042">The high pressure low density polyethylene (B) may contain
units derived from an α-olefin having 3 to 10 carbon atoms
at an amount of less than 1 mole %. </p>
    <p num="0043">The composition of the high pressure low density
polyethylene (B) is determined by the same measurement method
as for the composition of the ethylene/α-olefin copolymer (A)
stated above.</p>
    <p num="0044">The density (ASTM D 1505) of the high pressure low density
polyethylene (B) is usually 910 to 930 kg/m<sup>3</sup>, preferably 915
to 930 kg/m<sup>3</sup>, and more preferably 915 to 925 kg/m<sup>3</sup>.</p>
    <p num="0045">The melt flow rate (MFR; ASTM D 1238, 190°C, 2.16 kg load)
of the high pressure low density polyethylene (B) is within
a range of 0.1 to 50 g/10 min, preferably 0.5 to 20 g/10 min,
and more preferably 0.5 to 10 g/10 min. When the melt flow
rate is within the above range, a composition with excellent
moldability, which can provide a high strength crosslinked
foam, can be obtained.</p>
    <p num="0046">The high pressure low density polyethylene (B) is used,
as necessary, in a proportion of 5 to 100 parts by weight,
preferably 10 to 70 parts by weight, and more preferably 15
to 45 parts by weight based on 100 parts by weight of the
ethylene/α-olefin copolymer (A). When the high pressure low
density polyethylene (B) is used in the above proportion, an
elastomeric composition that can provide crosslinked foam
having high strength and excellent tear strength can be
obtained. </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymer (C)</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0047">The ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymer (C), that is
optionally used in the present invention, is obtained by
copolymerization of ethylene and vinyl acetate.</p>
    <p num="0048">The ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymer (C) contains 10 to
30% by weight, preferably 15 to 30% by weight, and more
preferably 15 to 25% by weight of vinyl acetate unit.</p>
    <p num="0049">The melt flow rate (MFR; ASTM D 1238, 190°C, 2.16 kg load)
of the ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymer (C) is within a range
of 0.1 to 50 g/10 min, preferably 0.5 to 20 g/10 min, and more
preferably 0.5 to 10 g/10 min.</p>
    <p num="0050">The ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymer (C) is used, as
necessary, in a proportion of more than 0 part by weight to
1, 900 parts by weight, preferably 5 to 1, 900 parts by weight,
based on 100 parts by weight of the ethylene/α-olefin copolymer
(A). When the ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymer (C) is used
in the above proportion, an elastomeric composition that can
provide a crosslinked foam having excellent tear strength can
be obtained.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Organic peroxide (D)</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0051">Examples of organic peroxides (D) used as a crosslinking
agent in the present invention include dicumyl peroxide,
di-t-butyl peroxide, 2,5-dimethyl-2,5-di-(t-butyl 
peroxy)hexane, 2,5-dimethyl-2,5-di-(t-butyl
peroxy)hexyne-3, 1,3-bis(t-butyl peroxy isopropyl)benzene,
1,1-bis(t-butyl peroxy)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane,
n-butyl-4,4-bis(t-butyl peroxy)valerate, benzoyl peroxide,
p-chlorobenzoyl peroxide, 2,4-dichlorobenzoyl peroxide,
t-butyl peroxy benzoate, t-butyl perbenzoate, t-butyl peroxy
isopropyl carbonate, diacetyl peroxide, lauroyl peroxide,
t-butyl cumyl peroxide, etc.</p>
    <p num="0052">In the present invention, the organic peroxide (D) is
used in a proportion of usually 0.1 to 1.5 parts by weight,
preferably 0.2 to 1.0 parts by weight, based on 100 parts by
weight of the total amount of the ethylene/α-olefin copolymer
(A), the high pressure low density polyethylene (B) and the
ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymer (C). When the organic
peroxide (D) is used in the above proportion together with
a crosslinking assistant (E), a crosslinked foam having an
appropriate crosslinked structure can be obtained.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Crosslinking assistant (E)</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0053">Examples of crosslinking assistants (E) used in the
present invention include peroxy crosslinking assistants such
as sulfur, p-quinone dioxime, p,p' -dibenzoyl quinone dioxime,
N-methyl-N-4-dinitrosoaniline, nitrosobenzene,
diphenylguanidine and 
trimethylolpropane-N,N'-m-phenylenedimaleimide,
divinylbenzene, triallyl cyanurate (TAC) and triallyl
isocyanurate (TAIC). Moreover, the examples also include
multifunctional methacrylate monomers such as ethylene glycol
dimethacrylate, diethylene glycol dimethacrylate,
polyethylene glycol dimethacrylate, trimethylolpropane
trimethacrylate and allyl methacrylate, and multifunctional
vinyl monomers such as vinyl butylate and vinyl stearate. Of
these, triallyl cyanurate (TAC) and triallyl isocyanurate
(TAIC) are preferable.</p>
    <p num="0054">In the present invention, the crosslinking assistant (E)
as stated above is desirably used in an amount where the weight
ratio [(E)/(D)] of the crosslinking assistant (E) to the
organic peroxide (D) is 1/30 to 5/1, preferably 1/20 to 3/1,
and more preferably 1/15 to 2/1.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Foaming agent (F)</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0055">Examples of foaming agents (F) used in the present
invention include organic pyrolytic foaming agents such as
azodicarbonamide (ADCA),
N,N'-dinitrosopentamethylenetetramine,
4,4'-oxybis(benzenesulfonyl hydrazide),
diphenylsulfone-3,3'-disulfonyl hydrazide,
p-toluenesulfonyl semicarbazide and trihydrazinotriazine, 
and inorganic pyrolytic foaming agents such as sodium hydrogen
carbonate, sodium carbonate, ammonium hydrogen carbonate and
ammonium carbonate. Of these, azodicarbonamide (ADCA) and
sodium hydrogen carbonate are particularly preferable.</p>
    <p num="0056">The foaming agent (F) is used in the present invention
in a proportion of usually 3 to 20 parts by weight, preferably
5 to 15 parts by weight, based on 100 parts by weight of the
total amount of the ethylene/α-olefin copolymer (A) , the high
pressure low density polyethylene (B) and the ethylene/vinyl
acetate copolymer (C). When the foaming agent (F) is used
in the above proportion, a foamed product having a high
expansion ratio and a closed cell ratio can be obtained. The
amount of the foaming agent (F) is determined considering the
expansion ratio of the crosslinked foam.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Organic metal compound (G)</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0057">The organic metal compound (G) used in the present
invention has, per one molecule, at least two groups containing
unsaturated carbon bond and at least one atom selected from
oxygen, sulfur and nitrogen.</p>
    <p num="0058">The organic metal compound (G) is a compound of metal
selected from Groups 2 to 12 of the periodic table. Among
them, metals of Groups 3 to 12 are classified into transition
metal. That is, compounds of metals of Groups 3 to 12 are 
organic transition metal compounds. In the present invention,
preferred metals are Groups 2 and 12, more preferred are Mg
and Zn, and
particularly preferred is Zn.</p>
    <p num="0059">The group containing unsaturated carbon bond and at least
one atom selected from oxygen, sulfur and nitrogen is
preferably a group having a structure wherein oxygen atom,
sulfur atom or nitrogen atom is directly bonded to the metal
atom, more preferably unsaturated aliphatic carboxyl group,
and particularly CH<sub>2</sub>=CH-CO-O- and CH<sub>2</sub>=C(CH<sub>3</sub>)-CO-O-.</p>
    <p num="0060">The organic metal compound (G) used in the present
invention has at least two CH<sub>2</sub>=CH-CO-O- or CH<sub>2</sub>=C(CH<sub>3</sub>)-CO-O-
groups per molecule, and a zinc compound is preferably used
as an organic metal compound. Specifically, zinc diacrylate
(ZDA) or zinc dimethacrylate (ZDMA) represented by the
respective formulas shown below is preferable:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/">(CH<sub>2</sub>=CH-CO-O-)<sub>2</sub>Zn</st32:che><st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/">(CH<sub>2</sub>=C(CH<sub>3</sub>)-CO-O-)<sub>2</sub>Zn</st32:che></p>
    <p num="0061">ZDA may simply be called "zinc acrylate". Similarly,
ZDMA may simply be called "zinc methacrylate".</p>
    <p num="0062">The organic metal compounds(G) include those formed in
compositionbyareactionduringmelt-extrusionof, for example,
metal oxide such as zinc oxide and organic compound such as 
acrylic acid and methacrylic acid together with the
aforementioned components (A) to (F).</p>
    <p num="0063">The above organic metal compound (G) is used in a
proportion of usually 0.05 to 5 parts by weight, preferably
0.05 to 4 parts by weight, more preferably 0.1 to 2 parts by
weight, based on 100 parts by weight of the total amount of
the ethylene/α-olefin copolymer (A), the high pressure low
density polyethylene (B) and the ethylene/vinyl acetate
copolymer (C). When the organic metal compound (G) is used
in the above proportion, foaming cells become more fine and
homogeneous since the gel fraction in the obtained crosslinked
foam increases. As a result, mechanical properties of the
crosslinked foam such as compression set, tear strength and
impact resilience are enhanced.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0064">The olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam of the present
invention can be obtained by crosslinking and foaming the
above-stated elastomeric composition for preparing
an olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam of the present
invention, which is usually performed under conditions of a
temperature of 130°C to 200°C and a load of 30 to 300 kgf/cm<sup>2</sup>
for 10 to 90 minutes. However, the time period of the crossing 
and foaming can be altered appropriately beyond the
above-defined range, depending on the thickness of a mold.</p>
    <p num="0065">Moreover, the olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam of the
present invention may be a crosslinked foam obtained by
compression molding of the formed article obtained by
crosslinking and foaming under the above conditions, under
the following conditions: a temperature of 130°C to 200°C,
a loading of 30 to 300 kgf/cm<sup>2</sup>, and a compression ratio of
1.1 to 3, preferably 1.3 to 2 for 5 to 60 minutes.</p>
    <p num="0066">These crosslinked foams have a specific gravity (JIS K
7222) of 0.05 to 0.25, a surface hardness (Asker C hardness;
JIS S 6050) of 20 to 80, and a gel fraction of 70% or more,
usually 80 to 99%.</p>
    <p num="0067">The olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam of the present
invention having the above properties has a low compression
set, high tear strength and high impact resilience.</p>
    <p num="0068">The gel fraction (gel content = xylene-insoluble
fraction) is determined as follows:</p>
    <p num="0069">An olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam sample was weighed
and cut into small pieces, and then the obtained pieces and
xylene were placed into a closed container and refluxed for
3 hours.</p>
    <p num="0070">Subsequently, the sample was placed on a filter for
absolute drying. The weight of the dried residue minus the 
weight of xylene-insoluble components (e.g. a filler, abulking
agent, a pigment, etc.) other than polymeric components is
defined as "corrected final weight (Y)".</p>
    <p num="0071">The weight of the sample minus both the weight of
xylene-soluble components (e.g. a stabilizer etc.) other than
polymeric components and the weight of xylene-insoluble
components (e.g. a filler, a bulking agent, a pigment, etc.)
other than polymeric components is defined as "corrected
initial weight (X)".</p>
    <p num="0072">Now, gel content (xylene-insoluble fraction) is
determined by the following formula:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">Gel fraction [% by weight] = [corrected final weight (Y)]<st32:break type="required"/>
divided by [corrected initial weight (X)] × 100</st32:df></p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Preparation of olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0073">The olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam of the present
invention can be prepared, for an example, by the following
method.</p>
    <p num="0074">The above-stated various components of the elastomeric
composition for preparing an olefinic elastomer crosslinked
foam of the present invention are mixed with a Henschel mixer,
and the obtained mixture is then subjected to melt mixing with
a Banbury mixer, a roll or an extruder. In this melt mixing
process, the mixture should be mixed and kneaded under the 
decomposition temperature of the foaming agent (F) and the
organic peroxide (D) as a crosslinking agent. More
specifically, the mixture should be mixed and kneaded under
a condition where the temperature of the composition in a molten
state is set at 100°C to 140°C, so that the composition becomes
homogeneous.</p>
    <p num="0075">In addition to the above-described ethylene/α-olefin
copolymer (A), high pressure low density polyethylene (B),
ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymer (C), organic peroxide (D),
crosslinkingassistant (E) , foaming agent (F) and organicmetal
compound (G), the composition of the present invention may
optionally include fillers such as talc, calcium carbonate,
aluminum hydroxide and magnesium hydroxide, or various
additives such as a heat stabilizer, a weathering stabilizer,
a flame retardant, an absorbent for hydrochloric acid, a
pigment, a lubricant and a slip agent to the extent that they
do not impair the object of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0076">A sheet of the elastomeric composition for preparing an
olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam of the present invention
can be obtained, for example, sheeting mixture obtained by
the above mixing and kneading process by a calendaring machine,
pressing machine or T-die extruder. In this sheet forming
process, the mixture should be sheet formed under the
decomposition temperature of foaming agent (F) and organic 
peroxide (D). More specifically, the mixture should be sheet
formed under a condition where the temperature of the
composition in a molten state is set at 100°C to 140°C.</p>
    <p num="0077">The sheeted composition obtained by the above sheet
forming process is cut to size within a ratio range of 1.0
to 1.2 time based on the capacity of a mold kept at a temperature
of 130 °C to 200°C, and then the piece is inserted into the
mold. The primary crosslinked foam is prepared by process
comprising melting the composition under conditions of a
clamping pressure of 30 to 300 kgf/cm<sup>2</sup> and a retention time
of 10 to 90 minutes, performing crosslinking reaction and
decomposition of foaming agent, and opening the mold to foam
the composition.</p>
    <p num="0078">The form of the above mold used for forming the crosslinked
foaming is not particularly limited, but generally a mold
having a form from which a sheet can be obtained is used. This
mold used for forming the crosslinked foaming should have a
fully closed structure so that molten resin and gases generated
by decomposition of the foaming agent do not escape . Moreover,
a retaining mold preferably has a taper inside for release
of the resin from the mold.</p>
    <p num="0079">The primary crosslinked foam obtained by the above method
is then formed to a predetermined shape by compression molding.
The conditions for this compression molding are: a mold 
temperature of 130°C to 200°C, a clamping pressure of 30 to
300 kgf/cm<sup>2</sup>, a compression time of 5 to 60 minutes, and a
compression ratio within a range of 1.1 to 3.0.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Footwear parts</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0080">The footwear parts of the present invention is made of
the olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam of the present
invention described above.</p>
    <p num="0081">Examples of the footwear parts include sandals and the
soles, midsoles, and innersoles of shoes.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EFFECT OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0082">The present invention provides an elastomeric
composition for preparing an olefinic elastomer crosslinked
foam that can provide an olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam
having an Asker C hardness of 20 to 80, a low specific gravity,
a low compression set (CS), an excellent tear strength and
impact resilience, and crosslinked foam made of this.</p>
    <p num="0083">Moreover, the present invention provides footwear parts
made of the above olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam, e.g.
sandals, and soles, midsoles, and innersoles of shoes.</p>
    <heading>Examples</heading>
    <p num="0084">The present invention will be further described in the
following examples. The examples are provided for
illustrative purposes only, and are not intended to limit the
scope of the invention.</p>
    <p num="0085">For each of the crosslinked foams obtained in the Examples
and Comparative examples, specific gravity, compression set,
tear strength, Asker C hardness (surface hardness) and impact
resilience were determined by the following method. Moreover,
the gel fraction (gel content) was determined by the
above-stated method.</p>
    <heading>(1) Specific gravity</heading>
    <p num="0086">Specific gravity was determined according to JIS K 7222.</p>
    <heading>(2) Compression set</heading>
    <p num="0087">A compression set test was carried out under conditions
of 50°C × 6 hrs and a compression amount of 50% to determine
compression set (CS), in accordance with JIS K 6301.</p>
    <heading>(3) Tear strength</heading>
    <p num="0088">A tear strength test was carried out at a pulling rate
of 100 mm/min to determine tear strength, in accordance with
BS5131-2.6.</p>
    <heading>(4) Asker C hardness</heading>
    <p num="0089">Asker C hardness was determined according to "Method for
carrying out a spring hardness test (type C test)" described
in attachment 2 of JIS K7312-1996. </p>
    <heading>(5) Impact resilience</heading>
    <p num="0090">Impact resilience was determined according to JIS K6255.</p>
    <p num="0091">Ethylene/α-olefin copolymers used in the Examples and
Comparative examples are as follows:
<sl><li>(1) Ethylene/1-butene copolymer (A1)

MFR (ASTM D 1238, 190°C, 2.16 kg load) = 0.5 g/10 min

Density (ASTM D 1505) = 885 kg/m<sup>3</sup>

Mw/Mn = 2.0

MFR<sub>10</sub>/MFR<sub>2.16</sub> = 6.0</li><li>(2) Ethylene/1-butene copolymer (A2)

MFR (ASTM D 1238, 190°C, 2.16 kg load) = 0.5 g/10 min

Density (ASTM D 1505) = 885 kg/m<sup>3</sup>

Mw/Mn = 2.1

MFR<sub>10</sub>/MFR<sub>2.16</sub> = 10.4</li><li>(3) Ethylene/1-butene copolymer (A3)

MFR (ASTM D 1238, 190°C, 2.16 kg load) = 3.6 g/10 min

Density (ASTM D 1505) = 895 kg/m<sup>3</sup>

Mw/Mn = 2.1

MFR<sub>10</sub>/MFR<sub>2.16</sub> = 5.7</li><li>(4) Ethylene/1-butene copolymer (A4)

MFR (ASTM D 1238, 190°C, 2.16 kg load) = 3.6 g/10 min

Density (ASTM D 1505) = 895 kg/m<sup>3</sup>

Mw/Mn = 2.0

MFR<sub>10</sub>/MFR<sub>2.16</sub> = 8.3 </li><li>(5) Ethylene/1-butene copolymer (A5)

MFR (ASTM D 1238, 190°C, 2.16 kg load) = 1.2 g/10 min

Density (ASTM D 1505) = 905 kg/m<sup>3</sup>

Mw/Mn = 2.1

MFR<sub>10</sub>/MFR<sub>2.16</sub> = 5.9</li><li>(6) Ethylene/1-hexene copolymer (A6)

MFR (ASTM D 1238, 190°C, 2.16 kg load) = 1.3 g/10 min

Density (ASTM D 1505) = 905 kg/m<sup>3</sup>

Mw/Mn = 3.0

MFR<sub>10</sub>/MFR<sub>2.16</sub> = 6.5</li></sl></p>
    <heading>[Example 1]</heading>
    <p num="0092">25 parts by weight of the above ethylene/1-butene
copolymer (A1), 45 parts by weight of the above
ethylene/1-butene copolymer (A3), 30 parts by weight of the
above ethylene/1-hexene copolymer (A6), 3 parts by weight of
zinc oxide, 1 part by weight of stearic acid, 4 parts by weight
of titanium white, 0.6 parts by weight of dicumyl peroxide,
0.15 parts by weight of triallyl cyanurate, 7.0 parts by weight
of azodicarbonamide and 0.4 parts by weight of zinc acrylate
were mixed and kneaded for 10 minutes with twin rolls having
a roll surface temperature of 120°C, and the mixture was then
molded into a sheet shape. </p>
    <p num="0093">After being filled in a press mold, the obtained sheet
was pressurized and heated under conditions of 150 kg/cm<sup>2</sup>,
155°C and 30 minutes to obtain the primary crosslinked foam.
The size of the press mold was 15 mm in thickness, 150 mm in
length and 200 mm in width.</p>
    <p num="0094">Then, the primary crosslinked foam was compression molded
under conditions of 155°C, 150 kg/cm<sup>2</sup> and 10 minutes to obtain
the secondary crosslinked foam. The size of the thus obtained
secondary crosslinked foam was 15 mm in thickness, 160 mm in
length and 250 mm in width.</p>
    <p num="0095">Subsequently, the specific gravity, compression set,
tear strength, Asker C hardness, impact resilience and gel
fraction of the secondary crosslinked foam were determined
according to the above-described methods. The results are
shown in Table 1.</p>
    <heading>[Example 2]</heading>
    <p num="0096">Example 2 was carried out according to the same method
as Example 1 with the exception that 25 parts by weight of
ethylene/1-butene copolymer (A2) was used instead of 25 parts
by weight of ethylene/1-butene copolymer (A1) and that 45 parts
by weight of ethylene/1-butene copolymer (A4) was used instead
of 45 parts by weight of ethylene/1-butene copolymer (A3).
The results are shown in Table 1. </p>
    <heading>[Example 3]</heading>
    <p num="0097">18.8 parts by weight of the above ethylene/1-butene
copolymer (A1), 50 parts by weight of the above
ethylene/1-butene copolymer (A3), 31.2 parts by weight of the
above ethylene/1-hexene copolymers (A6), 25 parts by weight
of the above high pressure low density polyethylene [HPLDPE;
density (ASTM D 1505) = 920 kg/m<sup>3</sup>, MFR (ASTM D 1238, 190°C,
2.16 kg load) = 3.0 g/10 min], 3 parts by weight of zinc oxide,
1 part by weight of stearic acid, 4 parts by weight of titanium
white, 0.6 parts by weight of dicumyl peroxide, 0.15 parts
by weight of triallyl cyanurate, 7.0 parts by weight of
azodicarbonamide and 0.4 parts by weight of zinc acrylate were
mixed and kneaded for 10 minutes with twin rolls having a roll
surface temperature of 120°C, and the mixture was then molded
into a sheet shape.</p>
    <p num="0098">The obtained sheet was filled in a press mold, and then
was pressurized and heated under conditions of 150 kg/cm<sup>2</sup>,
155°C and 30 minutes to obtain the primary crosslinked foam.
The size of the press mold was 15 mm in thickness, 150 mm in
length and 200 mm in width.</p>
    <p num="0099">Then, the primary crosslinked foam was compression molded
under conditions of 155°C, 150 kg/cm<sup>2</sup> and 10 minutes to obtain
the secondary crosslinked foam. The size of the thus obtained 
secondary crosslinked foam was 15 mm in thickness, 160 mm in
length and 250 mm in width.</p>
    <p num="0100">Subsequently, the specific gravity, compression set,
tear strength, Asker C hardness, impact resilience and gel
fraction of the secondary crosslinked foam were determined
according to the above-described methods. The results are
shown in Table 1.</p>
    <heading>[Comparative example 1]</heading>
    <p num="0101">Comparative example 1 was carried out in the same manner
as Example 1 with the only exception that zinc acrylate was
not used therein. The results are shown in Table 1. <img id="img-00300001" orientation="unknown" wi="135" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00300001.tif" inline="no" he="233"/></p>
    <heading>[Example 4]</heading>
    <p num="0102">33.3 parts by weight of the above ethylene/1-butene
copolymer (A3), 66.7 parts by weight of the above
ethylene/1-hexene copolymer (A6), 122 parts by weight of
ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymer [EVA; vinyl acetate content
= 21% by weight, MFR (ASTM D 1238, 190°C, 2.16 kg load) = 1.5
g/10 min], 3 parts by weight of zinc oxide, 1 part by weight
of stearic acid, 4 parts by weight of titanium white, 0.6 parts
by weight of dicumyl peroxide, 0.15 parts by weight of triallyl
cyanurate, 6.5 parts by weight of azodicarbonamide and 0.4
parts by weight of zinc acrylate were mixed and kneaded for
10 minutes with twin rolls having a roll surface temperature
of 120°C, and the mixture was then molded into a sheet shape.</p>
    <p num="0103">The obtained sheet was filled in a press mold, and then
was pressurized and heated under conditions of 150 kg/cm<sup>2</sup>,
155°C and 30 minutes to obtain the primary crosslinked foam.
The size of the press mold was 15 mm in thickness, 150 mm in
length and 200 mm in width.</p>
    <p num="0104">Then, the primary crosslinked foam was compression molded
under conditions of 155°C, 150 kg/cm<sup>2</sup> and 10 minutes to obtain
the secondary crosslinked foam. The size of the thus obtained
secondary crosslinked foam was 15 mm in thickness, 160 mm in
length and 250 mm in width.</p>
    <p num="0105">Subsequently, the specific gravity, compression set,
tear strength, Asker C hardness, impact resilience and gel 
fraction of the secondary crosslinked foam were determined
according to the above-described methods. The results are
shown in Table 2.</p>
    <heading>[Example 5]</heading>
    <p num="0106">Example 5 was carried out in the same manner as Example
4 with the only exception that 66.7 parts by weight of
ethylene/1-butene copolymer (A5) was used instead of 66 . 7 parts
by weight of ethylene/1-hexene copolymer (A6). The results
are shown in Table 2.</p>
    <heading>[Comparative example 2]</heading>
    <p num="0107">Comparative example 2 was carried out in the same manner
as Example 4 with the only exception that zinc acrylate was
not used therein. The results are shown in Table 2.</p>
    <heading>[Comparative example 3]</heading>
    <p num="0108">Comparative example 3 was carried out in the same manner
as Example 5 with the only exception that zinc acrylate was
not used therein. The results are shown in Table 2. <img id="img-00330001" orientation="unknown" wi="118" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00330001.tif" inline="no" he="230"/></p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>An elastomeric composition for preparing an olefinic
elastomer crosslinked foam, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>an ethylene/α-olefin copolymer (A) which has a density
(ASTM D 1505) of 880 to 920 kg/m3, and a melt flow rate (ASTM
D 1238, 190°C, 2.16 kg load), MFR2.16, of 0.1 to 10 g/10 min;</claim-text><claim-text>an organic peroxide (D);</claim-text><claim-text>a crosslinking assistant (E);</claim-text><claim-text>a foaming agent (F); and</claim-text><claim-text>an organic metal compound (G) which is a compound of metal
selected from Groups 2 to 12 of the periodic table, and having
at least two groups containing unsaturated carbon bond and
at least one atom selected from oxygen, sulfur and nitrogen
per one molecule.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The elastomeric composition according to claim 1 further
comprising, based on 100 parts by weight of said
ethylene/α-olefin copolymer (A), 5 to 100 parts by weight of
a high pressure low density polyethylene (B) having a melt
flow rate (ASTM D 1238, 190°C, 2.16 kg load) of 0.1 to 50 g/10
min, and/or 5 to 1,900 parts by weight of an ethylene/vinyl
acetate copolymer (C) having a vinyl acetate content of 10
to 30% by weight and a melt flow rate (ASTM D 1238, 190°C,
2.16 kg load) of 0.1 to 50 g/10 min.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The elastomeric composition according to claim 1 or 2,
wherein the α-olefin in said ethylene/α-olefin copolymer (A)
is an α-olefin 3 to 10 carbon atoms.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The elastomeric composition according to any one of claims
1 to 3, wherein there is used, as said ethylene/α-olefin
copolymer (A), a mixture of two or more ethylene/α-olefin
copolymers, having a molecular weight distribution (Mw/Mn)
determined by gel permeation chromatography (GPC) within a
range of 1.5 to 4, and a ratio (MFR10/MFR2.16) of a melt flow
rate (ASTM D 1238, 190°C, 2.16 kg load), MFR2.16 to a melt flow
rate (ASTM D 1238, 190°C, 10 kg load), MFR10 within a range
of 5 to 20.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The elastomeric composition according to claim 4, wherein
said mixture of two or more of the ethylene/α-olefin
copolymers is produced by blending or multistage
polymerization so that it has a molecular weight distribution
(Mw/Mn) determined by GPC within a range of 2.3 to 6.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The elastomeric composition according to claim 1, wherein
said organic metal compound (G) has at least two CH2=CH-CO-O-
or CH2=C(CH3)-CO-O- groups per molecule.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>The elastomeric composition according to claim 6, wherein
said organic metal compound (G) is an organic zinc compound.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The elastomeric composition according to claim 7, wherein
said organic zinc compound is zinc diacrylate or zinc
dimethacrylate.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>The elastomeric composition according to any one of claims
1 to 8, which contains 0.05 to 5 parts by weight of said organic
metal compound (G) based on 100 parts by weight of the total
amount of the ethylene/α-olefin copolymer (A), the high
pressure low density polyethylene (B) and the ethylene/vinyl
acetate copolymer (C).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>An olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam, which is obtained
by crosslinking and foaming the elastomeric composition for
preparing olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam according to
any one of claims 1 to 9.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>An olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam, which is obtained
by a secondary compression of the crosslinked foam according
to claim 10.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>The olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam according to
claim 11, wherein said secondary compression is performed under
conditions of a temperature of 130°C to 200°C and a load of
30 to 300 kgf/cm2 for 5 to 60 minutes.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>The olefinic elastomer crosslinked foam according to any
one of claims 10 to 12 having a specific gravity (JIS K 7222)
of 0.05 to 0.25, a surface hardness (Asker C hardness) of 20
to 80, and a gel fraction of 70% or more.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>A footwear part, which is made of the crosslinked foam
according to any one of claims 10 to 13.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>The footwear part according to claim 14, which is a midsole,
innersole or sole.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
