<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1231222-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1231222" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="18897967" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020814">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1231222-A1" status="new" fvid="23513982">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1231222</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20020814</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02250885-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02250885</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020208</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001034340-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001034340</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010209</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   8/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   8/12        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08F   8/12</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Bei Raumtemperatur härtbare Zusammensetzungen</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Room temperature curable compositions</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Compositions durcissables à température ambiante</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SHINETSU CHEMICAL CO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SHIN-ETSU CHEMICAL CO., LTD.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>SHIN-ETSU CHEMICAL CO., LTD.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>6-1, Otemachi 2-chome</street>
              <city>Chiyoda-ku Tokyo</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KIMURA TSUNEO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SAKAMOTO TAKAFUMI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KIMURA, TSUNEO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SAKAMOTO, TAKAFUMI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Kimura, Tsuneo, c/o Shin-Etsu Chemical Co.,</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Ltd., 1-10, Oaza Hitomi, Matsuida-machi</street>
              <city>Usui-gun, Gunma-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Sakamoto, Takafumi, c/o Shin-Etsu Chemical Co.,</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Ltd., 1-10, Oaza Hitomi, Matsuida-machi</street>
              <city>Usui-gun, Gunma-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Stoner, Gerard Patrick</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>MEWBURN ELLIS York House 23 Kingsway</street>
              <city>London WC2B 6HP</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A composition comprising (A) a saturated hydrocarbon
polymer having a number average molecular weight in the
range of 500-50,000 and bearing at least two hydrolyzable
silyl groups at an end of the backbone and/or an end of a
side chain per molecule, (B) an organic compound having at
least one C=O group in a molecule, and (C) an organic
compound having at least one NH<sub>2</sub> group in a molecule, the
C=O group and the NH<sub>2</sub> group being reactive with each other,
is improved in room temperature curing, especially in fast
curing and deep curing.</p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">This invention relates to room temperature curable
compositions, and more particularly, to room temperature
curable compositions of the condensation curing type having
fast curing and deep curing capabilities.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BACKGROUND</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0002">Nowadays elastic sealing materials are widely employed
in a variety of applications, typically in buildings and
automobiles. On use, sealing materials are filled in joints
and gaps between various members for forming water- and gas-tight
seals. The sealing materials are therefore required,
after being filled in joints or around window frames, to
quickly cure and form a firm bond to various substrates,
typically of inorganic materials such as glass, ceramics,
metals, cement and mortar and organic materials such as
plastics.</p>
    <p num="0003">Room temperature fast curable saturated hydrocarbon
polymer compositions are known effective as the sealing
material. For improving the adhesion of such compositions,
a primer composition and a bonding method have been proposed
as disclosed in JP-A 11-209701. However, these compositions
are not satisfactory in curing capability and a need exists
for further improvements in curing performance.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0004">An object of the invention is to provide a room
temperature fast curable composition of the condensation
curing type which is improved in curability, especially in
fast curing at room temperature and curing to depth.</p>
    <p num="0005">We have found that by blending (A) a saturated
hydrocarbon polymer having a number average molecular weight
in the range of 500 to 50,000 and bearing at least two 
hydrolyzable silyl groups at an end of the backbone and/or
an end of a side chain per molecule, with (B) an organic
compound having at least one C=O group in a molecule, and
(C) an organic compound having at least one NH<sub>2</sub> group in a
molecule, the C=O group in component (B) and the NH<sub>2</sub> group
in component (C) being selected so as to be reactive with
each other, we can get a room temperature fast curable
composition of the condensation curing type which is
improved in both fast curing at room temperature and curing
to depth.</p>
    <p num="0006">Room temperature fast curable organopolysiloxane
compositions of the condensation curing type known in the
art include compositions of one part type comprising a both
end hydroxy-terminated organopolysiloxane as a base polymer
and a crosslinking agent in an amount minimized so as to
increase the rate of crosslinking through hydrolysis, and
compositions of two part type wherein a both end hydroxy-terminated
organopolysiloxane as a base polymer and a
crosslinking agent are separately packed.</p>
    <p num="0007">The compositions of one part type, however, are not
regarded as fast curing since they merely have a high curing
rate from the surface and require a certain time for deep
curing. By contrast, the compositions of two part type are
relatively fast in depth curing, but are difficult to handle
on account of a mixing ratio of the two parts departing from
1:1 and thus inapplicable to an automatic mixing dispenser.
In order to drive complete curing to depths, the quantity of
hydroxyl at both ends of organopolysiloxane or
polyoxyalkylene polymer and the quantity of crosslinking
agent added must be strictly controlled, or water must be
further added as a deep curing agent.</p>
    <p num="0008">On the other hand, organopolysiloxane compositions of
the addition curing type are efficient to work since the two
parts are mixed in a ratio of 1:1. However, the working
environment is limited since a heating oven is generally
necessary for curing and the curing catalyst can be poisoned
in the presence of an addition poison. </p>
    <p num="0009">To solve these problems, we proposed in JP-A 5-279570
a composition comprising a diorganopolysiloxane or
polyoxyalkylene as a base polymer, an organic compound
having a double bond in the form of a C=O group and an
organic compound having a NH<sub>2</sub> group wherein instead of
directly adding water necessary for condensation curing,
water is generated within the composition by reaction
between the organic compounds. The composition is improved
in deep curing and fast curing properties. However, the
silicone base compositions are less stain resistant as the
sealing agent, and the polyether base compositions are
insufficient in durability and curability. Where saturated
hydrocarbon polymers are used, stain resistance is good, but
curability is very low as compared with silicone base
compositions.</p>
    <p num="0010">Continuing investigations, we have found that in the
composition comprising the saturated hydrocarbon polymer
(A), organic compound (B) and organic compound (C),
crosslinking reaction takes place between a hydrolyzable
silyl group at an end of the backbone and/or a side chain of
the saturated hydrocarbon polymer (A) and air-borne
moisture, and in parallel therewith, dehydration
condensation reaction takes place between compound (B) and
compound (C) according to the following scheme (I):
<st32:chr xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/">R<sub>2</sub>C=O + H<sub>2</sub>NR' → R<sub>2</sub>C=NR' + H<sub>2</sub>O</st32:chr>
wherein R and R' are organic groups, allowing crosslinking
reaction to proceed with the water generated in depth within
the composition as well. As a result, we found
compositions improved in fast curing and also drastically
improved in deep curing. Additionally, the composition has
good stain resistance and durability.</p>
    <p num="0011">This also overcomes the problems of water separation
and a decline of workability due to increased thixotropy as
found in prior art compositions wherein water is added as a
deep curing agent. </p>
    <p num="0012">Accordingly, the invention provides a room temperature
curable composition comprising (A) 100 parts by weight of a
saturated hydrocarbon polymer having a number average
molecular weight in the range of 500 to 50,000 and bearing
at least two hydrolyzable silyl groups at an end of the
backbone and/or an end of a side chain per molecule, (B) an
organic compound having at least one C=O group in a
molecule, in such an amount as to give 0.001 to 1 mol of the
C=O group per 100 parts by weight of polymer (A), and (C) an
organic compound having at least one NH<sub>2</sub> group in a
molecule, in such an amount as to give 0.001 to 1 mol of the
NH<sub>2</sub> group per 100 parts by weight of polymer (A), components
(B) and (C) being selected such that the C=O and NH<sub>2</sub> groups
in the respective components are reactive with each other.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</u>
    </heading>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Component (A)</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0013">Component (A) is a base polymer. Any of saturated
hydrocarbon polymers excluding polyether polymers is used.
The saturated hydrocarbon polymer must have at least two
hydrolyzable silyl groups at an end of the backbone and/or
an end of a side chain per molecule. Owing to the presence
of hydrolyzable silyl groups, the base polymer undergoes
hydrolysis and polycondensation in the presence of air-borne
moisture and water generated by reaction of components (B)
and (C) to be described later, forming a cured product of
rubber elastomer.</p>
    <p num="0014">The hydrolyzable silyl group is defined as a silicon
atom having at least one hydrolyzable group attached thereto
and represented by the following formula.
<img id="img-00040001" orientation="unknown" wi="38" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040001.tif" inline="no" he="22"/>
Herein X is a hydrolyzable group, p is an integer of 1 to 3,
and R<sup>1</sup> is substituted or unsubstituted monovalent
hydrocarbon group. Examples of the hydrolyzable group (X) 
include carboxyl, ketoxime, alkoxy, alkenoxy, amino,
aminoxy, and amide groups. The hydrolyzable group attached
to a single silicon atom is not limited to one, and two or
three hydrolyzable groups may be attached to a common
silicon atom. Another organic group or groups may, of
course, be attached to the silicon atom having the
hydrolyzable group or groups attached thereto. Examples of
the organic groups (R<sup>1</sup>) include alkyl groups such as methyl,
ethyl and propyl, cycloalkyl groups such as cyclohexyl,
alkenyl groups such as vinyl and allyl, aryl groups such as
phenyl and tolyl, and substituted ones of the foregoing
groups in which some hydrogen atoms are replaced by halogen
atoms or the like, such as chloromethyl and 3,3,3-trifluoropropyl.</p>
    <p num="0015">The base polymer (A) should have a number average
molecular weight in the range of 500 to 50,000. Outside the
range, there arise inconvenient problems including
difficulty to form a cured rubber having satisfactory
properties and inefficient working.</p>
    <p num="0016">The base polymer is not critical as long as it is
selected from saturated hydrocarbon polymers such as
ethylene polymers, propylene polymers and isobutylene
polymers. Preferably the polymer (A) has in its backbone a
structure of the following general formula (1):
<img id="img-00050001" orientation="unknown" wi="151" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00050001.tif" inline="no" he="28"/>
wherein R, which may be the same or different, is a
substituted or unsubstituted monovalent hydrocarbon group, m
and n are positive integers such that the polymer has a
number average molecular weight in the range of 500 to
50,000. More preferably the polymer (A) has the following
general formula (2): <img id="img-00060001" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00060001.tif" inline="no" he="30"/>
wherein R and R<sup>1</sup>, which may be the same or different, are
substituted or unsubstituted monovalent hydrocarbon groups,
X is a hydrolyzable group as defined above, p is an integer
of 1 to 3, preferably 2 or 3, and m and n are positive
integers as defined above. Examples of the group R are the
same as the organic groups (R<sup>1</sup>), other than the hydrolyzable
groups, enumerated above in connection with the hydrolyzable
silyl groups. Letters m and n are such that the unsaturated
hydrocarbon polymer has a number average molecular weight
within the above-defined range.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Component (B)</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0017">Component (B) is an organic compound having at least
one C=O group in a molecule, which reacts with an organic
compound having at least one NH<sub>2</sub> group in a molecule as
component (C) to produce water serving as a curing agent in
the deep interior of the composition.</p>
    <p num="0018">Any desired organic compound may be used as long as it
has a carbonyl (C=O) group capable of reaction as shown by
scheme (I). Examples include ketones such as acetone,
methyl ethyl ketone, and acetophenone, esters such as ethyl
acetate, butyl acetate, methyl propionate, ethyl acrylate
and butyrolactone, amides such as dimethylformamide,
diethylacetamide, and butyrolactam, carboxylic acids such as
acetic acid, propionic acid, and benzoic acid, silane
coupling agents having the foregoing as a functional group,
and oligomers and polymers having C=O groups. Among
others, ketones are especially preferred. Preferred from
the standpoint of steric hindrance during reaction with
component (C) is a compound in which the carbon atom at α-position
relative to the carbonyl group is primary,
secondary or a part of an aromatic ring. If the carbon atom 
at α-position is a tertiary carbon atom as usual, reactivity
with an amino group may be low, with a failure to achieve
the desired cure. These compounds may be used alone or in
admixture of two or more.</p>
    <p num="0019">The amount of component (B) blended is to give 0.001
to 1 mol and preferably 0.01 to 0.1 mol of the carbonyl
(C=O) group per 100 parts by weight of component (A). Less
amounts of component (B) fail to achieve satisfactory deep
curing whereas excessive amounts of component (B) result in
cured elastomers which will not exhibit the desired physical
properties.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Component (C)</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0020">Component (C) is an organic compound having at least
one NH<sub>2</sub> group, which reacts with component (B) to produce
water serving as a curing agent in the deep interior of the
composition as described above.</p>
    <p num="0021">Any desired organic compound may be used as long as it
has a reactive amino (NH<sub>2</sub>) group capable of reaction e.g. as
shown by scheme (I). Examples include amines such as
methylamine, ethylamine, butylamine, ethylenediamine, and
aniline; silane coupling agents having NH<sub>2</sub> as a functional
group such as γ-aminopropyltriethoxysilane, and oligomers
and polymers having NH<sub>2</sub> groups. From the standpoint of
steric hindrance during reaction with component (B),
component (C) is preferably an organic compound in which the
carbon atom at α-position relative to the amino group is
primary, secondary or a part of an aromatic ring. If the
carbon atom at α-position is a tertiary carbon atom as
usual, then the amino group in component (C) may become less
reactive with the carbonyl group in component (B), sometimes
failing to achieve the desired effect. These compounds may
be used alone or in admixture of two or more.</p>
    <p num="0022">The amount of component (C) blended is to give 0.001
to 1 mol and preferably 0.01 to 0.1 mol of the amino (NH<sub>2</sub>)
group per 100 parts by weight of component (A). Less 
amounts of component (C) fail to achieve satisfactory deep
curing whereas excessive amounts of component (C) result in
cured elastomers which will not exhibit the desired physical
properties.</p>
    <p num="0023">Components (B) and (C) are preferably blended such
that the molar ratio of C=O to NH<sub>2</sub> may range from 1/10 to
10/1, especially from 1/5 to 5/1.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Other components</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0024">In addition to the foregoing essential components (A)
to (C), various other addenda may be added to the
composition of the invention, Preferably they do not
adversely affect the fast curing and deep curing at room
temperature. Since it is crucial for the invention that
components (B) and (C) react to form water serving as a deep
curing agent as seen from scheme (I), organic compounds are,
of course, selected for components (B) and (C) so that this
type of reaction may promptly take place, and various
addenda which are optional must be selected so as not to
inhibit the formation of water.</p>
    <p num="0025">As a typical addendum, it is preferred to blend in the
composition a hydrocarbon plasticizer (D) such as paraffinic
process oil. The hydrocarbon plasticizer is preferably
blended in amounts of 5 to 200 parts, especially 10 to 100
parts by weight per 100 parts by weight of component (A).</p>
    <p num="0026">Other exemplary addenda include condensation catalysts
such as organic tin esters, organic titanate esters, tetramethylguanidylpropyltrimethoxysilane;
storage stabilizers
such as methyltrimethoxysilane, methyltripropenoxysilane,
vinyltributanoximesilane and methyltriacetoxysilane; and
reinforcing fillers such as fumed silica, precipitated
silica, quartz flour, titanium oxide, aluminum oxide, carbon
powder, bentonite, wood chips, pulp, cotton chips, asbestos,
glass fibers, carbon fibers, mica, ground walnut shell,
ground chaff, graphite, diatomaceous earth, terra abla,
silicic anhydride, carbon black, calcium carbonate, clay,
talc, magnesium carbonate, aluminum fine powder, print 
powder and zinc powder. Of these fillers, precipitated
silica, fumed silica, carbon black, calcium carbonate,
titanium oxide and talc are preferred. Also included are
radical inhibitors and antiozonants, for example, phenolic
antioxidants, aromatic amine antioxidants, sulfurous
hydroperoxide decomposers, phosphorous hydroperoxide
decomposers, benzotriazole UV absorbers, salicylate UV
absorbers, benzophenone UV absorbers, hindered amine photo-stabilizers,
and nickel photo-stabilizers. Further included
are fibrous fillers such as asbestos, glass fibers and
organic fibers; coloring agents such as pigments and dyes;
heat resistance modifiers such as red iron oxide and cerium
oxide; freeze resistance modifiers; dehydrating agents;
rust-preventing agents; tackifiers such as γ-glycidoxy-propyltriethoxysilane;
liquid reinforcing agents such as a
network polysiloxane consisting of triorganosiloxy units and
SiO<sub>2</sub> units; metal inactivating agents, lubricants, pigments
and foaming agents. These addenda may be used in
conventional amounts.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Curable composition</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0027">The composition of the invention can be formulated as
a room temperature fast curable composition of one part type
by uniformly mixing predetermined amounts of components (A)
to (C) and optional components and in a dry or anhydrous
atmosphere if necessary. To insure shelf stability,
component (B) or (C) may be microcapsulated prior to
blending into a room temperature fast curable composition of
one part type.</p>
    <p num="0028">Alternatively, the composition of the invention can be
formulated as a two part type wherein the two parts are
mixed on use. In one example, one part is composed of
components (A) and (B) and the other part is composed of
components (A) and (C). In these examples, the two parts
can be mixed in a ratio of 1:1.</p>
    <p num="0029">The inventive composition thus obtained will cure in
the presence of moisture in air. During the process, water 
forms at depths to induce curing thereat. Both curing from
the surface and curing at depths take place at the same
time, facilitating fast curing and deep curing.</p>
    <p num="0030">When the inventive composition is formulated as a two
part package whereupon the two parts are mixed on use, the
mixing step is very easy on account of the mixing ratio of
1:1. Furthermore, the respective components are readily
available. Thus the invention is of great worth in
practical application.</p>
    <p num="0031">Because of the fast curing and deep curing advantages
as well as stain resistance and durability, the inventive
composition is very suitable as automobile oil seal material
and also useful as sealing agents and potting agents in
electric and electronic applications where simple, efficient
steps are strongly demanded for manufacture.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLE</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0032">Examples of the invention are given below by way of
illustration and not by way of limitation. Note that the
viscosity is a measurement at 23°C, Mn is number average
molecular weight, Mw is weight average molecular weight, and
Me is methyl.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Comparative Example 1</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0033">A curable composition was prepared by mixing under
anhydrous conditions 150 g of a mixture of a saturated
hydrocarbon polymer of formula (3) below (Mn = 5,800, Mw/Mn
= 1.21) and a paraffinic process oil (trade name Diana
Process PS-32 by Idemitsu Industries, Ltd.) as a hydrocarbon
plasticizer in a weight ratio of 2:1, 3.0 g of dibutyltin
dilaurate, 75 g of colloidal light calcium carbonate (trade
name MT-100 by Maruo Calcium K.K.), 75 g of heavy calcium
carbonate (trade name Softon 1500 by Shiraishi Calcium
K.K.), and 10 g of fumed silica (trade name Aerosil R-972 by
Nippon Aerosil Co., Ltd.). <img id="img-00110001" orientation="unknown" wi="160" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00110001.tif" inline="no" he="28"/></p>
    <p num="0034">The composition was worked into a sheet of 2 mm thick,
which was allowed to stand in an atmosphere of 23°C and RH
50% for one hour. The resulting rubber elastomer was
examined for physical properties (hardness, elongation and
tensile strength) according to JIS K-6249. The results are
shown in Table 1. Separately, the composition was cast into
a glass cylinder having a diameter of 20 mm and a length of
100 mm and allowed to cure in an atmosphere of 23°C and RH
50% for 24 hours. At the end of curing, the cured product
was taken out by breaking the glass cylinder. The thickness
of a rubbery elastomer portion was measured to be 0.5 mm.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Example 1</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0035">A curable composition was prepared by mixing under
anhydrous conditions 150 g of a mixture of a saturated
hydrocarbon polymer of formula (3) (Mn = 5,800, Mw/Mn =
1.21) and a paraffinic process oil (trade name Diana Process
PS-32 by Idemitsu Industries, Ltd.) as a hydrocarbon
plasticizer in a weight ratio of 2:1, 75 g of colloidal
light calcium carbonate (trade name MT-100 by Maruo Calcium
K.K.), 75 g of heavy calcium carbonate (trade name Softon
1500 by Shiraishi Calcium K.K.), 10 g of fumed silica (trade
name Aerosil R-972 by Nippon Aerosil Co., Ltd.), 2.90 g
(0.05 mol) of acetone, 6.45 g (0.05 mol) of n-butylamine,
and 3.0 g of dibutyltin dilaurate.</p>
    <p num="0036">Rubber properties of this composition were examined as
in Comparative Example 1, with the results shown in Table 1.
Also as in Comparative Example 1, the composition was cured
in a glass cylinder, and the thickness of a rubbery
elastomer portion was measured to be 100 mm. It is thus
evident that the composition within the scope of the
invention is good in deep curing. </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Comparative Example 2</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0037">A curable composition was prepared by mixing under
anhydrous conditions 150 g of a mixture of a saturated
hydrocarbon polymer of formula (4) below (Mn = 5,800, Mw/Mn
= 1.21) and a paraffinic process oil (trade name Diana
Process PS-32 by Idemitsu Industries, Ltd.) as a hydrocarbon
plasticizer in a weight ratio of 2:1, 1.0 g of
tetramethylguanidylpropyltrimethoxysilane, 75 g of colloidal
light calcium carbonate (trade name MT-100 by Maruo Calcium
K.K.), 75 g of heavy calcium carbonate (trade name Softon
1500 by Shiraishi Calcium K.K.), and 10 g of fumed silica
(trade name Aerosil R-972 by Nippon Aerosil Co., Ltd.).
<img id="img-00120001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00120001.tif" inline="no" he="38"/></p>
    <p num="0038">Rubber properties of this composition were examined as
in Comparative Example 1, with the results shown in Table 1.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Example 2</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0039">A curable composition was prepared by mixing under
anhydrous conditions 150 g of a mixture of a saturated
hydrocarbon polymer of formula (4) (Mn = 5,800, Mw/Mn =
1.21) and a paraffinic process oil (trade name Diana Process
PS-32 by Idemitsu Industries, Ltd.) as a hydrocarbon
plasticizer in a weight ratio of 2:1, 2.90 g (0.05 mol) of
acetone, 11.05 g (0.05 mol) of γ-aminopropyltriethoxysilane,
1.0 g of tetramethylguanidylpropyltrimethoxysilane, 75 g of
colloidal light calcium carbonate (trade name MT-100 by
Maruo Calcium K.K.), 75 g of heavy calcium carbonate (trade
name Softon 1500 by Shiraishi Calcium K.K.), and 10 g of
fumed silica (trade name Aerosil R-972 by Nippon Aerosil
Co., Ltd.). </p>
    <p num="0040">Rubber properties of this composition were examined as
in Comparative Example 1, with the results shown in Table 1.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Comparative Example 3</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0041">A curable composition was prepared by mixing under
anhydrous conditions 150 g of a mixture of a saturated
hydrocarbon polymer of formula (4) (Mn = 11,000, Mw/Mn =
1.45) and a paraffinic process oil (trade name Diana Process
PS-32 by Idemitsu Industries, Ltd.) as a hydrocarbon
plasticizer in a weight ratio of 2:1, 1.0 g of
tetramethylguanidylpropyltrimethoxysilane, 75 g of colloidal
light calcium carbonate (trade name MT-100 by Maruo Calcium
K.K.), 75 g of heavy calcium carbonate (trade name Softon
1500 by Shiraishi Calcium K.K.), and 10 g of fumed silica
(trade name Aerosil R-972 by Nippon Aerosil Co., Ltd.).</p>
    <p num="0042">Rubber properties of this composition were examined as
in Comparative Example 1, with the results shown in Table 1.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Example 3</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0043">A curable composition was prepared by mixing under
anhydrous conditions 150 g of a mixture of a saturated
hydrocarbon polymer of formula (4) (Mn = 11,000, Mw/Mn =
1.45) and a paraffinic process oil (trade name Diana Process
PS-32 by Idemitsu Industries, Ltd.) as a hydrocarbon
plasticizer in a weight ratio of 2:1, 2.90 g (0.05 mol) of
acetone, 11.05 g (0.05 mol) of γ-aminopropyltriethoxysilane,
1.0 g of tetramethylguanidylpropyltrimethoxysilane, 75 g of
colloidal light calcium carbonate (trade name MT-100 by
Maruo Calcium K.K.), 75 g of heavy calcium carbonate (trade
name Softon 1500 by Shiraishi Calcium K.K.), and 10 g of
fumed silica (trade name Aerosil R-972 by Nippon Aerosil
Co., Ltd.).</p>
    <p num="0044">Rubber properties of this composition were examined as
in Comparative Example 1, with the results shown in Table 1. <tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">CE1</entry><entry align="center">E1</entry><entry align="center">CE2</entry><entry align="center">E2</entry><entry align="center">CE3</entry><entry align="center">E3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hardness, Duro-A</entry><entry align="center">UM</entry><entry align="center">16</entry><entry align="center">UM</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">UM</entry><entry align="center">10</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Elongation at break, %</entry><entry align="center">UM</entry><entry align="center">540</entry><entry align="center">UM</entry><entry align="center">600</entry><entry align="center">UM</entry><entry align="center">1050</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tensile strength, MPa</entry><entry align="center">UM</entry><entry align="center">0.92</entry><entry align="center">UM</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry><entry align="center">UM</entry><entry align="center">1.2</entry></row><row><entry>UM: unmeasurable</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0045">There has been described a room temperature curable
composition of the condensation curing type based on a
saturated hydrocarbon polymer and having improved fast and
deep curing capabilities.</p>
    <p num="0046">Japanese Patent Application No. 2001-034340 is
incorporated herein by reference.</p>
    <p num="0047">Although some preferred embodiments have been
described, many modifications and variations may be made
thereto in light of the above teachings. It is therefore to
be understood that the invention may be practiced otherwise
than as specifically described in the Examples.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A room temperature curable composition comprising
<claim-text><claim-text>(A) 100 parts by weight of saturated hydrocarbon
polymer having a number average molecular weight in the
range of 500 to 50,000 and bearing at least two hydrolyzable
silyl groups, at an end of the backbone and/or an end of a
side chain, per molecule,</claim-text><claim-text>(B) organic compound having at least one C=O group
in a molecule, in such an amount as to give 0.001 to 1 mol
of the C=O group per 100 parts by weight of polymer (A), and</claim-text><claim-text>(C) organic compound having at least one NH2 group
in a molecule, in such an amount as to give 0.001 to 1 mol
of the NH2 group per 100 parts by weight of polymer (A),
components (B) and (C) being selected such that the C=O and
NH2 groups in the respective components are reactive with
each other.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The composition of claim 1 wherein polymer (A) has in
its backbone a structure of the following general formula
(1):

wherein R is independently a substituted or unsubstituted
monovalent hydrocarbon group, m and n are positive integers
such that polymer (A) has a number average molecular weight
in the range of 500 to 50,000.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The composition of claim 1 comprising (D) a
hydrocarbon plasticizer.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A composition according to any one of the preceding
claims which is a one part composition.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A composition according to any one of claims 1 to 3 which
is a two part composition, one part comprising A mixed with B,
and the other part comprising A mixed with C.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A method comprising the preparation of a composition
according to any one of claims 1 to 5.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>Use of a composition according to any one of claims 1 to
5 as a sealant.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
