<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1247644-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1247644" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="26613000" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021009">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1247644-A2" status="new" fvid="23559207">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1247644</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021009</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02007296-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02007296</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020403</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001104242-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001104242</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010403</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001221804-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001221804</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010723</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41C   1/10        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41C   1/10        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41N   3/03        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41N   3/03        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41N   3/03P</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L41C1:10A</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Träger für Flachdruckplatte und Original für Flachdruckplatte</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Support for lithographic printing plate and original forme for lithographic printing plate</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Support pour plaque d'impression lithographique et original pour plaque d'impression lithographique</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>FUJI PHOTO FILM CO LTD</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>FUJI PHOTO FILM CO., LTD.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>FUJI PHOTO FILM CO., LTD.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>210,Nakanuma, Minami-Ashigara-shi</street>
              <city>Kanagawa</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HOTTA HISASHI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HOTTA YOSHINORI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MAEMOTO KAZUO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HOTTA, HISASHI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HOTTA, YOSHINORI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MAEMOTO, KAZUO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>HOTTA, HISASHI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Fuji Photo Film Co., Ltd., 4000, Kawashiri</street>
              <city>Yoshida-cho, Haibara-gun, Shizuoka</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>HOTTA, YOSHINORI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Fuji Photo Film Co., Ltd., 4000, Kawashiri</street>
              <city>Yoshida-cho, Haibara-gun, Shizuoka</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>MAEMOTO, KAZUO</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Fuji Photo Film Co., Ltd., 4000, Kawashiri</street>
              <city>Yoshida-cho, Haibara-gun, Shizuoka</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>HOFFMANN - EITLE</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Patent- und Rechtsanwälte Arabellastrasse 4</street>
              <city>81925 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>This invention provides a support for a lithographic
printing plate, and an original form of a heat-sensitive
lithographic printing plate, which comprises a hydrophilic
film formed on a metallic base whose surface has been
roughened, said hydrophilic film having a heat conductivity
of 0.05 - 0.5 W/(m·K) in the direction of its film
thickness, which when used as the development on machine
type, exhibits good on-press, or good non-treatment
developability, a high sensitivity, a long press life and a
preferable stain resistance and ink removal property upon
printing and which, when used as a conventional thermal
positive or negative type, makes efficient utilization of
heat for the formation of image, has a high sensitivity and
exhibits a long press life and a good stain resistance in a
nonimage area, wherein the non-treatment in which the
development is not performed.</p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <heading>1. Field of the Invention:</heading>
    <p num="0001">This invention relates to a support for a
lithographic printing plate and an original forme for the
lithographic printing plate (hereinafter also abbreviated
as lithographic printing original plate for ease of
description). More specifically, the present invention
relates to: an original forme for a heat-sensitive
lithographic printing plate, which may be used suitably for
the computer-to-plate system that does not require the
development process, in particular a heat-sensitive
lithographic printing plate which may be image-recorded by
means of infrared-scanning exposure based on digital
signals and may be mounted directly to a printing machine
to perform printing without performing the conventional
development process using a developer after exposure; and a
support for the lithographic printing plate which is used
therefor. Also, it relates to: an original forme for a
heat-sensitive lithographic printing plate, which is
printable after performing a conventional development
process using a developer after the exposure; and a support 
for the lithographic printing plate which is used therefor.</p>
    <heading>2. Description of the Related Art:</heading>
    <p num="0002">There have been many studies on a lithographic
printing original plate used for the computer-to-plate
system which has developed remarkably in recent years. In
particular, aiming at a further rationalized printing
process and the solution for the problem of waste liquor
disposal, a number of studies have been conducted and a
variety of proposals have been made as to a lithographic
printing original plate which may be directly mounted to a
printing machine after the exposure to carry out printing.</p>
    <p num="0003">As a promising technique, there is a lithographic
printing original plate which comprises as a heat-sensitive
image-forming layer of a water receptive layer in which
particles of hydrophobic thermoplastic polymer are
dispersed in a hydrophilic binder polymer. This
lithographic printing original plate utilizes the principle
such that, when the heat-sensitive layer is heated, the
particles of hydrophobic thermoplastic polymer are fused
together so that the surface of a hydrophilic heat-sensitive
layer is changed to an ink-receptive image area.</p>
    <p num="0004">For such a lithographic printing original plate
utilizing the thermal fusion of particles of hydrophobic
thermoplastic polymer, as one means to reduce the number of 
treatment processes, there is a method called on-press
development wherein the lithographic printing original
plate after the exposure is mounted to the cylinder of a
printing machine without performing thereon a treatment
with developer solution and then nonimaged areas of the
original forme is removed by feeding ink and/or damping
solution while rotating the cylinder, or a lithographic
printing original plate of a non-treatment type in which
the development is not performed. In the latter method,
the lithographic printing original plate is directly
mounted to a printing machine after performing the exposure
and printing is completed without performing the
development according to a conventional printing process.</p>
    <p num="0005">Such a lithographic printing original plate, which is
suitable for the on-press development or non-treatment type
printing plate, includes a heat-sensitive layer soluble in
a damping solution or ink solvent and is required to have
handleability under light which is suitable for performing
the development on a printing machine placed in a light
room.</p>
    <p num="0006">For example, JP 2,938,397 B describes a lithographic
printing plate wherein a heat-sensitive layer, in which
fine particles of thermoplastic hydrophobic polymer are
dispersed in a hydrophilic binder polymer, is formed on a 
hydrophilic support. In the specification thereof, it is
described that the on-press development can be carried out
by exposing the above-mentioned lithographic printing
original plate to an infrared laser to thereby unite fine
particles of thermoplastic hydrophobic polymer by heat to
form an image, and then mounting it to a cylinder of a
printing machine and feeding ink and/or damping solution.</p>
    <p num="0007">JP 9-127683 A and WO 99/10186 describe the production
of a lithographic printing plate by uniting thermoplastic
fine particles by heat and then performing the on-press
development.</p>
    <p num="0008">Such a lithographic printing original plate, on which
an image is formed by the uniting of fine particles by heat,
exhibits a good on-press developability. However, it has
such problems as reduced sensitivity due to loss of heat to
the metal support, and an insufficient press life due to
reduced hardness of an image area on the heat sensitive
layer in the case where the uniting of the fine particles
was insufficient.</p>
    <p num="0009">As a countermeasure to these problems, a method has
been proposed, in which a water-insoluble organic polymer
is provided between an aluminum support and a heat-sensitive
layer (for example, JP 2000-23983 A). Although
this method provides higher sensitivity, it has a problem 
in that contamination occurs.</p>
    <p num="0010">Incidentally, examples of the conventional thermal-type
lithographic printing plates in which on-press
development is not performed include: the so-called thermal
type positive lithographic printing original plate wherein
an infrared absorbent in the heat-sensitive layer expresses
it photothermal conversion action and generates heat upon
the exposure and the exposed areas of the heat-sensitive
layer are alkali-solubilized with the heat thus generated
to form a positive image; and the thermal type negative
lithographic printing original plate wherein a radical-yielding
agent and an acid-generating agent respectively
generate radicals and acids with the heat thus generated,
whereby the radical polymerization and acid bridging
reactions proceed to insolubilize the exposed areas to
thereby form a negative image. However, these have the
problems as mentioned below.</p>
    <p num="0011">That is, in such an image formation process of a
thermal type, a heat is produced by a photothermal
conversion in the heat-sensitive layer by means of laser
beam and the thus produced heat causes a reaction for the
image-formation. Here, in the aluminum support whose
surface has been roughened and on which an anodized film is
formed, the heat conductivity of the support is extremely 
higher than that of the heat-sensitive layer, so that the
heat generated in the vicinity of the interface between the
heat-sensitive layer and the support is dispersed into the
inside of the support before it is adequately used for the
formation of image. As a result, the following problems
occur on the interface between the heat-sensitive layer and
the support.</p>
    <p num="0012">First, with respect to the positive type heat-sensitive
layer, there is a problem of low sensitivity.
That is, when the heat is dispersed into the inside of
support to cause an insufficient alkali-solubilization
reaction, a film remains on otherwise nonimage areas, which
is regarded as an essential problem of a positive type
heat-sensitive layer.</p>
    <p num="0013">Further, in such a lithographic printing original
plate of thermal positive type, an infrared absorbent
having a photothermal conversion function must be provided.
Such an infrared absorbent has a low solubility due to its
relatively high molecular weight, and is difficult to
remove since it is adsorbed onto the micro-openings formed
through the anodic oxidation, so that during the
development process using the alkaline developer, the
problem of residual films can easily occur.</p>
    <p num="0014">On the other hand, in the negative type heat-sensitive 
layer, when the heat is dispersed into the inside
of support to cause insufficient developer-insolubilization
of the heat-sensitive layer in the vicinity of the
interface between the heat-sensitive layer and the support,
an image may not be formed in a satisfactory manner in an
area that should be the image area and is carried away
during the development, or even if an image is formed, it
may be easily peeled off during the printing.</p>
    <heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0015">The present invention has been made in view of the
above, and an object thereof is to provide an original
forme of a heat-sensitive lithographic printing plate which
overcome the defects of the above-mentioned prior art, and
a support for a lithographic printing plate which may be
suitably used therefor. Namely, the object of the
invention is to provide: an original forme of a heat-sensitive
lithographic printing plate, which when used as
the development on machine type, exhibits good on-press
developability, a high sensitivity, a long press life and a
preferable stain resistance and ink removal property upon
printing and which, when used as a conventional thermal
positive or negative type, makes efficient utilization of
heat for the formation of image, has a high sensitivity and 
exhibits a long press life and a good stain resistance in a
nonimage area; and a support for the lithographic printing
plate, which may be suitably used therefor.</p>
    <p num="0016">The present inventors, as a result of intensive
studies, have found that the above object may be
accomplished by forming a hydrophilic film having a heat
conductivity of a specified range on a metallic base and/or
aluminum base applied with a special surface treatment and
then forming an image recording layer being exposable with
infrared laser, thereby completing this invention.</p>
    <p num="0017">Namely, the present invention provides the following
inventions and any combination thereof.</p>
    <p num="0018">There is provided a support for a lithographic
printing plate, which comprises a hydrophilic film formed
on a metallic base whose surface has been roughened, the
hydrophilic film having a heat conductivity of 0.05 - 0.5
W/(m·K) in the direction of its film thickness.</p>
    <p num="0019">Here, the film thickness of the above hydrophilic
film is preferably 0.1 - 5 µm.</p>
    <p num="0020">There is provided an original forme for a
lithographic printing plate, which comprises a recording
layer formed on the above-mentioned support for a
lithographic printing plate, the recording layer being
writable by exposure with infrared laser. </p>
    <p num="0021">There is provided an original forme for a
lithographic printing plate, comprising a recording layer
which is writable by exposure with infrared laser and which
is formed on a support for a lithographic printing plate,
the support being subjected to electrochemical roughening
treatment with an aqueous solution containing hydrochloric
acid and including a hydrophilic film having a heat
conductivity of 0.05 - 0.5 W/(m·K).</p>
    <p num="0022">There is provided an original forme of a lithographic
printing plate, comprising a recording layer which is
writable by exposure with infrared laser and which is
formed on a support for a lithographic printing plate, the
support being subjected to electrochemical roughening
treatment with an aqueous solution containing hydrochloric
acid and including a hydrophilic film having a density of
1000 - 3200 kg/m<sup>3</sup> and/or a porosity of 20-70%.</p>
    <p num="0023">There is provided an original forme of a lithographic
printing plate, comprising a recording layer which is
writable by exposure with infrared laser and which is
formed on a support for a lithographic printing plate
having a hydrophilic film, the hydrophilic film having a
mean opening diameter of roughened small pits of 0.01-3 µm,
a ratio of mean depth to mean opening diameter of the
roughened small pits of 0.1 - 0.5, and a heat conductivity 
of 0.05 - 0.5 W/(m·K).</p>
    <p num="0024">There is provided an original forme of a lithographic
printing plate, comprising a recording layer which is
writable by exposure with infrared laser and which is
formed on a support for a lithographic printing plate
having a hydrophilic film, the hydrophilic film having a
mean opening diameter of roughened small pits of 0.01 - 3
µm, a ratio of mean depth to mean opening diameter of the
roughened small pits of 0.1 - 0.5, and a density of 1000-3200
kg/m<sup>3</sup> and/or a porosity of 20 - 70%.</p>
    <p num="0025">It is preferable that the mean opening diameter of
large undulation of the support for a lithographic printing
plate is 3 - 20 µm.</p>
    <p num="0026">It is preferable that the hydrophilic film is an
anodic oxide film.</p>
    <p num="0027">It is preferable that the amount of the anodic oxide
film formed is 3.2 g/m<sup>2</sup> or more than 3.2 g/m<sup>2</sup>.</p>
    <p num="0028">It is preferable that the pore diameter on the
surface layer of the anodic oxide film is 40 nm or less
than 40 nm.</p>
    <p num="0029">It is preferable that the anodic oxide film is pore-sealed.</p>
    <p num="0030">It is preferable that a layer of particles having a
mean particle size of 8 - 800 nm is formed on the anodic 
oxide film.</p>
    <p num="0031">It is preferable that the anodic oxide film is formed
by anodic oxidation that consists of more than two steps.</p>
    <p num="0032">It is preferable that the anodic oxidation is
performed with an electrolyte containing sulfuric acid in
the first step and then with an electrolyte containing
phosphoric acid in the second and subsequent steps.</p>
    <p num="0033">According to a preferable aspect of the present
invention, the above-mentioned recording layer is a heat-sensitive
layer containing one of: (a) fine polymer
particles having heat reactive functional group; and (b)
microcapsuls including a compound having heat reactive
functional group.</p>
    <p num="0034">There is provided a plate-making and printing method
for a lithographic printing plate, in which the above-mentioned
original forme for a lithographic printing plate
is printable by either exposing it to a laser beam and then
directly mounting it to a printing machine, or directly
exposing it to a laser beam after mounting it to a printing
machine.</p>
    <heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
    <p num="0035">In the accompanying drawings:
<sl><li>Fig. 1 is a waveform diagram showing an example of a 
trapezoidal wave used for an electrochemical surface
roughening treatment using AC, which can be suitably used
for the present invention;</li><li>Fig. 2 is a side view showing an example of a radial
cell used for an electrochemical surface roughening
treatment, which can be suitably used for the production of
an aluminum substrate for the original forme for a
lithographic printing plate according to the present
invention; and</li><li>Fig. 3 is a schematic view of a thermocomparator
which can be used to measure the thermal conductivity in a
film thickness direction of a hydrophilic film that is
included in the original forme for a lithographic printing
plate according to the present invention.</li></sl></p>
    <heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0036">This invention will be explained in detail
hereinbelow.</p>
    <heading>[Support for lithographic printing plate]</heading>
    <heading>&lt;Metallic base&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0037">The metallic base to be used as a support for a
lithographic printing plate according to this invention is
not particularly specified. Examples thereof include iron,
stainless steel and aluminum. Above all, aluminum is 
preferred.</p>
    <p num="0038">The aluminum plate used as aluminum base is a metal
containing as its main component a dimensionally stable
aluminum, which is formed of aluminum or aluminum alloy.
Other than pure aluminum, an alloy plate containing
aluminum as its main component and a slight amount of
foreign elements, or a plastic film or paper laminated or
vapor-deposited with aluminum or aluminum alloy may be used.
Further, a composite sheet in which an aluminum sheet is
bound on a polyethylene terephthalate film, such as one
described in JP 48-18327 B, may also be used.</p>
    <p num="0039">The aluminum plate to be used in this invention is
not particularly limited. However, a plate formed of pure
aluminum is used preferably. Since the production of
completely pure aluminum is difficult with the currently
available refining technique, aluminum containing a slight
amount of foreign elements may be used. For example, known
products described in "Aluminum Handbook, 4th ed., (Light
Metal Association, 1990), specifically JIS 1050, JIS 1100,
JIS 3003, JIS 3103, JIS 3005 etc., may be used. Moreover,
an aluminum alloy, scrapped aluminum or aluminum plate
using a secondary ground metal having an aluminum (Al)
content of 99.4 - 95 wt% and containing at least more than
5 elements selected from iron (Fe), silicon (Si), copper 
(Cu), magnesium (Mg), manganese (Mn), zinc (Zn), chromium
(Cr) and titanium (Ti) within the range described later may
be used.</p>
    <p num="0040">Further, in this invention, an aluminum plate having
an Al content of 95 - 99.4 wt%, which enables reduction of
cost, may be also used. If the content of Al exceeds 99.4
wt%, the maximum permissible amount of impurities is
reduced so that the cost reduction effect may become less
remarkable. If the content of Al is less that 95 wt%, such
a large amount of impurities may cause troubles such as
breakage of the plate during rolling. The more preferable
content of Al is therefore 95 - 99 wt%, and in particular
preferably 95 - 97 wt%.</p>
    <p num="0041">The content of Fe is preferably 0.1 - 1.0 wt%. Fe is
an element that is contained at about 0.1 - 0.2 wt% even in
a new ground metal, which is hardly solid-solved in Al so
that the almost all of Fe remains as intermetallic
compounds. If the content of Fe exceeds 1.0 wt%, the
breakage of the plate during rolling may occur easily; if
it is less than 0.1 wt%, the cost reduction effect is
reduced disadvantageously. The more preferable content of
Fe is therefore 0.3 - 1.0 wt%.</p>
    <p num="0042">The content of Si is preferably 0.03 - 1.0 wt%. Si is
an element often contained in scraps of JIS 2000, 4000, 
6000 series. Further, Si is an element contained at about
0.03 - 0.1 wt% even in a new ground metal and exists as
solid solution or intermetallic compounds in Al. When an
aluminum plate is heated during the production of the
support, the Si that is solid-solved may be separated as
simple substance. It is known that the intermetalllic
compound of the simple Si and Fe-Si series adversely affect
the resistance against severe ink stain. The term "severe
ink stain" means dot- or ring-like stains which appear on a
printed paper or the like due to the increased adhesion of
ink to the surface of a nonimage area of the lithographic
printing plate in the case where the printing is repeated
with frequent interruptions. If the content of Si exceeds
1.0 wt%, Si may be not removed completely by, for example,
the treatment with sulfuric acid mentioned later
(desmutting); if the content of Si is less than 0.03 wt%,
the cost reduction effect becomes less remarkable. A
preferred content of Si is 0.05 - 1.0 wt%.</p>
    <p num="0043">The content of Cu is preferably 0.000 - 1.0 wt%. Cu
is an element often contained in scraps of JIS 2000 and JIS
4000 series. Cu is solid-solved relatively easily in Al.
If the content of Cu exceeds 1.0 wt%, it may be not removed
completely by the treatment with sulfuric acid as mentioned
hereinafter. A preferred content of Cu is 0.000 - 0.03 wt%. </p>
    <p num="0044">The content of Mg is preferably 0.000 - 1.5 wt%. Mg
is an element that is contained in a large amount in scraps
of JIS 2000, JIS 3000, JIS 5000, and JIS 7000 series. In
particular, Mg is often contained in can end materials and
is thus one of main impurity metals contained in scraps.
Mg is relatively easily solid-solved in Al and forms
intermetallic compounds together with Si. If the content
of Mg exceeds 1.5 wt%, it may be not removed completely by,
for example, the treatment with sulfuric acid as mentioned
hereinafter.</p>
    <p num="0045">The content of Mn is preferably 0.000 - 1.5 wt%. Mn
is an element that is contained in a large amount in scraps
of JIS 3000 series. Mn is often contained especially in
can body materials and is thus one of main impurity metals
contained in scraps. Mn is relatively easily solid-solved
in Al and forms intermetallic compounds together with Al,
Fe and Si. If the content of Mn exceeds 1.5 wt%, it may
not be removed completely by, for example, the treatment
with sulfuric acid as mentioned hereinafter.</p>
    <p num="0046">The content of Zn is preferably 0.000 - 0.5 wt%. Zn
is an element contained especially in scraps of JIS 7000
series. Zn is dissolved relatively easily in Al. If the
content of Zn exceeds 0.5 wt%, it may be not removed
completely by, for example, the treatment with sulfuric 
acid as mentioned hereinafter.</p>
    <p num="0047">The content of Cr is preferably 0.000 - 0.1 wt%. Cr
is an impurity metal, which is contained in a small amount
in scraps of JIS A5000, 6000, 7000 series. If the content
of Cr exceeds 0.1 wt%, it may not be removed completely by,
for example, the treatment with sulfuric acid as mentioned
hereinafter.</p>
    <p num="0048">The content of Ti is preferably 0.003 - 0.5 wt%. Ti
is an element which is added generally as a grain-refining
agent in an amount of 0.005 - 0.04 wt%. Ti is contained in
a relatively large amount as impurity metal in scraps of
JIS 5000, 6000, 7000 series. If the content of Ti exceeds
0.5 wt%, it may not be removed completely by, for example,
the treatment with sulfuric acid as mentioned hereinafter.</p>
    <p num="0049">The aluminum plate to be used in this invention is
produced by casting the raw materials as mentioned above in
a conventional manner, subjecting the resulting cast to
rolling and heat treatment as appropriate to provide a
thickness of, for example, 0.1 - 0.7 mm and, if necessary,
reforming its flatness. The thickness may be varied
suitably according to the size of a printing machine and
printing plate as well as the request of the user.</p>
    <p num="0050">In addition, there may be used as the method for
producing the aluminum plate, for example, DC casting, DC 
casting without soaking treatment and/or annealing, as well
as continuous casting.</p>
    <p num="0051">The supports for lithographic printing plate
according to this invention can be obtained by roughening
the metallic base surface and, further, forming a specified
hydrophilic film. Here, in the production process of the
support for a lithographic printing plate according to this
invention, various kinds of processes may be included other
than the roughening treatment and the formation of a
hydrophilic film.</p>
    <p num="0052">Hereinafter, the support for a lithographic printing
plate according to this invention will be explained with
respect to a case where an aluminum plate is used as the
metallic base.</p>
    <p num="0053">Preferably, the aluminum plate to be used as the
support is subjected to: defatting step of removing an
adhered rolling oil; desmutting step of dissolving the smut
on the surface of an aluminum plate; roughening step of
roughening the surface of the aluminum plate; and so on.</p>
    <p num="0054">The production process for the support for a
lithographic printing plate according to this invention
preferably includes the roughening treatment, in which
surface of the aluminum plate is electrochemically
roughened by using alternating current in aqueous acid 
solution (electrochemical roughening treatment). In
particular, the electrochemical roughening treatment using
aqueous solution containing hydrochloric acid is more
preferable.</p>
    <p num="0055">Further, the production process for the support for a
lithographic printing plate according to this invention may
also include a surface treatment step of the aluminum plate
in which mechanical roughening treatment, chemical etching
in acid or alkaline aqueous solution and the like are
performed in combination, other than the electrochemical
roughening treatment as mentioned above. The production
process of the support for a lithographic printing plate
according to this invention, including the roughening
treatment, may be performed according to both a continuous
method and a non-continuous method; the continuous method
is industrially preferable. Further, in the support for a
lithographic printing plate according to this invention,
the mean opening diameter of roughened small pits and the
ratio of mean depth to the mean opening diameter of the
pits are preferably set within a specified range.</p>
    <p num="0056">The support for a lithographic printing plate
according to this invention is provided with a hydrophilic
film having a specified heat conductivity. Moreover, the
support may be formed, if necessary, through pore-widening 
treatment (acid or alkaline treatment), pore-sealing
treatment, and hydrophilic surface treatment. Further, if
necessary, an undercoat layer may be provided after the
formation of the support.</p>
    <heading>&lt;Roughening treatment (Graining)&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0057">Now, the roughening treatment is explained.</p>
    <p num="0058">An aluminum plate is grained in a more preferable
form. The graining treatment includes mechanical graining
(mechanical roughening), chemical etching, electrolytic
graining etc. as described in JP 56-28893 A. Further,
electrochemical graining (electrochemical roughening,
electrolytic roughening) in which graining is performed
electrochemically in an electrolyte of hydrochloric or
nitric acid, and other mechanical graining (mechanical
roughening) such as: wirebrush graining, in which the
aluminum surface is scratched by metal wires; ball graining,
in which the aluminum surface is grained with grinding
balls and abrasives; and brush graining, in which the
aluminum surface is grained with nylon brush and abrasive,
may be used. These graining methods may be used alone or
in combination thereof. For example, there may be used the
combination of mechanical roughening treatment using nylon
brush and abrasives with electrolytic roughening treatment
using an electrolyte of hydrochloric and/or nitric acid, or 
the combination of a plurality of electrolytic roughing
treatments. Above all, the electrochemical roughening
treatment is preferred. Further, the combination of
mechanical and electrochemical roughening treatment is also
preferable and, in particular, it is preferable to perform
the electrochemical roughening treatment after the
mechanical roughening treatment.</p>
    <p num="0059">The electrochemical roughening treatment is a process
wherein an aluminum plate as electrode is applied with an
alternating current in acid aqueous solution to thereby
electrochemically roughen the surface of aluminum plate,
which differs from the mechanical roughening treatment
mentioned later.</p>
    <p num="0060">As acid aqueous solution used for the electrochemical
roughening, there may be used those used in the ordinary
electrochemical roughening treatment using direct or
alternating current. Of these, it is especially preferred
to use acid aqueous solution containing mainly nitric or
hydrochloric acid. Here, the phrase "containing mainly"
means that the content of the main component in the aqueous
solution is 30 wt% or more, preferably 50 wt% or more based
on the whole components. The same will apply to other
components hereinafter.</p>
    <p num="0061">In this invention, it is preferred to use a base 
plate whose surface is roughened electrochemically with an
electrolyte of aqueous solution containing hydrochloric
acid. In the electrochemical roughening treatment using an
electrolyte containing mainly hydrochloric acid, small pits
having a mean opening diameter of 0.01 - several µm and a
ratio of depth to mean opening diameter of 0.1 - 0.5 are
formed and, at the same time, a large undulation having a
mean opening diameter of several to 10 µm is formed easily.
That is, a double structure is formed, with a result that a
roughened surface that is preferable in terms of stain
resistance and press life may be obtained. If necessary,
nitrates, chlorides, amines, aldehydes, phosphoric acid,
cromic acid, boric acid, acetic acid, sulfuric acid, oxalic
acid etc. can be added to the electrolyte; in particular,
acetic and sulfuric acid are preferred.</p>
    <p num="0062">In this invention, in the electrochemical roughening
treatment as mentioned above, the ratio of Q<sub>C</sub>/Q<sub>A</sub>, wherein Q<sub>C</sub>
is the quantity of electricity of aluminum plate as cathode
and Q<sub>A</sub> is the quantity of electricity of aluminum plate as
anode, is selected, for example, within the range of 0.95 -
2.5. In this way, uniform honeycomb pits may be formed on
the surface of aluminum plate. If the ratio of Q<sub>C</sub>/Q<sub>A</sub> is
less than 0.95 or exceeds 2.5, nonuniform honeycomb pits
can be formed easily. Preferably, the ratio of Q<sub>C</sub>/Q<sub>A</sub> is 
within the range of 1.5 - 2.0.</p>
    <p num="0063">The waveform of alternating current to be used for
the electrochemical roughening includes sine, rectangular,
triangular, trapezoidal wave etc. Above all, rectangular
or trapezoidal wave is preferred. In view of the cost for
manufacturing a power supply device, the frequency of
alternating current is preferably 30 - 200 Hz, and more
preferably 40 - 120 Hz.</p>
    <p num="0064">An example of trapezoidal wave to be used preferably
in this invention is shown in Fig. 1, in which the axis of
ordinate shows a value of current and the axis of abscissa
shows a time. Ta is an anode reaction time; tc is a
cathode reaction time; tp and tp' each represents a time
required for the current value to reach the peak value from
zero; Ia is a peak value of current at the side of anode
cycle; Ic is a peak value of current at the side of cathode
cycle. When a trapezoidal wave is used as the waveform of
alternating current, the time tp or tp' required for the
current to reach the peak value from zero is preferably 0.1
- 2 msec, more preferably 0.3 - 1.5 msec. If tp and tp'
are less than 0.1 msec, a large power source voltage may
become required at the beginning of formation of current
waveform, due to the influence of impedance of the power
source circuit so that the installation cost of power 
source becomes higher. If the values of tp and tp' exceed
2 msec, the influence of trace components in the acid
aqueous solution becomes great so that the uniform
roughening treatment may become difficult to perform in
some cases.</p>
    <p num="0065">The duty of alternating current to be used in the
electrochemical roughening treatment is preferably within
the range of 0.25 - 0.5, more preferably 0.3 - 0.4, in view
of achieving the uniform roughening of the surface of
aluminum plate. The duty as described in this invention
means the ratio of ta/T, wherein T is the period of
alternating current and ta is the time during which the
anode reaction of the aluminum plate continues (anode
reaction time). Particularly, on the surface of the
aluminum plate during the cathode reaction, a smut
component comprising mainly aluminum hydroxide is formed
and moreover the dissolution and breakage of an oxide film
occur which serves the beginning points of the pitting
reaction at the time of next anode reaction of the aluminum
plate. Therefore, the selection of duty of alternating
current may greatly affect the uniform roughening process.</p>
    <p num="0066">As to the current density of alternating current, in
a case of trapezoidal or rectangular wave, the current
density Iap at the peak current value at the side of anode 
cycle and the current density Icp at the peak current value
at the side of cathode cycle are preferably 10 - 200 A/dm<sup>2</sup>
respectively. Further, the ratio of Icp/Iap is preferably
within the range of 0.9 - 1.5.</p>
    <p num="0067">In the electrochemical roughening treatment, the sum
of quantity of electricity used for the anode reaction of
the aluminum plate at the end of the electrochemical
roughening treatment is preferably 50 - 1000 C/dm<sup>2</sup>. The
electrochemical roughening treatment is performed
preferably for one second to 30 min.</p>
    <p num="0068">As mentioned above, as acid aqueous solutions
containing mainly nitric acid, there may be used solutions
which are used in the ordinary electrochemical roughening
treatment using a direct or alternating current. For
example, more than one of nitrate compounds such as
aluminum nitrate, sodium nitrate, ammonium nitrate etc. may
be added for use at a concentration of from 0.01 g/L to
saturation, to nitric acid aqueous solution having a nitric
acid concentration of 5- 15 g/L. In the acid aqueous
solution containing mainly nitric acid, metals contained in
aluminum alloys, such as iron, copper, manganese, nickel,
titanium, magnesium, silicon etc. may be dissolved.</p>
    <p num="0069">As acid aqueous solutions containing mainly nitric
acid, in particular, there may be used preferably those 
solutions which contain nitric acid, salts of aluminum and
nitrates and are obtained by adding aluminum and ammonium
nitrate into a nitric acid aqueous solution having a nitric
acid concentration of 5 - 15 g/L, such that concentration
of aluminum ion becomes 1 - 15g/L, preferably 1 - 10g/L,
and the ammonium ion is present at 10 - 300 ppm. The
quantities of the aluminum and ammonium ions mentioned
above spontaneously increase during the electrochemical
roughening treatment. The temperature of solution at this
time is preferably 10 - 95°C, more preferably 20 - 90°C,
and especially preferably 40 - 80°C.</p>
    <p num="0070">In the electrochemical roughening treatment, known
electrolytic apparatus of vertical, flat, or radial type
may be used. The electrolytic apparatus of radial type
described in JP 5-195300 A is especially preferred.</p>
    <p num="0071">Fig. 2 shows an outline of an electrolytic apparatus
of radial type to be used preferably in this invention. In
the electrolytic apparatus of radial type shown in Fig. 2,
an aluminum plate 11 is wound around a radial roller 12
arranged in the main electrolytic bath 21 and electrolyzed
during the conveyance thereof by means of main electrodes
13a and 13b connected to an alternating current source 20.
The acid aqueous solution 14 is fed from the solution feed
opening 15 through a slit 16 to a solution passage 17 
between the main electrodes 13a and 13b.</p>
    <p num="0072">Then, the aluminum plate 11 to which treatment has
been performed in the main electrolytic cell 21 is
electrolyzed in an auxiliary anode bath 22. Auxiliary
anodes 18 are arranged opposite to the aluminum plate 11 in
the auxiliary bath 22 and the acid aqueous solution 14 is
fed so as to flow between the auxiliary anodes 18 and the
aluminum plate 11. The current supply to the auxiliary
anodes is controlled by means of thyristors 19a and 19b.</p>
    <p num="0073">The main electrodes 13a and 13b can be selected from
carbon, platinum, titanium, niobium, zirconium, stainless
steel, cathode used for fuel cell, etc.; of these, carbon
is particularly preferred. Impermeable graphite for
chemical equipment or resin-impregnated graphite commonly
available on the market, etc. can be used.</p>
    <p num="0074">The auxiliary anode 18 can be selected from the known
oxygen-generating electrodes, such as ferrite, iridium
oxide, and platinum, or platinum that is clad or plated
with bulb metal such as titanium, niobium, zirconium, etc.</p>
    <p num="0075">The feed direction of acid aqueous solution passing
through the main electrolytic bath 21 and the auxiliary
anode bath 22 may be parallel or counter to the advancement
direction of aluminum plate 11. The flow rate of acid
aqueous solution relative to the aluminum plate is 
preferably 10 - 1000 cm/sec.</p>
    <p num="0076">One or more alternating current sources can be
connected to an electrolytic apparatus. More than two
electrolytic apparatuses may be also used. The
electrolytic condition of each apparatus may be the same or
different.</p>
    <p num="0077">Further, after the finish of electrolytic treatment,
it is preferred to perform liquid removal by a nip roller
and the washing by spray so as not to leave the treating
liquid to the next step</p>
    <p num="0078">In a case of using the electrolytic apparatus as
mentioned above, it is preferable to maintain a constant
concentration of the acid aqueous solution by adding acid
and water while adjusting the amount of addition thereof
based on the concentration of acid and aluminum ions, which
are proportional to the current applied in the acid aqueous
solution, in which the aluminum plate in the electrolytic
apparatus reacts with the anode, and obtained, for example,
from (i) electroconductivity of the solution, (ii)
propagation velocity of supersonic wave and (iii)
temperature; and by sequentially overflowing the same
amount of acid aqueous solution as the volume of acid and
water added.</p>
    <p num="0079">Each of the surface treatments, such as mechanical 
roughening treatment, chemical etching in an acid or
alkaline aqueous solution, and desmutting, will be
explained in the stated order. Each surface treatment is
performed before the electrochemical roughening treatment
mentioned above, or after the electrochemical roughening
treatment but before the anodic oxidation as mentioned
hereinafter. However, the explanation of each surface
treatment as mentioned below is merely an example and this
invention is not limited to the following surface treatment.
Further, each treatment including the surface treatment as
mentioned above may be performed arbitrarily.</p>
    <p num="0080">The mechanical roughening is the treatment in which
the surface of aluminum plate is roughened by using brush
etc., which is performed preferably before the
electrochemical roughening.</p>
    <p num="0081">The preferred mechanical roughening treatment is
performed by using a rotary nylon brush roll having a
bristle diameter of 0.07 - 0.57 mm and a slurry of abrasive
that is fed to the surface of aluminum plate.</p>
    <p num="0082">Preferred is a nylon brush having a low water
absorption, for example, NYLON BRISTLE 200T from Toray
Industries, Inc. (6,10-nylon; softening point: 180°C;
melting point: 212 - 214; specific gravity: 1.08 - 1.09;
water partition rate: 1.4 - 1.8 at 20°C and 65% R.H, 2 - 
2.8 at 20°C and 100% R.H.; dry tensile strength: 4.5 - 6
g/d; dry tensile elongation: 20 - 35%; reduction rate in
boiling water: 1 - 4%; dry tensile resistance: 39 - 45 g/d;
Young's modulus (dry): 380 - 400 kg/mm<sup>2</sup>).</p>
    <p num="0083">Any known abrasive can be used. Preferably, quartz
sand, quartz, aluminum hydroxide or the mixture thereof
described in JP 6-135175 A and JP 50-40047 B are used.</p>
    <p num="0084">A slurry having a specific gravity within the range
of 1.05 - 1.3 is preferred. As a method for feeding the
slurry solution to the surface of aluminum plate, there are,
for example: a method of spraying the slurry solution; a
method in which wirebrushes are used; and a method of
transferring the surface profile of an uneven reduction
rolling roll onto the aluminum plate. The methods
described in JP 55-074898 A, JP 61-162351 A, and JP 63-104889
A may be also used. Further, as described in JP 9-509108
A, a method can be used in which the surface of the
aluminum plate is brushed in an aqueous slurry containing a
mixture of aluminum and quartz particles at a mass ratio
within the range of 95:5 - 5:95. The mean particle size of
the above mixture is preferably 4 - 40 µm, particularly
preferably within the range of 1 - 20 µm.</p>
    <heading>&lt;Alkaline Etching&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0085">The alkaline etching is the treatment in which the 
surface of an aluminum plate is etched chemically in an
alkaline aqueous solution, and is preferably carried out
both before and after the electrochemical roughening
treatment. When the mechanical roughening treatment is
performed before the electrochemical roughening treatment,
it is carried out preferably after the mechanical
roughening treatment. The alkaline etching is more
advantageous than the acid etching mentioned hereinafter
because the micro structure can be broken in a short period
of time in the alkaline etching.</p>
    <p num="0086">Examples of the alkaline aqueous solutions used in
the alkaline etching treatment include aqueous solutions
containing one or more of caustic soda, sal soda, aluminate
of soda, metasilicate of soda, phosphate of soda, potassium
hydroxide and lithium hydroxide. Especially, an aqueous
solution mainly containing sodium hydroxide (caustic soda)
is preferred. The alkaline aqueous solution may contain
not only aluminum but alloy components contained in the
aluminum plate in an amount of 0.5 - 10 wt%.</p>
    <p num="0087">Preferably, the concentration of alkaline aqueous
solution is 1 - 50 wt%, more preferably 1 - 30 wt%.</p>
    <p num="0088">The alkaline etching is performed preferably at a
temperature of the alkaline aqueous solution of 20 - 100°C,
preferably 40 - 80°C and for 1 - 120 sec, preferably 2 - 60 
sec. The amount of aluminum dissolved is preferably 5 - 20
g/m<sup>2</sup> when the alkaline etching is performed after the
mechanical roughening treatment and 0.01 - 20 g/m<sup>2</sup> when the
alkaline etching is performed after the electrochemical
roughening treatment. When a chemical etching solution is
mixed in an alkaline aqueous solution for the first time,
it is preferred to prepare the treating solution by using
liquid sodium hydroxide (caustic soda) and sodium aluminate
(alumic acid soda).</p>
    <p num="0089">Further, after finishing the alkaline etching, it is
preferable to perform removal of the solution by the nip
roller and the washing by spray so as not to leave the
treating solution to the next step.</p>
    <p num="0090">When the alkaline etching is performed after the
electrochemical roughening treatment, the smut generated
due to the electrochemical roughening treatment can be
removed. As such alkaline etching, preferred are a method
described in JP 53-12739 A in which the plate is contacted
with sulfuric acid of 15 - 65 wt% and at a temperature of
50 - 90°C, and the alkaline etching method described in JP
48-28123 B.</p>
    <heading>&lt;Acid Etching&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0091">The acid etching is the treatment in which the
aluminum plate is chemically etched in an acid aqueous 
solution, which is preferably performed after the
electrochemical roughening treatment. When the acid
etching is carried out before and/or after the
electrochemical roughening treatment, it is also preferred
to perform the acid etching after the alkaline etching.</p>
    <p num="0092">When the acid etching is performed on the aluminum
plate after the alkaline etching, intermetallic compounds
containing silica or single substance Si on the surface of
aluminum plate can be removed, whereby defects of an anodic
oxide film that may be generated in the subsequent anodic
oxidation treatment can be eliminated. As a result, a
trouble may be prevented in which dot-like ink called as
dust-like stain is adhered to the non-image area during the
printing.</p>
    <p num="0093">As acid solutions to be used in the acid etching,
there are aqueous solutions containing phosphoric, nitric,
sulfuric, chromic and hydrochloric acid, or a mixed acid of
more than two acids thereof. In particular, sulfuric acid
aqueous solution is preferred. The concentration of acid
aqueous solution is preferably 50 - 500 g/L. The acid
aqueous solution may contain not only aluminum but alloy
components contained in the aluminum plate.</p>
    <p num="0094">The acid etching is performed preferably at a
temperature of the solution of 60 - 90°C, preferably 70 - 
80°C, for 1 - 10 sec. And, the concentration of acid, for
example, the concentration of sulfuric acid and aluminum
ion are selected preferably within the range so that no
separation occurs at ordinary temperature. The preferred
concentration of aluminum ion is 0.1 - 50 g/L, more
preferably 5 - 15 g/L.</p>
    <p num="0095">Further, after finishing the acid etching, it is
preferred to carry out removal of the solution by nip
roller and washing by spray so as not to leave the treating
solution to the next step.</p>
    <heading>&lt;Desmut Treatment&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0096">When the alkaline etching is performed before and/or
after the above-mentioned electrochemical roughening
treatment, smut is generally formed on the surface of the
aluminum plate due to the alkaline etching. Therefore, the
so-called desmutting, in which the smut is dissolved in an
acid solution containing phosphoric, nitric, sulfuric,
chromic, hydrochloric, hydrofluoric and borofluoric acid,
or a mixed acid containing more than two of these acids, is
preferably performed after the alkaline etching.
Incidentally, after the alkaline etching treatment, it is
sufficient to perform any one of the acid etching and
desmutting.</p>
    <p num="0097">The concentration of acid solution is preferably 1 - 
500 g/L. Not only aluminum but alloy components contained
in the aluminum plate may be dissolved in an amount of
0.001 - 50 g/L in the acid solution.</p>
    <p num="0098">The temperature of acid solution is preferably 20 -
95°C, and more preferably 30 - 70°C. The treatment is
performed preferably for 1 - 120 sec, more preferably for 2
- 60 sec.</p>
    <p num="0099">As the desmut treatment solution (acid solution), the
waste liquor of the acid aqueous solution used in the
above-mentioned electrochemical roughening treatment is
used preferably in view of reducing the amount of waste
liquor.</p>
    <p num="0100">After finishing the desmutting, it is preferred to
carry-out removal of the solution by a nip roller and
washing by spray, so as not to leave the treating solution
to the next step.</p>
    <p num="0101">A preferred embodiment of the combination of these
surface treatment is described below:</p>
    <p num="0102">First, the mechanical roughening treatment and/or
alkaline etching is performed and then the desmutting.
Secondly, the electrochemical roughening treatment is
performed, and then, any one of (1) acid etching, (2)
alkaline etching and the subsequent desmutting, (3)
alkaline etching and the subsequent acid etching is carried 
out.</p>
    <p num="0103">The lithographic printing original plate according to
this invention that has been subjected to the roughening
treatment has preferably roughened small pits having a mean
opening diameter of 0.01 - 3 µm, more preferably 0.05 - 2
µm, and especially preferably 0.05 - 1.0 µm. The above
diameter range may ensure satisfactory stain resistance
upon printing and satisfactory or excellent press life.</p>
    <p num="0104">The ratio of the mean depth to the mean opening
diameter of the small pits is preferably 0.1 - 0.5, more
preferably 0.1 - 0.3, and especially preferably 0.15 - 0.2.
The above range is preferred since it ensure that the stain
resistance upon printing and the press life are not
deteriorated.</p>
    <p num="0105">The mean opening diameter of the large roughened
undulation is preferably 3 - 20 µm, more preferably 3 - 17
µm, and especially preferably 4 - 10 µm. The above range
is preferred as it ensures that the stain resistance and
press life upon printing, as well as general stain
resistant property are not deteriorated.</p>
    <heading>&lt;Formation of Hydrophilic Film&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0106">Treatment is performed with respect to the aluminum
plate whose surface has been thus roughened and, if
necessary, other treatments as described above, to form a 
hydrophilic film having a low heat conductivity.</p>
    <p num="0107">The hydrophilic film has a heat conductivity in the
direction of film thickness of more than 0.05 W/(m·K),
preferably more than 0.08 W/(m·K), but less than 0.5
W/(m·K), preferably less than 0.3 W/(m·K), and more
preferably less than 0.2 W/(m·K). If the heat conductivity
in the direction of film thickness is 0.05 - 0.5 W/(m·K),
the heat generated on the recording layer by the exposure
to laser beam is not diffused in the support. As a result,
when the lithographic printing original plate is used as
the on-press development type or the non-treatment type, a
higher sensitivity is obtained; when it is used as a
conventional thermal positive type, a higher sensitivity is
obtained and the problem of a residual film is eliminated;
and when it is used as a conventional thermal negative type,
the problem such as insufficient formation of image is
eliminated.</p>
    <p num="0108">The heat conductivity of the hydrophilic film in the
direction of its film thickness, which is defined in this
invention, will be explained hereinafter:</p>
    <p num="0109">There have been hitherto reported various kinds of
methods for measuring the heat conductivity of a thin film.
In 1996, Ono et al. reported on a method of measuring the
heat conductivity of a thin film in the direction of its 
plane using a thermograph. An attempt has been also
reported, in which a method of heating with alternating
current was applied to the measurement of thermal
properties of a thin film. Although the origin of the
method of heating with alternating current can go back to a
report in 1863, various methods have been proposed in
recent years by the development of a heating method with
laser and the combination thereof with Fourier
transformation. An apparatus using the laser Ångstöm
method is actually available on the market. All these
methods are for measuring the heat conductivity of a thin
film in the direction of its plane (direction in plane).</p>
    <p num="0110">However, when measuring the heat conductivity of a
thin film, the heat diffusion in the depth direction of the
film is actually considered as a more important factor.
Various reports suggest that the heat conductivity of a
thin film is anisotropic and, particularly in this
invention, it is very important to directly measure the
heat conductivity of a thin film in the direction of its
film thickness. In this respect, as an attempt to measure
the heat properties of a thin film in the direction of its
film thickness, a method using a thermocomparator was
reported in the paper of Lambropoulos et al. (J, Appl.
Phys., 66(9), (1 November 1989) and the paper of Henager et 
al. (APPLIED OPTICS, Vol., 32, No.1 (1 January 1993)).
Moreover, recently, Hashimoto et al. reported a method in
which the thermal difusivity of a thin polymer film was
measured by the temperature wave thermal analysis applying
Fourier analysis (Netsu Sokutei, 27(3) (2000)).</p>
    <p num="0111">The heat conductivity of a hydrophilic film in the
direction of its film thickness defined in this invention
is measured by a method using a thermocomparator. The
method will be explained hereinafter in detail. The
fundamental principle thereof is described in detail in the
paper of Lambropoulos et al and Henager et al. The
apparatus to be used for the method is not limited to the
apparatus described hereinafter.</p>
    <p num="0112">Fig.3 shows the outline of a thermocomparator 30
which can be used for the measurement of the heat
conductivity of a hydrophilic film for the lithographic
printing plate according to this invention, in the
direction of its film thickness. The method using a
thermocomparator is affected largely by the contact area
with a thin film and the state (roughness) of the contact
surface. Therefore, it is important that the tip end of
the thermocmoparator which contacts with the thin film be
made as small as possible. For example, a tip (wire rod)
31 formed of oxygen-free copper and having a vary small 
point (radius r<sub>1</sub> = 0.2mm) is used.</p>
    <p num="0113">The tip 31 is fixed at the center of a reservoir 32
formed of constantan and a heating jacket 34 formed of
oxygen-free copper and having electric heaters 33 is fixed
around the reservoir 32. When the heating jacket 34 is
heated by the electric heaters 33 and the temperature of
the reservoir 32 is controlled so as to be 60 ± 1°C while
feed-backing the output of a thermo-couple 35 equipped
inside the reservoir 32, the tip 31 is heated up to the
temperature of 60 ± 1°C. On the other hand, a heat sink 36
formed of oxygen-free copper and having a radius of 10cm
and a thickness of 10mm is prepared, and a metallic base 38
having thereon a film 37 to be determined is placed on the
heat sink 36. The temperature of the surface of the heat
sink 36 is measured by a contact type thermometer 39.</p>
    <p num="0114">After the thermocomparator 30 is placed as mentioned
above, the point of the heated tip 31 is closely contacted
with the surface of the film 37. The thermocomparator 30
is, for example, attached instead of an indenting tool, to
the point of a dynamic small handness meter so as to be
vertically driven, and is adapted such that the tip 31 may
abut with the surface of the film 37 and be pressed up to
the load of 0.5 mN. Thus, variation in the contact area
between the film 37 to be determined and the tip 31 can be 
minimized.</p>
    <p num="0115">When the heated tip 31 is contacted with the film 37,
the temperature at the point of the tip 31 is lowered but
it reaches a steady state at a certain constant temperature.
This is because the heat quantity which is imparted by the
electric heater 33 to the tip 31 through the heating jacket
34 and reservoir 32 is balanced with the heat quantity
which is diffused from the tip 31 to the heat sink 36 the
thorough the metallic base 38. Then, at this time, the
temperature at the point of the tip, the temperature of the
heat sink and the temperature of the reservoir are recorded
by a temperature recorder 40 for recording the temperature
at the point of the tip, a temperature recorder 41 for
recording the temperature of the heat sink and a
temperature recorder 42 for recording the temperature of
the reservoir, respectively.</p>
    <p num="0116">The relationship between these temperatures and the
heat conductivity of the film is represented as the
following equation(1):
<img id="img-00410001" orientation="unknown" wi="112" img-format="tif" img-content="mf" file="00410001.tif" inline="no" he="24"/></p>
    <p num="0117">Wherein the symbols in the equation are as follows: <sl><li>T<sub>t</sub>: Temperature at the point of tip;</li><li>T<sub>b</sub>: Temperature of heat sink;</li><li>T<sub>r</sub>: Temperature of reservoir;</li><li>T<sub>tf</sub>: Heat conductivity of film;</li><li>K<sub>1</sub>: Heat conductivity of reservoir;</li><li>K<sub>2</sub>: Heat conductivity of tip (tip formed of oxygen-free
copper: 400 W/(m·K))</li><li>K<sub>4</sub>: Heat conductivity of metallic base (when film is not
formed);</li><li>r<sub>1</sub>: Radius of curvature of the point of tip;</li><li>A<sub>2</sub>: Contact area between reservoir and tip;</li><li>A<sub>3</sub>: Contact area between tip and film;</li><li>t<sub>1</sub>: Thickness of film;</li><li>t<sub>2</sub>: Contact thickness (nearly 0).</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0118">Each temperature (Tt, Tb and Tr) is measured while
varying the film thickness (t) and plotted, so that the
gradient of the equation (1) and the heat conductivity of
film may be obtained. Namely, as is apparent from the
equation (1), the gradient is given by the heat
conductivity of reservoir (K<sub>1</sub>), the radius of curvature of
the point of the tip (r<sub>1</sub>), the heat conductivity of film
(K<sub>tf</sub>) and the contact area between the tip and the film (A<sub>3</sub>).
Since the values of K<sub>1</sub>, r<sub>1</sub>, and A<sub>3</sub> are known, the value of
K<sub>tf</sub> may be obtained from the gradient. </p>
    <p num="0119">The present inventors used the measurement method as
mentioned above to seek the heat conductivity of an anodic
oxide film (Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>) formed on the aluminum base plate. The
heat conductivity of Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, which was obtained from the
gradient of a graph plotted by measuring the temperature
with varying the film thickness and, was 0.69 W/(m·K). The
value coincides with the result from the paper of
Lambropoulos et al. as mentioned above. The result also
proves that the thermophysical properties of a thin film is
different from these of bulk (the heat conductivity of
Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> of bulk is 28 W/(m·K)).</p>
    <p num="0120">It is preferable to apply the method as mentioned
above to the measurement of heat conductivity in the
direction of film thickness of a hydrophilic film of the
lithographic printing plate according to this invention,
because a result without variations or inconsistencies can
be obtained also with respect to the roughened surface for
the lithographic printing plate since it allows the point
of the tip to be made very small and the press load can be
kept constant. The heat conductivity will be obtained
preferably as a mean value of measurements performed at a
plurality of different points on a sample, for example, at
five points.</p>
    <p num="0121">The film thickness of the hydrophilic film is, in 
view of scratch resistance and press life, preferably more
than 0.1 µm, more preferably more than 0.3 µm, and
especially preferably more than 0.6 µm. Since, in view of
manufacturing cost, formation of a thick film requires a
large amount of energy, the film thickness is preferably
less than 5 µm, more preferably less than 3 µm, and
especially preferably less than 2 µm.</p>
    <p num="0122">In view of the effect on the heat insulation, the
strength of film and the stain resistance upon printing,
the density of the hydrophilic film according to this
invention is preferably 2000 - 3200 kg/m<sup>3</sup>.</p>
    <p num="0123">The density to be measured can be calculated
according to the following equation using, for example, the
mass determined by Mason's method (i.e. a method of
weighing an anodic oxide film by dissolving it in mixture
of chromic and phosphoric acids) and the film thickness
determined by observing the section of the film with SEM.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">Density (kg/m<st32:sup pos="post">3</st32:sup>) = (Mass of hydrophilic film per unit
area / Film thickness)</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0124">The method for forming the hydrophilic film is not
especially limited; anodic oxidation, vapor deposition, CDV,
Sol-Gel method, spattering, ion plating, diffusion etc. may
be used suitably. Also, there may be used a method of
coating on the plate a solution in which hydrophilic resin 
or sol-gel solution is admixed with hollow particles.</p>
    <p num="0125">Above all, it is most preferable to use the treatment
for forming an oxide by the anodic oxidation, i.e., the
anode oxidation treatment. The anode oxidation treatment
can be performed in a manner known in this field.
Specifically, when a direct or alternating current is fed
to the aluminum plate in aqueous or non-aqueous solution
containing a single or a combination of more than two of
sulfuric, phosphoric, chromic, oxalic, sulfuric or
benzensulfonic acid etc., an anodic oxide film as a
hydrophilic film can be formed on the surface of the
aluminum plate.</p>
    <p num="0126">The condition of anode oxidation treatment can not be
uniquely determined because it may vary depending on the
electrolyte to be used. However, the following will be
generally appropriate: 1 - 80 wt%; temperature of solution:
5 - 70°C; density of current: 0.5 - 60 A/dm<sup>2</sup>; voltage: 1 -
200 V; and time period of electrolysis: 1 - 1000 sec.</p>
    <p num="0127">Among these anode oxidation treatments, the method
described in BP 1412768 A, that is, anodic oxidation is
performed at high current density in a sulfuric acid
electrolyte, and the method described in US 3511661 A, that
is, anodic oxidation performed in a phosphoric acid
electrolyte, are preferred. Further, a multiple anode 
oxidation treatment comprising performing the anodic
oxidation in sulfuric acid and then in phosphoric acid may
be performed.</p>
    <p num="0128">In this invention, in view of scratch resistance and
press life, the basis weight of anodic oxide film is
preferably more than 0.1 g/m<sup>2</sup>, more preferably 0.3 g/m<sup>2</sup> or
more, especially preferably 2 g/m<sup>2</sup> or more, and further
more preferably 3.2 g/m<sup>2</sup> or more. Considering a large
amount of energy required to form a thick film, it is
preferably less than 100 g/m<sup>2</sup>, more preferably less than 40
g/m<sup>2</sup>, and especially preferably less than 20 g/m<sup>2</sup>.</p>
    <p num="0129">Fine concaves called as micro pores are formed with
uniform distribution on the surface of the anodic oxide
film. The density of micro pores formed on the anodic
oxide film may be adjusted by selecting suitably the
condition of treatment. Increasing the density of micro
pores can result in heat conductivity in the direction of
film thickness of the anodic oxide film of 0.05 - 0.5
W/(m·K).</p>
    <p num="0130">The diameter of micro pores formed on the anodic
oxide film may be adjusted by selecting suitably the
condition of treatment. Increasing the diameter if micro
pores can result in heat conductivity in the direction of
film thickness of the anodic oxide film of 0.05 - 0.5 
W/(m·K).</p>
    <p num="0131">In this invention, for the purpose of decreasing the
heat conductivity, it is preferable to perform pore-widening
treatment to increase the diameter of micro pore
after the anodic oxidation. In the pore-widening treatment,
the aluminum base plate having an anodic oxide film formed
thereon is dipped in acid or alkaline aqueous solution to
dissolve the film and thus widen the diameter of a micro
pore. The pore-widening treatment is performed in such a
manner that the amount of the anodic oxide film dissolved
is within the range of preferably 0.01 - 20 g/m<sup>2</sup>, more
preferably 0.1 - 5 g/m<sup>2</sup>, and especially preferably 0.2 - 4
g/m<sup>2</sup>.</p>
    <p num="0132">When using an acid aqueous solution for the pore-widening
treatment, an aqueous solution of inorganic acid,
such as sulfuric, phosphoric, nitric, and hydrochloric acid,
or of the mixture thereof is used preferably. The
concentration of acid solution is preferably 10 - 1000 g/L,
and more preferably 20 - 500 g/L. The temperature of acid
solution is preferably 10 - 90°C, and more preferably 30 -
70°C. The dipping time in the acid solution is preferably
1 - 300 sec, and more preferably 2 - 100 sec.</p>
    <p num="0133">On the other hand, when using an alkaline aqueous
solution for the pore-widening treatment, an alkaline 
solution of alkali selected from the group consisting of
sodium, potassium and lithium hydroxide is used preferably.
The pH value of the alkaline solution is preferably 10 - 13,
and more preferably 11.5 - 13.0. The temperature of the
alkaline aqueous solution is preferably 10 - 90°C, and more
preferably 30 - 50°C. The dipping time in the alkaline
aqueous solution is preferably 1 - 500 sec, and more
preferably 2 - 100 sec.</p>
    <p num="0134">However, if the diameter of a micro pore on the
uppermost surface is widen too much the stain resistance in
press working deteriorates. Preferably the diameter of a
micro pore on the uppermost surface is 40 or less than 40
µm, more preferably 20 or less than 20 µm, most preferably
10 or less than 10 µm. If it is set within the range
mentioned above the heat insulating property in anodic
oxide film is consistent with stain resistance.</p>
    <p num="0135">As to the more preferably shape of the pores in
anodic oxide film the pore diameter on the uppermost
surface is 0 - 40 µm and the pore diameter in the inside is
20 - 300 µm.</p>
    <p num="0136">For example, it is known that the diameter of a micro
pore performed by anodic oxidation treatment is
proportionally increased by the electric voltage charged in
electrolysis within the same electrolyte. By using this 
tendency the following producing method may be applied.
When the electric voltage gradually increases in
electrolysis the pore diameter in the bottom of the pore
may be widen. It is also known that the diameter of a
micro pore produced in anodic oxidation treatment varies
according to the variation of electrolytes. The diameter
of a micro pore produced by anodic oxidation treatment in
various electrolytes increases in the order of sulfuric
acid &lt; oxalic acid &lt; phosphoric acid.</p>
    <p num="0137">It is preferable that the anodic oxide film is formed
by anodic oxidation that consists of more than two steps.
And more preferably the anodic oxidation is performed with
an electrolyte containing sulfuric acid in the first step
and then with an electrolyte containing phosphoric acid in
the second and subsequent steps. Furthermore the support
treated by anodic oxidation treatment and/or pore widening
treatment may be treated by the pore-sealing process as
described below.</p>
    <p num="0138">Other than the anodic oxide film as mentioned above,
the hydrophilic film may be an inorganic film formed by
spattering, CVD method etc. The compounds forming the
inorganic film include, for example, oxides, nitrides,
silicates, borates and carbides. The inorganic film may
consist of only simple compound or of a mixture of 
compounds.</p>
    <p num="0139">As compounds for forming the inorganic film, specific
examples thereof include: aluminum, silicon, titanium,
zirconium, bafnium, vanadium, niobium, tantalum, molybdenum,
wolfram and chromium oxide; aluminum, silicon, titanium,
zirconium, bafnium, vanadium, niobium, tantalum, molybdenum,
wolfram, chromium and boron nitride; titanium, zirconium,
bafnium, vanadium, niobium, tantalum, molybdenum, wolfram,
and chromium silicate; titanium, zirconium, bafnium,
vanadium, niobium, tantalum, molybdenum, wolfram and
chromium boride; aluminum, silicon, titanium, zirconium,
bafnium, vanadium, niobium, tantalum, molybdenum, wolfram
and chromium carbide.</p>
    <heading>&lt;Pore-Sealing Treatment&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0140">In this invention, the support for lithographic
printing plate according to this invention, on which a
hydrophlic film is formed, may be subjected to pore-sealing
treatment.</p>
    <p num="0141">As the pore-sealing treatment to be used in this
invention, there is mentioned the pore-sealing treatment
for the anodic oxide film by means of pressure steam or hot
water, which is described in JP 4-176690 A and Japanese
Patent Application No. 10-106819 (JP 11-301135 A). Known
treatment methods using silicate, dichromate aqueous 
solution, nitrite, ammonium acetate, electrodeposition
sealing, triethanolamine, barium carbonate, hot water
containing extremely small amount of phosphate etc. may be
used. The pore-sealed film is formed, for example, from
the bottom of pores in the case where electrodeposition
sealing is performed, and from the upper parts of pores in
the case where steam sealing is performed; the manner of
the formation of pore-sealed film is different depending on
the type of the pore-sealing treatment performed.</p>
    <p num="0142">Alternatively examples thereof include dipping in
solution, spraying, coating, vapor deposition, spattering,
ion-plating, flame coating, plating etc., but are not
limited to these treatments.</p>
    <p num="0143">Above all, especially preferred is the pore-sealing
treatment using particles having a mean particle size of 8-800
nm, described in JP 2001-9871 A.</p>
    <p num="0144">In the pore-sealing treatment using particles, the
treatment is performed with particles having a mean
particles size of 8-800 nm, preferably 10-500nm, and more
preferably 10-150 nm. Within the range of mean particle
size, there is little fear of the particles entering into
micro pores on the hydrophilic film, and a sufficient
sensitization effect can be obtained. Further, the
adhesion of film to the image recording layer becomes 
satisfactory, whereby an excellent press life can be
attained. The thickness of the particle layer is
preferably 8-800 nm, and more preferably 10-500 nm.</p>
    <p num="0145">The heat conductivity of particles to be used in this
invention is preferably less than 60W/(m·K), more
preferably less than 40W/(m·K), and especially preferably
0.3-10 or less than 0.3-10W/(m·K). If the heat
conductivity is less than 60W/ (m·K), the heat diffusion to
the aluminum base plate is prevented sufficiently and thus
satisfactory sensitization effect can be obtained.</p>
    <p num="0146">As the method for forming a particle layer, there are
mentioned, for example, dipping in solution, spraying,
coating, electrolysis, vapor deposition, spattering, ion-plating,
flame coating, plating etc.; however, the method
is not limited to these treatment.</p>
    <p num="0147">The electrolysis is performed with direct or
alternating current. The waveform of alternating current
used for the electrolysis includes sine, rectangular,
triangular and trapezoidal wave etc. In view of the cost
of manufacturing power source, the frequency of alternating
current is preferably 30-200Hz, and more preferably 40-120Hz.
When using a trapezoidal wave as the waveform of
alternating current, the time tp necessary for the current
to reach the peak value from zero is preferably 0.1-2 msec, 
and more preferably 0.3-1.5 msec respectively. If tp is
less than 0.1 msec, a large power source voltage becomes
required at the beginning of formation of current waveform
due to the influence of the power source circuit so that
the installation cost of power source may become higher.</p>
    <p num="0148">As the hydrophilic particles, single or a combination
of more than two of Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> TiO<sub>2</sub>, SiO<sub>2</sub>, and ZrO<sub>2</sub> is used
preferably. The electrolyte is obtained, for example, by
suspending the hydrophilic particles in water etc. in such
manner that the content thereof is 0.01-20% of the whole.
The pH value of the electrolyte may be adjusted, for
example, by adding sulfuric acid to charge positive or
negative. The electrolysis is performed using the aluminum
plate as cathode and with direct current, by using the
electrolyte as mentioned above at an voltage of 10-200V for
1-600 sec. According to this method, the micro pores in
the anodic oxide film may be sealed while leaving spaces
inside the micro pores.</p>
    <p num="0149">For the pore-sealing treatment, there is mentioned a
method of forming by coating a layer such as: a layer
composed of a compound having at least one amino group and
at least one group selected from the group consisting of
carboxyl and the salt thereof and sulfonyl and the salt
thereof, which is described in JP 60-149491 A; a layer 
composed of a compound selected from compounds having at
least one amino group and at least one hydroxy group and
their salts, which is described in JP 60-232998 A; a layer
containing phosphate described in JP 62-19494 A; and a
layer composed of a high molecular compound in molecule at
least one monomer unit having sulfo group as repeated unit,
which is described in JP 59-101651 A.</p>
    <p num="0150">Other examples thereof include a method of forming a
layer composed of a compound that is selected from:
carboxymethylcellulose; dextrim; gum arabic; phosphonic
acid having amino group, such as 2-aminoethyl phosphonic
acid; organo phosphonic acid, such as pheny-, naphthyl-,
alkyl-, glycero-, methglendi- and ethylendiphorphonic acid,
which may have substituents; organo phosphoric acid ester
such as phenyl, naphthyl, alkyl and glycero phosphate,
which may have substituents; and organo phosphinic acid
such as phenyl, naphthyl, alkyl and glycero phosphinic acid,
which may have substituents; amino acid such as glycine and
β-alanine; hydrochloride of amine having hydroxy group,
such as triethanolamine hydrochloride.</p>
    <p num="0151">A silane coupling agent having unsaturated group may
be coated for the pore-sealing treatment. As silane
coupling agents there are, for example, N-3-(acryloxy-2-hydroxypropyl)-3-aminopropyltriethoxysilane,
(3-acryloxypropyl)dimethylmethoxysilane, 
(3-acryloxypropyl)methyldimethoxysilane,
(3-acryloxypropyi)trimethoxysilane,
3-(N-allylamino)propyltrimethoxysilane,
allyldimethoxysilane,
allyltriethoxysilane, allyltrimethoxysilane, 3-butenyltriethoxysilane,
2-(chloromethyl)allyltrimethoxysilane,
methacrylamidopropyltriethoxysilane,
N-(3-methacryloxy-2-hydroxypropyl)-3-aminopropyltriethoxysilane,
(methacryloxymethyl)dimethylethoxysilene,
methacryloxymethyltriethoxysilane, methacryloxymethyltrime
thoxysilane, methacryloxypropyldimethylethoxysilane,
methacryloxypropyldimethylethoxysilane,
methacryloxypropylmethyldiethoxysilane,
methacryloxypropylmethyldimethoxysilane,
methacryloxypropylmethyltriethoxysilane, methacryloxy
propylmethyltrimethoxysilane,
methacryloxypropyltris(methoxyethoxy)silane,
methoxydimethyl-vinylsilane, 1-methoxy-3-(trimethylsiloxy)butdiene,
stylyl-ethyltrim ethoxysilane,
3-(N-stylylmethyl-2-aminoethyl-amino)-propyltrimethoxysilane
hydrochloride, vinyldimethylethoxysilane,
vinyldiphenylethoxysilane,
vinylmethyldiethoxysilane, vinylmethyldimethoxysilane, O-(vinyloxyethyl)-N-(triethoxysilylpropyl)urethane, 
vinyltriethoxysilane, vinyltrimethoxysilane, vinyltri-t-butoxysilane,
vinyltriisopropoxysilane,
vinyltriphenoxysilane, vinyltris(2-methoxyethoxy)silane,
diallylaminopropylmethoxysilane. Above all, preferred is a
silane coupling agent having methacroyl or acroyl group, of
which unsaturated group exhibits a rapid reactivity.</p>
    <p num="0152">In addition, examples of the pore-sealing treatment
include: Sol-gel coating described in JP5-50779A; coating
with phosphonic acid, described in JP5-246171A; treating
backcoat material with coating, described in JP6-234284A,
JP6-191173A and JP6-230563A; treatment with phosphonic
acids, described in JP6-262872A; coating described in JP6-297875A;
anodic oxidation described in JP10-109480A; and
dipping treatment described in Japanese Patent Application
No.10-252078(JP2000-81704A) and Japanese Patent Application
No.10-253411(JP2000-89466A). Any one of these may be used.</p>
    <heading>&lt;Hydrophilic Surface Treatment&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0153">In this invention, the support for lithographic
printing plate according to this invention, which is
obtained by forming a hydrophilic film in the manner as
mentioned above, may be subjected to the hydrophilic
surface treatment by further dipping it in aqueous solution
containing more the one hydrophilic compound. As 
hydrophilic compounds, suitable examples thereof include
compounds having polyvinyl phosphonic acid or compounds
having sulfonic acid group, sugar compounds, and silicate
compounds.</p>
    <p num="0154">Compounds having sulfonic acid group include aromatic
sulfonic acids, aldehyde condensates thereof, there
derivatives thereof and their salts.</p>
    <p num="0155">As aromatic sulfonic acids, preferred are, for
example, phenol sulfonic acid, catechol sulfonic acid,
resorcinol sulfonic acid, benzene sulfonic acid, toluene
sulfonic acid, lignin sulfonic acid, naphthalene sulfonic
acid,

acenaphthene-5-sulfonic acid, pheanthrene-2-sulfonic acid,
benzaldehyde-2(or 3)-sulfonic acid, benzaldehyde-2,4-(or
3,5)-disulfonic acid, oxybenzyl sulfonic acids,
sulfobenzoic acid, sulfanilic acid, naphthionic acid and
taurine. Above all, benzene sulfonic acid, naphthalene
sulfonic acid and ligmin sulfonic acid are preferred. The
formaldehyde condensate of benzene, naphthalene and ligium
sulfonic acids are also preferred.</p>
    <p num="0156">Further, these compounds may be used as sulfonic acid
salts. For example, there are mentioned sodium, potassium,
lithium, calcium and magnesium salts. The sodium and
potassium salts are especially preferred. </p>
    <p num="0157">The pH value of aqueous solution containing compound
having sulfonic acid group is preferably 4-6.5 and can be
adjusted to the range as mentioned above by using sulfonic
acid, sodium hydroxide, ammonia etc.</p>
    <p num="0158">The sugar compounds include monosaccharides and their
sugar alcohols, oligosaccharides, polysaccharides and
glycosides.</p>
    <p num="0159">As monosaccharides and their sugar alcohols, there
are, for example, trioses such as glycerol and their sugar
alcohols; tetroses such as threose, erythritol etc. and
sugar alcohols thereof; pentoses such as arabinose,
arabital etc. and sugar alcohols thereof; hexoses such as
glucose, sorbitol etc. and sugar alcohols thereof; heptose
such as D-glycero-D-galacto-heptose, D-glycero-D-galactoheptitol
etc. and sugar alcohols thereof; octoses
such as D-erythro-D-galactooctytol etc. and sugar alcohols
thereof; nonoses such as D-erythro-L-glucononose etc. and
sugar alcohols thereof.</p>
    <p num="0160">As olygosaccharides, there are, for example, bioses
such as saccharose, trehalose, lactose etc.; and
trisaccharides such as raffinose.</p>
    <p num="0161">As polysaccharides, there are, for example, amylose,
arabinan, cyclodextrin, cellulose alginate etc.</p>
    <p num="0162">"Glycosides" in this invention means compounds in 
which the sugar section and non-sugar section are bound
together through the ether-bound or the like.</p>
    <p num="0163">The glycosides are classified by the non-sugar
section. For example, there are alkyl glycoside, phenol
glycoside, cumarim glycoside, oxycumarin glycoside,
flavonoid glycosidese, anthraquinone glycoside, triterpene
glycoside, steroid glycoside, mustered oil glycoside.</p>
    <p num="0164">As the sugar section, there are monosaccharides as
mentioned above and sugar alcohols thereof;
olygosaccharides; and polysaccharides. Especially,
monosaccharides and olygosaccharide are preferable, and
monosaccharides and disaccharides are more preferable.</p>
    <p num="0165">Example of preferred glycosides are the compounds
represented by the following formula (I):
<img id="img-00590001" orientation="unknown" wi="124" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00590001.tif" inline="no" he="42"/></p>
    <p num="0166">In the formula (I), R represents alkyl, alkenyl or
alkynyl group having a linear or branched chain of 1 - 20
carbon atoms.</p>
    <p num="0167">Examples of an alkyl group having 1 - 20 carbon atoms
include methyl, ethyl, propyl, butyl, pentyl, hexyl, heptyl, 
octyl, nonyl, decyl, undecyl, dodecyl, tridecyl, tetradecyl,
pentadecyl, hexadecyl, heptadecyl, oatadecyle, nonadecyl,
and eicocyl group. These may be linear or branched, or
cyclic alkyl.</p>
    <p num="0168">Examples of an alkenyl group having 1 - 20 carbon
atoms include allyl and 2-butenyl group, and these may be
linear or branched, or cyclic alkenyl.</p>
    <p num="0169">Examples of an alkynyl group having 1 - 20 carbon
atoms include 1-pentynyl group, which may be linear or
branched, or cyclic alkynyl.</p>
    <p num="0170">Specific examples of the glucoside compounds
represented by the formula (I) include methyl, ethyl,
propyl, isopropyl, butyl, isobutyl, n-hexyl, octyl, capryl,
decyl, 2-ethylhexyl, 2-pentylnonyl, 2-hexyldecyl, lauryl,
myristyl, stearyl, cyclohexyl and 2-butynyl glucoside.
These compounds are glucosides as a kind of glycoside, in
which the hemiacetalhydroyl group of dextrose combines with
other compound through the ether bond, and can be obtained,
for example, by a known method in which glucose is reacted
with alcohols. Some of these alkyl glucosides are on the
market under the trade name of "GLUCOPON" by Henkel in
Germany, which can be used in this invention.</p>
    <p num="0171">Other examples of preferred glycosides are saponins,
rutin trihydrate, hesperidin methyl chalcone, hesperidin, 
nalidin hydrate, phenol-β-D-glucopyranoside, salicin,
3',5,7-methoxy-7-rutinoside.</p>
    <p num="0172">The pH value of aqueous solution containing sugar
compound is preferably 8 - 11 and can be adjusted to be
within the range mentioned above by using potassium
hydroxide, sulforic acid, carbonic acid, sodium carbonate,
phosphoric acid, sodium phosphate etc.</p>
    <p num="0173">The concentration of aqueous solution of polyvinyl
phosphonic acid is preferably 0.1-5 wt%, and more
preferably 0.2-2.5 wt%. The dipping temperature is
preferably 10-70°C, and more preferably 30-60°C. The
dipping time is preferably 1-20 sec.</p>
    <p num="0174">The concentration of aqueous solution of compound
having sulforic acid group is preferably 0.02-0.2 wt%. The
dipping temperature is preferably 60-100°C. The dipping
time is preferably 1-300 sec, and more preferably 10-100
sec.</p>
    <p num="0175">In addition, the concentration of sugar compound is
preferably 0.5-10 wt%. The dipping temperature is
preferably 40-70°C. The dipping time is preferably 2-300
sec, and more preferably 5-30 sec.</p>
    <p num="0176">In this invention, as the aqueous solution containing
hydrophilic compound other than the aqueous solution of
organic compounds as mentioned above, an aqueous solution 
of inorganic compound such as aqueous solution containing
alkali metal silicate, zirconium potassium fluoride
(K<sub>2</sub>ZrF<sub>6</sub>), or phosphoric acid/inorganic fluoro compound is
also used preferably.</p>
    <p num="0177">The treatment using the aqueous solution of alkali
metal silicate is performed by dipping a support in aqueous
solution of alkali metal silicate, preferably at a
temperature of 30-100°C, and more preferably at 50-90°C,
for preferably 0.5-40 sec, and more preferably for 1-20 sec,
the aqueous solution having a concentration of preferably
0.01-30 wt%, and more preferably 0.1-10 wt% and having a
preferred pH value of 10-13 at 25°C.</p>
    <p num="0178">Examples of the alkali metal silicates to be used in
this invention include sodium silicate, potassium silicate,
and lithium silicate. Especially, sodium or potassium
silicate is preferable.</p>
    <p num="0179">The aqueous solution of alkali metal silicate may
contain a suitable amount of hydroxide such as sodium,
potassium, and lithium hydroxide to raise the pH value.
Especially, sodium or potassium hydroxide is preferable.</p>
    <p num="0180">The aqueous solution of alkali metal silicate may
contain alkali earth metal salts or the fourth group (IVB)
metal salts. The alkaline earth metal salts are, for
example, water soluble salts such as: nitrates such as 
potassium, strontium, magnesium, and barium nitrate;
sulfate; hydrochloride; phosphate; acetate; oxalate; and
borate. The fourth group (IVB) metal salts are, for
example, titanium tetrachloride, titanium tri-chloride,
titanium potassium fluoride, titanium potassium oxalate,
titanium sulfate, titanium tetrachloride, zirconium
chloroxide, zirconium dioxide, zirconium oxychloride, and
zirconium tetrachloride etc. These alkaline earth metal
salts and the fourth (IVB) metal salts may be used alone or
in combination of more than two thereof.</p>
    <p num="0181">The treatment with aqueous solution of zirconium
potassium fluoride is performed by dipping a support at
preferably 30-80°C and for preferably 60-180 sec, in the
aqueous solution of zirconium potassium fluoride whose
concentration is preferably 0.1-10 wt%, and more preferably
0.5-2 wt%.</p>
    <p num="0182">In the treatment with phosphate/inorganic fluoro
compound, a support is dipped at preferably 20-100°C, more
preferably at 40-80°C and for preferably 20-300 sec, more
preferably for 5-30 sec, in aqueous solution in which the
concentration of phosphate compound is 5-20 wt% and the
concentration of inorganic fluoro compound is 0.01-1 wt%
and which preferably has a pH value of 3-5.</p>
    <p num="0183">The phosphates to be used in this invention are, for 
example, phosphates of metal such as alkali metal, alkaline
earth metal etc.</p>
    <p num="0184">Specific examples thereof include zinc, aluminium,
ammonium, hydrogen diammonium, dihydrogen ammonium,
monoammonium, monopotassium monosodium, dihydrogen
potassium, hydrogen dipottasium, calium, hydrogen ammonium
sodium, hydrogen magnesium, magnesium, ferrous, ferric,
dihydrogen sodium, sodium, hydrogen disodium, lead,
diammonium, dihydrogen calcium and lithium phosphate;
phosphotungstic acid; ammonium phosphotungstate, sodium
phosphotungstate; ammonium phosphomolybdate; sodium
phosphomolybdate; sodium phosphite; sodium
tripolyphosphate; and sodium pyrophosphate. Especially,
dihydrogen sodium phosphate, hydrogen disodium phosphate,
dihydrogen potassium phosphate and hydrogen dipotassium
pohosphate are preferred.</p>
    <p num="0185">As inorganic fluoro compounds to be used in this
invention, there may be preferably used metal fluorides.</p>
    <p num="0186">Specific examples thereof include sodium fluoride,
potassium fluoride, calcium fluoride, magnesium fluoride,
hexafluoro zirconium sodium, hexafluoro zirconium potassium,
sodium hexafluorotitanate, potassium hexafluorotitanate,
hexafluoro zirconium hydro acid, hexafluoro titanium hydro
acid, hexafluoro zirconium ammonium, hexafluoro ammonium 
titanate, hexafluoro silicic acid, nickel fluoride, iron
fluoride, fluorinated phosphonic acid, and fluorinated
ammonium phospohate.</p>
    <p num="0187">The aqueous solution to be used for the
phosphate/inorganic fluoro compound treatment may contain
one or more than two of phosphate and fluoro compounds
respectively.</p>
    <p num="0188">The support is washed with water etc. after dipping
it in aqueous solution containing these hydrophilic
compounds as mentioned above and dried.</p>
    <p num="0189">The problem of printing stain such as the
deterioration of ink removal, which is caused in exchange
for the improved sensitivity (improved press life in the
case of a negative type sensitive layer) due to the pore-widening
treatment performed after anodic oxidation, is
solved by the hydrophilic surface treatment as mentioned
above. That is, the hydrophilic surface treatment will
alleviate the problem such that the removal of ink becomes
difficult (i.e. deterioration of ink removal occurs) during
the printing due to the widened pore diameter, especially
at the restart of printing after the printing machine is
stopped and the lithographic printing plate is left as it
is on the machine.</p>
    <heading>&lt;Undercoat Layer&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0190">In this invention, for example, an inorganic
undercoat layer of water soluble metal salt such as zinc
borate or organic undercoat layer may be formed, if
necessary, on the resulting support for a lithographic
printing plate according to this invention, before forming
a recording layer that is writable by exposure with
infrared laser.</p>
    <p num="0191">As organic compounds to be used for the organic
undercoat layer, there are, for example, carboxymethyl
cellulose; dextrine; gum arabic; polymer and copolymer
having sulfonic acid group in a side chain; polyacrylic
acid; phosphonic acids having an amino group such as diaminoethyl
phosphonic acid; organic phosphonic acid such as
phenyl, naphthyl, alkyl, glycero, methylendi- and
ethylendi-phosphonic acid, which may have substituent;
organo phosphoric acid, such as phenyl, naphthyl, alkyl and
glycero phosphoric acid, which may have substituent; organo
phosphinic acid, such as phenyl, naphthyl, alkyl and
glycero phosphinic acid, which may have substituent; amino
acids such as glycine and β-alanine; hydrochloride of amine
having hydroxyl group, such as triethandamine
hydrochloride; and yellow dyes. These compounds may be
used alone or in combination of more than two thereof.</p>
    <p num="0192">The organic undercoat layer is formed by coating an 
aluminum plate with a solution in which organic compound
such as mentioned above is dissolved in water or organic
solvent such as methanol, ethanol, and methylethyl ketone,
or in the mixed solvent thereof, and drying. The
concentration of solution in which the organic compound is
dissolved is preferably 0.005 - 10 wt%. The method for
coating is particularly limited; any method such as bar
coater coating, rotary coating, spray coating, curtain
coating may be used.</p>
    <p num="0193">The amount of coat after drying the organic undercoat
layer is preferably 2 - 200 mg/m<sup>2</sup>, and more preferably 5 -
100 mg/m<sup>2</sup>. An improved press life is obtained if it is set
within the range as mentioned above.</p>
    <heading>&lt;Backcoat Layer&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0194">The resulting support may be provided on its back
surface (surface without the recording layer) with a coat
layer (called as "backcoat layer" hereinafter) of organic
high molecular compound in order that the recording layers
are damaged when piled on top of each other on a
lithographic printing original plate.</p>
    <p num="0195">The main component of the backcoat layer is
preferably at least one resin having a glass transition
point of 20°C or higher, which is selected from the group
consisting of saturated copolymeric polyester resin, 
phenoxy resin, polyvinyl acetal resin and vinyliden
chloride copolymeric resin.</p>
    <p num="0196">The saturated copolymeric polyester resin is composed
of a dicarboxylic acid unit and a diol unit. Examples of
the discarboxylic acid unit include: an aromatic
dicarboxylic acid such as phthalic, terephthalic,
isophthalic, tetrabromophtalic, and tetrachlorophthalic
acid; and a saturated aliphatic dicarboxylic acid such as
adipic, azelaic, succimic, oxalic, subenic, subacic,
malonic, and 1,4-cyclohexandicarboxylic acid.</p>
    <p num="0197">The backcoat layer can contain suitably: dye and
pigment for coloring; silane coupling agent, diazo resin of
diazonium salt, organo phosphoric acid, and cationic
polymer, for improving the adhesion to the support; wax,
higher fatty acid, higher fatty acid amide, silicone
compound of dimethylsiloxane, modified dimethylsiloxane,
and polyethylene powder, which are conventionally used as
slilding agents.</p>
    <p num="0198">The thickness of the backcoat layer may be such that
the recording layers to be described later are not easily
damaged basically even without providing an interleaving
sheet, and is preferably 0.01 - 8 µm. If the thickness is
less than 0.01 µm, it is difficult to prevent the abrasion
of recording layers when lithographic printing original 
plates are piled on top of one another. If the thickness
exceeds 8 µm, the backcoat layer is swollen and its
thickness is changed, due to chemicals used around the
lithographic printing plate during printing. Thus the
printing pressure is changed, whereby the printing property
may deteriorate.</p>
    <p num="0199">To form the backcoat layer on the back surface of the
support, various methods can be used. For example, there
are: a method wherein components for the backcoat layer are
dissolved in a suitable solvent to apply it as a solution
or as an emulsion dispersion and dried; a method wherein a
film of the backcoat layer is formed in advance and adhered
by means of adhesive or heat; and a method wherein a molten
film is formed by means of melting extruder and is adhered
onto a support.</p>
    <p num="0200">To secure a preferable thickness of the backcoat
layer, the most preferable method comprises dissolving the
components for the backcoat layer in a suitable solvent and
applying the resulting solution onto a support and then
drying it. In this method, the organic solvents such as
described in JP 62-251739 A may be used alone or as the
mixture thereof.</p>
    <p num="0201">In the manufacture of a lithographic printing
original plate, either the backcoat layer on the back 
surface thereof or the recording layer on the front surface
thereof may be formed first on the support, and both layers
may also be simultaneously formed on the support.</p>
    <heading>[Original Forme for Lithographic Printing Plate]</heading>
    <p num="0202">The original forme for a lithographic printing plate
according to this invention can be obtained by forming a
recording layer that is writable by exposure with infrared
laser, on the support for a lithographic printing plate
according to this invention which is obtained as mentioned
above.</p>
    <heading>&lt;Recording Layer&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0203">The recording layer in the lithographic printing
original plate according to this invention is preferably a
heat-sensitive layer containing (a) fine polymer particles
having heat reactive functional group; or (b) micro
capsules containing a compound having heat reactive
functional group. When the heat reactive layer is used,
the lithographic printing original plate thus obtained
affords the on-press development process.</p>
    <p num="0204">As a heat-reactive functional group that may be used
commonly to (a) and (b) above, there are, for example,
ethylenical unsaturated group for polymerization (e.g.
acryloyl, methacryloyl, vinyl, and allyl group); isocyanate
group for addition reaction or the blocked type thereof as 
well as functional group having active hydrogen atom as
reactant thereto (e.g. amino, hydroxyl, and carboxyl
group); epoxy group for addition reaction as well as amino
group as reactant thereto; carboxyl and hydroxyl group;
carboxyl or hydroxyl or amino group for condensation
reaction; and acid anhydride and amino or hydroxyl group
for ring-opening addition reaction. The heat reactive
functional group to be used in this invention is not
limited to the above-mentioned groups and any functional
group may be used as long as chemical bond is formed.</p>
    <p num="0205">As heat reactive functional group suitable for (a)
fine polymer particles, there are, for example, acryloyl,
methacryloyl, vinyl, allyl, epoxy, amino, hydroxyl,
carboxyl, isocyanate, acid anhydride, and protected groups
thereof. The introduction of heat reactive group into the
polymer particles may be performed during the
polymerization polymer or after the polymerization by
utilizing a polymer reaction.</p>
    <p num="0206">When the heat-reactive group is introduced during the
polymerization of polymer, it is preferable to carry out
the emulsion or suspension polymerization using monomer
having the heat reactive group.</p>
    <p num="0207">Specific examples of monomer having the heat reactive
group include allyl methacrylate, allyl acrylate, vinyl 
methacrylate, vinyl acrylate, glycidyl methacrylate,
glycidyl acrylate, 2-isocyanate ethyl methacrylate, blocked
each of these isocyanates with alcohol, 2-isocyanate ethyl
acrylate, blocked each of these isocyanates with alcohol,
2-amino ethyl methacrylate, 2-amino ethyl acrylate, 2-hydroxyethyl
methacrylate, 2-hydroxy ethyl acrylate,
acrylic acid, methacrylic acid, malaic anhydride,
bifunctional acrylate, and bifunctional methacrylate. The
monomer having the heat reactive group to be used in this
invention is not limited to these.</p>
    <p num="0208">Examples of the monomer which is copolymerizable with
these monomers and has no heat reactive group include
stylene, alkyl acrylate, alkyl methacrylate, acrylonitrile,
and vinyl acetate. The monomer having no heat reactive
group to be used in this invention is not limited to these.</p>
    <p num="0209">As the polymer to be performed in the case where
heat-reactive functional group is introduced after the
polymerization of polymer, there is, for example, the
polymer reaction described in WO 96/34316.</p>
    <p num="0210">Preferably, the fine polymer particles described in
(a) above are united by heat. More preferably, they have
hydrophilic surfaces to allow their dispersion in water.
It is also preferred that the contact angle (with waterdrop
in air) of a film which is formed by coating only fine 
polymer particles and drying at a lower temperature than
the freezing point, is smaller than the contact angle (with
waterdrop in air) of a film which is formed at a higher
temperature than the freezing point.</p>
    <p num="0211">To make the surface of the fine polymer particles
hydrophilic, as mentioned above, hydrophilic polymer or
oligomers such as polyvinyl alcohol and polyethylen glycol,
or hydrophilic low molecular compound may be adsorbed onto
the surfaces of the fine polymer particles; however, the
method is not limited thereto.</p>
    <p num="0212">The freezing point of the fine polymer particles (a)
is preferably 70°C or higher, and more preferably 100°C or
higher in view of stability as to aging.</p>
    <p num="0213">The mean particle size of the fine polymer particles
(a) is preferably 0.01 - 20 µm, more preferably 0.05 - 2.0
µm, and especially preferably 0.1 - 1.0 µm. A good
resolution and aging stability are obtained when it is set
within the range mentioned above.</p>
    <p num="0214">The addition amount of the fine polymer particles (a)
is preferably 50 wt% or more, and more preferably 60 wt% or
more based on the solid of the heat-sensitive layer.</p>
    <p num="0215">Examples of the heat reactive functional group
suitable for the microcapsules described in (b) above
include: polymeric unsaturated group; hydroxyl, carboxyl, 
carboxylate, acid anhydride, amino, epoxy, or isocyanate
group; and blocked type of isocyanate.</p>
    <p num="0216">The compound having polymeric unsaturated group is
preferably those having at least one, preferably more than
two of ethylenical unsaturated bonds, for example, acryloyl,
methacryloyl, vinyl and allyl. These compounds are widely
known in this industrial field and may be used in this
invention without any particular limitation thereon. From
the viewpoint of chemical morphology, these compounds are
monomer, prepolymer, namely dimer, trimer and oligomer, or
the mixture and copolymer thereof.</p>
    <p num="0217">Specific examples thereof include unsaturated
carboxylic acid (e.g. acrylic, methacrylic, itaconic,
crotonic, isocrotonic or maleic acid) and ester thereof,
and unsaturated carboxylic acid amide. Especially, the
ester of unsaturated carboxylic acid and aliphatic
polyhydric alcohol and amide of unsaturated carboxylic acid
and aliphatic polyfunctional amine are preferable.</p>
    <p num="0218">The addition reaction product of unsaturated
carboxylic acid ester or unsaturated carboxylic acid amide
having nucleophilic substituent such as hydroxyl, amino and
mercapto group with monofunctional or polyfunctional
isocianate or epoxide as well as the dehydration
condensation product of the ester or amide with 
monofunctional or polyfunctional carboxylic acid are used
preferably.</p>
    <p num="0219">The addition reaction product of unsaturated
carboxylic acid ester or amide having electrophilic
substituent such as isocyanate and epoxy group with
monofunctional or polyfunctional alcohol, amine or thiol,
as well as the substitution reaction product of unsaturated
carboxylic acid ester or amide having leaving substituent
such as halogen and tosyloxy group with monofunctional or
polyfunctional alcohol, amine or thiol are used preferably.</p>
    <p num="0220">Further, another preferable examples thereof is a
compound in which the above unsaturated phosphonic acid is
substituted by unsaturated phosphonic acid or chloromethyl
stylene.</p>
    <p num="0221">Among polymeric compounds of ester of unsaturated
carboxylic acid and aliphatic polyhydric alcohol, examples
of the acrylic esters include ethylenglycol diacrylate,
triethyleneglycol diacrylate, 1,3-butanediol diacrylate,
tetramethyleneglycol diacrylate, propyreneglycol diacrylate,
neopentylglycol diacrylate, trimethylolpropane diacrylate,
trimethylelpropane triacrylate, trimethylolpropane tris
(acryloyloxypropyl) ether, trimethylolethane triacrylate,
hexanediol diacrylate, 1,4-cyclohexanediol diacrylate,
tetraethylenglycol diacrylate, pentaerythritol diacrylate, 
pentaerythritol triacrylate, pentaerythritol tetracrylate,
dipentaerythritol diacrylate, dipentaerythritol
pentacrylate, dipentaerythritol hexacrylate, sorbitol
triacrylate, sorbitol tetracrylate, sorbitol pentacrylate,
sorbitol hexacrylate, tris (acroyloxyethyl) isocyanulate,
polyester acrylate oligomer.</p>
    <p num="0222">There are mentioned as methacrylic acid esters, for
example, tetramethyleneglycol dimethacrylate,
triethylenglycol dimethacrylate, neopentylglycol
dimethacrylate, trimethylolpropane trimethacrylate,
trimethyleolethane trimethacrylate, ethylenglycol
dimethacrylate, 1,3-butanediol dimethacrylate, hexanediol
dimethacrylate, pentaerythritol dimethacrylate,
pentaerythritol trimethacrylate, pentaerythritol
tetramethacrylate, dipentaerythritol dimethacrylate,
dipentaerythritol hexamethacrylate, sorbitol
trimethacrylate, sorbitol tetramethacrylate, bis[p-(3-methacryloyloxy-2-hydroxy-propoxy)phenyl]
dimethylmethane,
bis-[p-(methacryloyl-oxyethoxy)phenyl] dimethylmethane.</p>
    <p num="0223">Examples of the itaconic acid esters include
ethylenglycol diitaconete, propyleneglycol diitaconete,
1,3-butanediol diitaconete, 1,4-butanediol diitaconete,
tetramethyleneglycol diitaconete, and pentaerythritol
diitaconete; and sorbitol tetraitaconate. </p>
    <p num="0224">There are mentioned as crotonic acid ester, for
example, ethylenglycol dicrotonate, tetramethyleneglycol
dicrotonate and pentaerythritol dicrotonate, and sorbitol
tetracrotonate.</p>
    <p num="0225">There are mentioned as isocrotonic acid ester, for
example, ethylenglycol diisocrotonate and pentaerythritol
diisocrotonate, and sorbitol tetraisocrotonate.</p>
    <p num="0226">There are mentioned as maleic adic ester, for example,
ethylenglycol dimalate, triethylenglycol dimalate and
pentaerythritol dimalate, and sorbitol tetramalate.</p>
    <p num="0227">There are mentioned as other ester, for example,
esters of aliphatic alcohol based described in JP 46-27926
B, JP 51-47334 B and JP 57-196231 B; esters having aromatic
skeleton described in JP 59-5240 A, JP 59-5241 A and JP 2-226149
A; and esters having amino group described in JP 1-165613
A.</p>
    <p num="0228">Specific examples of monomer of amide between
aliphatic polyfunctional amine compound and unsaturated
carboxylic acid include methylene bis-acrylamide, methylene
bis-methyacrylamide, 1,6-hexamethylene bis-acrylamide, 1,6-hexamethylene
bis-methacrylamide, diethylenetriamine tris
acrylamide, xylylene bis-acrylamide and xylylene bis-methyacrylamide.</p>
    <p num="0229">There are mentioned as other preferable amide based 
monomers, for example, monomers having the cyclohexylene
structure described in JP 54-21726 B.</p>
    <p num="0230">Also preferred is polymeric addition compounds of
urethane based, which is produced by using the addition
reaction of isocyanate and hydroxyl groups. Specific
examples thereof include an urethane compound containing
more than two polymeric unsaturated groups in one molecule,
which is obtained by adding the unsaturated monomer having
hydroxyl group represented by the formula (II) below to a
polyisocyanate compound having more than two isocyanate
groups in the molecule which is described in JP 48-41708 B.
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/">CH<sub>2</sub>=C(R<sup>1</sup>)COOCH<sub>2</sub>CH(R<sup>2</sup>)OH</st32:che>
   (wherein R<sup>1</sup> and R<sup>2</sup> each represents H or CH<sub>3</sub>.)</p>
    <p num="0231">Also preferred are: urethane acrylates described in
JP 51-37193 A, JP 2-32293 B and JP 2-16765 B; and urethane
compounds having the ethylene oxide skeleton described in
JP 58-49860 B, JP 56-17654 B, JP 62-39417 B and JP 62-39418
B.</p>
    <p num="0232">Also preferred are radical polymeric compounds having
the amino and sulfide structures in the molecule, which are
described in JP 63-277653 A, JP 63-260909 A and JP 1-105238
A.</p>
    <p num="0233">Other preferable examples thereof include
polyfunctional acrylates and methacrylates, such as 
polyacrylates, epoxyacrylates obtained by the reaction of
epoxy resin and (metha) acrylic acid, described in JP 48-64183
A, JP 49-43191 B and JP 52-30490 B.</p>
    <p num="0234">Also preferred are the specified unsaturated
compounds described in JP 46-43946 B, JP 1-40337 B and JP
1-40336 B, and compounds of vinyl phosphoric acid described
in JP 2-25493 A. In some cases, compounds containing
perfluoroalkyl group described in JP 61-22048 A are also
preferable. Further, photo setting monomers and oligomers
reported in the "The Adhesion Society of Japan" Journal,
vol. 20, No. 7, p.300-308 (1984) are also preferred.</p>
    <p num="0235">Examples of suitable epoxy compounds include
glycerine polyglycidylether, polyethyleneglycol
diglycidylether, polypropylene diglycidylether,
trimethylolpropane polyglycidylether, sorbitol
polyglycidylether, and bisphenols or polyphenols or
polyglycidyether as the hydrogenation product thereof.</p>
    <p num="0236">There are mentioned as preferable isocyanate
compounds, for example, tolylene diisocyanate,
diphenylmethane diisocyanate, polymethylene polyphenyl
polyisocyanate, xylylene diisocyanate, naphthalene
diisocyanate, cyclohexane phenylen diisocyanate, isophoron
diisocyanate, hexamethylene diisocyanate, cyclohexyl
diisocyanate, or compounds in which these are blocked by 
alcohol or amine.</p>
    <p num="0237">There are mentioned as preferable amine compounds,
for example, ethylenediamine, diethylenetriamine,
triethylenetetramine, hexamethylenediamine,
propylenediamine, polyethyleneimine.</p>
    <p num="0238">There are mentioned as preferable compounds having
hydroxyl group, for example, compounds having terminal
methylol group, polyhydnic alcohol such as pentaerythritol,
bisphenol, polyphenols.</p>
    <p num="0239">There are mentioned as preferable compounds having
carboxylic group, for example, aromatic polybasic
carboxylic acid such as pyromeritic, trimeritic and
phthalic acid, aliphatic polybasic carboxylic acids such as
adipic acid.</p>
    <p num="0240">There are mentioned as preferable acid anhydrids, for
example, pyromeritic and benzo phenonetetracarboxylic acid
anhydride.</p>
    <p num="0241">There are mentioned as preferable copolymers of
ethylenical unsaturated compounds, for example, copolymers
of allylmethacrylate. Specific examples thereof include
allylmethacrylate/methacrylic acid copolymer,
allylmethacrylate/ethylmethacrylate copolymer, and
allylmethacrylate/butylmethacrylate copolymer.</p>
    <p num="0242">As a method for the micro capsulation, known methods 
may be used. There are mentioned, for example, a method
using coacervation described in US 2800457 B and US 2800458
B; a method using interfacial polymerization described in
BP 990443 B, US 3287154 B, JP 38-19574 B, JP 42-446 B and
JP 42-711 B; a method using the separation of polymer
described in US 3418250 B and US 3660304 B; a method using
wall material of isocyanate polyol described in US 3796669
B; a method using wall material of isocyanate described in
US 3914511 B; a method using wall material of ureaformaldehyde
or urea-formaldehyde-resorcinol system
described in US 4001140 B, US 4087376 B and US 4089802 B; a
method using wall material such as melamine-formaldehyde
resin, hydroxycellulose etc. described in US 4025445 B; in
situ method using the monomer polymerization, described in
JP 36-9163 B and JP 51-9079 B; a spray-drying method
described in BP 930422 A and US 3111407 B; a method using
electrolytic dispersion cooling described in BP 952807 A
and BP 967074 A. The method, however, is not limited to
these in this invention.</p>
    <p num="0243">The wall of microcapsule to be used preferably for
(b) the microcapsules have three-dimensional bridges and
are swollen with solvent. From this viewpoint, the wall
material of microcapsule is preferably polyurea,
polyurethane, polyester, polycarbonate, polyamide or the 
mixture thereof, and especially preferably polyurea and
polyurethane. Compounds having heat reactive functional
group may be introduced into the wall of microcapsule.</p>
    <p num="0244">The mean particle size of (b) the microcapsule is
preferably 0.01-20 µm, more preferably 0.05-20 µm, and
especially preferably 0.10-1.0 µm. A good resolution and
aging stability can be obtained when it is set within the
range mentioned above.</p>
    <p num="0245">The (b) microcapsules may be united by heat or may
not be united at all. It is sufficient that, among the
substances contained in microcapsules, those which
penetrate onto the surface or out of the capsules or enter
into the wall of the capsules during application thereof
can cause a chemical reaction with heat. Alternatively,
these may react with a hydrophilic resin added or low
molecular compound added. Microcapsules may be reacted
with each other by introducing heat-reactive functional
groups, which are different from each other, into two kinds
or more of microcapsules.</p>
    <p num="0246">Accordingly, in view of image formation, it is
preferred that the microcapsules be fused and united to
each other by heat. However, this is not essential.</p>
    <p num="0247">The amount of (b) the microcapsule added to the heat
sensitive layer is preferably 10-60 wt%, and more 
preferably 15-40 wt%, based on reduced solid. A good on-press
developability, sensitivity and presslife may be
obtained if it is set within the range mentioned above.</p>
    <p num="0248">(b) In a case where microcapsules are added to a
heat-sensitive layer, a solvent in which the inclusion is
dissolved and wall material swells may be added into the
microcapsule dispersion. Such a solvent accelerates
diffusion of the included compound having a heat-reactive
functional group to outside the microcapsules.</p>
    <p num="0249">Such a solvent may be readily selected from many
commercially available solvents although it may vary
depending on the microcapsule dispersant, material and
thickness of the wall of microcapsule, and inclusion. For
example, in a case of waster-dispersible microcapsules
having a crosslinked polyurea or polyurethane wall,
alcohols, ethers, acetals, esters, ketones, polyhydric
alcohols, amides, amines, fatty acids and the like are
preferred.</p>
    <p num="0250">Specific examples thereof include methanol, ethanol,
tertiary butanol, n-propanol, tetrahydrofuran, methyl
lactate, ethyl lactate, methyl ethyl ketone, propylene
glycol monomethyl ether, ethylene glycol diethyl ether,
ethylene glycol monomethyl ether, γ-butyrolactone, N,N-dimethylformamide,
N,N-dimethylacetamide, etc. The present 
invention is not limited to these. Also, two or more of
these solvents may be used.</p>
    <p num="0251">A solvent that does not dissolve in the microcapsule
dispersion but dissolves in it when the above-mentioned
solvent is mixed may also be used. The addition amount is
determined depending on the combination of materials but
usually it is preferably 5 to 95 wt%, more preferably 10 to
90 wt% and most preferably 15 to 85 wt% of the coating
solution.</p>
    <p num="0252">In a case where a heat-sensitive layer containing (a)
particulates of a polymer having a heat-reactive functional
group or (b) microcapsules including a compound having a
heat-reactive functional group is used as the recording
layer, a compound that initiates or accelerates the
reaction of them may be added as necessary. Examples of
the compound that initiates or accelerates the reaction
include compounds that generate radicals or cations by heat.
Specific examples thereof include roffin dimer,
trihalomethylated compounds, peroxides, azo compounds,
onium salts including diazonium salts or diphenyliodonium
salts, acylphosphines, and imide sulfonates.</p>
    <p num="0253">These compounds are added in amounts in the range of
preferably 1 to 20 wt%, more preferably 3 to 10 wt% of the
solids content of heat-sensitive layer. In the above range, 
on-press developability is not deteriorated and good
reaction initiating or accelerating effect can be obtained.</p>
    <p num="0254">The heat-sensitive layer may contain a hydrophilic
resin. Addition of the hydrophilic resin not only provides
good on-press developability but also improves film
strength of the hat-sensitive layer itself.</p>
    <p num="0255">As the hydrophilic resin, those having a hydrophilic
group such as a hydroxyl, carboxyl, hydroxyethyl,
hydroxypropyl, amino, aminoethyl, aminopropyl, or
carboxymethyl are preferred.</p>
    <p num="0256">Specific examples of the hydrophilic resin include
gum arabic, casein, gelatin, starch derivatives,
carboxymethylcellulose and sodium salt thereof, cellulose
acetate, sodium alginate, vinyl acetate/maleic acid
copolymers, styrene/maleic acid copolymers, polyacrylic
acids and salts thereof, polymethacrylic acids and salts
thereof, homopolymers and copolymers of hydroxyethyl
methacrylate, homopolymers and copolymers of hydroxyethyl
acrylate, homopolymers and copolymers of hydroxypropyl
methacrylate, homopolymers and copolymers of hydroxypropyl
acrylate, homopolymers and copolymers of hydroxybutyl
methacrylate, homopolymers and copolymers of hydroxybutyl
acrylate, polyethylene glycols, hydroxypropylene polymers,
polyvinyl alcohols, hydrolyzed polyvinyl acetate having a 
degree of hydrolysis of at least 60 wt%, preferably at
least 80 wt%, polyvinyl formal, polyvinyl butyral,
polyvinyl pyrolidone homopolymers and copolymers of
acrylamide, homopolymers and polymers of methacrylamide,
and homopolymers and copolymers of N-methylolacrylamide.</p>
    <p num="0257">The addition amount of the hydrophilic resin to the
heat-sensitive layer is preferably 5 to 40 wt%, more
preferably 10 to 30 wt% of the solids content of the heat-sensitive
layer. In the above-mentioned range, good on-press
developability and film strength can be obtained.</p>
    <p num="0258">The heat-sensitive layer may contain a light-heat
converting agent that absorbs infrared ray and generates
heat in order to improve sensitivity. Such a light-heat
converting agent may be a light absorbing substance having
an absorbing band in at least a portion of 700 to 1,200 nm
and various pigments, dyes and metal particulates may be
used as the light-heat converting agent.</p>
    <p num="0259">As for the kinds of pigment, black pigments, brown
pigments, red pigments, violet pigments, blue pigments,
green pigments, fluorescent pigments, metal powder pigments,
and in addition polymer binding dyes are exemplified.
Specific examples include insoluble azo pigments, azo lake
pigments, condensed azo pigments, chelate azo pigments,
phthalocyanine-based pigments, anthraquinone-based pigments, 
perylene- and perynone-based pigments, thioindigo-based
pigments, quinacridone-based pigments, dioxazine-based
pigments, isoindolinone-based pigments, quinophthalone-based
pigments, dyeing lake pigments, azine pigments,
nitroso pigments, nitro pigments, natural pigments,
fluorescent pigments, inorganic pigments, and carbon black.</p>
    <p num="0260">The pigments may be used without surface treatment or
with surface treatment. Examples of the method of surface
treatment include a method of surface-coating a hydrophilic
resin or an ink receptive resin, a method of attaching a
surfactant, and a method of binding a reactive substance
(for example, silica sol, alumina sol, silane coupling
agent, epoxy compound or isocyanate compound) to the
surface of the pigment. The above-mentioned surface
treatment methods are described in "Properties and
Application of Metal Soaps" (Saiwai Shobo), "Printing Ink
Technologies" (CMC Publishing, 1984), and "Current Pigment
Application Technologies" (CMC Publishing, 1986). Among
these pigments, those that absorb infrared rays are
preferred for their applicability to lasers that emit
infrared rays. As such a pigment absorbing an infrared ray,
carbon black is preferred.</p>
    <p num="0261">The particle size of pigment is in the range of
preferably 0.01 to 1 µm, more preferably 0.01 to 0.5 µm. </p>
    <p num="0262">As the dye, those available on the market and the
known dyes described in literature (for example, "Manual of
Dyes" ed. by Organic Synthetic Chemical Association, 1970,
"Near infrared-absorbing pigments" in "Chemical Industry",
May, 1986, p.45-51, "Development and trend in market of
functional pigments during the 1990s", Chapter 2 section
2.3 (1990) CMC") or patents may be used.</p>
    <p num="0263">Specifically, infrared-absorbing dyes such as azo
dyes, metal complex salt azo dyes, pyrazolone azo dyes,
anthraquinone dyes, phthalocyanine dyes, carbonium dyes,
quinoneimine dyes, polymethyne dyes, and cyanine dyes are
preferred.</p>
    <p num="0264">Further examples thereof include cyanine dyes
described in JP 58-125246 A, JP 59-84356 A, JP 60-78787 A,
etc., methyne dyes described in JP 58-173696 A, JP 58-181690
A, JP 58-194595 A, etc., naphthoquinone dyes
described in JP 58-112793 A, JP 58-224793 A, JP 59-48187 A,
JP 59-73996 A, JP 60-52940 A, JP 60-63744 A, etc.,
squalylium dyes described in JP 58-112792 A, cyanine dyes
described in BP 434,875 B, dyes described in US 4,756,993 A,
cyanine dyes described in US 4,973,572 A, dyes described in
JP 10-268512 A and phthalocyanine compounds described in JP
11-235883 A.</p>
    <p num="0265">Also, as the dyes, near infrared-absorbing 
sensitizing agents described in US 5,156,938 A are suitably
used. In addition, substituted arylbenzo(thio)pyrylium
salts described in US 3,881,924 A, trimethynethiapyrylium
salts described in JP 57-142645 A, pyrylium-based compounds
described in JP 58-181051 A, JP 58-220143 A, JP 59-41363 A,
JP 59-84248 A, JP 59-84249 A, JP 59-146063 A, and JP 59-146061
A, cyanine dyes described in JP 59-216146 A,
pentamethynethiopyrylium salts described in US 4,283,475 A
and the like, pyrylium compounds described in JP 5-13514 B
and JP 5-19702 B, Epolite III-178, Epolite III-130, Epolite
III-125 (from Epoline Co.), and the like may be suitably
used.</p>
    <p num="0266">Hereinafter, some specific examples will be shown.
<img id="img-00890001" orientation="unknown" wi="117" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00890001.tif" inline="no" he="95"/><img id="img-00900001" orientation="unknown" wi="139" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00900001.tif" inline="no" he="199"/><img id="img-00910001" orientation="unknown" wi="130" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00910001.tif" inline="no" he="215"/><img id="img-00920001" orientation="unknown" wi="115" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00920001.tif" inline="no" he="50"/></p>
    <p num="0267">In a case where the light-heat converting agent is
added in an ink receptive substance such as polymer
particulates or microcapsules, the above-mentioned
infrared-absorbing pigments or dyes may be used but those
which are more ink receptive are preferred. Suitable dyes
include those exemplified below.
<img id="img-00920002" orientation="unknown" wi="142" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00920002.tif" inline="no" he="95"/><img id="img-00930001" orientation="unknown" wi="130" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00930001.tif" inline="no" he="204"/><img id="img-00940001" orientation="unknown" wi="121" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00940001.tif" inline="no" he="157"/></p>
    <p num="0268">It is preferred that the above-mentioned organic
light-heat converting agent is added in the range of up to
30 wt%, more preferably 5 to 25 wt% and most preferably 7
to 20 wt% in the heat-sensitive layer. In the above-mentioned
range, good sensitivity can be obtained.</p>
    <p num="0269">In the heat-sensitive layer, also metal particulates
may be used as the light-heat converting agent. Most of 
the metal particulates are light-heat converting and self
heat generating. Preferred metal particulates include
particulates of simple elements such as Si, Al, Ti, V, Cr,
Mn, Fe, Co, Ni, Cu, Zn, Y, Zr, Mo, Ag, Au, Pt, Pd, Rh, In,
Sn, W, Te, Pb, Ge, Re, and Sb or alloy thereof or oxides or
sulfides thereof.</p>
    <p num="0270">Among the metals that constitute these metal
particulates, preferred metals are those metals that tend
to be united by heat upon light irradiation, have a melting
point at about 1,000°C or lower and absorb light in
infrared, visible or ultraviolet regions, for example, Re,
Sb, Te, Au, Ag, Cu, Ge, Pb, and Sn.</p>
    <p num="0271">Particularly preferred are particulates of those
metals that have relatively low melting points and
relatively high absorbance for infrared rays, for example,
Ag, Au, Cu, Sb, Ge, and Pb. Most preferred elements
include Ag, Au, and Cu.</p>
    <p num="0272">Also, the light-heat converting agent may be
constituted by two or more light-heat converting substances,
for example, use of a mixture of particulates of a low
melting metal such as Re, Sb, Te, Au, Ag, Cu, Ge, Pb, or Sn
and particulates of a self heat generation metal such as Ti,
Cr, Fe, Co, Ni, W, or Ge. It is also preferable to use in
combination minute particles of a metal species that has 
particularly high light absorption when it is rendered
minute fragments, such as AG, Pt or Pd and minute fragments
of other metal.</p>
    <p num="0273">The particle size of these particles is preferably 10
µm or less, more preferably 0.003 to 5 µm and most
preferably 0.01 to 3 µm. In the above range, good
sensitivity and resolution can be obtained.</p>
    <p num="0274">In the present invention, when these metal
particulates are used as light-heat converting agents, the
addition amount thereof is preferably 10 wt% or more, more
preferably 20 wt% or more and most preferably 30 wt% or
more of the solids content of the heat-sensitive layer. In
the above range, high sensitivity can be obtained.
The light-heat converting agent may be contained in
an undercoat layer adjacent to the heat-sensitive layer or
a water soluble overcoat layer described later. Since at
least one layer out of the heat-sensitive layer, undercoat
layer and overcoat layer contains the light-heat converting
agent, the efficiency of infrared ray absorption increases
and sensitivity can be improved.</p>
    <p num="0275">The heat-sensitive layer may contain various
compounds beside those described above as necessary. For
example, a polyfunctional monomer may be added into the
matrix of heat-sensitive layer in order to further increase 
the impression capacity. As the polyfunctional monomer,
the monomers exemplified as those that can be added in the
microcapsules. Particularly preferred monomer may include
trimethylolpropane triacrylate.</p>
    <p num="0276">In the heat-sensitive layer, a dye having a strong
absorption may be used as a coloring agent for an image in
the visible range in order to make it easy to distinguish
an image area from a non-image area after image formation.
Specifically such a dye includes Oil Yellow #101, Oil
Yellow #103, Oil Pink #312, Oil Green BG, Oil Blue BOS, Oil
Blue #603, Oil Black BY, Oil Black BS, Oil Black T-505
(these being produced by Orient Chemical Industry Co.,
Ltd.), Victoria Pure Blue, Crystal Violet (CI42555), Methyl
Violet (CI42535), Ethyl Violet, Rhodamine B (CI145170B),
Malachite Green (CI42000), Methylene Blue (CI52015), and
dyes described in JP 62-293247 A. In addition, pigments
such as phthalocyanine-based pigments, azo-based pigments,
and titanium oxide may be preferably used. It is preferred
that the addition amount is 0.01 to 10 wt% of all the
solids content of the coating solution for the heat-sensitive
layer.</p>
    <p num="0277">Also, in the present invention, in order to prevent
unnecessary heat polymerization of ethelene unsaturated
compounds during preparation or storage of a coating 
solution for the heat-sensitive layer, it is preferred to
add a small amount of heat polymerization preventing agent.
Examples of suitable heat polymerization preventing agent
include hydroquinone, p-methoxyphenol, di-t-butyl-p-cresol,
pyrogallol, t-butylcathecol, benzoquinone, 4,4'-thiobis(3-methyl-6-t-butylphenol),
2,2'methylenebis(4-methyl-6-t-butylphenol),
and N-nitroso-N-phenylhydroxylamine aluminum
salt. The addition amount of heat polymerization
preventing agent is preferably about 0.01 to 5 wt% of the
mass of total composition.</p>
    <p num="0278">As necessary, in order to prevent inhibition of
polymerization by oxygen, higher fatty acid or derivatives
thereof such as behenic acid or behenic acid amide may be
added so as to localize it on the surface of the heat-sensitive
layer in the process of drying after coating.
The addition amount of higher fatty acid or derivatives
thereof is preferably about 0.1 to about 10 wt% of the
solids content of the heat-sensitive layer.</p>
    <p num="0279">Further, the heat-sensitive layer may contain a
plasticizer as necessary in order to impart it flexibility
and the like of the coating film. Examples of the
plasticizer include polyethylene glycol, tributyl citrate,
diethyl phthalate, dibutyl phthalate, dihexyl phthalate,
dioctyl phthalate, tricresyl phosphate, tributyl phosphate, 
trioctyl phosphate, and tetrahydrofurfuryl oleate.</p>
    <p num="0280">The heat-sensitive layer is formed by dissolving each
of necessary components described above in a solvent to
prepare a coating solution and coating it. Examples of the
solvent used here include ethylene dichloride,
cyclohexanone, methyl ethyl ketone, methanol, ethanol,
propanol, ethylene glycol monomethyl ether, 1-methoxy-2-propanol,
2-methoxy ethyl acetate, 1-methoxy-2-propyl
acetate, dimethoxyethane, methyl lactate, ethyl lactate,
N,N-dimethylacetamide, N,N-dimethylformamide,
tetramethylurea, N-methylpyrrolidone, dimethyl sulfoxide,
sulfolane, γ-butyrolactone, toluene, water and the like but
is not limited to these. The solvents may be used singly
or as mixtures. The solids concentration of the coating
solution is preferably 1 to 50 wt%.</p>
    <p num="0281">The coating amount of heat-sensitive layer (solids
content) on the substrate obtained after coating and drying
may vary depending on the purpose but generally it is
preferably 0.5 to 5.0 g/m<sup>2</sup>. If the coating mount is
smaller than the above range, apparent sensitivity
increases but the film property of the heat-sensitive layer
that performs the function of image recording is decreased.
As the coating method, various methods may be used.
Examples thereof include bar coater coating, rotation 
coating, spray coating, curtain coating, dip coating, air
knife coating, blade coating, and roll coating.</p>
    <p num="0282">The coating solution of heat-sensitive layer may
contain a surfactant for improving coatability, for example,
a fluorine-based surfactant described in JP 62-170950 A.
The addition amount is preferably 0.01 to 1 wt%, more
preferably 0.05 to 0.5 wt% of the total solids content of
the heat-sensitive layer.</p>
    <p num="0283">In the original forme for a lithographic printing
plate according to the present invention, in order to
prevent an occurrence of contamination on the surface of
the heat-sensitive layer by ink receptive substances, a
water soluble overcoat layer may be provided on the heat-sensitive
layer. The water soluble overcoat layer used in
the present invention can be readily removed at the time of
printing and contains a resin selected from water-soluble
organic polymer compounds.</p>
    <p num="0284">The water-soluble organic polymer compounds include
those in which a coating sheet formed by coating followed
by drying has a film forming property when they are coated
and dried. Specific examples thereof include polyvinyl
acetate (provided that it has a hydrolysis ratio of 65% or
more); polyacrylic acid, and alkali metal salts or amine
salts thereof; polyacrylic acid copolymers, and alkali 
metal salts or amine salts thereof; polymethacrylic acid,
and alkali metal salts or amine salts thereof;
polymethacrylic acid copolymers, and alkali metal salts or
amine salts thereof; polyacrylamide, and copolymers
thereof; polyhydroxyethyl acrylate; polyvinylpyrrolidone
and copolymers thereof; polyvinyl methyl ether; vinyl
methyl ether/maleic anhydride copolymer; poly-2-acrylamide-2-methyl-1-propanesulfonate
and alkali metal salts or amine
salts thereof; poly-2-acrylamide-2-methyl-1-propansulfonate
copolymer, and alkali metal salts or amine salts thereof;
gum arabic; cellulose derivatives (for example,
carboxymethylcellulose, carboxyethylcellulose,
methylcellulose) and modified products thereof; white
dextrin; pullulan; and enzyme-decomposed etherated dextrin.
Depending on the purpose, a mixture of two or more of these
may be used.</p>
    <p num="0285">The overcoat layer may contain the aforementioned
water-soluble light-heat converting agent. Furthermore,
when it is formed by coating a water-soluble solution for
the purpose of maintaining evenness of coating, the
overcoat layer may contain a nonionic surfactant such as
polyoxyethylene nonyl phenyl ether, polyoxyethylene dodecyl
ether or the like.</p>
    <p num="0286">The dry coating amount of the overcoat layer is 
preferably 0.1 to 2.0 g/m<sup>2</sup>. In this range, it is possible
to effectively prevent occurrence of contamination on the
surface of the heat-sensitive layer with ink receptive
substance, such as fingerprint, without deteriorating the
on-press developability.</p>
    <p num="0287">In the original forme for a lithographic printing
plate according to the present invention, the recording
layer may be other than the aforementioned heat-sensitive
layer containing (a) the polymer particles having a heat-reactive
functional group or (b) microcapsules including a
compound having a heat-reactive functional group. Examples
of such a layer includes photosensitive layers such as a
photosensitive layer using a negative-type infrared laser
recording material, a photosensitive layer using a
positive-type infrared laser recording material, and a
photosensitive layer using a sulfonate-type infrared laser
recording material.</p>
    <p num="0288">In a case where the original forme for a lithographic
printing plate according to the present invention is an
original forme of a negative-type lithographic printing
plate which may be exposed with infrared laser, that is, a
so-called thermal negative-type lithographic printing
original plate, the photosensitive layer may be suitably
made of a negative-type infrared laser recording material. </p>
    <p num="0289">As the negative-type infrared laser recording
material, those compositions comprising (A) a compound that
is decomposed by light or heat to generate acid, (B) a
crosslinking agent that corsslinks with the acid, (C) an
alkali-soluble resin, (D) an infrared absorbent, and (E) a
compound represented by the general formula (R<sup>3</sup>-X)<sub>n</sub>Ar-(OH)<sub>m</sub>
(wherein R<sup>3</sup> represents an alkyl group or alkenyl group
having 6 to 32 carbon atoms, X represents a single chemical
bond, O, S, COO or CONH, Ar represents an aromatic
hydrocarbyl group, an aliphatic hydrocarbyl group, or a
heterocyclic group, n is an integer of 1 to 3, and m is an
integer of 1 to 3) are suitably used.</p>
    <p num="0290">Generally, the thermal negative-type lithographic
printing original plate has drawbacks such that
fingerprints can be easily attached onto it after
development and the strength of the image area is poor.
Such drawbacks can be solved by forming the photosensitive
layer from the above-mentioned composition.</p>
    <p num="0291">Examples of the compound (A) which is decomposed by
light or heat to generate an acid include compounds which
are subjected to a photodecomposition to generate sulfonic
acid, typified by iminosulfonates described in Japanese
Patent Application No. 3-140109 (JP 04-365048 A) and
compounds which generate an acid by exposure to light 
having a wavelength of 200 to 500 nm or by heating at 100°C
or more.</p>
    <p num="0292">Preferred acid generating agents include
photocationic polymerization initiators, photoradical
polymerization initiators, and photocolor fading and
photocolor changing agents of pigments. The acid
generating agent is preferably added in an amount of 0.01
to 50 wt% based on the total solid content of a recording
material.</p>
    <p num="0293">Preferred examples of the crosslinking agent (B) for
crosslinking by an acid include (i) aromatic compounds
having an alkoxymethyl group or hydroxyl group as a
substituent, (ii) compounds having an N-hydroxymethyl group,
N-alkoxymethyl group or N-acyloxymethyl group and (iii)
epoxy compounds.</p>
    <p num="0294">Examples of the alkali soluble resin (C) include
novolak resin and polymers having a hydroxyaryl group in
the side chain.</p>
    <p num="0295">Examples of the composition (D) comprising an
infrared-absorbing agent include: commercially available
dyes such as azo dyes, anthraquinone dyes and
phthalocyanine dyes all of which absorb infrared ray having
a wavelength of 760 to 1,200 nm effectively; and black
pigments, red pigments, metal powder pigments and 
phthalocyanine-based pigments which are listed in color
indices. An image coloring agent such as Oil Yellow or Oil
Blue #603 is preferably added to make it easier to see an
image. A plasticizer such as polyethylene glycol or
phthalate may be added to improve the softness of a
photosensitive layer coating film.</p>
    <p num="0296">It is recommended to form a photosensitive layer from
a positive type infrared laser recording material when the
original forme for a lithographic printing plate of the
present invention is to be changed to a positive type
original forme for a lithographic printing plate which can
be exposed to infrared laser light, a so-called thermal
positive type lithographic printing original plate.</p>
    <p num="0297">As the positive type infrared laser recording
material may be advantageously used a positive type
infrared laser recording material which comprises (A) an
alkali-soluble polymer, (B) a compound which is compatible
with the alkali-soluble polymer to reduce its alkali
solubility, and (C) a compound which absorbs infrared laser
light.</p>
    <p num="0298">When this positive type infrared laser recording
material is used, the poor solubility in an alkali
developer of a non-image area can be solved and an original
forme for a lithographic printing plate which is hardly 
scratched and has excellent alkali-resistant developability
of an image area and development stability can be obtained.</p>
    <p num="0299">Examples of the alkali-soluble polymer (A) include
(i) polymer compounds having a phenolic hydroxyl group
typified by phenolic resin, cresol resin, novolak resin and
pyrogallol resin, (ii) compounds obtained by
homopolymerizing a polymerizable monomer having a
sulfonamide group or by copolymerizing it with another
polymerizable monomer, and (iii) compounds having an active
imide group typified by N-(p-toluenesulfonyl)methacrylamide
or N-(p-toluenesulfonyl)acrylamide in the molecule.</p>
    <p num="0300">Examples of the compound which is compatible with the
above-mentioned component (A) to reduce its alkali
solubility include compounds which interact with the above
component (A), such as sulfone compounds, ammonium salts,
sulfonium salts and amide compounds. When the above
component (A) is a novolak resin, a cyanine pigment is
suitably used as the component (B).</p>
    <p num="0301">The compound which absorbs infrared laser light (C)
is preferably a material which absorbs light having an
infrared region of 750 to 1,200 nm and has photo thermal
convertion function. Examples of the material having such
a function include squalilium pigment, pyrylium pigment,
carbon black, insoluble azo dye and anthraquinone-based dye. 
They are preferably as large as 0.01 to 10 µm.</p>
    <p num="0302">The thermal positive type original forme for a
lithographic printing plate can be obtained by dissolving
this positive type infrared laser recording material in an
organic solvent such as methanol or methyl ethyl ketone,
adding a dye as required, applying this solution to a
support to such a degree as being 1 to 3 g/m<sup>2</sup> in terms of
mass after drying, and drying the coating film.</p>
    <p num="0303">In the original forme for a lithographic printing
plate of the present invention, a sulfonate-based infrared
laser recording material may be used as a recording layer.</p>
    <p num="0304">As the sulfonate-based infrared laser recording
material may be used sulfonate compounds described in JP
270480 B and JP 2704872 B. A photosensitive material
which generates sulfonic acid by heat generated upon
irradiation with infrared laser light to become soluble in
water, a photosensitive material whose surface polarity is
changed by fixing a styrene sulfonic acid ester with sol-gel
and applying thereto an infrared laser light, and
photosensitive materials whose hydrophobic surface is
turned hydrophilic by exposure to laser light as disclosed
in Japanese Patent Application No. 9-89816 (JP 10-282646 A),
No. 10-22406 (JP 11-218928 A) and No. 10-027655 (JP 10-282672
A) may also be used. </p>
    <p num="0305">The following methods are preferably used in
combination to further improve the characteristics of a
photosensitive layer made of a polymer compound which can
generate a sulfonic acid group by the above-mentioned heat.
The methods include, for example, (1) one in which an acid
or base generating agent is used together as disclosed in
Japanese Patent Application No. 10-7062 (JP 11-202483 A),
(2)one in which a particular intermediate layer is formed
as disclosed in Japanese Patent Application No. 9-340358
(JP 11-174685 A), (3) one in which a particular
crosslinking agent is used together as disclosed in
Japanese Patent Application No. 9-248994 (JP 11-84658 A),
and (4) one in which the photosensitive layer is used with
the surface of a solid particle is modified as disclosed in
Japanese Patent Application No. 10-115354 (JP 11-301131 A).</p>
    <p num="0306">Other examples of the composition which changes the
hydrophilic or hydrophobic nature of a photosensitive layer
by heat generated upon exposure to laser light include, for
example, a composition which comprises a Werner complex and
turns hydrophobic by heat as disclosed in US 2,764,085 B, a
composition which turns hydrophilic upon exposure, such as
a particular sugars or melamine formaldehyde resin
disclosed in JP 46-27219 B, a composition which turns
hydrophobic upon heat mode exposure as disclosed in JP 51-63704 
A, a composition comprising a polymer which turns
anhydrous or hydrophobic by heat, such as a phthalyl
hydrazide polymer disclosed in US 4,081,572 B, a
composition which has a tetrazolium salt structure and
turns hydrophilic by heat as disclosed in JP 3-58100 B, a
composition which comprises a sulfonic acid modified
polymer and turns hydrophobic upon exposure as disclosed in
JP 60-132760 A, a composition which comprises an imide
precursor polymer and turns hydrophobic upon exposure as
disclosed in JP 64-3543 A, and a composition which
comprises a carbon-fluorine polymer and turns hydrophilic
upon exposure as disclosed in JP 51-74706 A. A recording
layer can be formed from these compositions.</p>
    <p num="0307">The above examples further include a composition
which comprises a hydrophobic crystalline polymer and turns
hydrophilic upon exposure as disclosed in JP 3-197190 A, a
composition which comprises a polymer and photo thermal
convertion agent and whose insolubilized side group turns
hydrophilic by heat as disclosed in JP 7-186562 A, a
composition which comprises a 3-D crosslinked hydrophilic
binder containing microcapsules and turns hydrophobic upon
exposure as disclosed in JP 7-1849 A, a composition which
is subjected to a valence isomerization and isomerized by
or proton shift as disclosed in JP 8-3463 A, a composition 
which undergoes a phase structural change
(compatibilization) in layer by heat to change its
hydrophilic/hydrophobic nature as disclosed in JP 8-141819
A, and a composition whose surface form or whose surface
hydrophilic/hydrophobic nature is changed by heat as
disclosed in JP 60-228 B. A recording layer can be formed
from these compositions.</p>
    <p num="0308">Other preferred examples of the recording material
used in the recording layer in the present invention
include a composition which changes adhesion between a
photosensitive layer and a support by heat generated by
high-power and high-density laser light, so-called "heat
mode exposure". Specifically, the composition is a
composition which comprises a thermally fusible material or
heat-reactive material as disclosed in JP 44-22957 B.</p>
    <p num="0309">A description is subsequently given of the device for
producing an aluminum support which is a preferred form of
the support for lithographic printing plates of the present
invention.</p>
    <p num="0310">The process for producing an aluminum support which
is a preferred form of the support for lithographic
printing plates of the present invention preferably
comprises (1) the step of winding off an aluminum plate
which has been rolled and wound like a coil from a wind-off 
unit which is a multi-axis turret, (2) the step of drying
the aluminum plate after the above treatments (mechanical
surface roughening treatment, electrochemical surface
roughening treatment, alkali etching, acid etching,
desmutting, formation of a low thermally conductive
hydrophilic coating film, pore widening (acid treatment or
alkali treatment), pore-sealing, hydrophilic surface
treatment, etc.), and (3) the step of winding up the
aluminum plate like a coil by a wind-up unit which is
formed from the above multi-axis turret or correcting the
flatness of the aluminum plate, cutting it to a
predetermined length and collecting cut pieces. As
required, in the above process, the step of forming an
undercoat layer or recording layer and drying it may be
provided to prepare an original forme for a lithographic
printing plate which is then wound up like a coil by the
above wind-up unit.</p>
    <p num="0311">Preferably, the production process of an aluminum
support comprises at least one step of inspecting a surface
defect in the aluminum plate continuously using a device
for inspecting the defect and labeling an edge portion of a
discovered defect for the purpose of marking. Further, in
the step of winding off the aluminum plate and the step of
winding up the aluminum plate in the production of the 
original forme for a lithographic printing plate of the
present invention, even when the running of the aluminum
plate is suspended for the exchange of an aluminum coil, a
reserver unit for maintaining the running speed of the
aluminum plate at a constant speed in each step is
preferably used and the step of bonding the aluminum plate
by ultrasonic waves or arc welding is preferably provided
after the step of winding off the aluminum plate.</p>
    <p num="0312">The apparatus used for the production of an aluminum
support preferably comprises at least one unit for
detecting the running position of the aluminum plate to
correct the running position, and at least one drive unit
for reducing the tension of the aluminum plate and
controlling the running speed of the aluminum plate and at
least one dancer roll unit for controlling the tension of
the aluminum plate.</p>
    <p num="0313">It is also preferred that a tracking unit be used to
record whether the conditions of each step are desirable or
not in order to label an edge portion of an aluminum web
before the aluminum coil is wound up like a coil so that it
can be judged later whether conditions of portions after
labeled portion are desired or not.</p>
    <p num="0314">In the present invention, it is preferred that the
aluminum plate and an interleaving sheet be charged to be 
adsorbed to each other, cut to a predetermined length
and/or slit. It is also preferred that based on
information from the label as a mark pasted to the edge
portion of the aluminum plate, the aluminum plate is
divided into an acceptable portion and a defective portion
after or before it is cut to a predetermined length so that
only acceptable portion is collected.</p>
    <p num="0315">In each step including the above wind-off step etc.,
it is important to set the optimum tension according to
conditions such as the size (thickness and width) of the
aluminum plate, the material of the aluminum plate or the
running speed of the aluminum web. It is preferred to
install a plurality of tension controllers for feed-back
controlling a signal from a tension detector, making use of
a drive unit for reducing tension and controlling the
running speed and a dancer roll for controlling tension.
The drive unit generally employs a control method which
combines a DC motor and a main drive roller. The main
drive roller is made from general rubber and a roller made
of a nonwoven cloth laminate may be used in the step where
the aluminum web is in a wet state. Although each pass
roller is generally made from rubber or metal, a motor or
decelerator may be connected to each pass roller and an
auxiliary drive unit for controlling the revolution of the 
pass roller at a constant speed based on a signal from the
main drive unit may be provided to prevent a slip between
the pass roller and the aluminum web in such a portion that
this slip is likely to occur.</p>
    <p num="0316">In the aluminum support used in the present invention,
as disclosed in JP 10-114046 A, when the arithmetic average
roughness (R<sub>a</sub>) in the rolling direction is represented by
R<sub>1</sub> and the arithmetic average roughness (R<sub>a</sub>) in the width
direction is represented by R<sub>2</sub>, R<sub>1</sub> - R<sub>2</sub> is preferably 30 %
or less of R<sub>1</sub>, the average curvature in the rolling
direction is preferably 1.5 x 10<sup>-3</sup> mm<sup>-1</sup> or less, the average
curvature in the width direction is preferably 1.5 x 10<sup>-3</sup>
mm<sup>-1</sup> or less, and the average curvature in a direction
perpendicular to the rolling direction is preferably 1.0 x
10<sup>-3</sup> mm<sup>-1</sup> or less.</p>
    <p num="0317">The aluminum support produced through the above
surface roughening treatment etc. is preferably
straightened with a straightening roll having a diameter of
20 to 80 mm and a rubber hardness of 50 to 90 degrees.
Thereby, even in the step of automatically conveying a
photosensitive lithographic printer, a flat aluminum coiled
plate which is free from an exposure shift in an original
forme for a lithographic printing plate can be supplied.
JP 9-194093 A discloses a method of measuring the curl of a 
web and device therefor, a curl correcting method and
device therefore, and a web cutting device all of which may
be used in the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0318">For the continuous production of an aluminum support,
whether each step is carried out in suitable conditions is
electrically monitored, whether the conditions of each step
are desirable or not is recorded by a tracking unit, and
the edge portion of an aluminum web is labeled before the
aluminum coil is wound up so that it can be judged later
whether a portion after the label is in desired conditions
or not, thereby making it possible to judge whether the
portion is acceptable or not at the time of cutting and
collection.</p>
    <p num="0319">The aluminum plate treating apparatus used for the
above surface roughening treatment preferably maintains the
concentration of a solution at a constant value through
feed-back control and/or feed forward control by measuring
at least one of the temperature, specific gravity,
conductivity and ultrasonic wave propagation velocity of
the solution and obtaining the composition of the solution.</p>
    <p num="0320">Components contained in the aluminum plate such as
aluminum ions dissolve in an acidic aqueous solution
contained in the above treating apparatus along with the
proceeding of the surface treatment of the aluminum plate. 
To maintain the concentration of aluminum ion and the
concentration of an acid or alkali at constant values, it
is preferred that water and an acid, or water and an alkali
be added intermittently to keep constant the composition of
the solution. The concentration of the acid or alkali
added is preferably 10 to 98 wt%.</p>
    <p num="0321">To control the concentration of the above acid or
alkali, for example, the following method is preferred.</p>
    <p num="0322">A data table is first prepared by measuring the
conductivity, specific gravity or ultrasonic wave
propagation velocity for each component solution having a
predetermined concentration to be used at each temperature.
Then, the concentration of a component solution is obtained
with reference to the previously prepared data table of the
solution to be measured from data on the conductivity,
specific gravity or ultrasonic wave propagation velocity of
the solution to be measured and temperature data. The
method of measuring the above ultrasonic wave propagation
velocity at a high accuracy and high stability is disclosed
in JP 6-235721 A. The concentration measuring system
making use of the above ultrasonic wave propagation
velocity is disclosed in JP 58-77656 A. The method of
measuring concentration of a multi-component solution with
reference to a data table which shows correlation among a 
plurality of physical quantity data for each solution
component is disclosed in JP 4-19559 A.</p>
    <p num="0323">When the above method of measuring the concentration
using the ultrasonic wave propagation velocity is applied
to the step of roughening the surface of an aluminum
support by combining the conductivity and temperature value
of a solution to be measured, process control can be
carried out in a real-time accurately, thereby making it
possible to produce products of fixed quality and improve
yield. When the method of measuring the concentration of a
multi-component solution with reference to a prepared data
table which shows not only the correlation among
temperature, ultrasonic wave propagation velocity and
conductivity but also the correlation between temperature
and specific gravity, the correlation between temperature
and conductivity, or the correlation among temperature,
conductivity and specific gravity, etc. in terms of
physical quantity at each concentration and each
temperature, the same effect as above is obtained.</p>
    <p num="0324">The concentration of a slurry can also be measured
quickly and accurately by obtaining the concentration of
the slurry to be measured with reference to a data table
previously prepared by measuring specific gravity and
temperature. </p>
    <p num="0325">Since the measurement of the above ultrasonic wave
propagation velocity is easily affected by bubbles
contained in the solution, it is more preferably carried
out in a pipe installed vertically and having a flow of a
solution going upward. The measurement of the above
ultrasonic wave propagation velocity is preferably carried
out at a pipe pressure of 1 to 10 kg/cm<sup>2</sup> and the frequency
of ultrasonic waves is preferably 0.5 to 3 MHz.</p>
    <p num="0326">Since the measurement of the above specific gravity,
conductivity and ultrasonic wave propagation velocity is
easily affected by temperature, it is preferably carried
out in a pipe which is kept warm and whose temperature
variations are controlled within ±0.3°C. Further, since
conductivity and specific gravity or conductivity and
ultrasonic wave propagation velocity are preferably
measured at the same temperature, they are particularly
preferably measured in the same pipe or the same pipe flow.
As pressure variations during measurement lead to
temperature variations, they are preferably as small as
possible. A flow velocity distribution in a pipe to be
measured is also as small as possible. Further, as the
above measurement is easily affected by a slurry, dirt and
bubbles, a solution which has passed through a filter or
deaeration device is preferably measured. </p>
    <p num="0327">An image is formed on the thus obtained lithographic
printing original plate according to the present invention
by heat. More specifically, an image is preferably
directly recorded by a thermal recording head or the like
and exposed by scanning with infrared laser light, high-illuminance
flash from a xenon discharge lamp and solid
high-output infrared laser light from an infrared lamp.</p>
    <p num="0328">When the recording layer is a so-called heat-sensitive
layer of the on-press development type which
contains (a) a fine polymer particles having a heat-reactive
functional group or (b) microcapsules containing a
compound having a heat-reactive functional group, the
original forme for a lithographic printing plate according
to the present invention can be mounted to a printer
without performing a further treatment thereon after
exposure to print using an ink and/or a damping solution
according to a normal procedure. As described in JP
2938398 B, after the original forme for a lithographic
printing plate is mounted on the cylinder of a printer, it
may be exposed by a laser mounted to the printer to perform
on-press development by applying an ink and/or a damping
solution. Since the heat-sensitive layer is removed by the
ink and/or damping solution on the printer in this case, a
separate development step is not needed and the printer 
does not need to be stopped for printing after development,
thereby making it possible to carry out printing right
after development.</p>
    <p num="0329">That is, as for the plate-making and printing method
for a lithographic printing plate according to the present
invention, the original forme for a lithographic printing
plate having a heat-sensitive layer of the on-press
development type is exposed to laser light and directly
mounted to the printer for printing, or mounted to a
printer, exposed to laser light and then used for printing
as it is. As the laser may be used a solid laser or
semiconductor laser for irradiating infrared ray having a
wavelength of 760 to 1,200 nm.</p>
    <p num="0330">Even when the original forme for a lithographic
printing plate has a heat-sensitive layer of the on-press
development type, it can be used for printing after
development with a developer which is water or suitable
aqueous solution.</p>
    <p num="0331">When the original forme for a lithographic printing
plate of the present invention has a conventional thermal
positive type or thermal negative type recording layer, it
is exposed, developed with a developer and mounted to a
printer for printing in accordance with a commonly used
method. </p>
    <p num="0332">The support of the present invention can be further
used in a treatment-free lithographic printing original
plate having an image forming layer composed of a water
receptive layer which can be hydrophobilized by heat.</p>
    <p num="0333">Such an original forme has a water receptive layer
(image forming layer) which contains microcapsule particles
containing thermoplastic polymer fine particles or an ink-receptive
substance, including (a) the above-described fine
polymer particles having a heat-reactive group or (b)
microcapsules containing a compound having a heat-reactive
functional group, or fine particles such as hydrophobic
resin fine particles dispersed in a matrix such as a
hydrophobic resin. When heat is applied to the water
receptive layer, the hydrophilic substance contained in the
fine particles escape from the fine particles and only a
heat-irradiated portion of the surface of the water
receptive layer is selectively converted to ink-receptive
portion.</p>
    <p num="0334">Using this surface consisting of an ink-receptive
image area and a hydrophilic non-image area composed of an
unheat-irradiated hydrophilic matrix as a printing surface,
it is possible to perform lithographic printing using a
damping solution, which does not require development and is
completely treatment-free. </p>
    <p num="0335">Further, in an infrared laser light scanning exposure
recording system, the water receptive layer preferably
contains a photo thermal converting agent.</p>
    <p num="0336">Such a treatment-free lithographic printing original
plate can be directly mounted to a printer without
development after exposure, or exposed on a printer and
used for printing as it is.</p>
    <p num="0337">Use of the support having a specific thermal
conductivity of the present invention makes it possible to
form a high-accuracy image on an image area after image
formation, improve printing ink-receptivity and print a
large number of printing sheets.</p>
    <p num="0338">Examples of the heat-sensitive original forme for a
lithographic printing plate having a water receptive layer
which can be hydrophobilized by heat include, for example,
original formes having a heat-sensitive layer containing
thermoplastic polymer fine particles dispersed in a
hydrophilic resin as described in JP 59-174394 A, Research
Disclosure No. 33303 issued on January, 1992 and JP 2001-47755
A, a water receptive layer (heat-sensitive layer)
containing water self-dispersible hydrophobilized resin
particles having a double-layer structure as described in
the paragraphs [0057] to [0088] of JP 2001-315453 A, a
water receptive layer containing hydrophobilized resin 
particles having a hydrophilic surface and containing
surface hydrophobilized metal fine particles as described
in the paragraphs [0021] to [0066] of JP 2002-29165 A, a
water receptive layer containing hydrophobilized resin
particles including a particular vinyloxy group-containing
compound as described in the paragraphs [0008] to [0038] of
JP 2002-36745 A, and a water receptive layer containing a
hydrophilic polymer having a silanol group and a metal
oxide as described in the paragraphs [0033] to [0047] of JP
2002-6504 A.</p>
    <p num="0339">The contents of the treatment-free lithographic
printing original plate according to the present invention
are not limited to the above examples. The contents of all
the public documents and pending patent applications
described in this specification are hereby incorporated
into this specification by reference.</p>
    <heading>Examples</heading>
    <p num="0340">The following examples are provided for the purpose
of further illustrating the present invention but are in no
way to be taken as limiting.</p>
    <heading>[Production Examples of Aluminum Substrates]</heading>
    <p num="0341">Aluminum substrates used in Examples were produced
from a 0.24 mm-thick JIS1050-based aluminum plate by
carrying out a pre-treatment, surface roughening treatment, 
hydrophilic film formation and optionally post-treatment in
the mentioned order. The surface roughening treatment was
carried out in accordance with any one of A to J below, and
the hydrophilic film formation and the post-treatment were
carried out by the methods described in the Production
Examples of Substrates.</p>
    <heading>&lt;surface roughening treatments A, B and C&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0342">The aluminum plate was immersed in a 1 % aqueous
solution of sodium hydroxide maintained at 50°C to carry
out a dissolution treatment until the amount of dissolution
became 2 g/m<sup>2</sup>. After rinsing, the aluminum plate was
immersed in an aqueous solution having the same composition
as an electrolyte used in the subsequent electrochemical
surface roughening treatment for 10 seconds to be
neutralized, and then rinsed.</p>
    <p num="0343">This aluminum substrate material was subjected to a
plurality of electrochemical surface roughening treatments
using a sine wave alternating current with a current
density of 50 A/dm<sup>2</sup> and a quiescent time therebetween.
Table 1 shows the composition of the electrolyte, the
amount of electricity for each treatment, the number of
electrolytic treatments and the quiescent time. After the
electrochemical surface roughening treatments, the aluminum
substrate material was immersed in a 1 % aqueous solution 
of sodium hydroxide maintained at 50°C to dissolve in an
alkali until the amount of dissolution became 2 g/m<sup>2</sup>,
rinsed, immersed in a 10 % aqueous solution of sulfuric
acid maintained at 25°C for 10 seconds to be neutralized
and then rinsed.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry nameend="6" namest="1">Table 1 Conditions of surface roughening treatments A, B and C</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1">Type of surface roughening treatment</entry><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2">Composition of electrolyte</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">Amount of electricity for each treatment (C/dm<sup>2</sup>)</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">Number of electrolytic treatments</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">Quiescent time (seconds)</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Hydrochloric acid (g/l)</entry><entry align="center">Acetic acid (g/l)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">A</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">80</entry><entry align="center">6</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="center">B</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">40</entry><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="center">4.0</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">0.8</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <heading>&lt;surface roughening treatment D&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0344">The aluminum plate was immersed in a 10 % aqueous
solution of sodium hydroxide maintained at 50°C for 20
seconds to be degreased and etched, washed with running
water, neutralized with a 25 % aqueous solution of sulfuric
acid for 20 seconds and rinsed. Thereafter, the aluminum
plate was subjected to an electrolytic surface roughening
treatment at 20°C using a 1 % aqueous solution of
hydrochloric acid (containing 0.5 % of aluminum ions) and
trapezoidal rectangular waves having a time (TP) required
for the current value to reach a peak from 0 of 2 msec, a 
frequency of 60 Hz and a duty ratio of 1:1 and carbon
electrodes as counter electrodes so that the average
current density at the time of aluminum anode became 27
A/dm<sup>2</sup> (ratio of current density at the time of aluminum
anode to the time of aluminum cathode of 1: 0.95) and the
amount of quantity of electricity at the time of aluminum
anode became 350 C/dm<sup>2</sup>. Thereafter, the aluminum plate was
etched by spraying an aqueous solution containing 26 % of
sodium hydroxide and 6.5 % of aluminum ions at a liquid
temperature of 45°C until the total amount of etching
including smuts became 0.7 g/m<sup>2</sup>. Then, desmutting was
carried out by spraying a 25 % aqueous solution of nitric
acid (containing 0.3 % of aluminum ions) at 60°C for 10
seconds.</p>
    <heading>&lt;surface roughening treatment E&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0345">The surface of the aluminum plate was roughened using
a nylon brush having a bristle diameter of 0.72 mm and a
bristle length of 80 mm and a water suspension of pumice
powder having an average particle size of about 15 to 35 µm
and rinsed well. Thereafter, the aluminum plate was
immersed in a 10 % aqueous solution of sodium hydroxide at
70°C for 30 seconds to be etched, washed with running water,
neutralized with a 20 % aqueous solution of nitric acid and
rinsed. Thus, the aluminum plate whose surface had been 
roughened mechanically was further subjected to the
following electrochemical surface roughening treatment.</p>
    <p num="0346">AC was applied to the aluminum plate whose surface
had been roughened mechanically in an aqueous solution of
hydrochloric acid having a hydrochloric acid concentration
of 7.5 g/l and an aluminum ion concentration of 5 g/l
prepared by adding aluminum chloride to hydrochloric acid,
using a radial cell shown in Fig. 2, at a liquid
temperature of 35°C to carry out AC electrolysis. Sine
waves generated by regulating the current and voltage of
commercial AC having a frequency of 60 Hz by means of an
induction voltage regulator and a transformer were used as
AC. The total amount of electricity when the aluminum
plate was an anode was 50 C/dm<sup>2</sup> and Qc/Qa at one cycle of
the above AC was 0.95.</p>
    <p num="0347">The hydrochloric acid concentration and aluminum ion
concentration of the above aqueous solution of hydrochloric
acid were maintained at constant values by obtaining the
relationship among temperature, conductivity, ultrasonic
wave propagation velocity, the concentration of
hydrochloric acid and the concentration of aluminum ion and
by adding a concentrated hydrochloric acid having a
concentration of 35 % and water to an electrolytic tank
from a circulation tank and overflowing an excess of the 
aqueous solution of hydrochloric acid so that the
temperature, conductivity and ultrasonic wave propagation
velocity of the aqueous solution of hydrochloric acid
became predetermined values. Thereafter, an alkali
solution containing 5 % of sodium hydroxide and 0.5 % of
aluminum ion and having a liquid temperature of 45°C was
used as a treating solution to etch the aluminum plate
until the dissolution amount of the roughened surface of
the aluminum plate became 0.1 g/m<sup>2</sup> and the dissolution
amount of the opposite surface became 0.05 g/m<sup>2</sup>.</p>
    <p num="0348">The both sides of the etched aluminum plate were
sprayed with an aqueous solution of sulfuric acid having a
sulfuric acid concentration of 300 g/l and an aluminum ion
concentration of 5 g/l and a liquid temperature of 50°C for
desmutting.</p>
    <heading>&lt;surface roughening treatment F&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0349">After the surface roughening treatment A, the
following electrolytic surface roughening treatment was
further carried out in an aqueous solution of nitric acid.</p>
    <p num="0350">The aluminum plate was subjected to an electrolytic
surface roughening treatment at 50°C using a 1 % solution
of nitric acid (containing 0.5 % of aluminum ions) and
trapezoidal rectangular waves having a time (TP) required
for the current value to reach a peak from "0" of 2 msec, a 
frequency of 60 Hz and a duty ratio of 1:1 and carbon
electrodes as counter electrodes so that the average
current density at the time of aluminum anode became 27
A/dm<sup>2</sup> (ratio of current density at the time of aluminum
anode to the time of aluminum cathode of 1: 0.95) and the
amount of quantity of electricity at the time of aluminum
anode became 350 C/dm<sup>2</sup>, using a radial cell shown in Fig.2
Thereafter, the aluminum plate was etched by spraying an
aqueous solution containing 26 % of sodium hydroxide and
6.5 % of aluminum ions at a liquid temperature of 45°C
until the total amount of etching including smuts became
0.2 g/m<sup>2</sup>. Then, desmutting was carried out by spraying a
25 % aqueous solution of nitric acid (containing 0.3 % of
aluminum ions) at 60°C for 10 seconds.</p>
    <heading>&lt;surface roughening treatment G&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0351">Out of the surface roughening treatment E, a
treatment excluding an electrochemical surface roughening
treatment and the subsequent treatments (i.e. a treatment
including mechanical surface roughening, alkali etching,
neutralization and rinsing) is designated as surface
roughening treatment G.</p>
    <heading>&lt;surface roughening treatment H&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0352">The aluminum plate was immersed in a 1 % aqueous
solution of sodium hydroxide maintained at 50°C to carry 
out a dissolution treatment until the amount of dissolution
became 2 g/m<sup>2</sup>. After rinsing, the aluminum plate was
immersed in an aqueous solution having the same composition
as an electrolyte used in the subsequent electrochemical
surface roughening treatment for 10 seconds to be
neutralized, and then rinsed.</p>
    <p num="0353">This aluminum substrate material was then subjected
to electrochemical surface roughening treatments using a 1
% aqueous solution of nitric acid (containing 0.5 % of
aluminum ion) and sine wave AC with a current density of 50
A/dm<sup>2</sup> and a quiescent time of 0.5 second each and an
electricity amount of 250 C/dm<sup>2</sup> for each treatment,
totaling 500 C/dm<sup>2</sup>, and then rinsed. After the
electrochemical roughening treatments, the aluminum
substrate material was immersed in a 1 % aqueous solution
of sodium hydroxide maintained at 50°C to dissolve in an
alkali until the amount of dissolution became 5 g/m<sup>2</sup>,
rinsed, immersed in a 10 % aqueous solution of sulfuric
acid maintained at 25°C for 10 seconds to be neutralized
and then rinsed.</p>
    <heading>&lt;surface roughening treatment I&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0354">The same surface roughening treatment as the surface
roughening treatment H was carried out except that an
alkali dissolution treatment was not carried out after the 
electrochemical surface roughening treatment.</p>
    <heading>&lt;surface roughening treatment J&gt;</heading>
    <heading>(1) mechanical surface roughening treatment</heading>
    <p num="0355">A mechanical surface roughening treatment was carried
out using a brush roller having rotating nylon brushes
while a suspension of silica sand having a specific gravity
of 1.12 (abrasive having an average particle size of 25 µm)
and water was supplied as an abrasive slurry solution to
the surface of the aluminum plate by a spray tube.</p>
    <p num="0356">The nylon brushes used were made from 6,10-nylon and
had a bristle length of 50 mm and a bristle diameter of
0.48 mm. The nylon brushes were manufactured by making
holes in a stainless cylinder having a diameter of 300 mm
and transplanting bristles densely.</p>
    <p num="0357">Three nylon brushes were used in the brush roller and
the interval between two support rollers (diameter of 200
mm) below the brushes was 300 mm.</p>
    <p num="0358">The above brush roller was pressed against the
aluminum plate to ensure that the arithmetical mean
roughness (R<sub>a</sub>) of the roughened aluminum plate became 0.45
µm by controlling the load of a drive motor for rotating
the brushes based on the load before the nylon brushes were
pressed against the aluminum plate. The rotation direction
of the brushes was the same as the moving direction of the 
aluminum plate. Thereafter, the aluminum plate was rinsed.</p>
    <p num="0359">The concentration of the abrasive was obtained from
temperature and specific gravity with reference to a table
prepared based on the relationship among the concentration
of the abrasive, temperature and specific gravity, and
water and the abrasive were added by feed-back control in
order to maintain the concentration of the abrasive at a
constant value. Since the surface form of the roughened
aluminum plate is changed when the abrasive was ground to
reduce its size, an abrasive having a small size was
continuously removed to the outside of the system by a
cyclone. The particle size of the abrasive was in the
range of 1 to 35 µm.</p>
    <heading>(2) alkali etching</heading>
    <p num="0360">Alkali etching was carried out by spraying the
aluminum plate with an aqueous solution containing 27 wt%
of NaOH and 6.5 wt% of aluminum ion and having a liquid
temperature of 70°C with a spray tube. The dissolution
amount on the surface of the aluminum plate to be
electrochemically roughened later was 8 g/m<sup>2</sup> and the
dissolution amount on the rear surface thereof was 2 g/m<sup>2</sup>.</p>
    <p num="0361">The concentration of an etching solution used for
alkali etching was maintained at a constant value by
obtaining the concentration of an etching solution from 
temperature, specific gravity and conductivity with
reference to a table prepared on advance based on the
relationship among the concentration of NaOH, the
concentration of aluminum ion, temperature, specific
gravity and the conductivity of the solution and by adding
water and a 48 wt% aqueous solution of NaOH by feed-back
control. Thereafter, the aluminum plate was rinsed.</p>
    <heading>(3) desmutting</heading>
    <p num="0362">The aluminum plate was sprayed with an aqueous
solution of nitric acid having a liquid temperature of 35°C
by using a spray to carry out desmutting for 10 seconds.
The aqueous solution of nitric acid was waste water
overflown from an electrolytic cell used in the subsequent
step. Then, spray tubes for spraying a desmutting solution
were installed at several locations to prevent the surface
of the aluminum plate from being dried until the following
step was carried out.</p>
    <heading>(4) electrochemical surface roughening treatment</heading>
    <p num="0363">An electrochemical surface roughening treatment was
carried out continuously using trapezoidal AC shown in Fig.
1 and two electrolytic cells shown in Fig. 2. The acidic
aqueous solution was an aqueous solution of nitric acid
having 1 wt% of nitric acid(containing 0.5 wt% of aluminum
ion and 0.007 wt% of ammonium ion). The temperature of the 
solution was 50°C. As for AC, the times TP and TP'
required for the current value to reach a peak from "0"
were 1 msec and carbon electrodes were used as counter
electrodes. The current density at the time of an AC peak
was 50 A/dm<sup>2</sup> when the aluminum plate was an anode or a
cathode. Further, the ratio (Q<sub>c</sub>/Q<sub>a</sub>) of the amount of
electricity (Q<sub>C</sub>) when AC was a cathode to the amount of
electricity (Q<sub>A</sub>) when AC was an anode, duty, frequency and
the total amount of electricity at the time of aluminum
anode are shown below. Thereafter, the aluminum plate was
rinsed by spraying.
<sl><li>Duty: 0.50</li><li>Frequency: 60 Hz</li><li>Total amount Q<sub>A</sub> of electricity at the time of aluminum
anode: 180 C/dm<sup>2</sup></li><li>Ratio Q<sub>C</sub>/Q<sub>A</sub> of amount of electricity: 0.95</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0364">The control of the concentration of the aqueous
solution of nitric acid was carried out by adding 67 wt%
nitric acid concentrate solution and water in proportion to
the amount of applied electricity and overflowing the same
amount of an acidic aqueous solution (nitric acid aqueous
solution) as the total volume of nitric acid and water
added from the electrolytic cell continuously to discharge
it to the outside of the electrolytic cell. With reference 
to a table prepared based on the relationship among the
concentration of nitric acid, the concentration of aluminum
ion, temperature, the conductivity of the solution and the
ultrasonic wave propagation velocity of the solution, the
concentration of the nitric acid aqueous solution was
obtained from the temperature, conductivity and ultrasonic
wave propagation velocity of the nitric acid aqueous
solution to perform controlling so as to adjust the adding
amounts of nitric acid concentrate solution and water
continuously in order to maintain the concentration at a
constant value.</p>
    <heading>(5) alkali etching</heading>
    <p num="0365">Alkali etching was carried out by spraying the
aluminum plate with an aqueous solution containing 26 wt%
of NaOH and 6.5 wt% of aluminum ion and having a liquid
temperature of 45°C, by using a spray tube. The
dissolution amount of the aluminum plate was 1 g/m<sup>2</sup>. The
concentration of an etching solution was maintained at a
constant value by obtaining the concentration of an etching
solution from temperature, specific gravity and
conductivity with reference to a table prepared on advance
based on the relationship among the concentration of NaOH,
the concentration of aluminum ion, temperature, specific
gravity and the conductivity of the solution and by adding 
water and a 48 wt% aqueous solution of NaOH by feed-back
control. Thereafter, the aluminum plate was rinsed.</p>
    <heading>(6) acid etching:</heading>
    <p num="0366">Sulfuric acid (sulfuric acid concentration: 300 g/l,
aluminum ion concentration: 15 g/l) was used as an acid
etching solution and sprayed onto the aluminum plate from a
spray tube at 80°C for 8 seconds to carry out acid etching.
The concentration of the acid etching solution was
maintained at a constant value by obtaining the
concentration of the acid etching solution from temperature,
specific gravity and conductivity with a reference to a
table prepared in advance based on the relationship among
the concentration of sulfuric acid, the concentration of
aluminum ion, temperature, specific gravity and the
conductivity of the solution and by adding water and 50 wt%
of sulfuric acid by feed-back control. Thereafter, the
aluminum plate was rinsed.</p>
    <heading>&lt;production of substrates 1 to 6 and 20&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0367">The surface roughened substrates A to F and J were
anodized by an anodizing device at a sulfuric acid
concentration of 170 g/l (containing 0.5 % of aluminum ion),
a liquid temperature of 40°C and a current density of 30
A/dm<sup>2</sup> for 20 seconds and rinsed. Thereafter, they were
immersed in an aqueous solution of sodium hydroxide having 
a pH of 13 and a temperature of 30°C for 70 seconds and
rinsed. They were then immersed in a 1 % aqueous solution
of colloidal silica (Snowtex ST-N of Nissan Chemical
Industries, Ltd., having a particle size of about 20 nm) at
70°C for 14 seconds and rinsed. Subsequently, they were
immersed in a 2.5 % aqueous solution of No. 3 sodium
silicate at 70°C for 14 seconds and rinsed to produce
substrates 1 to 6 and 20.</p>
    <heading>&lt;production of substrate 7&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0368">The aluminum plate which had been subjected to a
surface roughening treatment E was anodized in a 50 g/l
solution of oxalic acid at 30°C and at a current density of
12 A/dm<sup>2</sup> for 2 minutes and rinsed to form a 4 g/m<sup>2</sup> anodized
film. Thereafter, the aluminum plate was immersed in an
aqueous solution of sodium hydroxide having a pH of 13 and
a temperature of 50°C for 2 minutes and rinsed. It was
then immersed in a 2.5 % aqueous solution of No. 3 sodium
silicate at 70°C for 14 seconds and rinsed to produce a
substrate 7.</p>
    <heading>&lt;production of substrate 8&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0369">The aluminum plate which had been subjected to a
surface roughening treatment E was anodized at a sulfuric
acid concentration of 170 g/l (containing 0.5 % of aluminum
ion), a solution temperature of 30°C and a current density 
of 5 A/dm<sup>2</sup> for 70 seconds and rinsed. Thereafter, the
aluminum plate was immersed in an aqueous solution of
sodium hydroxide having a pH of 13 and a temperature of
30°C for 30 seconds and rinsed. It was then treated with
sodium silicate in the same manner as in Production Example
7 and rinsed to produce a substrate 8.</p>
    <heading>&lt;production of substrates 9 to 13&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0370">Substrates 9 to 13 were produced in the same manner
as in Production Example 5 except that the anodic oxidation
time of Production Example 5 (substrate 5) in which the
substrate which had been subjected to a surface roughening
treatment E was used was changed to 12 seconds, 16 seconds,
24 seconds, 44 seconds and 90 seconds, respectively.</p>
    <heading>&lt;production of substrate 14&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0371">A substrate 14 was produced in the same manner as in
Production Example 5 of substrate 5 except that immersion
in an aqueous solution of colloidal silica was not carried
out.</p>
    <heading>&lt;production of substrate 15&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0372">A substrate which had been subjected to a surface
roughening treatment E was anodized using an electrolyte
having a sulfuric acid concentration of 100 g/l and an
aluminum ion concentration of 5 g/l at a solution
temperature of 51°C and a current density of 30 A/dm<sup>2</sup> and 
rinsed to form a 2 g/m<sup>2</sup> anodized film. Thereafter, it was
anodized using an electrolyte having a sulfuric acid
concentration of 170 g/l and an aluminum ion concentration
of 5 g/l at a solution temperature of 40°C and a current
density of 30 A/dm<sup>2</sup> so that a total amount of an anodized
film becomes 4.0 g/m<sup>2</sup> and rinsed to form an anodized film.
It was then immersed in a 2.5 % aqueous solution of No. 3
sodium silicate at a solution temperature of 70°C for 14
seconds and rinsed to produce a substrate 15.</p>
    <heading>&lt;production of substrate 16&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0373">A substrate which had been subjected to a surface
roughening treatment E was anodized using an electrolyte
having a sulfuric acid concentration of 170 g/l and an
aluminum ion concentration of 5 g/l at a solution
temperature of 43°C and a current density of 30 A/dm<sup>2</sup> and
rinsed to form a 2 g/m<sup>2</sup> anodized film. Thereafter, it was
anodized using an electrolyte having a phosphoric acid
concentration of 170 g/l and an aluminum ion concentration
of 5 g/l at a solution temperature of 40°C and a current
density of 18 A/dm<sup>2</sup> and rinsed. It was then immersed in a
2.5 % aqueous solution of No. 3 sodium silicate at a
solution temperature of 70°C for 14 seconds and rinsed to
produce a substrate 16.</p>
    <heading>&lt;production of substrates 17 to 19&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0374">Substrates 17 to 19 were produced in the same manner
as in Production Example 14 except that substrate which had
been subjected to surface roughening treatments G, H and I
were used in place of the surface roughened substrate of
Production Example 14 (substrate 14), respectively.</p>
    <heading>&lt;production of comparative substrate (Comparative Example
1)&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0375">A comparative substrate 1 was produced in the same
manner as in Production Example 7 except that the treatment
time with sodium hydroxide in Production Example 7
(substrate 7) was changed to 3 minutes.</p>
    <heading>&lt;production of comparative substrate (Comparative Example
2)&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0376">A substrate which had been subjected to a surface
roughening treatment A was anodized using an electrolyte
having a sulfuric acid concentration of 200 g/l and an
aluminum ion concentration of 5 g/l at a solution
temperature of 45°C, a voltage of about 10 V and a current
density of 1.5 A/dm<sup>2</sup> for about 300 seconds to form a 3 g/m<sup>2</sup>
anodized film and rinsed. Thereafter, it was post-treated
with an aqueous solution of sodium bicarbonate having a
concentration of 20 g/l at a solution temperature of 40°C
for 30 seconds, rinsed with 20°C water for 120 seconds and
dried. The obtained substrate was. immersed in a 5 % 
aqueous solution of citric acid for 60 seconds, rinsed and
dried at 40°C to produce a comparative substrate 2.</p>
    <p num="0377">The shapes of the roughened surfaces and the physical
property values of the hydrophilic films of the aluminum
substrates obtained in the above production examples are
shown in Table 2. The methods for measuring each of the
physical property values are as follows. The method of
measuring density is described above.</p>
    <heading>&lt;methods of measuring the average opening diameter of large
undulations, the average opening diameter of small pits,
the ratio of average depth of small pits to average opening
diameter of small pits&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0378">The above values were measured by taking a SEM
photomicrograph of the surface of an aluminum substrate.
The average opening diameter d<sub>2</sub> (µm) of large undulations
was obtained by measuring the long diameter and short
diameter of each undulation whose outline could be clearly
recognized from a 1000X SEM photomicrograph, averaging the
measurement values as the opening diameter of each
undulation and dividing the total of opening diameters of
large undulations measured in the SEM photomicrograph by
the number of measured large undulations (50). SEM was the
T-20 of JEOL Ltd.</p>
    <p num="0379">The average opening diameter d<sub>1</sub> (µm) of small pits was 
measured by the same technique as used for measuring the
opening diameters of large undulations using a 30000X SEM
photomicrograph. SEM used in this case was the S-900 of
Hitachi, Ltd.</p>
    <p num="0380">The ratio h/d<sub>1</sub> of the average depth h (µm) of small
pits to the average opening diameter d<sub>1</sub> (µm) of small pits
was obtained by averaging 50 measurement values obtained by
using a 30000X SEM photomicrograph of the section of each
pit.</p>
    <heading>&lt;method of measuring thermal conductivity in film thickness
direction of hydrophilic film&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0381">First, two aluminum substrates which differed only in
the thickness of a hydrophilic film from each of the
aluminum substrates 1 to 20 of the present invention and
the comparative substrates 1 and 2 were prepared in
addition to the aluminum substrates 1 to 20 of the present
invention and the comparative substrates 1 and 2. The
aluminum substrates that differed only in the film
thickness were produced in the same manner as the aluminum
substrates shown in production examples except that the
anodizing time was 0.5 time and 2 times the anodizing time
of each of the aluminum substrates 1 to 20 of the present
invention and the comparative substrates 1 and 2.</p>
    <p num="0382">Three different aluminum substrates which differed in 
film thickness were provided for measurement using a device
shown in Fig. 3 to calculate thermal conductivity in the
thickness direction of the hydrophilic film from the above
equation (1). The measurement was made at different 5
points on each sample and the average value of the
measurement data was used.</p>
    <p num="0383">As for the thickness of the hydrophilic film, the
cross section of the hydrophilic film was observed through
the T-20 SEM of JEOL Ltd., the actual film thicknesses at
50 locations were measured, and the average value of the
measurement data was used.</p>
    <heading>&lt;method of measuring pore diameter of micropores in anodic
oxide film&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0384">As for the pore diameter of micropores in the
anodized film, the diameters of pores in the surface layer
and the diameters of pores at a depth of 0.4 µm from the
surface layer were measured. The surface of the anodized
film was observed in the case of the diameters of pores in
the surface layer and the side surface of a cracked portion
generated by bending the anodized aluminum substrate was
observed through a super high-resolution SEM (S-900 of
Hitachi, Ltd.) in the case of the diameters of pores at a
depth of 0.4 µm from the surface layer. Observation was
carried out at a relatively low acceleration voltage of 12 
V and a magnification of 150,000X without an evaporation
treatment for imparting conductivity. The average value of
the measurement data of 50 pores selected at random was
used for both diameters. The standard deviation was ±10 %
or less for both diameters.</p>
    <heading>&lt;method of measuring porosity&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0385">The porosity of the anodized film was obtained from
the following equation.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">Porosity (%) = {1 - (density of anodized film/3.98)} x 100</st32:df>
wherein 3.98 is the density of aluminum oxide according to
Kagaku Binran. <img id="img-01450001" orientation="unknown" wi="127" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="01450001.tif" inline="no" he="232"/></p>
    <heading>&lt;Production Example 1 of polymer fine particles
(thermoplastic polymer fine particles)&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0386">15.0 g of styrene and 20 ml of an aqueous solution
(concentration of 1.48 x 10<sup>-2</sup> mol/l) of polyoxyethylene
nonylphenyl ether (average number of mols of ethylene oxide
added of 10) were added and stirred at 250 rpm and the
inside of the system was substituted by nitrogen gas.
After this solution was made to be at 25°C, 10 ml of an
aqueous solution (concentration of 0.984 x 10<sup>-3</sup> mol/l) of a
cerium (IV) ammonium salt was added. An aqueous solution
of ammonium nitrate (concentration of 58.8 x 10<sup>-3</sup> mol/l)
was added to adjust pH to 1.3 to 1.4. Thereafter, the
solution was stirred for 8 hours. The solids concentration
of the thus obtained polystyrene fine particle dispersion
was 6.7 % and the average particle size of the polystyrene
fine particles was 0.1 µm.</p>
    <heading>&lt;Production Example 2 of polymer fine particles (light-heat
converting agent/color coupler incorporating fine
particles)&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0387">7.5 g of polystyrene (weight average molecular weight
of 10,000), 1.5 g of an infrared-absorbing dye (IR-24), 0.2
g of the Pergascript Blue SRB leuco dye (of Ciba Geigy Co.,
Ltd.), 0.1 g of 4-(p-N-(p-hydroxybenzoyl)aminophenyl)2,6-bis(trichloro)-s-triazine
and 0.1 g of an anionic 
surfactant (Pionin A41C of Takemoto Oil &amp; Fat Co., Ltd.)
were dissolved in 12.0 g of ethyl acetate and 6.0 g of
methyl ethyl ketone as an oil phase component. A solution
obtained by adding 9.6 g of pure water to 25. 4 g of a 4 %
aqueous solution of polyvinyl alcohol (PVA205 of Kuraray
Co., Ltd.) was prepared as a water phase component. The
oil phase component and the water phase component were
mixed together and emulsified by a homogenizer at 15,000
rpm. Thereafter, 20 g of water was added and stirred at
room temperature for 30 minuets and at 40°C for 3 hours to
evaporate ethyl acetate. The solids concentration of the
thus obtained polymer fine particles was 15.0 % and the
average particle size thereof was 0.20 µm.</p>
    <heading>&lt;Production Example 3 of polymer fine particles (polymer
fine particles having a heat-reactive group)&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0388">A fine particle dispersion having a heat-reactive
group was obtained in the same manner as in Production
Example 1 of polymer fine particles except that 15.0 g of
styrene of Production Example 1 of polymer fine particles
was changed to 7.5 g of glycidyl methacrylate and 7.5 g of
butyl methacrylate. The solids concentration of this
solution was 6.7 % and the average particle size of the
fine particles was 0.08 µm.</p>
    <heading>&lt;Production Example 1 of microcapsule (color coupler 
incorporating microcapsules)&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0389">40 g of the Takenate D-110N (an ethyl acetate
solution of polisocyanate manufactured by Takeda Chemical
Industries, Ltd.), 10 g of trimethylolpropane diacrylate,
10 g of a copolymer (molar ratio of 7/3, weight average
molecular weight of 20,000) of allyl methacrylate and butyl
methacrylate, 0.2 g of the Pergascript Blue SRB leuco dye
(of Ciba Geigy Co., Ltd.), 0.1 g of a triazine compound
structural (formula 1) and 0.1 g of Pionin A41C (of
Takemoto Oil &amp; Fat Co., Ltd.) were dissolved in 40 g of
ethyl acetate and 20 g of acetonitrile as an oil phase
component. 120 g of a 4 % aqueous solution of PVA205 (of
Kuraray Co., Ltd.) was prepared as a water phase component.
The oil phase component and the water phase component were
emulsified by a homogenizer at 15,000 rpm. Thereafter, 40
g of water was added and stirred at room temperature for 30
minutes and at 40°C for 3 hours to evaporate ethyl acetate.
The solids concentration of the thus obtained microcapsule
dispersion was 30 % and the average particle size of the
microcapsules was 0.20 µm.</p>
    <heading>&lt;Production Example 2 of microcapsules (light-heat
converting agent incorporating microcapsules)&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0390">Microcapsules were produced in the same manner as in
Production Example 1 of microcapsules except that 4.0 g of 
a light-heat converting agent (IR-24 dye described in this
specification) was added to the oil component in Production
Example 1 of microcapsules. The solids concentration of
the thus obtained microcapsule dispersion was 30 % and the
average particle size of the microcapsules was 0.20 µm.</p>
    <heading>&lt;Production Example 4 of water self-dispersible
hydrophobilized resin fine particles (synthesis of acrylic
polymer fine particles)&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0391">400 g of methyl ethyl ketone was fed to a 1-liter
four-necked flask equipped with a stirrer, reflux unit,
nitrogen feed pipe, dropping unit and thermometer and
heated up to 80°C. A solution prepared by mixing together
80 g of styrene, 300 g of methyl methacrylate, 24.5 g of
methacrylic acid and 8 g of 2,2'-azobis(isobutyric
acid)dimethyl (V-601, polymerization initiator of Wako Pure
Chemical Industries, Ltd.) well was added dropwise to the
flask in 2 hours. After 8 hours of agitation, 0.5 g of V-601
was added and further stirred for 8 hours to obtain an
acrylic polymer having a dry solids ratio of 50 %, an acid
value of 39.2 and a number average molecular weight of
20,000. 100 g of the above acrylic polymer solution was
neutralized with 2.71 g of triethylamine and water was
added dropwise to the solution while being stirred. The
viscosity of the solution increased gradually and greatly 
reduced after about 150 g of water was added dropwise to
complete phase inversion. After 150 g of water was further
added, the obtained dispersion was heated up to 40°C to
remove an organic solvent and an excess of water under
reduced pressure so as to obtain a water dispersion of
acrylic polymer fine particles having a dry solids ratio of
33.7 % and an average particle size of 0.12 µm.</p>
    <heading>[Examples 1 to 16 and Comparative Examples 1 and 2]</heading>
    <p num="0392">An image recording layer coating solution 1 having
the following composition was applied onto the aluminum
substrate shown in Table 3 so that a dry coating amount
becomes 0.8 g/m<sup>2</sup> and it was dried in an oven at 60°C for
150 seconds.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">(image recording layer coating solution 1)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">polymer fine particles of Production Example 1 in terms of solid content</entry><entry align="left">5 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">polyacrylic acid (weight average molecular weight of 25,000)</entry><entry align="left">0.5 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">light-heat converting agent (IR-11 in this specification)</entry><entry align="left">0.3 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">water</entry><entry align="left">100 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0393">The thus obtained lithographic printing original
plate that affords on-press development was exposed by 
using the Trendsetter 3244 VFS at a outer drum revolution
of 210 rpm, a plate surface energy of 200 mJ/cm<sup>2</sup> and a
resolution of 2,400 dpi, the plate was attached to the
plate cylinder of the SOR-M printer of Hidelberg Co., Ltd.
without a development, and after supplying a damping
solution, ink and then paper were fed to execute the
printing. On-press development and printing were possible
with all the printing plates without a problem and the
printing results obtained with the printing plates are
shown in Table 3.</p>
    <heading>&lt;evaluation of lithographic printing plate&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0394">
      <sl>
        <li>(1) The term "the number of sheets printed until complete
on-press development" refers to the number of paper sheets
printed until a complete on-press development was attained,
which indicates the difficulty of the on-press development.</li>
        <li>(2) stain-resistance after non-usage period</li>
      </sl>
    </p>
    <p num="0395">The term "the number of sheets printed until stain-free
printing" refers to the number of paper sheets printed
until a clean, stain-free sheet is obtained upon resuming
the printing after stopping the printer upon printing
10,000 sheets and leaving the printer at room temperature
for 1 hour, with the printing plate being kept attached to
the plate cylinder as it is. It indicates a stain
resistance of the printing plate. <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1">Table 3 Printing results of Examples 1 to 20 and Comparative Examples 1 and 2</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Used substrate</entry><entry align="center">Number of printed sheets (unit: 10,000 sheets)</entry><entry align="center">Number of sheets printed until complete on-press development</entry><entry align="center">Number of sheets printed until stain-free printing</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 1</entry><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 2</entry><entry align="left">2</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 3</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 4</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 5</entry><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 6</entry><entry align="left">6</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 7</entry><entry align="left">7</entry><entry align="center">1.9</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 8</entry><entry align="left">8</entry><entry align="center">1.2</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 9</entry><entry align="left">9</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 10</entry><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 11</entry><entry align="left">11</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 12</entry><entry align="left">12</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 13</entry><entry align="left">13</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 14</entry><entry align="left">14</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 15</entry><entry align="left">15</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 16</entry><entry align="left">16</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 17</entry><entry align="left">17</entry><entry align="center">1.2</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 18</entry><entry align="left">18</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 19</entry><entry align="left">16</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 20</entry><entry align="left">20</entry><entry align="center">1.2</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 1</entry><entry align="left">Comparative Example 1</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">70</entry><entry align="center">130</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 2</entry><entry align="left">Comparative Example 2</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <heading>[Examples 21 to 40 and Comparative Examples 3 and 4]</heading>
    <p num="0396">An image recording layer coating solution 2 having
the following composition was applied onto the aluminum
substrate shown in Table 4 so that a dry coating amount
becomes 0.8 g/m<sup>2</sup> and it was dried in an oven at 60°C for 
150 seconds. Then, the thus obtained original forme for a
lithographic printing plate was exposed and used for
printing in the same manner as in Example 1 and the
obtained printing results are shown in Table 4.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">(image recording layer coating solution 2)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">polymer fine particles of Production Example 2 in terms of solid content</entry><entry align="left">5 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">water</entry><entry align="left">100 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables> <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1">Table 4 Printing results of Examples 21 to 40 and Comparative Examples 3 and 4</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Used substrate</entry><entry align="center">Number of printed sheets (unit: 10,000 sheets)</entry><entry align="center">Number of sheets printed until complete on-press development</entry><entry align="center">Number of sheets printed until stain-free printing</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 21</entry><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 22</entry><entry align="left">2</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 23</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 24</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 25</entry><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 26</entry><entry align="left">6</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 27</entry><entry align="left">7</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">60</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 28</entry><entry align="left">8</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">50</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 29</entry><entry align="left">9</entry><entry align="center">1.7</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 30</entry><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="center">1.9</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 31</entry><entry align="left">11</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 32</entry><entry align="left">12</entry><entry align="center">2.2</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 33</entry><entry align="left">13</entry><entry align="center">2.6</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 34</entry><entry align="left">14</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">40</entry><entry align="center">45</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 35</entry><entry align="left">15</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 36</entry><entry align="left">16</entry><entry align="center">1.6</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">45</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 37</entry><entry align="left">17</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 38</entry><entry align="left">18</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 39</entry><entry align="left">16</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 40</entry><entry align="left">20</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 3</entry><entry align="left">Comparative Example 1</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">120</entry><entry align="center">100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 4</entry><entry align="left">Comparative Example 2</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <heading>[Examples 41 to 60 and Comparative Examples 5 and 6]</heading>
    <p num="0397">An image recording layer coating solution 3 having
the following composition was applied onto the aluminum
substrate shown in Table 5 so that a dry coating amount
becomes 0.8 g/m<sup>2</sup> and it was dried in an oven at 60°C for 
150 seconds. Then, the thus obtained original forme for a
lithographic printing plate was exposed and used for
printing in the same manner as in Example 1 and the
obtained printing results are shown in Table 5.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">(image recording layer coating solution 3)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">polymer fine particles in Production Example 3 in terms of solid content</entry><entry align="left">5 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">polyacrylic acid (weight average molecular weight of 25,000)</entry><entry align="left">0.5 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">light-heat converting agent (IR-11 in this specification)</entry><entry align="left">0.3 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">water</entry><entry align="left">100 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1">Table 5 Printing results of Examples 41 to 60 and Comparative Examples 5 and 6</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Used substrate</entry><entry align="center">Number of printed sheets (unit: 10,000 sheets)</entry><entry align="center">Number of sheets printed until complete on-press development</entry><entry align="center">Number of sheets printed until stain-free printing</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 41</entry><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 42</entry><entry align="left">2</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 43</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">22</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 44</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 45</entry><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">23</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 46</entry><entry align="left">6</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 47</entry><entry align="left">7</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 48</entry><entry align="left">8</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">35</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 49</entry><entry align="left">9</entry><entry align="center">2.2</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 50</entry><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="center">2.4</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 51</entry><entry align="left">11</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 52</entry><entry align="left">12</entry><entry align="center">2.8</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 53</entry><entry align="left">13</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 54</entry><entry align="left">14</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">37</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 55</entry><entry align="left">15</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 56</entry><entry align="left">16</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">33</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 57</entry><entry align="left">17</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 58</entry><entry align="left">18</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 59</entry><entry align="left">16</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 60</entry><entry align="left">20</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 5</entry><entry align="left">Comparative Example 1</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry><entry align="center">70</entry><entry align="center">70</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 6</entry><entry align="left">Comparative Example 2</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <heading>[Examples 61 to 80 and Comparative Examples 7 and 8]</heading>
    <p num="0398">The following image recording layer coating solution
4 containing the microcapsules was used to form an image
recording layer on the substrates shown in Table 6. The
image recording layer was dried in an oven at 100°C for 60 
seconds and the dry coating amount was 0.7 g/m<sup>2</sup>.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">(image recording layer coating solution 4)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">microcapsules in Production Example 1</entry><entry align="left">5g in terms of solid content</entry></row><row><entry align="left">trimethylolpropane triacrylate</entry><entry align="left">3 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">infrared-absorbing dye (IR-11 in this specification)</entry><entry align="left">0.3 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">water</entry><entry align="left">60 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1-methoxy-2-propanol</entry><entry align="left">40 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0399">The thus obtained original forme for a lithographic
printing plate was exposed by the Luxel T-9000CTP equipped
with a multi-channel laser head of Fuji Photo Film Co., Ltd.
at an output per beam of 250 mW, an outer drum revolution
of 800 rpm and a resolution of 2,400 dpi. Printing was
carried out in the same manner as in Example 1 and the
printing results are shown in Table 6. <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1">Table 6 Printing results of Examples 61 to 80 and Comparative Examples 7 and 8</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Used substrate</entry><entry align="center">Number of printed sheets (unit: 10,000 sheets)</entry><entry align="center">Number of sheets printed until complete on-press development</entry><entry align="center">Number of sheets printed until stain-free printing</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 61</entry><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="center">1.6</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">23</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 62</entry><entry align="left">2</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">24</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 63</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="center">1.6</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 64</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="center">1.6</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">23</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 65</entry><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">23</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 66</entry><entry align="left">6</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 67</entry><entry align="left">7</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 68</entry><entry align="left">8</entry><entry align="center">1.2</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 69</entry><entry align="left">9</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 70</entry><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">18</entry><entry align="center">26</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 71</entry><entry align="left">11</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 72</entry><entry align="left">12</entry><entry align="center">2.2</entry><entry align="center">19</entry><entry align="center">26</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 73</entry><entry align="left">13</entry><entry align="center">2.6</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">26</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 74</entry><entry align="left">14</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">44</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 75</entry><entry align="left">15</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="center">21</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 76</entry><entry align="left">16</entry><entry align="center">1.6</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 77</entry><entry align="left">17</entry><entry align="center">1.6</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">20</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 78</entry><entry align="left">18</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 79</entry><entry align="left">16</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 80</entry><entry align="left">20</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 7</entry><entry align="left">Comparative Example 1</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">80</entry><entry align="center">130</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 8</entry><entry align="left">Comparative Example 2</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <heading>[Examples 81 to 100 and Comparative Examples 9 and 10]</heading>
    <p num="0400">The following image recording layer coating solution
5 containing the microcapsules obtained in Production
Example 2 of microcapsules was used to form an image
recording layer on the substrates shown in Table 7. The 
image recording layer was dried in an oven at 100°C for 60
seconds and the dry coating amount was 0.7 g/m<sup>2</sup>. The thus
obtained original forme for a lithographic printing plate
was exposed in the same manner as in Example 1 and used for
printing. The printing results are shown in Table 7.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">(image recording layer coating solution 5)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">microcapsules in Production Example 2</entry><entry align="left">5g interms of solid content</entry></row><row><entry align="left">water</entry><entry align="left">60 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1">Table 7 Printing results of Examples 81 to 100 and Comparative Examples 9 and 10</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Used substrate</entry><entry align="center">Number of printed sheets (unit: 10,000 sheets)</entry><entry align="center">Number of sheets printed until complete on-press development</entry><entry align="center">Number of sheets printed until stain-free printing</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 81</entry><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 82</entry><entry align="left">2</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 83</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">22</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 84</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 85</entry><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry><entry align="center">23</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 86</entry><entry align="left">6</entry><entry align="center">2.2</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 87</entry><entry align="left">7</entry><entry align="center">3.5</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 88</entry><entry align="left">8</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">35</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 89</entry><entry align="left">9</entry><entry align="center">2.7</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 90</entry><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="center">2.9</entry><entry align="center">18</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 91</entry><entry align="left">11</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 92</entry><entry align="left">12</entry><entry align="center">3.3</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 93</entry><entry align="left">13</entry><entry align="center">3.5</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 94</entry><entry align="left">14</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">37</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 95</entry><entry align="left">15</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 96</entry><entry align="left">16</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">33</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 97</entry><entry align="left">17</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">35</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 98</entry><entry align="left">18</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 99</entry><entry align="left">16</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">35</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 100</entry><entry align="left">20</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 9</entry><entry align="left">Comparative Example 1</entry><entry align="center">3.4</entry><entry align="center">70</entry><entry align="center">70</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 10</entry><entry align="left">Comparative Example 2</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <heading>[Examples 101 to 120 (thermal positive type image recording
layer) and Comparative Examples 11 and 12]</heading>
    <p num="0401">An undercoating solution having the following
composition was applied to the substrates (supports) shown
in Table 8 and dried at 80°C for 15 seconds to form coating
films. The coating amount of the dried coating film was 10 
mg/m<sup>2</sup>. The thus obtained original formes for lithographic
printing plates were exposed under the following conditions
and used for printing. The printing results are shown in
Table 8.</p>
    <heading>&lt;composition of undercoating solution&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0402">
      <ul list-style="bullet">
        <li>following polymer compound   0.2 g</li>
        <li>methanol   100 g</li>
        <li>water   1 g</li>
      </ul>
      <img id="img-01610001" orientation="unknown" wi="147" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01610001.tif" inline="no" he="55"/>
    </p>
    <p num="0403">Further, a coating solution for a heat-sensitive
layer having the following composition was prepared and
applied to an undercoated support for a lithographic
printing plate so that a coating amount after drying (heat-sensitive
layer coating amount) becomes 1.7 g/m<sup>2</sup> and dried
to form a heat-sensitive layer (thermal positive type image
recording layer) so as to obtain an original forme for a
lithographic printing plate.</p>
    <heading>&lt;composition of coating solution for the heat-sensitive 
layer&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0404"><ul list-style="bullet"><li>novolak resin (m-cresol/p-cresol = 60/40, weight average
molecular weight of 7,000, containing 0.5 wt% of unreacted
cresol)   1.0 g</li><li>cyanine dye A represented by the following structural
formula
0.1 g</li><li>tetrahydrophthalic anhydride   0.05
g</li><li>p-toluenesulfonic acid   0.002
g</li><li>ethyl violet having 6-hydroxy-β-naphthalenesulfonic acid
as a counter ion   0.02
g</li><li>fluorine-based surfactant (Megaface F-177 of Dainippon
Ink and Chemicals, Inc.)
   0.05 g</li><li>methyl ethyl ketone   12 g</li></ul><img id="img-01620001" orientation="unknown" wi="121" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01620001.tif" inline="no" he="56"/> 
exposure and development</p>
    <p num="0405">The thermal positive type image recording layer on
each original forme for a lithographic printing plate
obtained above was exposed and developed by the following
methods to obtain a lithographic printing plate.</p>
    <p num="0406">The original forme for a lithographic printing plate
was exposed by the Trendsetter 3244 equipped with a
semiconductor laser having an output of 500 mW, a
wavelength of 830 nm and a beam diameter of 17 µm (1/e<sup>2</sup>) of
CREO Co., Ltd. at a main scanning speed of 5 m/sec and a
plate surface energy amount of 50 mJ/cm<sup>2</sup>.</p>
    <p num="0407">Thereafter, the original forme was developed with an
alkali developer prepared by adding 1 g of
C<sub>12</sub>H<sub>25</sub>N(CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>COONa)<sub>2</sub> to 1 liter of an aqueous solution
containing 5.0 wt% of a potassium salt consisting of D-Sorbit/potassium
oxide K<sub>2</sub>O which is a combination of a
nonreducing sugar and a base and 0.015 wt% of Olfine AK-02
(of Nisshin Chemical Industry., Ltd.). Development was
carried out with the PS900NP automatic developer filled
with the above alkali developer (of Fuji Photo Film Co.,
Ltd.) at a development temperature of 25°C for 12 seconds.
After development, the plate was rinsed and treated with
gum (FP-2W (1:1)) or the like to obtain a lithographic
printing plate in which prepress processing was completed. </p>
    <heading>&lt;evaluation of lithographic printing plate &gt;</heading>
    <p num="0408">The stain resistance, stain-resistance after non-usage
period, press life and appearance after the
application of a damping solution of the obtained
lithographic printing plate were evaluated by the following
methods.</p>
    <heading>(3) stain resistance</heading>
    <p num="0409">Printing was performed using DIC-GEOS (s) red ink by
the Mitsubish Dia type F2 printer (of Mitsubishi Heavy
Industries, Ltd.) to print 10,000 sheets. Then, the stain
of a blanket after printing was evaluated with the eyes.</p>
    <p num="0410">The evaluation results are shown in Table 8. Stain
resistance was evaluated in 10 levels according to a degree
of the stain of the blanket. The larger the figure, the
more superior the stain resistance is.</p>
    <heading>(4) press life</heading>
    <p num="0411">Printing was performed using DIC-GEOS (N) black ink
of Dainippon Ink and Chemicals, Inc. by the Risron printer
of Komori Corporation and the press life was evaluated by
means of obtaining the number of printed sheets at which it
was confirmed visually that the density of a solid image
began to decrease.</p>
    <p num="0412">The results are shown in Table 8. <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1">Table 8 Printing results of Examples 101 to 120 and Comparative Examples 11 and 12</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Used substrate</entry><entry align="center">stain resistance</entry><entry align="center">Number of sheets printed until stain-free printing</entry><entry align="center">Number of printed sheets</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 101</entry><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">4.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 102</entry><entry align="left">2</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">4.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 103</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">4.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 104</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">18</entry><entry align="center">4.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 105</entry><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">18</entry><entry align="center">4.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 106</entry><entry align="left">6</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">18</entry><entry align="center">5.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 107</entry><entry align="left">7</entry><entry align="center">9</entry><entry align="center">22</entry><entry align="center">4.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 108</entry><entry align="left">8</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">23</entry><entry align="center">4.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 109</entry><entry align="left">9</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">19</entry><entry align="center">4.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 110</entry><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">21</entry><entry align="center">4.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 111</entry><entry align="left">11</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">21</entry><entry align="center">4.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 112</entry><entry align="left">12</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">21</entry><entry align="center">4.6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 113</entry><entry align="left">13</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">4.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 114</entry><entry align="left">14</entry><entry align="center">9</entry><entry align="center">22</entry><entry align="center">4.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 115</entry><entry align="left">15</entry><entry align="center">9</entry><entry align="center">21</entry><entry align="center">4.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 116</entry><entry align="left">16</entry><entry align="center">9</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">4.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 117</entry><entry align="left">17</entry><entry align="center">9</entry><entry align="center">24</entry><entry align="center">4.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 118</entry><entry align="left">18</entry><entry align="center">9</entry><entry align="center">24</entry><entry align="center">4.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 119</entry><entry align="left">16</entry><entry align="center">8</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">5.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 120</entry><entry align="left">20</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">4.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 11</entry><entry align="left">Comparative Example 1</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">4.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 12</entry><entry align="left">Comparative Example 2</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">40</entry><entry align="center">4.5</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <heading>[Example 121]</heading>
    <p num="0413">An image recording layer coating solution having the
following composition was applied to the substrate 20 of
the present invention obtained above and dried in an oven
at 60°C for 150 seconds to obtain the original forme for a
lithographic printing plate of Example 121. The dry 
coating amount of the image recording layer coating
solution was 3.0 g/m<sup>2</sup>.</p>
    <heading>(image recording layer coating solution 6)</heading>
    <p num="0414">
      <ul list-style="bullet">
        <li>sol-gel prepared solution   7.0 g
(a prepared mixture of 9.2 g of tetramethoxysilane, 16.2 g
of ethanol, 10.2 g of deionized water and an aqueous
solution of nitric acid having a concentration of 0.1
mol/l)</li>
        <li>20 % aqueous solution of colloidal silica (average
particle size of 20 nm)   4.0 g</li>
        <li>water self-dispersible hydrophobilized resin fine
particles described in Production Example 4 (aqueous
solution having a dry solids ratio of 11 %)
   10.0 g</li>
        <li>1.5 % aqueous solution of a light-heat converting agent
(IR having the following structure)   10.0 g</li>
        <li>deionized water   5 g</li>
      </ul>
      <img id="img-01660001" orientation="unknown" wi="128" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01660001.tif" inline="no" he="49"/>
    </p>
    <p num="0415">Printing was directly carried out in the same manner 
as in Example 1 without development. As for the printing
quality of the printed sheet, the obtained print was clear
and free from scumming, and press life was excellent with
over 20,000 or more sheets printed.</p>
    <p num="0416">According to the present invention, there is provided
an original forme for a lithographic printing plate which
can be mounted directly to a printer for printing without
performing a development thereon after exposure by scanning
with infrared ray based on a digital signal, which is used
for a heat-sensitive lithographic printing plate and
exhibits not only excellent on-press developability, high
sensitivity and a long press life, but also superior stain
resistance and ink removal during the printing. Also,
there is provided an original forme for a lithographic
printing plate which comprises a conventional thermal type
heat-sensitive layer and is developed after exposure to
infrared ray, which is used for a heat-sensitive
lithographic printing plate and exhibits not only high
sensitivity and a long press life but also superior stain
resistance and ink removal during the printing.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A support for a lithographic printing plate, which
comprises a hydrophilic film formed on a metallic base
whose surface has been roughened, said hydrophilic film
having a heat conductivity of 0.05 - 0.5 W/(m·K) in the
direction of its film thickness.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A support for a lithographic printing plate
according to claim 1, wherein the film thickness of said
hydrophilic film is 0.1 - 5 µm.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>An original forme for a lithographic printing
plate, which comprises a recording layer formed on said
support for a lithographic printing plate as set forth in
claim 1 or 2, said recording layer being writable by
exposure with infrared laser.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>An original forme for a lithographic printing
plate, comprising a recording layer which is writable by
exposure with infrared laser and which is formed on a
support for a lithographic printing plate, said support
being subjected to electrochemical roughening treatment
with an aqueous solution containing hydrochloric acid and
including a hydrophilic film having a heat conductivity of
0.05 - 0.5 W/(m·K).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>An original forme for a lithographic printing
plate, comprising a recording layer which is writable by
exposure with infrared laser and which is formed on a
support for a lithographic printing plate, said support
being subjected to electrochemical roughening treatment
with an aqueous solution containing hydrochloric acid and
including a hydrophilic film having a density of 1000 -
3200 kg/m3 and/or a porosity of 20-70%.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>An original forme for a lithographic printing
plate, comprising a recording layer which is writable by
exposure with infrared laser and which is formed on a
support for a lithographic printing plate having a
hydrophilic film, said hydrophilic film having a mean
opening diameter of roughened small pits of 0.01-3 µm, a
ratio of mean depth to mean opening diameter of the
roughened small pits of 0.1 - 0.5, and a heat conductivity
of 0.05 - 0.5 W/(m·K).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>An original forme for a lithographic printing
plate, comprising a recording layer which is writable by
exposure with infrared laser and which is formed on a
support for a lithographic printing plate having a
hydrophilic film, said hydrophilic film having a mean
opening diameter of roughened small pits of 0.01 - 3 µm, a
ratio of mean depth to mean opening diameter of the
roughened small pits of 0.1 - 0.5, and a density of 1000-3200
kg/m3 and/or a porosity of 20 - 70%.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>An original forme for a lithographic printing
plate according to any one of claims 4 to 7, wherein the
mean opening diameter of large undulation of said support
for a lithographic printing plate is 3 - 20 µm.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>An original forme for a lithographic printing
plate according to any one of claims 4 to 8, wherein said
hydrophilic film is an anodic oxide film.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>An original forme for a lithographic printing
plate according to claim 9, wherein the amount of said
anodic oxide film formed is 3.2 g/m2 or more than 3.2 g/m2.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>An original forme for a lithographic printing
plate according to claim 9 or 10, wherein the pore diameter
on the surface layer of said anodic oxide film is 40 nm or
less than 40 nm.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>An original forme for a lithographic printing
plate according to any one of claims 9 to 11, wherein said
anodic oxide film is pore-sealed.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>An original forme for a lithographic printing
plate according to any one of claims 9 to 12, wherein a
layer of particles having a mean particle size of 8 - 800
nm is formed on said anodic oxide film.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>An original forme for a lithographic printing
plate according to any one of claims 9 to 13, wherein said
anodic oxide film is formed by anodic oxidation that
consists of more than two steps.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>An original forme for a lithographic printing
plate according to claim 14, wherein the anodic oxidation
is performed with an electrolyte containing sulfuric acid
in the first step and then with an electrolyte containing
phosphoric acid in the second and subsequent steps.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>An original forme for a lithographic printing
plate according to any one of claims 3 to 15, wherein said
recording layer is a heat-sensitive layer containing one
of: (a) fine polymer particles having a heat reactive
functional group; and (b) microcapsuls including a compound
having heat reactive functional group.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>A plate-making and printing method for a
lithographic printing plate, wherein said original forme
for a lithographic printing plate as set forth in any one
of claims 3 to 16 is printable by one of: exposing it to a
laser beam and then directly mounting it to a printing
machine; and directly exposing it to a laser beam after
mounting it to a printing machine.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
