<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1246022-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1246022" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="26612884" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021002">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1246022-A2" status="new" fvid="23562057">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1246022</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021002</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02252368-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02252368</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020402</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001102017-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001102017</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010330</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001183101-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001183101</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010618</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C01G  23/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C01G  23/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C01G  23/07        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C09C   1/36        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C09C   1/36        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03G   9/097       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03G   9/097       20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">C01G  23/00</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">C01G  23/07</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09C   1/36</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09C   1/36D6</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G03G   9/097B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G03G   9/097B3</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M01P4:51</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M01P4:64</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M01P6:12</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M01P6:80</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">Y01N6:00</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Entwickler für elektrostatische Bilder</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Electrostatic image developer</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Révélateur d'images électrostatiques</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SHINETSU CHEMICAL CO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SHIN-ETSU CHEMICAL CO., LTD.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>SHIN-ETSU CHEMICAL CO., LTD.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>6-1, Ohtemachi 2-chome</street>
              <city>Chiyoda-ku Tokyo</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KONYA YOSHIHARU</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>UENO SUSUMU</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>WATANABE KOICHIRO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KONYA, YOSHIHARU</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>UENO, SUSUMU</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>WATANABE, KOICHIRO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Konya, Yoshiharu, Gunma Complex</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Shin-Etsu Chemical Co., Ltd., 2-13-1, Isobe</street>
              <city>Annaka-shi, Gunma-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Ueno, Susumu, c/o Gunma Complex</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Shin-Etsu Chemical Co., Ltd., 2-13-1, Isobe</street>
              <city>Annaka-shi, Gunma-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Watanabe, Koichiro, c/o Gunma Complex</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Shin-Etsu Chemical Co., Ltd., 2-13-1, Isobe</street>
              <city>Annaka-shi, Gunma-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Stoner, Gerard Patrick</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>MEWBURN ELLIS York House 23 Kingsway</street>
              <city>London WC2B 6HP</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>By atomizing a siloxane and an organic titanium
compound for flame combustion, spherical complex oxide fine
particles of amorphous silica-titania are obtained having a
particle size of 10-300 nm, a specific surface area of
20-100 m<sup>2</sup>/g, and a titania content of 1-99% by weight. By
hydrophobizing the fine particles and adding them to a
toner, a developer is obtained which is improved in
fluidity, cleanability and uniform and stable charging.</p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">This invention relates to a developer for developing
electrostatic images in electrophotography and electrostatic
recording process.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BACKGROUND</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0002">Dry developers used in electrophotography and similar
processes are generally divided into a one-component
developer using a toner having a colorant dispersed in a
binder resin alone and a two-component developer using the
toner in admixture with a carrier. When these developers
are used in copying operation, the developers must satisfy
many factors such as fluidity, anti-caking, fixation,
charging ability and cleanability in order that they adapt
to the process.</p>
    <p num="0003">For the purpose of improving the fluidity,
anti-caking, fixation and cleanability, and adjusting and
stabilizing the charging ability, inorganic fine particles
of silica, titania, alumina, etc. having a smaller particle
size than the toner particles are often added as the
external additive.</p>
    <p num="0004">As the copying speed is accelerated in the recent
years, the developer is required to have more fluidity,
cleanability, and stable and uniform charging ability. To
produce images of better quality, the toner has shifted to a
small particle size one. As compared with conventional
toners commonly used in the art, the small particle size
toner is poor in powder flow and its charging ability is
readily altered by additives such as external additive.
Then, depending on the type and particle size of inorganic
fine particles such as silica fine particles added to the
toner, the small particle size toner does not necessarily
promise satisfactory results with respect to fluidity, 
charging ability and cleanability. A choice of the
inorganic fine particles added thereto is important.
Commonly used silica fine particles, whose mean particle
size of primary particles is as small as 10 to 20 nm, are
highly cohesive to each other and poorly dispersible,
failing to meet the requirements of fluidity and
cleanability. Using spherical silica fine particles is
effective in improving fluidity and increasing the charge
quantity, but due to an excessive charge quantity, the
electrostatic adhesive force of fine particles to the toner
support becomes stronger, resulting in a lowering of
development, a lower image density and density variations.
The silica fine particles used sometimes contain impurities,
which affect the charging ability of the developer.</p>
    <p num="0005">On the other hand, titania fine particles having a low
charging ability are further added for the purpose of
controlling the charge quantity. However, crystalline
titania fine particles used in the art are poor in fluidity
and dispersibility due to their non-spherical shape. If a
certain amount of crystalline titania fine particles are
added for adjusting the charge quantity, they aggravate
fluidity and dispersion, which are likely to incur
liberation of the developer from the toner support,
resulting in images being fogged (background staining). A
compromise approach is to provide for fluidity by taking
advantage of spherical silica fine particles and to adjust
the charge quantity by blending silica fine particles with
titania fine particles. In order that these functions be
exerted in a satisfactory and consistent manner, the silica
and titania fine particles must be intimately and completely
mixed in a predetermined mixing proportion. However,
complete mixing of fine particles is difficult, and such
mixing is frequently accompanied with segregation and local
variation of charging ability. </p>
    <p num="0006">An object of the invention is to provide an
electrostatic image developer having good fluidity and
cleanability as well as a stable charging ability.</p>
    <p num="0007">We have found that when spherical complex oxide fine
particles of amorphous silica-titania obtained by atomizing
a siloxane and an organic titanium compound in a flame for
combustion, having a particle size of 10 to 300 nm, a
specific surface area of 20 to 100 m<sup>2</sup>/g, and a titania
content of 1 to 99% by weight are added as inorganic fine
particles to toner particles, there is obtained an
electrostatic image developer which exhibits smooth flow,
effective cleaning and uniform and stable charging
performance. As used herein, silica is silicon oxide and
titania is titanium oxide.</p>
    <p num="0008">Accordingly, the invention provides an electrostatic
image developer comprising spherical complex oxide fine
particles of amorphous silica-titania obtained by atomizing
a siloxane and an organic titanium compound in a flame for
combustion, having a particle size of 10 to 300 nm, a
specific surface area of 20 to 100 m<sup>2</sup>/g, and a titania
content of 1 to 99% by weight.</p>
    <p num="0009">Preferably, the complex oxide fine particles are
substantially free of chlorine. The organic titanium
compound is typically selected from among a
tetraalkoxytitanium compound, titanium acylate compound,
alkyltitanium compound and titanium chelate compound.</p>
    <p num="0010">In one preferred embodiment, the complex oxide fine
particles have been prepared by simultaneously atomizing the
siloxane and the organic titanium compound into a flame for
oxidative combustion, in which method, based on the
siloxane, the organic titanium compound, a combustion-assisting
gas and a combustion-supporting gas fed to a
burner, the siloxane, the organic titanium compound and the
combustion-assisting gas when burned have an adiabatic flame
temperature within a range of 1,650°C to 4,000°C. </p>
    <p num="0011">The complex oxide fine particles are preferably
hydrophobized fine particles having introduced at their
surface units represented by the following formula (1):
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/">R<sup>1</sup> <sub>x</sub>R<sup>2</sup> <sub>y</sub>R<sup>3</sup> <sub>z</sub>SiO<sub>(4-x-y-z)/2</sub></st32:che>
wherein R<sup>1</sup>, R<sup>2</sup> and R<sup>3</sup> each are independently a substituted or
unsubstituted monovalent hydrocarbon group having 1 to 6
carbon atoms, x, y and z each are an integer of 0 to 3,
x+y+z is from 1 to 3.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0012">The electrostatic image developer of the invention is
arrived at by adding spherical complex oxide fine particles
of silica-titania to toner particles.</p>
    <p num="0013">The toner used herein may be any of well-known toners
primarily comprising a binder resin and a colorant. If
necessary, a charge controlling agent may be added to the
toner. Examples of the binder resin used in the toner
include homopolymers and copolymers of styrenes such as
styrene, chlorostyrene and vinylstyrene, monoolefins such as
ethylene, propylene, butylene and isobutylene, vinyl esters
such as vinyl acetate, vinyl propionate, vinyl benzoate and
vinyl lactate, acrylates and methacrylates such as methyl
acrylate, ethyl acrylate, butyl acrylate, dodecyl acrylate,
octyl acrylate, phenyl acrylate, methyl methacrylate, ethyl
methacrylate, butyl methacrylate and dodecyl methacrylate,
vinyl ethers such as vinyl methyl ether, vinyl ethyl ether
and vinyl butyl ether, and ketones such as vinyl methyl
ketone, vinyl hexyl ketone, vinyl isopropenyl ketone and
vinyl ketone, though the resin is not limited thereto.
Typical binder resins are polystyrene, styrene-alkyl
acrylate copolymers, styrene-acrylonitrile copolymers,
styrene-butadiene copolymers, styrene-maleic anhydride
copolymers, polyethylene and polypropylene. Besides,
polyesters, polyurethanes, epoxy resins, silicone resins,
polyamides, modified rosin, paraffin and wax are also
useful. </p>
    <p num="0014">The colorant used in the toner is not critical.
Typical colorants include carbon black, Nigrosine dyes,
Aniline Blue, Chalcoyl Blue, Chrome Yellow, Ultramarine
Blue, Dupont Oil Red, Quinoline Yellow, Methylene Blue
chloride, Phthalocyanine Blue, Malachite Green oxalate, Lamp
Black, and Rose Bengale. Another useful toner powder is a
magnetic toner powder having a magnetic material
incorporated therein.</p>
    <p num="0015">The spherical complex oxide fine particles of silica-titania
are obtained by simultaneously atomizing a siloxane
and an organic titanium compound in a flame for oxidative
combustion.</p>
    <p num="0016">The siloxane used herein is typically a halogen-free
organopolysiloxane which is selected, for example, from
among linear organosiloxanes having the following general
formula (2):
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/">(R<sup>4</sup>)<sub>3</sub>SiO[SiR<sup>5</sup>R<sup>6</sup>O]<sub>m</sub>Si(R<sup>4</sup>)<sub>3</sub></st32:che>
wherein each of R<sup>4</sup>, R<sup>5</sup> and R<sup>6</sup> which may be the same or
different is a monovalent hydrocarbon group, alkoxy or
hydrogen, and m is an integer inclusive of 0, cyclic
organosiloxanes having the following general formula (3):
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/">[SiR<sup>5</sup>R<sup>6</sup>O]<sub>n</sub></st32:che>
wherein R<sup>5</sup> and R<sup>6</sup> are as defined above and n is an integer of
at least 3, and mixtures thereof.</p>
    <p num="0017">The monovalent hydrocarbon groups represented by R<sup>4</sup>-R<sup>6</sup>
include C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub> alkyl groups, alkenyl groups such as vinyl, and
phenyl groups. Of these, lower alkyl groups such as methyl,
ethyl and propyl are preferable, with methyl being most
preferred. The alkoxy groups represented by R<sup>4</sup>-R<sup>6</sup> are those
of 1 to 6 carbon atoms, such as methoxy and ethoxy, with
methoxy being most preferred. The letter m is an integer of
m ≥ 0, preferably 0 to 100, and more preferably 0 to 10; and
n is an integer of n ≥ 3, preferably 3 to 10, and more
preferably 3 to 7. </p>
    <p num="0018">Exemplary of the organosiloxane are hexamethyldisiloxane,
octamethyltrisiloxane, octamethylcyclotetrasiloxane,
and decamethylcyclopentasiloxane. These siloxanes
are preferably purified products which are free of halogen
(e.g., chlorine).</p>
    <p num="0019">On the other hand, the organic titanium compound is
usually selected from among tetraalkoxytitanium compounds,
titanium acylate compounds, alkyltitanium compounds and
titanium chelate compounds. Preferably they are
substantially free of chlorine. More illustratively, the
organic titanium compounds used herein include tetraalkoxytitanium
compounds represented by the following general
formula (4):
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/">Ti(OR<sup>7</sup>)<sub>4</sub></st32:che>
wherein OR<sup>7</sup> is an alkoxy group, preferably C<sub>1-8</sub> alkoxy such as
methoxy, ethoxy, propoxy, isopropoxy or butoxy,

titanium acylate compounds represented by the following
general formula (5):
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/">Ti(OCOR<sup>8</sup>)<sub>4</sub></st32:che>
wherein COR<sup>8</sup> is an acyl group such as formyl, acetyl,
propionyl, butyryl, valeryl, caproyl, heptanoyl, or
octanoyl,

alkyltitanium compounds represented by the following general
formula (6):
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/">TiR<sup>9</sup> <sub>4</sub></st32:che>
wherein R<sup>9</sup> is an alkyl group, preferably C<sub>1-8</sub> alkyl such as
methyl, ethyl, propyl, butyl or pentyl, and

titanium chelate compounds represented by the following
general formula (7) or (8):
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/">(R<sup>10</sup>O)<sub>2</sub>Ti(OR<sup>11</sup>OH)<sub>2</sub></st32:che><st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/">(R<sup>10</sup>O)<sub>2</sub>Ti(OR<sup>11</sup>NH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub></st32:che>
wherein OR<sup>10</sup> is an alkoxy group, preferably C<sub>1-8</sub> alkoxy such
as methoxy, ethoxy, propoxy, isopropoxy or butoxy, R<sup>11</sup> is an 
alkylene group, preferably C<sub>1-8</sub> alkylene such as methylene,
ethylene, trimethylene, tetramethylene or methylethylene.</p>
    <p num="0020">Of the organic titanium compounds, those which are
solid at room temperature are preferably dissolved in
suitable solvents such as siloxanes, alcohols (e.g.,
methanol, ethanol, propanol and butanol) and hydrocarbon
solvents (e.g., toluene and xylene) prior to use. As the
molecular weight of the organic titanium compound increases,
the formation ratio of titanium oxide to the starting
organic titanium compound becomes lower, losing economy.
For these reasons, liquid organic titanium compounds capable
of forming titanium oxide at a formation ratio of at least
0.2 are preferred from the standpoint of economical
efficiency. These organic titanium compounds are preferably
purified products which are free of chlorine. Due to the
substantial absence of impurities and the high purity, they
are best suited as the reactant to form a complex oxide.</p>
    <p num="0021">The siloxane and the organic titanium compound are
mixed in liquid form and fed to a burner or separately fed
to a burner whereby the mixture is atomized from the nozzle
of the burner. In order to impart the shape of silica and
the function of titania combined therewith to the resulting
complex fine particles of silica-titania, the content of
titania should be 1 to 99% by weight, preferably 5 to 95% by
weight. The siloxane and the organic titanium compound are
fed in such amounts that the combustion oxide may have a
stoichiometric ratio giving a titania content within the
range.</p>
    <p num="0022">For the atomization of liquid, an atomizing medium
such as air or steam may be used to assist in atomizing
through the nozzle. If the organic titanium compound used
is a hydrolyzable one, dehumidified, compressed air or
nitrogen may be used as the atomizing medium.</p>
    <p num="0023">Atomization may be carried out either by relying on
the pressure of the liquid itself or by using centrifugal
force. To achieve complete vaporization and pyrolysis for
combustion, the atomized droplets should be very small, 
preferably having a size of up to 100 µm, more preferably up
to 50 µm. To this end, the reactant liquids (siloxane and
organic titanium compound) should preferably have a
viscosity of up to 500 cs, more preferably up to 200 cs at
25° C.</p>
    <p num="0024">The droplets of atomized siloxane and organic titanium
compound are heated by their own combustion flame and by the
auxiliary flame of a combustion-assisting gas, and undergo
oxidative combustion concomitant with evaporation or
pyrolysis. Synthesis of silica from the siloxane and
synthesis of titania from the organic titanium compound
occur simultaneously in the gas phase whereby silica and
titania are fused together, resulting in spherical complex
oxide fine particles of silica-titania.</p>
    <p num="0025">Combustion forms core particles of silica and titania
which coalesce and grow into particles whose ultimate size
and shape are determined by the flame temperature, silica
and titania concentrations, and residence time within the
flame, with the flame temperature being predominant. At a
low flame temperature, the particle size becomes close to 10
nm, which is about the same as that of fumed silica.
Inducing the core particles to mutually collide and grow by
coalescence into larger particles requires that coalescence
and growth take place at a flame temperature which is at or
above the melting point of silica: 1,423°C, and more
preferably at or above the melting point of titania:
1,640°C.</p>
    <p num="0026">The flame temperature is largely affected by the heat
of combustion and the amount of excessive oxygen (air). In
the case of complete combustion, the heat of combustion is
determined by the type and amount of the siloxane, the
organic titanium compound and a combustion-assisting gas.
The siloxane as the silica source provides a substantial
heat of combustion and hence, a high energy efficiency, as
seen from the fact that hexamethyldisiloxane, a linear
siloxane, has a heat of combustion of 1,389 kcal/mol or
8,550 kcal/kg, and octamethylcyclotetrasiloxane, a cyclic 
siloxane, has a heat of combustion of 1,974 kcal/mol or
6,650 kcal/kg. Like the siloxane, the organic titanium
compound also provides a substantial heat of combustion as
seen from the fact that tetraisopropoxytitanium has a heat
of combustion of 1,623 kcal/mol or 5,710 kcal/kg, tetrabutoxysilane
has a heat of combustion of 2,209 kcal/mol or
6,490 kcal/kg, and titanium acetylacetonate (or diisopropoxybisacetylacetonatotitanium)
has a heat of combustion
of 2,112 kcal/mol or 5,800 kcal/kg. Simultaneously burning
the siloxane and the organic titanium compound creates a
combustion flame with high thermal energy efficiency to
promote formation of spherical particles.</p>
    <p num="0027">To keep the combustion of siloxane and organic
titanium compound stable and drive combustion to completion,
an auxiliary flame is formed using a combustion-assisting
gas. The combustion-assisting gas used here is preferably
one which does not leave unburned residues following
combustion. Suitable, non-limiting examples include
hydrogen and hydrocarbon gases such as methane, propane and
butane. However, a large amount of combustion-assisting gas
results in the formation of combustion by-products such as
carbon dioxide and steam, increasing the amount of
combustion exhaust and reducing the silica and titania
concentrations during combustion. Accordingly, the amount
of combustion-assisting gas is typically set at not more
than 2 moles, and preferably from 0.1 to 1.5 moles, per mole
of the starting materials, siloxane and organic titanium
compound combined.</p>
    <p num="0028">Moreover, a combustion-supporting gas is added at the
time of combustion. The combustion-supporting gas may be
any oxygen-containing gas, such as oxygen or air. If the
net amount of oxygen in the gas is insufficient, combustion
of the siloxane, the organic titanium compound and the
combustible gas used in the auxiliary flame (combustion-assisting
gas) is incomplete, leaving carbon residues in the
finished product. On the other hand, if a greater than
stoichiometric amount of combustion-supporting gas is used, 
the silica and titania concentrations within the flame
decrease and the flame temperature falls, which tends to
suppress coalescence and growth of the particles. Supplying
a large excess of the combustion-supporting gas results in
the incomplete combustion of the siloxane and organic
titanium compound, and excessively increases the load on
powder collecting equipment in the exhaust system.
Supplying combustion-supporting gas which contains a
stoichiometric amount of oxygen allows the highest flame
temperature to be achieved, but combustion tends to be
incomplete. A small excess of oxygen is required to achieve
complete combustion. Accordingly, it is advantageous for
the combustion-supporting gas fed from the burner to include
an amount of oxygen which is 1.0 to 4.0 times, and
preferably 1.1 to 3.0 times, the stoichiometric amount of
oxygen required for combustion. In addition to the gas fed
from the burner, the combustion-supporting gas may be
supplemented by by ambient air taken in along the burner.</p>
    <p num="0029">The spherical complex oxide fine particles of silica-titania
according to the invention should have a particle
size of 10 to 300 nm, preferably 20 to 200 nm and a specific
surface area of 20 to 100 m<sup>2</sup>/g, preferably 30 to 90 m<sup>2</sup>/g. If
the particle size is less than 10 nm and the surface area is
more than 100 m<sup>2</sup>/g, then particles are likely to coalesce,
failing to provide the developer with satisfactory flowing,
anti-caking and fixing capabilities. If the particle size
is more than 300 nm and the surface area is less than 20
m<sup>2</sup>/g, then there can occur modification and scraping of the
photoconductor drum and decreased adhesion to the toner.</p>
    <p num="0030">The size of the complex oxide particles formed from
combustion can be adjusted by varying the flame temperature,
silica and titania concentrations and residence time within
the flame. Control of the flame
temperature is achieved in particular by controlling the
adiabatic flame temperature calculated on a basis of the
siloxane, organic titanium compound, combustion-assisting
gas and combustion-supporting gas which are fed to the 
burner. "Adiabatic flame temperature," as used herein,
refers to the highest temperature attained by combustion
products and unburned residue, as an adiabatic system,
through the consumption of heat released by combustion. The
adiabatic flame temperature can be calculated as follows.
Letting the amounts of heat released per hour by combustion
of the siloxane, organic titanium compound and combustion-assisting
gas fed to the burner be respectively Q<sub>1</sub>, Q<sub>2</sub> and Q<sub>3</sub>
(in units of kcal/h), the total heat of combustion Q is
equal to the sum Q<sub>1</sub> + Q<sub>2</sub> + Q<sub>3</sub>.</p>
    <p num="0031">At the same time, letting the amounts of silica,
titania, steam, CO<sub>2</sub>, O<sub>2</sub> and N<sub>2</sub> formed per hour as a product
or by-product of combustion, or remaining unreacted, be
respectively N<sub>1</sub>, N<sub>2</sub>, N<sub>3</sub>, N<sub>4</sub>, N<sub>5</sub> and N<sub>6</sub> (in units of mol/h),
letting the corresponding specific heats be Cp<sub>1</sub>, Cp<sub>2</sub>, Cp<sub>3</sub>,
Cp<sub>4</sub>, Cp<sub>5</sub> and Cp<sub>6</sub> (in kcal/mol·°C), letting the adiabatic
flame temperature be ta (in °C), and assuming room
temperature to be 25°C, given that the total amount of heat
released by combustion is equivalent to the total amount of
heat consumed, we get
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">Q = (N<st32:sub pos="post">1</st32:sub>Cp<st32:sub pos="post">1</st32:sub> + N<st32:sub pos="post">2</st32:sub>Cp<st32:sub pos="post">2</st32:sub> + N<st32:sub pos="post">3</st32:sub>Cp<st32:sub pos="post">3</st32:sub> + N<st32:sub pos="post">4</st32:sub>Cp<st32:sub pos="post">4</st32:sub> + N<st32:sub pos="post">5</st32:sub>Cp<st32:sub pos="post">5</st32:sub> + N<st32:sub pos="post">6</st32:sub>Cp<st32:sub pos="post">6</st32:sub>) (ta - 25).</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0032">The JANAF (Joint Army-Navy-Air Force) Thermochemical
Tables indicate the standard enthalpy difference H°<sub>T</sub>-H<sub>298</sub>
(kJ/mol) between an absolute temperature of T in degrees
Kelvin (T = t°C + 273) and an absolute temperature of 298 K
(= 25°C) for various chemical substances. By referring to
these tables, and letting the heat quantity consumed per
mole of a chemical substance in raising the temperature of
the substance from 25°C to t°C (where t = T-273) be E (in
kcal/mol), we get
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">E = Cp(t-25) = (H<st32:sup pos="post">o</st32:sup> <st32:sub pos="post">T</st32:sub> - H<st32:sub pos="post">298</st32:sub>) × 0.2389.</st32:df>
It should be noted here that 1 kJ = 0.2389 kcal. Based on
this formula, letting the amount of heat consumed per mole
in raising the temperature of silica, titania, steam, CO<sub>2</sub>, O<sub>2</sub>
and N<sub>2</sub> from 298 K (25°C) to T K (where T = 273 + t°C) be
respectively E<sub>1</sub>, E<sub>2</sub>, E<sub>3</sub>, E<sub>4</sub>, E<sub>5</sub> and E<sub>6</sub> (kcal/mol), the
temperature at which <st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">Q = N<st32:sub pos="post">1</st32:sub>E<st32:sub pos="post">1</st32:sub> + N<st32:sub pos="post">2</st32:sub>E<st32:sub pos="post">2</st32:sub> + N<st32:sub pos="post">3</st32:sub>E<st32:sub pos="post">3</st32:sub> + N<st32:sub pos="post">4</st32:sub>E<st32:sub pos="post">4</st32:sub> + N<st32:sub pos="post">5</st32:sub>E<st32:sub pos="post">5</st32:sub> + N<st32:sub pos="post">6</st32:sub>E<st32:sub pos="post">6</st32:sub></st32:df>
is the adiabatic flame temperature ta.</p>
    <p num="0033">The adiabatic flame temperature may be controlled by
adjusting such factors as the type, feed rate, and feed
ratio to oxygen of the siloxane and organic titanium
compound. If the burner supplies a large amount of excess
oxygen or of an inert gas such as nitrogen which does not
take part in combustion, this lowers the flame temperature,
increases the fineness of the spherical complex oxide
particles of silica-titania, and compromises coalescence and
growth among the particles, both resulting in the formation
of agglomerates and increasing the load on the exhaust
collection system. If the adiabatic flame temperature for
combustion of the siloxane, organic titanium compound and
combustion-assisting gas, based on the siloxane, organic
titanium compound, combustion-assisting gas and combustion-supporting
gas fed to the burner is lower than 1,650°C, the
complex oxide particles are very fine and fail to unite by
coalescence and growth, becoming instead agglomerates and
contributing to no improvement in flow. In addition, both
the productivity and energy efficiency suffer. For these
reasons, the adiabatic flame temperature must be at least
1,650°C, preferably at least 1,700°C. On the other hand,
reducing the amount of inert gas and combustion-supporting
gas raises the adiabatic flame temperature and increases the
size of particles being formed. If the adiabatic flame
temperature exceeds 4,000°C, then particles have a diameter
in excess of 300 nm and a surface area of less than 20 m<sup>2</sup>/g.
Thus the adiabatic flame temperature must be up to 4,000°C,
preferably up to 3,600°C.</p>
    <p num="0034">Other than the foregoing, there are no limitations
concerning the introduction of air or an inert gas such as
nitrogen to prevent the deposition of powder on the walls of
the combustion furnace or to cool the exhaust gases
following combustion. The complex oxide fine particles thus
obtained by combustion are carried on the exhaust gases and 
collected e.g. by a cyclone, pneumatic classifier or bag
filter provided along the exhaust route.</p>
    <p num="0035">In this way, complex oxide fine particles are produced
which are spherical in shape, consist of silica and 1 to 99
wt% titania, are substantially free of chlorine, and have a
particle size of 10 to 300 nm and a specific surface area of
20 to 100 m<sup>2</sup>/g.</p>
    <p num="0036">To minimize the variation of charge quantity with
temperature and humidity, the complex oxide fine particles
of silica-titania according to the invention are preferably
hydrophobized, that is, fine particles having introduced at
their surface units represented by the following formula
(1):
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/">R<sup>1</sup> <sub>x</sub>R<sup>2</sup> <sub>y</sub>R<sup>3</sup> <sub>z</sub>SiO<sub>(4-x-y-z)/2</sub></st32:che>
wherein R<sup>1</sup>, R<sup>2</sup> and R<sup>3</sup> each are independently a substituted or
unsubstituted monovalent hydrocarbon group having 1 to 6
carbon atoms, x, y and z each are an integer of 0 to 3,
x+y+z is from 1 to 3.</p>
    <p num="0037">Examples of the hydrocarbon group represented by R<sup>1</sup>, R<sup>2</sup>
and R<sup>3</sup> include alkyl groups such as methyl, ethyl, propyl,
butyl, pentyl, hexyl and cyclohexyl, aryl groups such as
phenyl, and alkenyl groups such as vinyl and allyl, with
methyl being most preferred. The units of formula (1) can
be introduced according to a well-known method of surface
modifying silica fine powder. For example, a silazane
compound represented by the formula: R<sup>1</sup><sub>3</sub>SiNHSiR<sup>1</sup><sub>3</sub> is heated at
a temperature of 50 to 400°C in a gas, liquid or solid phase
in the presence of water, for removing the excessive
silazane compound.</p>
    <p num="0038">Examples of the silazane compound: R<sup>1</sup><sub>3</sub>SiNHSiR<sup>1</sup><sub>3</sub> include
hexamethyldisilazane, hexaethyldisilazane, hexapropyldisilazane,
hexabutyldisilazane, hexapentyldisilazane,
hexahexyldisilazane, hexacyclohexyldisilazane, hexaphenyldisilazane,
divinyltetramethyldisilazane, and dimethyltetravinyldisilazane.
Among others, hexamethyldisilazane is most 
preferred for hydrophobic property achievable by
modification and ease of its removal.</p>
    <p num="0039">The electrostatic image developer of the invention is
obtainable by adding the spherical complex oxide fine
particles to toner particles. The amount of the spherical
complex oxide fine particles blended is preferably 0.01 to
20 parts by weight, more preferably 0.1 to 10 parts by
weight per 100 parts by weight of the toner particles. Less
than 0.01 part of the oxide fine particles are insufficient
to improve the fluidity of toner particles whereas more than
20 parts of the oxide fine particles adversely affect the
charging ability. If necessary, additives such as a charge
controlling agent, parting agent and wax may be blended in
the developer.</p>
    <p num="0040">These components may be mixed by any desired method.
Use is made of, for example, rotary type mixers such as
V-type mixers and double cone mixers, impeller mixers such
as ribbon mixers and screw mixers, high-speed shear flow
type mixers, and ball mills. As a result of mixing, the
spherical complex oxide fine particles may be either
attached or fused to surfaces of the toner particles.</p>
    <p num="0041">The electrostatic image developer comprising spherical
complex oxide fine particles of silica-titania according to
the invention may be used as a one-component developer. It
may also be used as a two-component developer after further
mixing with a carrier. In the application as two-component
developer, the toner may also be surface coated with the
spherical complex oxide fine particles by adding the oxide
fine particles during the mixing of the toner and the
carrier rather than previously adding the oxide fine
particles to the toner.</p>
    <p num="0042">The carrier is in the form of particles having a mean
particle size which is close to the particle size of the
toner or up to 300 µm. Any well-known carrier may be used,
for example, iron, nickel, cobalt, iron oxide, ferrite,
glass beads, and particulate silicon. The carrier particles 
may be surface coated with fluoro-resins, acrylic resins or
silicone resins.</p>
    <p num="0043">The electrostatic image developer of the invention can
be used in developing electrostatic latent images on
photoconductor drums or dielectric-coated (electrostatic
recording) media. More particularly, electrostatic latent
images are electrophotographically formed on photoconductor
drums made of inorganic photoconductive materials such as
selenium, zinc oxide, cadmium sulfide and amorphous silicon,
or organic photoconductive materials such as phthalocyanine
pigments and bisazo pigments. Alternatively, electrostatic
latent images are formed on dielectric-coated media having
polyethylene terephthalate derivatives or the like by a
needle electrode or the like. Then a developing process
such as a magnetic brush, cascade or touch-down process is
used to apply the electrostatic image developer of the
invention to the electrostatic latent images for attaching
the toner thereto.</p>
    <p num="0044">The resulting toner images are then transferred to
transfer media such as paper and fixed thereto to form
duplicates. The residual toner on the surface of the
photoconductor drum or the like is cleaned by a suitable
process such as a blade, brush, web or roll process.</p>
    <p num="0045">The method of making the complex oxide fine particles, and a
method of making a developer by combining such fine particles
with toner, optionally including the making of the fine
particles, are further aspects of the invention.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLE</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0046">Examples of the invention are given below by way of
illustration and not by way of limitation.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Examples 1-7</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0047">A mixture of hexamethyldisiloxane or octamethylcyclotetrasiloxane
and tetraisopropoxytitanium or titanium
acetylacetonate (diisopropoxybisacetylacetonatotitanium) was
fed at room temperature and in a liquid state to a burner on
top of a vertical combustion furnace. From an atomizing
nozzle mounted at the tip of the burner, the mixture was
atomized as a fine mist with the aid of air as the atomizing
medium and combustion was induced by a propane-burning 
auxiliary flame. Oxygen and air were fed from the burner as
combustion-supporting gases. The mixing ratio of
hexamethyldisiloxane or octamethylcyclotetrasiloxane and
tetraisopropoxytitanium or titanium acetylacetonate, the
feed rates of the mixture, propane, oxygen and air
(including atomizing air) in each example are shown in
Tables 1 and 2, together with the respective adiabatic flame
temperatures. Table 3 shows how the adiabatic flame
temperature was calculated in Example 1.</p>
    <p num="0048">The spherical complex oxide fine particles of silica-titania
thus produced were recovered by collecting in a bag
filter. The spherical complex oxide fine powder, 500 g, was
admitted into a 5-liter high-speed agitation mixer equipped
with a heating/cooling jacket. While agitating at 500 rpm,
25 g of deionized water was sprayed and fed to the powder in
a closed state. Agitation was continued for 10 minutes.
Subsequently, 25 g of hexamethyldisilazane was added and
agitation was continued for a further 60 minutes in the
closed state. With agitation, the powder was then heated at
150°C and nitrogen was flowed for removing the ammonia gas
formed and the residual agent, obtaining a hydrophobized
spherical complex oxide fine powder.</p>
    <p num="0049">The hydrophobized spherical complex oxide fine powder
was measured for BET specific surface area by means of
Micro-Sope 4232 II (Micro Data Co.). The particle size was
measured by scanning electron microscopy (SEM). The
particle shape on the resulting micrograph was analyzed
using a particle shape analyzer Luzex F (manufactured by
Nireco Co., Ltd.), from which all the particles were found
to be spherical with a breadth-to-length ratio of at least
0.85. Titania contents, specific surface areas and particle
sizes measured for the products obtained in examples are
given in Tables 1 and 2. The chlorine impurity content was
less than 0.1 ppm, as measured by ion chromatography.</p>
    <p num="0050">Next, 4 parts by weight of Carmine 6BC as the colorant
was added to 96 parts by weight of a polyester resin having
Tg of 60°C and a softening point of 110°C. They were melt 
milled, followed by grinding and classification. Toner
particles having a mean particle size of 7 µm were obtained.
The toner, 40 g, was mixed with 1 g of the hydrophobized
spherical complex oxide fine powder in a sample mill,
obtaining a developer. The developer was examined for
fluidity, cleanability, and charging stability by the
following tests. The results of evaluation are also shown
in Tables 1 and 2.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Comparative Example 1</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0051">A developer was prepared as in Example 1 except that
the feed rates of oxygen and air during the atomizing
combustion were increased so that the adiabatic flame
temperature was lower than 1,650°C, while the hydrophobizing
conditions and the addition amount to the toner were the
same as in Example 1. Table 2 shows the feed rates of the
starting materials during combustion, burner gas conditions,
and adiabatic flame temperature as well as the specific
surface area and particle size distribution of hydrophobized
fine particles, and the fluidity, cleanability and charging
stability of the developer.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Comparative Example 2</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0052">A developer was prepared as in Example 1 except that a
spherical silica fine powder was produced by atomizing only
hexamethyldisiloxane for combustion without adding the
organic titanium compound, while the hydrophobizing
conditions and the addition amount to the toner were the
same as in Example 1. Table 2 shows the feed rate of the
starting material during combustion, burner gas conditions,
and adiabatic flame temperature as well as the specific
surface area and particle size distribution of hydrophobized
fine particles, and the fluidity, cleanability and charging
stability of the developer. </p>
    <heading>Evaluation of fluidity</heading>
    <p num="0053">Cohesiveness was measured, from which fluidity was
evaluated. The instrument used was Multi-Tester by Seishin
Kigyo K.K. A developer, 3 g, was placed on a measurement
unit having three sieves with an opening of 250 µm, 150 µm
and 75 µm stacked from top, which was vibrated at an
amplitude of 1 mm for 60 seconds. Provided that W<sub>1</sub>, W<sub>2</sub> and W<sub>3</sub>
(all in gram) are the weights of powder fractions left on
the upper, intermediate and lower sieves, respectively,
cohesiveness is given by the following equation. A powder
with a cohesiveness of less than 6% is regarded
satisfactory.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">Cohesivenss (%) = (W<st32:sub pos="post">1</st32:sub> + W<st32:sub pos="post">2</st32:sub> × 0.6 + W<st32:sub pos="post">3</st32:sub> × 0.2) × 100/3</st32:df></p>
    <heading>Evaluation of cleanability</heading>
    <p num="0054">A printer equipped with an organic photoconductor drum
was used. A two-component developer was prepared by
admixing 100 parts by weight of the developer with 8 parts
by weight of a carrier obtained by coating ferrite cores of
50 µm in diameter with a mixture of a perfluoroalkyl
acrylate resin and an acrylic resin. By loading the
two-component developer printer with the two-component
developer as a starter and the developer as a replenisher, a
printing test of 10,000 sheets of paper was conducted. The
adhesion of the developer to the photoconductor drum was
reflected by white spots in full solid images.</p>
    <heading>Evaluation of charging stability</heading>
    <p num="0055">By loading a one-component developer printer with the
one-component developer in Example, a printing test of
10,000 sheets of plain paper was conducted. On the image
transferred and fixed to plain paper, a fog level was
measured using a color difference meter. <tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry nameend="7" align="center" namest="2">Example</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Type of siloxane</entry><entry align="center">hexamethyl disiloxane</entry><entry align="center">hexamethyl disiloxane</entry><entry align="center">hexamethyl disiloxane</entry><entry align="center">hexamethyl disiloxane</entry><entry align="center">ootamethyl cyclotetra siloxane</entry><entry align="center">hexamethyl disiloxane</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Type of organic Ti compound Ti compound</entry><entry align="center">tetraiso propoxy titanium</entry><entry align="center">tetraiso propoxy titanium</entry><entry align="center">tetraiso propoxy titanium</entry><entry align="center">tetraiso propoxy titanium</entry><entry align="center">tetraiso propoxy titanium</entry><entry align="center">tetraiso propoxy titanium</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Siloxane/Ti compound mixing weight ratio</entry><entry align="center">3:2</entry><entry align="center">3:1</entry><entry align="center">2:3</entry><entry align="center">1:2</entry><entry align="center">2:1</entry><entry align="center">1:6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Feed rate of mixture (kg/h)</entry><entry align="center">4.0</entry><entry align="center">6.0</entry><entry align="center">4.0</entry><entry align="center">3.6</entry><entry align="center">6.6</entry><entry align="center">4.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Feed rate of propane (Nm<sup>3</sup>/h)</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Feed rate of oxygen (Nm<sup>3</sup>/h)</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry><entry align="center">9.0</entry><entry align="center">8.0</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Feed rate of air (Nm<sup>3</sup>/h)</entry><entry align="center">20.0</entry><entry align="center">18.0</entry><entry align="center">28.0</entry><entry align="center">35.0</entry><entry align="center">15.0</entry><entry align="center">20.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Adiabatic flame temperature (°C)</entry><entry align="center">2,423</entry><entry align="center">3,360</entry><entry align="center">2,071</entry><entry align="center">1,712</entry><entry align="center">3,387</entry><entry align="center">2,372</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Titania content (wt%) content</entry><entry align="center">20.2</entry><entry align="center">11.2</entry><entry align="center">36.3</entry><entry align="center">43.1</entry><entry align="center">14.8</entry><entry align="center">69.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">BET specific surface area (m<sup>2</sup>/g)</entry><entry align="center">40</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">60</entry><entry align="center">80</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">45</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Particle size distribution (nm)</entry><entry align="center">40-200</entry><entry align="center">60-300</entry><entry align="center">30-150</entry><entry align="center">20-100</entry><entry align="center">60-300</entry><entry align="center">40-180</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fluidity (cohesiveness %)</entry><entry align="center">3.9</entry><entry align="center">3.8</entry><entry align="center">5.1</entry><entry align="center">5.5</entry><entry align="center">3.4</entry><entry align="center">3.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Cleanabllity</entry><entry align="center">no white spots</entry><entry align="center">no white spots</entry><entry align="center">no white spots</entry><entry align="center">no white spots</entry><entry align="center">no white spots</entry><entry align="center">no white spots</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Charging stability (fog level %)</entry><entry align="center">1.2</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry><entry align="center">1.2</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry align="center" namest="2">Example</entry><entry nameend="4" align="center" namest="3">Comparative Example</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Type of siloxane</entry><entry align="center">hexamethyl disiloxane</entry><entry align="center">hexamethyl disiloxane</entry><entry align="center">hexamethyl disiloxane</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Type of organic Ti compound</entry><entry align="center">titanium acetylacetonate</entry><entry align="center">tetraisopropoxy titanium</entry><entry align="center">none</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Siloxane/Ti compound mixing weight ratio</entry><entry align="center">3:1</entry><entry align="center">1:1</entry><entry align="center">1:0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Feed rate of mixture (kg/h)</entry><entry align="center">3.6</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry><entry align="center">4.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Feed rate of propane (Nm<sup>3</sup>/h)</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Feed rate of oxygen (Nm<sup>3</sup>/h)</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry><entry align="center">7.0</entry><entry align="center">12.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Feed rate of air (Nm<sup>3</sup>/h)</entry><entry align="center">18.0</entry><entry align="center">40.0</entry><entry align="center">22.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Adiabatic flame temperature (°C)</entry><entry align="center">2,499</entry><entry align="center">1,410</entry><entry align="center">2,543</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Titania content (wt%)</entry><entry align="center">9.0</entry><entry align="center">27.5</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">BET specific surface area (m<sup>2</sup>/g)</entry><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">120</entry><entry align="center">45</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Particle size distribution (nm)</entry><entry align="center">50-250</entry><entry align="center">10-50 agglomerates</entry><entry align="center">50-250</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fluidity (cohesiveness %)</entry><entry align="center">3.8</entry><entry align="center">26</entry><entry align="center">4.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Cleanability</entry><entry align="center">no white spots</entry><entry align="center">white spots</entry><entry align="center">some white spots</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Charging stability (fog level %)</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry><entry align="center">9.8</entry><entry align="center">6.1</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><img id="img-00210001" orientation="unknown" wi="164" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00210001.tif" inline="no" he="138"/></p>
    <p num="0056">These results indicate many advantages. By atomising a
halogen-free purified siloxane and an organic titanium
compound as starting materials for flame combustion,
spherical complex oxide fine particles of high-purity
amorphous silica-titania substantially free of chlorine are
obtained. The high combustion temperature allows more core
particles of silica-titania to generate and promotes
coalescence and growth thereof, leading to spherical complex
oxide fine particles having a particle size of 10 to 300 nm,
a specific surface area of 20 to 100 m<sup>2</sup>/g, and a titania
content of 1 to 99% by weight. By further hydrophobizing
the fine particles and adding them to a toner, a developer
is obtained which is improved in fluidity, cleanability and
uniform and stable charging. </p>
    <p num="0057">Japanese Patent Application No. 2001-183101 is
incorporated herein by reference.</p>
    <p num="0058">Although some preferred embodiments have been
described, many modifications and variations may be made
thereto in light of the above teachings. It is therefore to
be understood that the invention may be practiced otherwise
than as specifically described in the examples.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>An electrostatic image developer comprising spherical
complex oxide fine particles of amorphous silica-titania
obtainable by atomising a siloxane and an organic titanium
compound in a flame for combustion, having a particle size
of 10 to 300 nm, a specific surface area of 20 to 100 m2/g,
and a titania content of 1 to 99% by weight.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The developer of claim 1 wherein the complex oxide
fine particles are substantially free of chlorine.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The developer of claim 1 or 2 wherein the organic titanium
compound is selected from the group consisting of a
tetraalkoxytitanium compound, titanium acylate compound,
alkyltitanium compound and titanium chelate compound.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>Developer of claim 1, 2 or 3 wherein the complex oxide
fine particles have been prepared by simultaneously
atomizing the siloxane and the organic titanium compound
into a flame for oxidative combustion, in which method,
based on the siloxane, the organic titanium compound, a
combustion-assisting gas and a combustion-supporting gas fed
to a burner, the siloxane, the organic titanium compound and
the combustion-assisting gas when burned have an adiabatic
flame temperature within a range of 1,650°C to 4,000°C.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>Developer according to any one of the preceding claims
wherein the complex oxide fine particles are hydrophobized
fine particles having introduced at their surface units
represented by the following formula (1):
R1 xR2 yR3 zSiO(4-x-y-z)/2
wherein R1, R2 and R3 each are independently a substituted or
unsubstituted monovalent hydrocarbon group having 1 to 6
carbon atoms, x, y and z each are an integer of 0 to 3,
x+y+z is from 1 to 3.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A method comprising the preparation of an image developer
according to any one of claims 1 to 5.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
