<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1266994-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1266994" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="25332331" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021218">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1266994-A1" status="new" fvid="23636972">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1266994</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20021218</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02253382-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02253382</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020510</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="US-86002501-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>86002501</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010516</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">D21B   1/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">D21B   1/16        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">D21C   9/10        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">D21C   9/10        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">D21C   9/16        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">D21C   9/16        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">D21D   1/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">D21D   1/20        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">D21C   9/16B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">D21D   1/20</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">N21C9:10F6</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Hochtemperatur-Peroxidbleichen von mechanischen Pulpen</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">High temperature peroxide bleaching of mechanical pulps</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Blanchissement au peroxyde à haute température de pâtes mécaniques</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>WEYERHAEUSER CO</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>WEYERHAEUSER COMPANY</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Weyerhaeuser Company</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>P.O. Box 9777</street>
              <city>Federal Way, WA 98063-9777</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>BROOKS ZEECHA L</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>CAMPBELL ROGER O</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HAMILTON ROBERT T</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HAYNES KAAREN K</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>PARRISH ANTHONY</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>BROOKS, ZEECHA L.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>CAMPBELL, ROGER O.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HAMILTON, ROBERT T.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HAYNES, KAAREN K.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>PARRISH, ANTHONY</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>BROOKS, ZEECHA L.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>13572 S.W. Ascension Drive</street>
              <city>Tigard, Oregon 97223</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>CAMPBELL, ROGER O.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>506 S.W. 324th Federal Way</street>
              <city>Washington 98023</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>HAMILTON, ROBERT T.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>3015 Northwest 58th Street</street>
              <city>Seattle, Washington 98107</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>HAYNES, KAAREN K.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>32621 49th Court Southwest Federal Way</street>
              <city>Washington 98023</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>PARRISH, ANTHONY</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>120 Great Northern</street>
              <city>Kalama, Washington 98625</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Trueman, Lucy Petra</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Barker Brettell, 138 Hagley Road, Edgbaston</street>
              <city>Birmingham B16 9PW</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A method of making bleached mechanical pulps is disclosed for pulping
mills having a primary and a secondary refiner. A first step (100) is to provide
cellulosic materials, such as wood chips to refine into the pulp; the wood chips
have an initial brightness level. A second step (102) is to provide a bleaching
liquor to the refining system of the pulp mill, wherein the liquor comprises an
amount of hydrogen peroxide and an amount of alkali having greater than 0% to
100% magnesium hydroxide or soda ash or a combination thereof. A third step
(104,106) is to hold the pulp with the bleaching liquor at a temperature in the
range of about 85° to about 160°C and for about 2 to about 180 minutes.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="53" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="125"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention is directed to processes for producing mechanical pulps,
and more particularly to hydrogen peroxide bleaching of thermomechanical pulps and
the resultant pulps made therefrom.</p>
    <heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0002">Mechanical pulping is a process of mechanically triturating wood into its fibers
for the purpose of making pulp. Mechanical pulping is attractive as a method for
pulping because it achieves high yields when compared to chemical pulping because
lignin is not removed from mechanically pulped woods, meaning scarce resources are
more efficiently utilized. Pulps made using any of the conventional mechanical pulping
methods are mainly used for newsprint, and are unsuitable for higher quality or more
durable paper and products. This is due, in part, to the fact that mechanical pulps are
generally more difficult to bleach than chemical pulps.</p>
    <p num="0003">There are many variants of mechanical pulping including stone grinding (SG),
pressurized stone grinding (PSG), refiner mechanical pulping (RMP), thermomechanical
pulping (TMP), and chemi-thermomechanical pulping (CTMP). The latter three can 
further be grouped generally under refiner pulping processes. In RMP, wood chips are
ground between rotating metal disks. The process usually is carried out in two stages.
The first stage is mainly used to separate the fibers, while the second stage is used to
treat the fiber surface for improved fiber bonding of paper products. In RMP, the wood
chips are refined at atmospheric pressure in both a first and a second stage refiner. The
refiner process generates heat by the friction of the metal disks against the wood. The
heat is liberated as amounts of steam which is often used to soften the incoming chips.</p>
    <p num="0004">TMP differs from RMP in that the pulp is made in a pressurized refiner. In this
process, two stages are normally used also. The first stage refiner operates at elevated
temperature and pressure, and the second stage refiner is at ambient conditions. The first
stage separates the fibers and the second stage then treats the fibers. Pulps made by
TMP have high strength, which makes the TMP process the most favored mechanical
pulping process. However, there is still room for improvements. The TMP process
consumes high energy, and the pulp produced by the TMP process tends to be darker
than most other pulps.</p>
    <p num="0005">CTMP uses both chemical and thermal pretreatment for processing the wood
chips into pulp. CTMP is a chemi-thermomechanical process that is similar to TMP,
except that the chips are first pretreated with relatively small amounts of sodium
hydroxide with hydrogen peroxide under elevated temperature and pressure prior to
refining. The adjuvant chemicals make the separation of the cellulosic fibers much
easier in the refiners.</p>
    <p num="0006">The foregoing list is by no means exhaustive. There are innumerable
combinations and variants of the pulping processes as exemplified in <i>The Handbook of
Pulping and Papermaking,</i> 2d ed., by Christopher J. Biermann, which is herein
incorporated by reference. Of the mechanical pulping processes, the one which is
considered by many in the field to be the most favorable, taking into consideration
market conditions and environmental regulations, is the TMP process. However, were it
not for the fact that chemi-thermomechanical pulping processes produce effluents of 
high color, high COD and BOD, which may be difficult to treat, CTMP processes would
have an advantage over TMP processes because the energy grinding requirements for
CTMP are about half that of TMP.</p>
    <p num="0007">Bleaching is a term applied to a semi-chemical or chemical step in a pulping
process to increase the brightness of both chemical and mechanical pulps. In mechanical
pulping, the increase in brightness is achieved by altering the chemical structure of the
conjugated double bonds in lignin. The conjugated double-bonded species are called
chromophores. "Brightening" is the term often used when referring to bleaching of
mechanical pulps to distinguish it from the bleaching process of chemical pulps, which
differs by removing lignin entirely. As used hereinafter "bleaching" will be intended to
cover the process of "brightening" as well. In mechanical pulps, brightening is often
carried out in a single step in the pulping process. The bleaching process is
conventionally carried out in a bleaching train in one or a plurality of vessels (bleach
towers or stages) in a distinct section of the mill plant, as opposed to the pulping section
of the mill. Brightening can be carried out using oxidative and/or reductive chemical
agents including oxidating reagents, such as hydrogen peroxide and reducing agents,
such as dithionite, or sodium hydrosulfate. Normally, hydrogen peroxide, an oxidizing
agent, is used with sodium hydroxide. For a more thorough discussion of bleaching
chemistry, reference is made to <i>Pulp Bleaching ― Principles and Practice,</i> by J. Ross
Anderson and B. Amini; Section V: Chapter 1: Peroxide Bleaching of
(Chemi)mechanical Pulps, by J.R. Presley and R.T. Hill. Sodium hydroxide is a strong
alkali and provides the requisite high pH necessary to produce the active perhydroxyl
ion, HOO<sup>-</sup>, thought to produce the bleaching effect in pulps. The cost of sodium
hydroxide has been increasing due to changes in availability and energy costs. Concern
over the environment has also meant a decrease in the available sodium hydroxide
supply. Therefore, different alkali sources and different methods have been tried to find
suitable alternatives for bleaching liquors and bleaching processes with limited success. </p>
    <p num="0008">Hence, there is a need to improve existing mechanical pulping processes to
provide higher brightness pulps by processes having added advantages.</p>
    <heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0009">When alkali peroxide bleaching at high temperatures, better brightness is
obtained when using an alkali buffer (such as soda ash or magnesium hydroxide),
instead of sodium hydroxide. Buffering the system at lower pH (about 9 to about 10.5)
prevents peroxide decomposition and alkali darkening, but still provides adequate alkali
to produce effective bleaching. The buffer releases alkalinity as necessary and provides
just enough alkalinity for a slow, even production of perhydroxyl ions. The present
invention provides a supply of perhydroxyl ions as needed for bleaching and prolongs
the effective bleaching time, making the peroxide more effective and giving higher
brightness and higher yields by reducing the breakdown of the wood fibers, thus
overcoming many of the aforementioned problems.</p>
    <p num="0010">A method of making bleached mechanical pulps is disclosed for pulping mills
having a refining system. A step according to the invention is to provide a cellulosic
material, such as wood chips, having an initial brightness level. A second step in the
method in accordance with the invention is to introduce the cellulosic material to a
refining system for conversion into a pulp. A third step in the method in accordance
with the invention is to provide a bleaching liquor to the refining system, wherein the
liquor comprises an amount of hydrogen peroxide and an amount of alkali, wherein up to
100% of alkali is either magnesium hydroxide, soda ash or a combination thereof. Any
additional balance required to arrive at a suitable amount of alkali is supplied by NaOH.
A fourth step in the method in accordance with the invention is to hold the pulp with the
bleaching liquor at an effective temperature and for an effective time sufficient to
increase the brightness of the pulp from the initial brightness level to brightness level
equal to or higher than what can be obtained when 100% of alkali is NaOH and the pulp
and bleaching liquor are contacted under about the same time and temperature 
conditions. Pulps having a brightness of at least 35 ISO or in the range of about 55 to
69.5 ISO are attainable by the methods of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0011">One embodiment uses a temperature in the range of about 85° to about 160°C for
about 2 to about 180 minutes, as the conditions under which the pulp and bleaching
liquor are held. Another alternate second suitable temperature range includes greater
than 100°C to about 160°C. Three other alternate suitable time ranges include the
ranges of from about 10 minutes to less than 180 minutes, or greater than 60 minutes to
less than 120 minutes, or greater than 2 minutes to less than 60 minutes and the
combination of these three alternate time ranges with the temperature ranges.
Furthermore, any time or temperature range within the aforementioned time and
temperature ranges can also be used.</p>
    <p num="0012">In another alternate embodiment, a step of increasing the pH of the pulp to the
range of about 9 to about 10.5 is provided, in addition to the steps mentioned above.</p>
    <p num="0013">In another alternate embodiment, a method of making bleached mechanical pulps
is disclosed for pulping mills having a refining system. A step according to the
invention is to provide a cellulosic material having an initial brightness level. A second
step in the method in accordance with the invention is to introduce a cellulosic material
to a refining system for conversion to a pulp. A third step in the method in accordance
with the invention is to provide a bleaching liquor to the refining system, wherein the
liquor comprises a first amount of hydrogen peroxide and alkali, wherein up to 100% of
alkali is magnesium hydroxide, soda ash, or a combination thereof. A fourth step in the
method in accordance with the invention is to hold the pulp and the bleaching liquor at a
temperature in the range of about 85°C to about 160°C for a time of about 2 to about
180 minutes. A fifth step in the method in accordance with the invention is to increase
the brightness of the pulp about equal to or less than a brightness level which can be
obtained if the bleaching liquor comprises a second amount of hydrogen peroxide which
is greater than the first amount, wherein 100% of alkali is sodium hydroxide and the 
pulp and bleaching liquor are held under about the same time and temperature
conditions.</p>
    <p num="0014">A method of brightening TMP pulps in accordance with the invention provides
significant advantages. The residual peroxide level is increased, meaning more effective
use of hydrogen peroxide. A decrease in the oxalate concentration is noticed, meaning
less scaling of process equipment, thereby reducing premature equipment wear. An
increase in pulp yields is also realized. Furthermore, COD and BOD levels of plant
effluents are reduced, which contribute to lower pollution levels entering waste water
facilities.</p>
    <heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
    <p num="0015">The foregoing aspects and many of the attendant advantages of this invention
will become more readily appreciated as the same become better understood by
reference to the following detailed description, when taken in conjunction with the
accompanying drawings, wherein:
<sl><li>FIGURE 1 shows a schematic illustration of a method of bleaching mechanical
pulps according to the present invention;</li><li>FIGURE 2 shows a schematic illustration of a mechanical pulping section of a
mill;</li><li>FIGURE 3 shows a schematic illustration of a second embodiment of a
mechanical pulping section of a mill;</li><li>FIGURE 4 shows a logic diagram for conducting lab sample studies of the
pulping mill of FIGURE 2 and FIGURE 3;</li><li>FIGURE 5 shows a graphical illustration of the energy requirements of sample
runs according to the present invention;</li><li>FIGURE 6 shows a graphical illustration of the brightness results of the sample
runs according to the present invention;</li><li>FIGURE 7 shows a graphical illustration of brightness point changes of the
sample runs in comparison to a control according to the present invention; </li><li>FIGURE 8 shows a graphical illustration of peroxide residual results of the
sample runs according to the present invention;</li><li>FIGURE 9 shows a graphical illustration of the cost of bleach chemicals in
dollars per ton per brightness point according to the present invention;</li><li>FIGURE 10 shows a graphical illustration of the cost of bleach chemicals in
dollars per ton;</li><li>FIGURE 11 shows a graphical illustration of the pulp yields of the sample runs
according to the present invention;</li><li>FIGURE 12 shows a graphical illustration of the pulp yield changes of the
sample runs in comparison to a control according to the present invention;</li><li>FIGURE 13 shows a graphical illustration of the oxalate concentration of the
sample runs according to the present invention;</li><li>FIGURE 14 shows a graphical illustration of the COD concentration of the
sample runs according to the present invention;</li><li>FIGURE 15 shows a graphical illustration of the BOD concentration of the
sample runs according to the present invention;</li><li>FIGURE 16 shows a schematic illustration of a second embodiment of a method
of bleaching mechanical pulps according to the present invention; and</li><li>FIGURE 17 shows a schematic illustration of a generic mechanical pulping
system.</li></sl></p>
    <heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
    <p num="0016">Referring to FIGURE 1, a schematic illustration of a method of making bleached
mechanical pulp according to the present invention is illustrated. In block 100, a supply
of cellulosic materials is provided; the cellulosic materials have an initial brightness
level. Suitable cellulosic materials to use in the present invention are wood chips,
conventionally used as feed to TMP processes. However, the present invention is not
limited to wood chips. Any materials containing a quantity of cellulose and which can 
undergo mechanical pulping are suitable cellulosic materials for use in the present
invention. This includes any softwood and hardwood species. In block 102, a supply of
bleaching liquor, containing hydrogen peroxide and alkali, where the alkali includes up
to 100% of magnesium hydroxide (Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub>), soda ash (Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>) or any mixtures
thereof with the balance being sodium hydroxide (NaOH) to arrive at a suitable quantity
of alkali, is added to the cellulosic material to produce a mixture. Virtually any amount
of buffer capacity provided by magnesium hydroxide or soda ash or any combination
thereof, partially or wholly substituted for sodium hydroxide provides favorable results.
It is also to be understood that the components of the bleaching liquor may be added
separately, meaning one at a time or concurrently, meaning two or more components
together. It should also be understood that alkali as used herein means one or more
compounds which provide alkalinity, which may be added to the bleaching liquid
separately or concurrently. In block 104, the cellulosic material and the bleaching liquor
are brought together as a mixture and heated to a temperature of about 85°C to about
160°C. In block 106, the pulp and liquor are held for about 2 to about 180 minutes. The
reaction of the mixture is carried out in a process vessel. It should be understood that the
process vessel can be any equipment, tank, or pipe and any combination of one or more
components that forms part of a refining system. In block 108, the brightness of the
cellulosic material within the mixture contained within the process vessel is increased to
a degree greater than the increase in brightness level achieved if the cellulosic material is
brightened using a bleaching liquor wherein alkali is 100% sodium hydroxide and the
pulp and bleaching liquor are held under about the same temperature and time
conditions.</p>
    <p num="0017">Referring to FIGURE 16, a schematic illustration of an alternate method of
making bleached mechanical pulp according to the present invention is illustrated. This
embodiment is similar to the embodiment mentioned above, containing all the blocks
recited above; however, an additional step, denoted as block 504, is provided to adjust 
the pH of the pulp mixture in the range of about 9 to about 10.5 using magnesium
hydroxide and/or soda ash as a pH buffer.</p>
    <p num="0018">The method according to the invention treats the ground wood in the refining
system of the mill, preferably, from prior to the first stage refiner through the second
stage refiner as illustrated in FIGURE 2, including the interstage section to
advantageously use the elevated pressures and temperatures associated with the first
stage refiner. The treatment includes mixing a bleaching composition (bleach liquor)
including hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) and partially or completely substituting a differing
alkali for 100% sodium hydroxide (NaOH), with the ground wood. As used herein,
ground wood is intended to mean the cellulosic material, together with any other
substances, including the bleaching composition, water or adjuvants. Ground wood,
therefore, can also be the term applied to the slurry as it is carried forward in the process.
Pulp is used interchangeably with ground wood, and also includes the resultant product
made by the process according to the invention.</p>
    <p num="0019">It is well known that the active species of hydrogen peroxide is the perhydroxyl
ion, HOO<sup>-</sup>. It is also well known that the equilibrium of the following reaction:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">I<st32:sub pos="post"><st32:italic>2</st32:italic></st32:sub><st32:italic>O</st32:italic><st32:sub pos="post"><st32:italic>2</st32:italic></st32:sub> + <st32:italic>OH</st32:italic><st32:sup pos="post">-</st32:sup> ↔ <st32:italic>H</st32:italic><st32:sub pos="post"><st32:italic>2</st32:italic></st32:sub><st32:italic>O</st32:italic> + <st32:italic>HOO</st32:italic><st32:sup pos="post">-</st32:sup></st32:df>
can be favored towards the right hand of the equation by increasing the pH of the
solution to produce the desired HOO<sup>-</sup> species. A conventional source of alkalinity is
sodium hydroxide. While sodium hydroxide is a viable alkali, reduced supplies and
increased costs have meant a corresponding reduction in its production, making sodium
hydroxide a less attractive source of alkalinity.</p>
    <p num="0020">The method according to the invention replaces wholly or partially alkalinity
derived from 100% sodium hydroxide with substitute alkali including magnesium
hydroxide (Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub>), and/or soda ash (Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>), or any combination thereof at
elevated temperatures. As used herein, alkali is meant to include any source of alkalinity
from NaOH, Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub>, and NaCO<sub>3</sub>. Magnesium hydroxide and soda ash also provide 
buffer capacity to prevent wide swings in pH. When alkaline peroxide bleaching at high
temperatures, better brightness is obtained when using a buffer (such as soda ash or
magnesium hydroxide), instead of or in addition to sodium hydroxide. Buffering the
system at lower pH (between about 9 to about 10.5) prevents peroxide decomposition
and darkening, but still provides adequate alkalinity to produce the desired species. The
buffer releases alkalinity as necessary, and provides just enough alkalinity for a slow and
even production of the perhydroxyl ions. The present invention provides a supply of
perhydroxyl ions as needed for bleaching and prolongs the effective bleaching time,
making the peroxide more effective and giving higher brightness. According to the
invention, the bleaching liquor includes a substitution of sodium hydroxide with
magnesium hydroxide or soda ash in the range of anywhere greater than 0% to 100%,
and suitably from about 40% to 100% on a weight percent basis. On an alkalinity basis,
each pound of sodium hydroxide is the equivalent of about 0.73 pounds of magnesium
hydroxide or about 1.31 pounds of soda ash.</p>
    <p num="0021">According to the present invention, a suitable buffer and substitute alkali for
sodium hydroxide is magnesium hydroxide which can be in any amount greater than 0%
to 100% of what would be considered a suitable quantity of sodium hydroxide,
preferably between about 40% to 100% of the suitable quantity of sodium hydroxide. A
suitable quantity of sodium hydroxide has been found to be in the range of about 10 to
about 100 pounds per ton of pulp on a dry basis. Then, according to the invention, the
bleaching liquor at the suitable composition can contain about 2.92 to about 7.3 pounds
of magnesium hydroxide at 40% replacement and about 29.2 to about 73 pounds of
magnesium hydroxide at 100% replacement for the range of 10 to 100 pounds of sodium
hydroxide, respectively, with any remainder of the alkalinity being supplied by sodium
hydroxide. According to the present invention of providing methods for bleaching
mechanical pulps, these amounts are suitable to use in such methods.</p>
    <p num="0022">According to the present invention, a suitable buffer and substitute alkali for
sodium hydroxide is soda ash that can be in any amount greater than 0% to 100% of 
what would be considered a suitable quantity of sodium hydroxide, suitably between
about 40% to 100% of the suitable quantity of sodium hydroxide, and more suitably
between about 50% to 100%. Then, according to the invention, the bleaching liquor at
the suitable composition can contain from about 5.24 pounds to about 13.1 pounds at
40% replacement and from about 52.4 to about 131 pounds of soda ash at 100%
replacement for the range of 10 to 100 pounds of sodium hydroxide, respectively, with
any remainder of the alkalinity being supplied by sodium hydroxide. These amounts of
alkali can be applied to the methods of brightening mechanical pulps, according to the
present invention. Hydrogen peroxide is included in the bleaching liquor and can be
added separately or concurrently with one or more of the liquor components.</p>
    <p num="0023">According to the invention, a suitable amount of hydrogen peroxide in the
bleaching liquor is about 10 to about 200 pounds per ton of pulp on a dry basis. The
hydrogen peroxide is conventionally obtained from suppliers as a mixture of 60% water
and 40% hydrogen peroxide on a weight basis, but other proportions of water and
hydrogen peroxide can be used, provided they are equivalent to 10 to 200 pounds of a
60:40 mixture. An acceptable ratio of alkalinity to hydrogen peroxide is about 0.25 to
about 3 on a weight basis of the 60:40 mixture. These amounts of hydrogen peroxide
can be applied to the methods of brightening mechanical pulps according to the present
invention.</p>
    <p num="0024">The bleaching liquor can also contain suitable chelating agents, such as, but not
limited to aminopolycarboxylic acids (APCA), ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA),
diethylene triamine pentaacetic acid (DTPA), nitrilotriacetic acid (NTA), phosphonic
acids, ethylenediaminetetramethylene-phosphonic acid (EDTMP),
diethylenetriaminepentamethylenephosphonic acid (DTPMP),
nitrilotrimethylenephosphonic acid (NTMP), polycarboxylic acids, gluconates, citrates,
polyacrylates, and polyaspartates or any combination thereof. A chelating agent may be
added to the bleaching liquor in an amount up to 10% by weight. As with all other
components of the bleaching liquor, chelating agents may be added separately or 
concurrently with one or more bleach liquor components at one or more chemical
addition points in the refining system. Chelating agents are thought to bind metals to
prevent the decomposition of hydrogen peroxide. In addition to chelating agents, the
bleaching liquor can also include bleaching aids in amounts of up to 10% by weight.
Bleaching aids further enhance the bleaching activity. Bleaching aids include adjuvants
such as Chip Aid® and HP Booster supplied from Constant Labs of Montreal, Canada.
Adjuvants such as chelating agents and bleaching aids can be applied to the methods of
brightening mechanical pulps according to the invention.</p>
    <p num="0025">The bleaching liquor can also contain a suitable amount of sodium silicate
(silicate) up to about 10% by weight. Silicate in these amounts can be applied to the
methods of brightening mechanical pulps according to the invention. Reference is made
to the aforementioned articles for detailed descriptions of the chemical activity provided
by chelating agents and silicates. Also, reference is made to <i>Pulp Bleaching: Principles
and Practice,</i> by Carlton W. Dence and Douglas W. Reeve, which is herein incorporated
by reference. Contrary to conventional wisdom, silicate need not be added as a
component to the bleach liquor when thermomechanically pulping wood chips according
to the present invention. It has been observed that when Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub> is substituted for
NaOH in amounts up to 100%, it is not required to include silicate, to produce pulps
having a brightness level similar to that which can be achieved when the alkali is NaOH
and silicate is added to the bleach liquor, and the pulp and bleach liquor are held for
about the same time and temperature conditions.</p>
    <p num="0026">While the composition of the bleaching liquor has been described as a mixture, it
should be readily apparent that the compounds of the bleach liquor can be added
separately in differing parts of the refining system of the mill or concurrently as a
mixture. For example, in one actual embodiment of a bleaching liquor that contains
Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub>, the Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub> is added at the first stage refiner, and any remaining alkali is
added downstream in the interstage section. This embodiment is applicable to the
methods for bleaching mechanical pulps according to the present invention. </p>
    <p num="0027">It is known that several variables will influence and play a role in a pulp's
brightness. Some of these variables are: consistency, residence time, temperature, and
alkalinity.</p>
    <p num="0028">The reaction shown as Eq. (1) above, is dependent on both pH and temperature.
Either raising the temperature or the pH will drive the reaction of equation (1) to the
right hand side producing more perhydroxyl species. According to the present
invention, the values of the aforementioned parameters such as time, temperature and
alkalinity have been determined to give greater brightness, improved yield, higher
residual values of hydrogen peroxide and lower oxalate, COD and BOD concentrations,
than is capable with 100% alkalinity derived solely from sodium hydroxide. The present
invention takes advantage of the greater pressure and temperature produced by the
refiners to arrive at the optimal value of the temperature and time parameters.
Furthermore, the time which the pulp is in contact with the bleaching liquor can be
adjusted by increasing or decreasing the rate of throughput of the pulp through the
refiners and ancillary equipment such as the blowline, bleach tower and the surge
vessels.</p>
    <p num="0029">Depending on the raw material wood species, the initial brightness and potential
brightness response of any mechanical or chemi-mechanical pulp will vary. The
brightness response of the pulp to peroxide bleaching is closely related to the method of
peroxide addition. For the most part, an increase in the peroxide dosage will lead to an
increase in the pulp brightness. However, while a high brightness level is a desirable
characteristic of pulps, the attainment of a high brightness level by dosing excessive
amounts of alkali must be balanced by the danger of overdosing, which causes a
darkening or yellowing of the pulp and reduces yield. Not enough alkalinity and
inefficient bleaching is likely to occur. Too much alkalinity and the pulp undergoes
yellowing, as well as inefficiently consuming the active perhydroxyl species by
competing side reactions and wasting hydrogen peroxide. The brightness of pulps is
measured by using TAPPI standards T452 and T525. According to the invention of 
providing methods for brightening mechanical pulps, a pulp brightness level can be
achieved when a buffering substitute alkali of soda ash or magnesium hydroxide or a
combination thereof is used, partially or wholly in place of sodium hydroxide, which is
equal to or higher than the pulp brightness level attained by using solely sodium
hydroxide. In one such method, the brightness of the pulp is increased by at least
1 brightness unit (ISO) in comparison to a method using only sodium hydroxide.</p>
    <p num="0030">It is believed that hydrogen peroxide bleaching can brighten with minimal
removal of the lignin from wood. Nevertheless, lignin and carbohydrates in mechanical
pulps are subject to attack by nucleophiles (HOO- and HO-), which is undesirable from a
yield standpoint. Nucleophiles are thought to be present in the bleaching liquor.
Nucleophiles can include the active oxygen species formed from hydrogen peroxide
decomposition. For example, the perhydroxyl ions can oxidize polysaccharide chains to
aldonic acids thereby degrading the cellulose molecules by what is called alkali
promoted "peeling" reactions. Furthermore, hydroxide ions can effect the release of
acetic acid in the pulp, leading to cellulose degradation. Also, acidic hemicelluloses
dissolve in alkaline bleach solutions. Many of the reactions occurring when an alkali
and hydrogen peroxide are brought in contact with pulp will reduce the total available
quantity of the cellulosic fibers, contributing to an overall loss of cellulose. Yield relates
to the amount of degradation of the carbohydrates of the cellulose fibers. Yield therefore
is a measure of the overall efficiency of the pulping process. A high yield is desirable,
which means that greater amounts of cellulose and lignin have undergone the refining
and bleaching processes without appreciable degradation. Yield is a measure of the dry
weight of the pulp produced by the process divided by the dry weight of the starting
material or wood chips, the resulting fraction being expressed as a percentage.
According to the invention of providing methods for brightening mechanical pulps, a
higher yield at the end of the method can be attained when a buffering substitute alkali
of soda ash or magnesium hydroxide or any combination thereof is used, which is higher
than the yield attained by using solely sodium hydroxide as the alkali. In one method, 
the yield is increased by at least one-half of a percent in comparison to a method using
only sodium hydroxide. In yet another method, the yield is greater than 95%. In the
case of magnesium hydroxide, the magnesium is believed to chelate heavy metals and
prevent radical formation and the associated cellulose degradation and yield loss.</p>
    <p num="0031">It is also known that conventional processes using solely sodium hydroxide and
hydrogen peroxide form compounds requiring oxidation to degrade into non-pollutant
forms. The quantities used to measure these compounds are called COD (chemical
oxygen demand) and BOD (biological oxygen demand). BOD and COD are theoretical
numbers signifying the amount of oxygen required by aerobic microorganisms to
transform the pollutants into harmless metabolites. If there are too many pollutants and
not enough oxygen in an effluent treatment system, the natural biological degradation of
these pollutants is hindered. Peroxide bleaching of mechanical pulps contributes to the
levels of COD and BOD of the mill plant effluent. BOD and COD levels are known to
be related to the amount of sodium hydroxide used in brightening mechanical pulps.
Compounds adding to high COD and BOD levels are made primarily of organics and
pulp residues, such as cellulose, hemicellulose, and lignin resulting from the pulp slurry
solution. According to the invention, both the COD and the BOD levels of the pulping
mill effluent streams can be reduced. COD is measured by the "HACH" test method,
while BOD is measured using SM 5210. According to the invention of providing
methods for brightening mechanical pulps, lower levels of COD and BOD can be
attained at the end of the method when a buffering substitute alkali such as soda ash or
magnesium hydroxide or any combination thereof is used partially or wholly in place of
sodium hydroxide compared to the COD and BOD levels attained by using solely
sodium hydroxide. In one method, the COD is reduced by at least 1 unit in kg/ODMT
(oven-dry metric ton) in comparison to a method using only sodium hydroxide. In
another method, the BOD is reduced by at least one-tenth of one unit in kg/ODMT in
comparison to a method using only sodium hydroxide. </p>
    <p num="0032">Consistency is a measure of the concentration of the pulp in the pulp slurry in
relation to water. Consistency also plays a role in the final brightness achieved
according to the present invention. The role of consistency has been, for the most part,
of lesser concern than either temperature or time in producing the desired perhydroxyl
ions necessary to achieve the bleaching effect in the present invention. However, in one
method of the present invention for bleaching mechanical pulps, the consistency of the
pulp is greater than 3%.</p>
    <p num="0033">It is well known that metals play a role in the undesirable decomposition of
hydrogen peroxide. A conventionally applied method to control decomposition of the
hydrogen peroxide is the treatment of the wood chips or pulp with chelating agents.
Chelating agents, such as the aforementioned agents, can be added to form organometallic
complexes, essentially binding to metals and removing them from the chemical
activity that would otherwise contribute to decomposition of hydrogen peroxide and
thus, the perhydroxyl ion species. Accordingly, the present invention takes advantage of
the chelating action of such agents. The bleaching liquor can include an amount of
silicate up to about 10% by weight. A second approach to minimizing hydrogen
peroxide decomposition is by the method of stabilizing the bleaching liquor. It is well
known that sodium silicate can have a stabilizing influence on alkaline bleaching with
hydrogen peroxide. Accordingly, the present invention also advantageously can include
a step for controlling the decomposition of the bleaching liquor whereby the addition of
sodium silicate (silicate) produces a stabilizing effect to minimize hydrogen peroxide
decomposition. The bleaching liquor can include an amount of silicate up to about 10%
by weight. It should be readily apparent that while the use of a chelating agent and
silicate is known in the pulping art, their optimal quantities in any particular application
are unknown since the many reactions and interactions between chemical species
ultimately affect the final brightness results. According to the present invention of
providing methods for bleaching mechanical pulps, the ranges of a chelating agent and 
silicate in the bleaching liquor for use in high temperature mechanical pulping
applications and for a specific alkalinity dosage has been determined.</p>
    <p num="0034">It is known that oxalate salts form detrimental deposits on mill bleaching
equipment. It is of special concern if bleaching is occurring in the refiners, since any
scale build up on the closely spaced rotating disks can cause premature failure and costly
equipment maintenance, as well as incomplete pulp processing. According to the
invention of providing methods for bleaching mechanical pulps, the amount of oxalic
acid that is produced at the end of the method, when a buffering substitute alkali such as
soda ash or magnesium hydroxide or any combination thereof is used partially or wholly
in place of sodium hydroxide, is lower than the oxalic acid amount produced when using
solely sodium hydroxide. In one method, the oxalate concentration of undiluted pressate
is reduced by at least 10 mg/l, in comparison to a method using only sodium hydroxide.
Accordingly, the present invention provides benefits by reducing the amount of scaling
associated with bleaching. Scaling is controlled by reduced amounts of oxalate at a
given brightness, and by the role magnesium plays in reducing oxalate production.
Oxalate concentration is measured using TAPP1 method T699.</p>
    <p num="0035">Residual hydrogen peroxide is an indication of the efficiency of the hydrogen
peroxide effect in bleaching pulp. A reduction in the initial hydrogen peroxide dosing
can also be attained if a final brightness level is desired. Hydrogen peroxide residual is
defined as the amount of peroxide left unconsumed at the end of the bleaching process in
comparison to the amount of hydrogen peroxide added to the process. Accordingly, the
more residual peroxide remaining for a given quantity of pulp throughput, the more
residual peroxide available for recycle back to the process or, alternatively, the
throughput of the pulp can be increased to make use of residual peroxide or the hydrogen
peroxide dosage can be initially reduced and still provide a brightness that is at least or
less than the brightness that can be achieved by a method using only sodium hydroxide,
but with a higher level of hydrogen peroxide. According to the present invention of
providing methods for bleaching mechanical pulps, a higher level of residual hydrogen 
peroxide can be attained at the end of the method when a buffering substitute alkali such
as soda ash or magnesium hydroxide or any combination thereof is used partially or
wholly in place of sodium hydroxide, compared to the level of residual peroxide attained
by using solely sodium hydroxide. In one method, the residual peroxide level is
increased by at least 0.5%, in comparison to a method using only sodium hydroxide. In
another method, the residual peroxide level is greater than 0.7%. Residual peroxide is
measured using iodometric titration or EM science: reflectoquant peroxide test.</p>
    <p num="0036">Implementation of the present invention of providing methods for bleaching
mechanical pulps will now be described with reference to specific embodiments and the
FIGURES.</p>
    <p num="0037">Referring now to FIGURE 2, a schematic representation of a thermomechanical
two stage refining system of a TMP mill suitable for carrying out the present invention
of providing methods for bleaching mechanical pulps is illustrated. Two stage refers to a
process having at least one refiner operating above atmospheric pressure and at least one
refiner operating at or about atmospheric pressure, so as to have an interstage section.
Interstage refers to the section of the pulping system, including any associated
equipment or the like, beginning with the exit of the first stage refiner and ending at the
entrance to the second stage refiner. It should be readily appreciated that the
configuration of a pulping system of a mill may have more or less unit operations as the
one which is being presented herein. For illustration purposes, some ancillary
equipment in the pulping system has been omitted. Still for illustration purposes, some
ancillary equipment preceding or following the pulping system depicted in FIGURE 2
has also been omitted.</p>
    <p num="0038">Wood chips suitable for use as cellulosic material in the present invention can be
derived from softwood tree species such as, but not limited to: fir (such as Douglas fir
and Balsam fir), pine (such as Eastern white pine and Loblolly pine), spruce (such as
White spruce), larch (such as Eastern larch), cedar, and hemlock (such as Eastern and
Western hemlock). Examples of hardwood species from which pulp useful as a starting 
material in the present invention can be derived include, but are not limited to: acacia,
alder (such as Red alder and European black alder) aspen (such as Quaking aspen),
beech, birch, oak (such as White oak), gum trees (such as eucalyptus and Sweetgum),
poplar (such as Balsam poplar, Eastern cottonwood, Black cottonwood and Yellow
poplar), gmelina, maple (such as Sugar maple, Red maple, Silver maple and Bigleaf
maple) and Eucalyptus.</p>
    <p num="0039">Wood chips, that are produced in another area of the mill, or transported from
outside the mill, or from whatever source, are stored in bins or silos 200. The chips are
washed in a washer 202 prior to refining, followed by dewatering in a dewatering
screen 204. Washing removes any grit or debris present in the chips which could
damage the equipment and cause premature wear.</p>
    <p num="0040">From the dewatering screen 204, the chips are moved through the process
equipment by a rotary feed valve 206. The feed valve empties onto a conveyor 208,
which can be a screw or a belt conveyor. However, any other suitable conveying
apparatus can be used. From the conveyor 208, the chips are fed into a preheater 210.
In this embodiment, the preheater 210 is a unit operation which uses recovered
steam 248 from a downstream cyclone 218 and steam from a makeup line 250 to heat
the chips prior to feeding into a first stage refiner 216. Chips are moved from the exit of
the preheater 210 to the refiner 216 by the conveyor 220. Heating softens the chips
which conserves energy in the refining stages. The first stage refiner 216 is a pressure
refiner which can operate in the range of from slightly above atmospheric pressure to
several tens of pounds per square inch pressure. Typical operating pressure is about 10
to 40 psi, but may be higher or lower. A refiner is commonly used in mechanical pulp
mills. A refiner is a machine that mechanically macerates and/or cuts the wood into its
constituent fibers, in essence, liberating the cellulosic fibers. There are two principal
types of refiners: a disk refiner and a conical refiner. For a general discussion of
refiners used in mechanical pulping, reference is made to the <i>Handbook of Pulping and
Papermaking</i>, 2nd Ed., Christopher J. Biermann, which is herein incorporated by 
reference. Refining adds a substantial amount of heat energy from friction to the wood
chips, which is emitted in the form of steam in downstream equipment and results in a
temperature rise in the ground wood or pulp. The steam is collected downstream of the
first stage refiner 216 in the cyclone 218. The pulp and steam travel through a
blowline 224 which connects the exit of the first stage refiner 216 to the cyclone 218.
The steam collected in the cyclone 218 is recycled to the preheater 210 for energy
conservation purposes. The pulp stream 246 exiting from the cyclone 218 can be mixed
with the recycled pulp rejects stream 262 and fed to a second stage refiner 222 via the
conveyor 258. Vessels 226 and 230 provide surge and storage capacity for any pulp
rejects 238, 240, 262 coming from the conveyor 258. While rejects 262 are shown being
recycled to second stage refiner 222, rejects 262 may be pumped to other sections of
pulp mill or discarded. Forward pulp in line 236 from second stage refiner 222, is
further processed and dewatered in vessels 228, 232 and 234. Line 242 from vessel 232
carries recycled pulp rejects to second stage refiner 222 via reject vessel 230 and
conveyor 258. The second stage refiner 222 is normally operated at about atmospheric
pressure. The pulp from the second stage refiner 222 is fed into the vessel 228 where it
is then pumped into one or a plurality of vessels 228, 232 and 234 and unit operations
equipment for further processing which can include screening, cleaning and dewatering.
The pulp 264 leaving the refining system, and produced according to the invention, may
be further treated and/or processed in other sections of the pulp mill (not shown). The
stream of rejects 238 taken from the feed 246 to the second stage refiner 222 is sent to a
surge vessel 226 and then on to a dewatering vessel 230. From the dewatering
vessel 230, the rejects are fed back to the second stage refiner 222.</p>
    <p num="0041">Referring again to FIGURE 2, a plurality of chemical addition points 260, 261,
262, and 263 are shown. A first chemical addition point 260, 261, and 263 can be before
or at the primary refiner and a second chemical addition point 262 can be at a location
which is interstage of the first 216 and second 222 refiners including blocks 218, 258,
226, 230, and all lines connected to such blocks. As used herein, when referring to 
"chemical addition at or in the primary refiner" means any block prior to or including the
primary refiner 216 in FIGURE 2 and prior to or including the blocks 324 and 326 in
FIGURE 3. According to the invention of providing methods for bleaching mechanical
pulps, the bleaching liquor can be introduced in the first stage refiner 216 at 260 or at the
interstage section between the first refiner 216 and the second refiner 222 at 262.
Alternatively, one or a plurality of components of the bleaching liquor can be introduced
at the first stage refiner 216 or preceding blocks and one or a plurality of components of
the bleaching liquor can be introduced at the interstage section 224 or in any
combination thereof. It should be pointed out that the interstage addition point can be at
any vessel or line from the exit of the first stage refiner 216 to the entrance to the second
stage refiner 222, including the units 218, 258, 226, 230 and the lines 224, 246, 262,
238, 240 and 266.</p>
    <p num="0042">It should also be readily apparent that more or less units such as tanks, filters,
vessels, first and second stage refiners, cyclones, pumps, conveyors, and valves can be
used in a variety of combinations to provide for a two-stage mechanical pulping system.</p>
    <p num="0043">Other thermomechanical pulping processes are described in United States Patent
No. 4,718,980 to Lowrie et al., which is herein incorporated by reference. All two stage
mechanical pulping processes can be modified according to the present invention by the
addition of a bleaching liquor at the first stage refiner and/or interstage and for the stated
process conditions, to advantageously produce pulps having a higher brightness, higher
yields, higher residual peroxide and less oxalate, COD and BOD production.</p>
    <p num="0044">Referring now to FIGURE 3, an actual embodiment of a refining system of a mill
with interstage and refiner chemical addition points according to the present invention is
illustrated. Wood chips are stored in three adjacent silos 300a, 300b and 300c. The silos
feed into a chip washing apparatus 302 where the chips are washed free of dirt and other
undesirable constituents. A dewatering screen 304 separates the water from the chips.
The chips are then moved by a rotary feeder 306 through a blow line (not shown) into a
chip cyclone 310 and surge bin 312. The chip cyclone 310 and surge bin 312 can be 
made into a single piece of equipment or may be two distinct pieces separated by a line.
From the surge bin 312, the chips are then weighed in the weight belt 314 and metered
by metering screw 316 to feed into a pre-heater 320. The pre-heater 320 operates on
steam to raise the temperature of the wood chips to soften them. The exit of the
pre-heater 320 is connected to the cross screw conveyor 322. Prior to the entrance of the
pre-heater 320, a valve 318 is present to control the wood chip supply. The screw
conveyor 322 feeds the primary refiner 324. The pressure in the primary refiner can
vary about 11 to 40 psi, but suitably operates about 30 to 33 psi, and at a consistency of
about 10% to 50%, suitably about 23% to 45% and at a temperature of about 85°C to
about 160°C. Magnesium hydroxide, soda ash or alternatively sodium hydroxide can be
stored in the vessel 326 and metered by metering pump (not shown) into the first stage
refiner 324 or preceding blocks. Refining introduces substantial heat into the chips
which is given off as steam 330 in the pressurized separating cyclone 328 exiting the
first stage refiner 324. The waste steam 330 can be used in the digestor 320 or in other
heat exchangers throughout the mill. The ground wood or pulp is moved from the first
pressurized cyclone 328 to a second atmospheric cyclone 338 by blow unit 332 where
further steam 340 is generated by the drop in pressure. The interstage section between
the first refiner 324 and the second refiner 362 can also be used as an addition point 336
for one, some or all of the bleaching liquor components. Alkali, oxidants, silicates and
chelating agents can be introduced into the blow line 334 at 336 between the first
pressured cyclone 328 to the second atmospheric cyclone 338. However, other addition
points in the interstage section are alternate embodiments. Alternate interstage addition
points are blocks 326, 328, 332, 338, 344, 346, 348, 350, 354, 358, 390, 384, 380, and
all lines into and leaving the blocks. Hydrogen peroxide 342 is introduced at the bottom
of the atmospheric cyclone 338. However, other alternates may have the addition point
at any location throughout the interstage section. From the atmospheric cyclone 340, the
ground wood or pulp is moved by screw conveyors 344 and 346 into a peroxide
tower 348 where the ground wood or pulp undergoes chemical activity to further 
brighten the ground wood or pulp. Average residence time can be adjusted at this stage
from about 2 minutes to about 180 minutes or any time in between. The temperature can
remain substantially at or about the exit temperature of cyclone 328. However, the
temperature is expected to stay within the aforementioned ranges. Longer residence
times can be achieved by increasing the size of the bleach tower 348. It should also be
apparent that sample taps (not shown) can be placed at any location beginning with the
first chemical addition point at or preceding the first stage refiner 324 to the second stage
refiner 362 to sample the pulp after about 1 minute of residence time and throughout the
process. From the peroxide tower 348, the pulp enters a dilution chest 350, where the
consistency of the pulp is reduced and chemical activity is slowed. The pulp is then fed
into a press 354 and then onto a second screw conveyor 358 and a second refiner 362.
The second refiner operates at about atmospheric pressure and at a consistency of about
13% to 40% and within one of the aforementioned temperature ranges.</p>
    <p num="0045">The pulp from the second refiner 362 empties into a refined stocked chest 364.
From the refined stocked chest 364, the pulp 368 is pumped to surge chest 366. From
surge chest 366, the pulp 372 is sent to primary screening unit 370. The pulp 372 is
divided into two streams 376 and 378 at the primary screens 370. The accepts pulp
stream 376 is sent to the dewatering screen 374. From the dewatering screen 374,
water 398 is transferred to the white water chest (not shown). The finished pulp
product 396 is sent to storage tanks 394. The rejects stream 378 from the primary
screening unit 370 is sent to the primary screen reject chest 380. From the primary
screen reject chest 380, the pulp is sent to a secondary screening unit 384. The
secondary screening unit includes a rejects stream 388 and an accepts stream 386. The
secondary screen rejects 388 are sent to the vessel 390 and further recycled to the
dilution vessel 350 to mix with newly refined pulp 352 from the refiner 324. The
accepts stream 386 enters surge chest 366 to be recycled again through primary
screening unit 370. The rejects stream 392 thus undergoes further refining in secondary
refiner 362. </p>
    <heading>EXAMPLE 1</heading>
    <p num="0046">NORPAC chips (70% hemlock/30% pine) were refined at Andritz pilot research
facility in Springfield, Ohio. A simplified schematic diagram showing several unit
operations taking place in a generic TMP unit is illustrated in FIGURE 17. It is to be
appreciated that each TMP process may have more or less unit operations, before or
following any of the blocks of the simplified process of FIGURE 17, including but not
limited to screens, washers, dryers, conveyors, pumps, and vessels. The pilot scale plant
used in carrying out the Example 1 included at least the unit blocks of FIGURE 17. The
pilot plant includes, among other units, unit operations for screening the wood chips 700,
presteaming the chips in block 702, a first refiner 704, a cyclone 706, a second
refiner 708, and a press unit 710. A press unit 710 can be any suitable device to remove
liquids from a pulp, including manually squeezing a pulp sample. No temperature
measuring devices were installed in the pilot facility; however, it is estimated that the
temperature at the first refiner was greater than 100°C, since the refiner was operated
above atmospheric pressure. The temperature of the second refiner was estimated to be
about 100°C or greater, since the refiner operates near atmospheric pressure, also the
pulp can retain much of the heat generated in the first refiner. It should be understood
that the pilot scale plant may have more or less units than an otherwise, full scale
commercial facility.</p>
    <p num="0047">A 36-inch pressurized double disk refiner was used for the primary refining
stage. Bleach liquor components were added in the first stage refiner and/or in the
downstream interstage blowline. The bleaching liquor included about 3% peroxide of
the 60:40 water to peroxide mixture, about 0.3% DTPA, and about 2% silicate. A total
alkalinity to peroxide ratio of about 0.7 was used. On an alkalinity basis one pound
NaOH has the same alkalinity as 0.73 pounds Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub> and 1.31 pound Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>. The
remainder of the bleaching liquor was made up of water and the alkali chemicals varied
and applied according to the flow sheet schematic of FIGURE 4 and Table 1 to produce
a plurality of bleach liquor compositions for each run. After primary refining, pulp 
samples were taken from the primary refiner cyclone and placed in 55 gallon drums
where they were held for up to 60 minutes of reaction time. These comprised the eleven
runs depicted in Table 1. The Example used a drum as an interstage bleach vessel 348
which is representative of the interstage reaction capable of being carried out by the
processes of FIGURES 2 and 3.</p>
    <p num="0048">FIGURE 4 shows a decision diagram indicating how the data of Table 1 was
collected. In block 600, a chip sample containing cellulose is provided. In block 602,
the chip sample is pre-steamed for about 150 seconds at about 141°C. In block 604, a
decision is made whether or not to add alkali at the primary refiner. If the answer in
block 604 is yes, any remaining bleach components are added at the blowline or
interstage section in block 606. If the answer in block 604 is no, all the bleach
components are added at the blowline or interstage section in block 608. Approximately
one gallon lab samples were taken from the 55 gallon drums and tested for brightness at
intervals of 2, 15, 30, and 45 minutes. The lab samples were quenched and diluted to
1% to stop the reaction and make a brightness pad. This data is presented in Table 1. At
60 minutes of reaction time, a sample was pulled directly from the 55 gallon drum to
measure brightness. The brightness, residual and yield is presented in the Table and
FIGURES 6, 7, 11, and 12, from these samples. The drum samples, as opposed to the
lab samples, were better able to maintain temperature due to the size of the samples.</p>
    <p num="0049">Block 612 shows runs 2A, 2B, 3, 4, and 5 had alkali added at the primary refiner.
In block 610, these runs are allowed to react for about 60 minutes, with lab samples
being pulled and measured for brightness at 2, 15, 30, and 45 minute intervals,
brightness was measured at 60 minutes using the drum sample. Block 616 shows runs 2,
3A, 4A, 6, and 7 did not have alkali added at the primary refiner. These runs had a
reaction time of about 60 minutes. Lab samples were pulled and measured for
brightness at 2, 15, 30, and 45 minute intervals, brightness was measured at 60 minutes
using the drum samples. Block 620 shows that run 1 had components added at the
blowline or interstage; however, run 1 did not include alkali as part of the bleach liquor. 
Therefore, in block 618, run 1 is, nevertheless, held for 60 minutes without any
appreciable reaction.</p>
    <p num="0050">In block 622, the drum samples are divided for secondary refining at three load
levels. The drum samples were refined with any residual chemicals and pH leftover
from the bleaching reaction, so that the pulps continued to react during secondary
refining. The conditions at the secondary refiner were adjusted to provide further
reaction times of about 65, 75, and 90 minutes of bleaching. In block 624, a thermal
mechanical pulp sample after secondary refining is obtained for 65, 75, or 90 minutes.
Total solids, oxalate content, COD, and BOD were measured using pressate samples
from the lowest freeness pulp after secondary refining corresponding to the 90 minute
sample.</p>
    <p num="0051">Referring to Table 1, the summary results of the brightness measurements for
eleven runs is presented at varying chemical concentrations and times. Runs appear in
rows beginning on the left side of the table and are read across; there are eleven
(11) runs. Runs 2a and 2b had sodium hydroxide added at the primary refiner. Run 2b
had silicate as well added at the primary refiner. Runs 3, 4 and 5 had Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub>, added
to the primary refiner. Conditions are for 3% by weight hydrogen peroxide. Brightness
was measured against time. The samples were taken from the blow line, reference
numeral 334 in FIGURE 3. The highest brightness level for a pulp after two minutes of
bleaching is a level of 55 brightness units by run 3, with about 40% of the alkali being
magnesium added at the primary refiner with the balance being sodium hydroxide added
interstage. After fifteen minutes, the highest brightness level for a pulp is
57.7 brightness units from the same run. After thirty minutes, the highest brightness
level for a pulp is 57.9 brightness units, once again from the same run. After forty-five
minutes, the highest brightness level for a pulp is 58.2 units, achieved by run 7, with
100% of the alkali being soda ash added interstage.</p>
    <p num="0052">Brightness after sixty minutes of reaction time is also shown. The highest
brightness level for a pulp after 60 minutes of bleaching time is 62.5 units by run 3 with 
40% magnesium hydroxide added at the primary refiner and 60% sodium hydroxide
added interstage. The pH range for the pulp samples 3, 3a, 4, 4a, 5, 6, and 7, having
some amount of sodium hydroxide substitution at sixty minutes of bleaching is from 8 to
8.3. The residual hydrogen peroxide achieved with a substitute alkali is between 1.13%
and 1.52% after sixty minutes of reaction time for the same samples; the highest residual
for a substituted alkali was 1.52% for 100% soda ash added interstage. However, the
highest residual value was 2.24% for 100% sodium hydroxide and silicate, added at the
primary refiner.</p>
    <p num="0053">Brightness after the secondary refiner was also measured. The highest brightness
level for a pulp after about 65 minutes of reaction time was 66.1 brightness units by
run 3, with 40% magnesium hydroxide added at the primary refiner and 60% sodium
hydroxide added interstage. The highest brightness level for a pulp after 75 minutes is
67.4, attained by run 4 with 50% magnesium hydroxide added at the primary refiner and
50% soda ash added interstage, and also attained by run 7 with 100% soda ash added
interstage. The highest brightness level for a pulp after about 90 minutes of reaction
time is 69.5 achieved by run 7 with 100% soda ash added interstage. The final pH
varied between 7.6 and 8.2 for the pulp samples 3, 3a, 4, 4a, 5, 6, and 7, containing
substitute alkali compounds. The hydrogen peroxide residual varied between 1.09% and
1.32% for the same runs containing some amount of substitute alkali. The highest
peroxide residual level of 1.32% was achieved by run 7, with 100% soda ash added
interstage. The highest residual recorded at 60 minutes was 2.24% for 100% sodium
hydroxide and silicate, added at the primary refiner. <img id="img-00280001" orientation="unknown" wi="134" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00280001.tif" inline="no" he="229"/></p>
    <heading>RESULTS</heading>
    <p num="0054">The sample data are representative of the results possible by a mill process.
The mill process of FIGURE 3 dilutes and slows the bleaching reaction in block 350
before the pulp is fed to the secondary refiners. In the Example conducted according
to the method of bleaching mechanical pulps, the pulp was not diluted nor was the
reaction quenched before the second refiner. The pulp was refined with the residual
chemicals and the pH of the bleaching reaction conditions. The data suggests that
significant efficiency is possible if the reaction was not quenched after the interstage
bleach tower 348.</p>
    <p num="0055">Refining energy was about the same among the runs, except that there was a
considerable advantage of about 15% in energy requirements of interstage treatments
over run 1, the unbleached control. Runs 2a and 2b, when sodium hydroxide was
added to the primary refiner, showed slightly higher energy requirements over the
other treatments. The energy requirements are depicted in FIGURE 5.</p>
    <p num="0056">FIGURE 6 shows the interstage brightness values after about 60 minutes of
bleaching reaction for each of the 11 runs of Table 1, listed vertically in rows. The
pulp of run 2 with 100% sodium hydroxide added interstage had a brightness of 59.4.
By changing to a bleach liquor with a substitute alkali having 40% to 100%
Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub> added at the primary refiner, a change in brightness from the previous
run 2 resulted in a brightness increase of about 3.0 to about 3.1 points. Pulp
samples 2a, 2b, 3, 4, and 5 were runs where an alkali chemical (either NaOH,
Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub> or NaOH with silicate) was added to the primary refiner. Comparison of
samples 3 with 3a, and 4 with 4a, shows the brightness increase is significantly
reduced when magnesium hydroxide is added to the interstage blow line and not at
the primary refiner. However, the opposite is true for NaOH. See runs 2 and 2a.
However, an increase is noted when silicate was also added with NaOH at the
primary refiner. See run 2b. The pulp of runs 6 and 7 containing soda ash also
resulted in a brightness increase of as much as 2.5 points in comparison to run 2.</p>
    <p num="0057">FIGURE 7 shows the differences in brightness levels of pulp in comparison
to the pulp sample of run 2 when 100% of the alkali is NaOH added interstage. </p>
    <p num="0058">FIGURE 8 shows the peroxide residual results. These peroxide residual
values are from the 60 minute samples. The pulp of run 2 with 100% sodium
hydroxide added interstage had a peroxide residual of 0.66%. All of the runs 2a-7,
having alkali substitution resulted in an increase of 70-130% larger peroxide residual
values than run 2 which means a range of about 1.13% to about 1.52%. The
increased peroxide residual represents an opportunity for further bleaching if
sufficient time and temperature were available. However, 100% NaOH added at the
primary refiner, like in run 2a or 2b gave the highest residual values of 1.81% and
2.24%, respectively. The bleach liquor run 2b also included silicate added at the
primary refiner.</p>
    <p num="0059">FIGURE 9 shows the percent increase of runs 2-7, in costs of bleach
chemicals for brightness point per ton in comparison to a control with no chemicals,
run 1. Bleach chemical cost is lowest for the magnesium hydroxide containing
bleach liquors of runs 3 and 5. Using an alternative substitute alkali reduces the cost
of bleaching by allowing the use of less bleach chemical to reach a given brightness
level.</p>
    <p num="0060">FIGURE 10 shows the percent increase of runs 2-7, in bleach chemical costs
of 2% and 3% peroxide in comparison to a control with no chemicals, run 1.
Momentarily, referring back to FIGURE 6, runs 2, 3, and 6 at 3% peroxide showed
an increase in brightness of about 3 points which can translate to a reduced peroxide
application going from 3% to 2% hydrogen peroxide application with an attendant
cost savings by using Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub>. Since soda ash is generally more expensive than
magnesium hydroxide, the cost savings are somewhat less, but still significant if soda
ash is used.</p>
    <p num="0061">Yield, total solids, oxalate content, COD and BOD, and were measured on
pulp samples leaving a press unit and being the lowest freeness pulp after secondary
refining for each of the runs. The pressate samples are undiluted. The total bleach
time was about 1.5 hours for these pulp samples. Pulp yield values are shown in
FIGURE 11. The pulp yield value was calculated from pressed bleach liquor solids
after the weight of chemicals is subtracted. Yield values of pulps when using bleach 
liquors containing soda ash are given with and without retention of CO<sub>2</sub>, as it is
possible that some or all of the CO<sub>2</sub> present in the soda ash is released during
bleaching. CO<sub>2</sub> may evolve from the breakdown of Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> caused by the high
temperatures. The calculations of yield, therefore, assume both a breakdown of
Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> into CO<sub>2</sub> (i.e., loss) and with no breakdown (i.e., retain). The pulp yield
when using the bleach liquor of run 2 with 100% NaOH added interstage was 95.6%.
The highest pulp yields were attained with bleach liquor having 50% Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub> and
50% NA<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>, at 98.0 and 98.1, respectively, assuming retention of CO<sub>2</sub>. Only a
slight improvement was noted when Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub> was added at the primary refiner. The
highest yield for a bleach liquor with 100% Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub> is 97.8, added at the primary
refiner.</p>
    <p num="0062">The change in pulp yield from the control of run 2 is shown in FIGURE 12.
For all runs with some degree of substitute alkali, an increase in yield was realized.
Run 7, taking into consideration CO<sub>2</sub> losses, was the only run which showed a
decrease in yield compared to run 2. There was an increase in pulp yield of up to
2.2% for substitution with magnesium hydroxide of up to 100% added at the primary
refiner. The bleach liquors containing soda ash, runs 6 and 7, showed from 0-1%
increase in yield. The yield increases are consistent with the decreases seen in
COD and BOD. Combination runs 4 and 4a, of 50% magnesium hydroxide and 50%
soda ash realized the greatest increases in yield, when not taking into consideration
any CO<sub>2</sub> losses. The highest yield increase of 2.5 was seen with run 4a, a 50%
Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub>, 50% Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> mixture, where chemicals were added interstage, for an
overall pulp yield of 98.1.</p>
    <p num="0063">FIGURE 13 shows the oxalate content of the undiluted pressate samples for
each run. The undiluted pressate from the unbleached sample, run 1, had an oxalate
content of 17 milligrams per liter, while the sample from run 2 with 100% NaOH
added interstage had an oxalate content of 200 milligrams per liter. Generally,
oxalate is 5-20% lower for the substituted alkali pulps, with the exception of run 5
with 100% Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub>, added at the primary refiner, which was about even with the
control of run 2. The lowest oxalate was recorded for run 2a, the sample treated with 
100% NaOH, added to the primary refiner, at 140 mg/L. The lowest oxalate levels
for runs with a substitute alkali are runs 3a, 6, and 7, all with an oxalate level of
160 mg/L. These were pulps treated with 40% Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub>, 50% Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>, and 100%
Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>, where none of the chemical is added at the primary refiner but at the
interstage section. The reduction of peroxide use through increased pulp brightness
will provide additional decreases in oxalate.</p>
    <p num="0064">FIGURE 14 shows the COD values of the samples for each run. The pulp of
run 2 showed a COD level of 97.5 kg/ODMT, for 100% NaOH added interstage.
There was a decrease in the COD of up to 18% for the runs having substituted alkali
bleach liquors in comparison to sample 2, with 100% NaOH. The runs having
magnesium-only bleach liquors, samples from runs 3, 3a, and 5, showed a decrease
of up to 15% in comparison with sample 2, while the runs having soda ash-only
bleach liquors, samples from runs 6 and 7, showed a decrease of up to 6% in
comparison with sample 2, and the runs having combination magnesium hydroxide
and soda ash bleach liquors, samples 4 and 4a, showed a decrease in COD of about
17-18% in comparison to sample 2. The lowest COD measurement was for run
sample 4 with an overall COD level of 79.6 kg/ODMT for a bleach liquor having
50% Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub> and 50% Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>, where Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub> is added at the primary refiner
and Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> is added interstage.</p>
    <p num="0065">FIGURE 15 shows the change in BOD of the samples for each run. The pulp
of run 2 showed a BOD level of 32.8 kg/ODMT, for 100% NaOH added interstage.
There was a decrease in BOD by as much as up to 21% for the samples using
substituted alkali bleach liquors in comparison to sample 2 with 100% NaOH added
interstage. The samples using magnesium hydroxide-only bleach liquors, run
samples 3, 3a, and 5, showed a percent decrease in BOD of about 3% to about
14.9%, in comparison to run sample 2 with 100% NaOH added interstage. The
samples using soda ash-only bleach liquors, run samples 6 and 7, showed a percent
decrease in BOD of about 3% to about 21%, in comparison to run sample 2 with
100% NaOH added interstage. The combination bleach liquor run samples 4 and 4a,
showed a percent decrease in BOD of about 14.9%, in comparison to run sample 2 
with 100% NaOH. The lowest BOD reading for a pulp was recorded for sample 7,
using 100% Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>, added interstage, at 25.9 kg/ODMT. A reduction in peroxide
use will result in further decreases in BOD.</p>
    <p num="0066">While the preferred embodiment of the invention has been illustrated and
described, it will be appreciated that various changes can be made therein without
departing from the spirit and scope of the invention.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A method of brightening mechanical pulp, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>providing cellulosic materials having an initial brightness level,</claim-text><claim-text>introducing the cellulosic materials to a refining system for conversion to a
pulp,</claim-text><claim-text>providing a bleaching liquor to the refining system, wherein the liquor
comprises hydrogen peroxide and alkali, wherein up to 100% of the alkali is
Mg(OH)2, Na2CO3, or a combination thereof;</claim-text><claim-text>holding the pulp and the bleaching liquor at a temperature in the range of
about 85°C to about 160°C for a time of about 2 to about 180 minutes; and</claim-text><claim-text>increasing the brightness of the pulp at least to a brightness level which can
be obtained if 100% of the alkali is NaOH and the pulp and bleaching liquor are held
at about the same time and temperature conditions.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 1, further comprising the step of:
<claim-text><claim-text>increasing the pH of the pulp to within the range of about 9 to about 10.5.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 1, wherein the temperature is greater than 100°C
to about 160°C.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 3, wherein the time is from about 10 minutes to
less than about 180 minutes.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 3, wherein the time is from greater than
60 minutes to less than 120 minutes.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 3, wherein the time is from greater than
2 minutes to less than 60 minutes.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 1, wherein the bleaching liquor comprises an
amount of alkali which is the equivalent of about 10 to about 100 pounds of NaOH
per ton of pulp on a dry basis.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 7, wherein about 40% to about 100% of the
alkali is Mg(OH)2.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 7, wherein about 50% to about 100% of the
alkali is Na2CO3.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 1, wherein the bleaching liquor comprises
hydrogen peroxide in an amount of about 10 to about 200 pounds per ton of pulp on a
dry basis.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 1, wherein the consistency of the pulp is greater
than about 3%.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 1, wherein the ratio of alkali to hydrogen
peroxide is about 0.25 to about 3 on a weight basis.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 1, wherein the bleaching liquor further
comprises a chelating agent in an amount up to about 10% by weight.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 13, wherein the chelating agent is selected from
the group consisting of aminopolycarboxylic acids (APCA),
ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA), diethylene trixamine pentaacetic acid
(DTPA), nitrilotriacetic acid (NTA), phosphonic acids,
ethylenediaminetetramethylene-phosphonic acid (EDTMP),
diethylenetriaminepentamethylenephosphonic acid (DTPMP),
nitrilotrimethylenephosphonic acid (NTMP), polycarboxylic acids, gluconates,
citrates, polyacrylates, and polyaspartates or any combination thereof.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 1, wherein the bleaching liquor further
comprises silicate in an amount up to about 10% by weight.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 1, wherein the brightness of the pulp is
increased by at least about 1 brightness unit (ISO).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 1, wherein the refining system defines a first
and second refiner and an interstage section between the first and second refiner.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="18">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 17, wherein an amount of alkali is provided at
the first refiner.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="19">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 18, wherein the alkali is Mg(OH)2.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="20">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 17, wherein an amount of alkali is provided at
the interstage section.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="21">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 20, wherein the alkali is Na2CO3.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="22">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 1, defining an ending residual peroxide level,
wherein the residual peroxide level is increased in comparison to the residual
peroxide level obtained if 100% of the alkali is NaOH and the pulp and bleaching
liquor are held at about the same time and temperature conditions.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="23">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 22, wherein the residual peroxide level of the
pulp is increased by at least about 0.5%.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="24">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 1, wherein the residual peroxide level is greater
than about 0.7%.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="25">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 1, defining an ending pulp yield, wherein the
pulp yield is increased in comparison to the pulp yield obtained if 100% of the alkali
is NaOH and the pulp and bleaching liquor are held at about the same time and
temperature conditions.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="26">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 25, wherein the pulp yield is increased by at
least about one-half of a percent.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="27">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 1, wherein the pulp yield is greater than about
95.9%.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="28">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 1, defining an ending oxalate concentration
wherein the oxalate concentration is decreased in comparison to the oxalate
concentration obtained if 100% of the alkali is NaOH and the pulp and bleaching
liquor are held at about the same time and temperature conditions.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="29">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 1, wherein the oxalate concentration of
undiluted pressate is reduced by at least about 10 mg/l.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="30">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 1, defining an ending COD level wherein the
COD is decreased in comparison with the COD if 100% of the alkali is NaOH and
the pulp and bleaching liquor are held at about the same time and temperature
conditions.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="31">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 30, wherein the COD is reduced by at least
about 1 unit in kg/ODMT.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="32">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 1, defining an ending BOD level, wherein the
BOD is decreased in comparison with the BOD if 100% of the alkali is NaOH and
the pulp and bleaching liquor are held at about the same time and temperature
conditions.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="33">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 32, wherein the BOD is reduced by at least
about one-tenth of one unit in kg/ODMT.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="34">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 1, wherein the refining system defines a first
and second refiner, wherein the bleaching reaction is not quenched before the second
refiner.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="35">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 1, wherein the bleaching liquor further
comprises a bleaching aid in an amount up to about 10% by weight.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="36">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 1, wherein the bleaching liquor comprises a
charge of hydrogen peroxide that is about the equivalent of 3% by weight of a
solution of 60:40 water to hydrogen peroxide.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="37">
      <claim-text>The method of Claim 1, wherein the bleaching liquor comprises a
charge of hydrogen peroxide that is about the equivalent of 2% by weight of a
solution of 60:40 water to hydrogen peroxide.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="38">
      <claim-text>A method of brightening mechanical pulps, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>providing cellulosic materials having an initial brightness level,</claim-text><claim-text>introducing the cellulosic materials to a refining system for conversion to a
pulp,</claim-text><claim-text>providing a bleaching liquor to the refining system, wherein the liquor
comprises a first amount hydrogen peroxide and an alkali, wherein up to 100% of the
alkali is Mg(OH)2, Na2CO3, or a combination thereof;</claim-text><claim-text>providing the pulp with the bleaching liquor at a temperature in the range of
about 85°C to about 160°C for a time of about 2 to about 180 minutes; and</claim-text><claim-text>increasing the brightness of the pulp about equal to or less than a brightness
level which can be obtained if the bleaching liquor comprises a second amount of
hydrogen peroxide which is greater than the first amount, wherein 100% of the alkali
is NaOH, and the pulp and bleaching liquor are held under about the same
temperature and time conditions.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="39">
      <claim-text>The pulp made by the method of Claim 1, having a brightness of at
least about 55 ISO.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="40">
      <claim-text>The pulp of Claim 39, having a brightness of about 55 to about
69.5 ISO.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="41">
      <claim-text>A method of brightening mechanical pulp, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>providing cellulosic materials having an initial brightness level,</claim-text><claim-text>introducing the cellulosic materials to a refining system for conversion to a
pulp,</claim-text><claim-text>providing a bleaching liquor to the refining system, wherein the liquor
comprises hydrogen peroxide, silicate and alkali, wherein up to 100% of the alkali is
Mg(OH)2, Na2CO3, or a combination thereof;</claim-text><claim-text>holding the pulp and the bleaching liquor at a temperature in the range of
about 85°C to about 160°C for a time of about 2 to about 180 minutes; and</claim-text><claim-text>increasing the brightness of the pulp at least to a brightness level which can
be obtained if 100% of the alkali is NaOH and the pulp and bleaching liquor are held
at about the same time and temperature conditions.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
