<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1241522-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1241522" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="18930016" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020918">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1241522-A1" status="new" fvid="23569634">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1241522</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20020918</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02005892-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02005892</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020314</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001072432-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001072432</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010314</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03C   5/305       20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03C   5/305       20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03C   5/40        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03C   5/44        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03C   5/50        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03C   5/50        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03C   7/407       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03C   7/407       20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03C   7/413       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03C   7/413       20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03C   7/42        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03C   7/42        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G03C   5/50</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G03C   7/413</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G03C   7/42B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">S03C5:305</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">S03C7:407+RV+DEV+BLE</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">S03C7:413+BUF+PO4</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">S03C7:42B+COOH</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Entwicklungsverfahren für farbphotographisches Silberhalogenidmaterial</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Processing method for silver halide color photographic material</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé pour le traitement d'un matériau photographique couleur à l'halogénure d'argent</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>FUJI PHOTO FILM CO LTD</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>FUJI PHOTO FILM CO., LTD.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Fuji Photo Film Co., Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>210 Nakanuma Minamiashigara-shi</street>
              <city>Kanagawa-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SEKI HIROYUKI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SEKI, HIROYUKI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>SEKI, HIROYUKI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Fuji Photo Film Co., Ltd., 210, Nakanuma</street>
              <city>Minami-Ashigara-shi, Kanagawa</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Grünecker, Kinkeldey, Stockmair &amp;amp; Schwanhäusser Anwaltssozietät</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Maximilianstrasse 58</street>
              <city>80538 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A method of processing a silver halide color photographic
Material, wherein the color-forming developer used for the color
development step comprises phosphate ion at a concentration
of from 0.05 to 0.25 mol/L, and the bleaching solution used
for the bleaching step comprises at least one iron (III) complex
salt of the compound represented by the following formula (I),
and at least one of compounds represented by the following
formulae (II), (III), (IV) and (V).</p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <u style="single">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a (development)
processing method for a silver halide color photographic
material (hereinafter described as simply photographic
material), and in particular a processing method using a
bleaching solution. The present invention specifically
relates to a photographic processing method with which
desilvering, color restoration and stain prevention are
improved to achieve an excellent development quality.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0002">Silver halide color photographic materials give rise to
images by processing after imagewise exposure. In such
processing, the material is subjected to development, and then
processed with a bleaching solution and a fixing solution. As
the bleaching agent contained in the bleaching solution, the
iron (III) complex salt of ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid
(EDTA) has been widely used. However, from the viewpoints of
rapid development processing and reduction of processing waste,
a more active bleaching agent showing a higher bleaching speed
with a smaller use amount than that of the EDTA iron (III) complex
salt is earnestly demanded, and a variety of bleaching agents
have been proposed. The iron (III) complex salt of
1,3-propylenediaminetetraacetic acid (1,3-PDTA), which is a 
specially desirable bleaching agent from the above viewpoints,
is increasingly used in replace of the EDTA iron (III) complex
salt. However, when a highly active bleaching agent such as
1,3-PDTA iron (III) complex salt, which works rapidly at a low
amount, is used in combination with a color-forming developer
containing phosphate ion, it has been confirmed that the
bleaching solution is liable to turn turbid or form a precipitate
along with a prolonged usage for processing. Thus, such a
bleaching agent has a serious disadvantage when the processing
is conducted in a continuous mode.</p>
    <p num="0003">Further, the processing with a highly active bleaching
agent has another drawback that photographic materials
processed such as color print papers and films processed with
the highly active bleaching agent tends to get stained when
stored under a high temperature and high humid condition. Still
another drawback accompanied by the highly active bleaching
agent exists that, when such a highly active bleaching agent
is used for a rapid bleaching treatment in the color-forming
development (i.e., the color development) using the
above-described developer, failure of color restoration, which
indicates the fact that the degree of dye formation is incomplete,
often takes place.</p>
    <p num="0004">It has been confirmed that these drawbacks are
particularly noticeable for photographic materials such as
color reversal photographic materials that form a large quantity 
of developed silver in the development step. In such cases,
an unfavorable image quality deterioration results.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0005">Accordingly, An object of the present invention to solve
is the drawbacks mentioned above associated with the processing
using a phosphate ion-containing color-forming developer, and
in particular the processing of reversal color photographic
materials. Specifically, the object is to provide a method
of processing a silver halide color photographic material
wherein the bleaching solution neither becomes turbid nor
generates any precipitate.</p>
    <p num="0006">Another object of the present invention is to provide
a method of processing a silver halide color photographic
material which gives sufficient color-formation and little
failure of color restoration in the processing, and shows little
stain formation even when the processed material is stored under
high temperature and highly humid conditions.</p>
    <p num="0007">As a result of the extensive study carried out by the
present inventors on the above-mentioned problems, they have
found that the use of the iron (III) complex salt of a specific
aminopolycarboxyacetic acid instead of EDTA iron (III) complex
salt together with a specific complex-forming agent can prevent
the above-described bleaching solution using a phosphate
ion-containing color-forming developer from becoming turbid
or precipitation formation. Based on this founding followed 
by a further thorough investigation, the present invention has
been made. That is, the present invention is achieved by the
following processing methods.
<sl><li>1. A method of processing a silver halide color photographic
material, wherein the color-forming developer used for the color
development step comprises phosphate ion at a concentration
of from 0.05 to 0.25 mol/L, and in which the bleaching solution
used for the bleaching step comprises at least one iron (III)
complex salt of the compound represented by the following formula
(I), and at least one compound represented by the following
formulae (II), (III), (IV) and (V):
<img id="img-00040001" orientation="unknown" wi="108" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040001.tif" inline="no" he="27"/>
wherein A<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>2</sub>, A<sub>3</sub> and A<sub>4</sub> may be the same or different, each
represents -CH<sub>2</sub>OH, -PO<sub>3</sub>(M<sup>2</sup>)<sub>2</sub> or -COOM<sub>1</sub>, and may be the same or
different; M<sub>1</sub> and M<sub>2</sub> each represents a hydrogen atom, an alkali
metal atom, an ammonium group or an organic ammonium group;
X<sub>1</sub> represents a straight-chain or branched-chain alkylene group
having 3 to 6 carbon atoms, a ring-forming, saturated or
unsaturated divalent organic group or - (B<sub>1</sub>O) n<sub>5</sub>-B<sub>2</sub>-; n<sub>5</sub>
represents an integer of 1 to 8; B<sub>1</sub> and B<sub>2</sub> may be the same or
different, each representing an alkylene group having 1 to 5
carbon atoms; and n<sub>1</sub>, n<sub>2</sub>, n<sub>3</sub> and n<sub>4</sub> may be the same or different, 
each represents an integer not exceeding 10;
<img id="img-00050001" orientation="unknown" wi="107" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00050001.tif" inline="no" he="35"/>
wherein R<sub>1</sub> represents a hydrogen atom, an alkyl group, a
hydroxyalkyl group, a carboxyalkyl group or an alkoxyalkyl
group; R<sub>2</sub> and R<sub>3</sub> each represents a hydrogen atom, an alkyl group
or an alkoxyalkyl group; and M<sub>6</sub>, M<sub>7</sub> and M<sub>8</sub> each represents a
hydrogen atom, an alkali metal atom, an alkaline earth metal
atom or an onium group;
<img id="img-00050002" orientation="unknown" wi="100" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00050002.tif" inline="no" he="23"/>
wherein L<sub>0</sub> represents a divalent alkylene group having 2 to
8 carbon atoms, and M<sup>9</sup> and M<sup>10</sup> each represents a hydrogen atom,
an alkali metal atom, an alkaline earth metal atom or an onium
group;
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/">M<sup>11</sup>OOC―X<sub>2</sub>―NH―X<sub>3</sub>―NH―X<sub>4</sub>―COOM<sup>12</sup></st32:che> 
wherein in the formula, X<sub>2</sub>, X<sub>3</sub> and X<sub>4</sub> each represents a substituted
or unsubstituted alkylene group having 1 to 3 carbon atoms,
and M<sup>11</sup> and M<sup>12</sup> each represents a hydrogen atom, an alkali metal
atom, an alkaline earth metal atom or an onium group;
<img id="img-00060001" orientation="unknown" wi="90" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00060001.tif" inline="no" he="31"/>
wherein Z represents a nitrogen-containing heterocyclic ring;
R<sup>4</sup> represents a hydrogen atom, an alkyl group or an alkoxyalkyl
group; M<sup>13</sup> represents a hydrogen atom, an alkali metal atom,
an alkaline earth metal atom or an onium group; and m represents
an integer of 1 to 3.</li><li>2. A method of processing a silver halide color photographic
material according to the above item 1, wherein the bleaching
solution further contains at least one iron (III) complex salt
of the compound represented by formula (VI):
<img id="img-00060002" orientation="unknown" wi="91" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00060002.tif" inline="no" he="52"/> 
wherein G<sub>1</sub> and G<sub>2</sub> each represents a carboxyl group, a phosphono
group, a sulfo group, a hydroxy group, a mercapto group, an
aryl group, a heterocyclic group, an alkylthio group, an amidino
group, a guanidino group or a carbamoyl group; L<sub>1</sub>, L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub>
each represents a divalent aliphatic or aromatic group or a
divalent linking group comprising a combination thereof; m and
n each represents 0 or 1; X represents a hydrogen atom, an
aliphatic or aromatic group; and M represents a hydrogen atom
or a cation.</li><li>3. The method of processing a silver halide color
photographic material according to the above item 2, wherein
the content ratio of the iron (III) complex salt of the compound
represented by formula (I) to the iron (III) complex salt of
the compound represented by formula (VI) is in the range of
from 0.1 to 0.8.</li><li>4. The method of processing a silver halide color
photographic material according to any one of the above items
1 to 3, wherein the compound represented by formula (I) is
1,3-propylenediaminetetraacetic acid. </li><li>5. The method of processing a silver halide color
photographic material according to any one of the above items
1 to 4, wherein the compound represented by formula (II) is
selected from the group consisting of iminodisuccinic acid,
N-carboxymethylaspartic acid and
N,N'-dicarboxymethylaspartic acid.</li><li>6. The method of processing a silver halide color
photographic material according to any one of the above items
1 to 5, wherein the compound represented by formula (III) is
N-(2-hydroxyethyl)aminodiacetic acid.</li><li>7. The method of processing a silver halide color
photographic material according to any one of the above items
1 to 6, wherein the compound represented by formula (IV) is
ethylenediamine-N,N'-diacetic acid.</li><li>8. The method of processing a silver halide color
photographic material according to any one of the above items
1 to 6, wherein the compound represented by formula (V) is
pyridine-2-carboxylic acid. </li><li>9. The method of processing a silver halide color
photographic material according to any one of the above items
1 to 8, wherein the compound represented by formula
(VI) is N-carboxymethylaspartic acid.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0008">One processing method that achieves the purpose of the
present invention characteristically uses a bleaching solution
containing at least one of the ion (III) complex salts of a
compound represented by formula (I) , and at least one of
compounds represented by one of formulae (II) to (V). This
type of bleaching solution will not become turbid when used
for a long time with a color-forming developer containing of
0.05 to 0.25 mol/L of phosphate ion. Moreover, failure of color
restoration as well as stain formation is suppressed. The
diaminopolycarboxylic acid compound represented by formula (I)
is characterized by the number of atoms in the linking group
for the two amino nitrogen atoms, the compound represented by
formula (II) is characterized by being a
carboxymethyliminosuccinic acid derivative, the compound
represented by formula (III) is characterized by being a
hydroxyalkyliminodiacetic acid derivative, the compound
represented by formula (IV) is characterized by being an
alkylenediaminedicarboxylic acid derivative, and the compound
represented by formula (V) is characterized by being a
nitrogen-containing heterocyclic carboxylic acid derivative. </p>
    <p num="0009">It has been further found that the advantageous features
of the bleaching solution according to the present invention
are enhanced by incorporating the ion (III) complex salt of
the compound represented by formula (VI).</p>
    <p num="0010">Though the processing method of the present invention
can be applied to any type of color photographic materials,
it is particularly preferable and effective to apply to color
reversal processing since phosphate ion-containing
color-forming developers are extensively used for the
processing of color reversal photographic materials.</p>
    <p num="0011">The method of the present invention can be applied to
the ordinary color processing comprising development with a
phosphate ion-containing color-forming developer followed by
desilvering with use of a processing solution having a bleaching
capability. However, since a color processing method in which
color-forming development (i.e., color development) is not
directly followed by bleaching but by other steps such as
pre-bleaching, etc., also suffers from the same problems
mentioned previously such as deposition or precipitation of
insoluble matters, the method of the present invention can be
effectively applied to such processing.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0012">The present invention is described more in detail below.
First of all, the compounds represented by formula (I) are
explained. </p>
    <p num="0013">In formula (I) , A<sub>1</sub> to A<sub>4</sub>, which may be the same or different,
each represents -CH<sub>2</sub>OH, -PO<sub>3</sub>(M<sup>2</sup>)<sub>2</sub> or -COOM<sup>1</sup>; M<sup>1</sup> and M<sup>2</sup> each
represents a hydrogen atom, an alkali metal atom (e.g., Na or
K), an ammonium group or an organic ammonium group (e.g.,
methylammonium or trimethylammonium).</p>
    <p num="0014">X<sub>1</sub> represents a straight-chain or branched-chain alkylene
group containing 3 to 6 carbon atoms, a ring-forming, saturated
or unsaturated divalent organic group, or -(B<sub>1</sub>O)n<sub>5</sub>-B<sub>2</sub>-. B<sub>1</sub> and
B<sub>2</sub> may be the same or different, each represents an alkylene
group having 1 to 5 carbon atoms (containing those of the
substituent). Symbols n<sub>1</sub> to n<sub>4</sub>, which may be the same or
different, each represents an integer of from 1 to 10, and at
least one of them is not less than 2. The alkylene group
represented by X<sub>1</sub> includes ethylene, trimethylene or
tetramethylene. The alkylene group represented by B<sub>1</sub> or B<sub>2</sub>
includes methylene, ethylene or trimethylene. Suitable
substituents for X<sub>1</sub> or the alkylene group represented by B<sub>1</sub> or
B<sub>2</sub> include hydroxyl and an alkyl group having 1 to 3 carbon
atoms (e.g., methyl or ethyl) . n<sub>5</sub> represents an integer of 1
to 8, preferably 1 to 4, and more preferably 1 to 2. In the
following, preferable examples of the compound represented by
formula (I) are shown not for the purpose of restricting the
scope of the present invention thereto. <img id="img-00120001" orientation="unknown" wi="128" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00120001.tif" inline="no" he="26"/><img id="img-00120002" orientation="unknown" wi="128" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00120002.tif" inline="no" he="25"/><img id="img-00120003" orientation="unknown" wi="129" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00120003.tif" inline="no" he="25"/><img id="img-00120004" orientation="unknown" wi="130" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00120004.tif" inline="no" he="24"/><img id="img-00120005" orientation="unknown" wi="130" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00120005.tif" inline="no" he="25"/><img id="img-00120006" orientation="unknown" wi="131" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00120006.tif" inline="no" he="26"/><img id="img-00120007" orientation="unknown" wi="132" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00120007.tif" inline="no" he="29"/><img id="img-00120008" orientation="unknown" wi="132" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00120008.tif" inline="no" he="27"/><img id="img-00130001" orientation="unknown" wi="128" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130001.tif" inline="no" he="28"/><img id="img-00130002" orientation="unknown" wi="128" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130002.tif" inline="no" he="26"/><img id="img-00130003" orientation="unknown" wi="73" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130003.tif" inline="no" he="38"/><img id="img-00130004" orientation="unknown" wi="74" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130004.tif" inline="no" he="39"/><img id="img-00130005" orientation="unknown" wi="73" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130005.tif" inline="no" he="40"/><img id="img-00130006" orientation="unknown" wi="74" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130006.tif" inline="no" he="38"/><img id="img-00140001" orientation="unknown" wi="82" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00140001.tif" inline="no" he="42"/><img id="img-00140002" orientation="unknown" wi="137" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00140002.tif" inline="no" he="28"/><img id="img-00140003" orientation="unknown" wi="138" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00140003.tif" inline="no" he="29"/><img id="img-00140004" orientation="unknown" wi="138" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00140004.tif" inline="no" he="31"/><img id="img-00140005" orientation="unknown" wi="139" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00140005.tif" inline="no" he="33"/><img id="img-00140006" orientation="unknown" wi="139" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00140006.tif" inline="no" he="35"/><img id="img-00150001" orientation="unknown" wi="125" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00150001.tif" inline="no" he="27"/><img id="img-00150002" orientation="unknown" wi="125" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00150002.tif" inline="no" he="29"/><img id="img-00150003" orientation="unknown" wi="126" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00150003.tif" inline="no" he="30"/><img id="img-00150004" orientation="unknown" wi="127" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00150004.tif" inline="no" he="28"/><img id="img-00150005" orientation="unknown" wi="128" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00150005.tif" inline="no" he="29"/><img id="img-00150006" orientation="unknown" wi="128" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00150006.tif" inline="no" he="34"/><img id="img-00150007" orientation="unknown" wi="128" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00150007.tif" inline="no" he="32"/></p>
    <p num="0015">Among the above-exemplified compounds, each of compounds
(I-11), (I-12), (I-13), (I-14) and (I-15) includes both of the
cis- and trans-forms.</p>
    <p num="0016">The compounds represented by formula (I) exemplified
above can be synthesized in the generally known processes.</p>
    <p num="0017">Among the specific examples, particularly preferable
compounds are (I-3), (I-4), (I-8), (I-11) and (I-16).</p>
    <p num="0018">In the iron (III) complex salt of the compound represented
by formula (I), those having the stoichiometric ratio of ferric
ion (i.e., iron (III) ion) to the compound of formula (I) of
1:1 are preferred. Further the complex salt may have an amine,
a thiocyanate group or a cyanate group as a ligand. Further,
the negative or positive excessive atomic valence is neutralized
with a water-soluble cation or anion. The complex salt may
be hydrated, too. In the following, some examples for the ion
(III) complex of the compound represented by formula (I) are
exemplified not for the purpose of restricting the scope of
the present invention thereto. <img id="img-00170001" orientation="unknown" wi="140" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00170001.tif" inline="no" he="35"/><img id="img-00170002" orientation="unknown" wi="140" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00170002.tif" inline="no" he="31"/><img id="img-00170003" orientation="unknown" wi="141" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00170003.tif" inline="no" he="36"/><img id="img-00170004" orientation="unknown" wi="142" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00170004.tif" inline="no" he="36"/><img id="img-00170005" orientation="unknown" wi="142" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00170005.tif" inline="no" he="35"/><img id="img-00170006" orientation="unknown" wi="142" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00170006.tif" inline="no" he="40"/><img id="img-00180001" orientation="unknown" wi="127" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00180001.tif" inline="no" he="46"/><img id="img-00180002" orientation="unknown" wi="127" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00180002.tif" inline="no" he="48"/><img id="img-00180003" orientation="unknown" wi="147" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00180003.tif" inline="no" he="48"/><img id="img-00180004" orientation="unknown" wi="147" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00180004.tif" inline="no" he="45"/><img id="img-00190001" orientation="unknown" wi="150" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00190001.tif" inline="no" he="48"/><img id="img-00190002" orientation="unknown" wi="113" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00190002.tif" inline="no" he="45"/></p>
    <p num="0019">Now, the compound represented by formula (II) is explained.
In formula (II) , R<sub>1</sub> represents a hydrogen atom, an alkyl group,
a hydroxyalkyl group, a carboxyalkyl group or an alkoxyalkyl
group; R<sub>2</sub> and R<sub>3</sub> each represents a hydrogen atom, an alkyl group,
a carboxyalkyl group or an alkoxyalkyl group; and M<sup>6</sup>, M<sup>7</sup> and
M<sup>8</sup> each represents a hydrogen atom, an alkali metal atom, an
alkaline earth metal atom or an onium group.</p>
    <p num="0020">In cases where R<sub>1</sub> represent an alkyl group, a hydroxyalkyl
group, a carboxyalkyl group or an alkoxyalkyl group, the number
of the carbon atoms contained in each alkyl group is 1 to 8,
preferably 1 to 4, and the alkyl group may be straight or branched.
The carbon atom number of the alkoxyalkyl group is 1 to 3,
preferably 1 or 2. Preferable R<sub>1</sub> include a hydrogen atom, methyl,
ethyl, carboxymethyl, and carboxyethyl groups, among these,
hydrogen, carboxymethyl and methyl groups are preferred.</p>
    <p num="0021">In cases where R<sub>2</sub> and R<sub>3</sub> each represents an alkyl group,
a craboxylalkyl group or an alkoxyalkyl gruop, the carbon atom
number of each alkyl group is 1 to 8, and more preferably 1
to 4. The alkyl group may be of straight chain or branched
chain. The carbon atom number of the alkoxy group in the
alkoxylalkyl group is 1 to 3, preferably 1 or 2. Preferable
R<sub>2</sub> or R<sub>3</sub> includes a hydrogen atom, methyl, ethyl, carboxymethyl
and carboxyethyl groups, among these, a hydrogen atom,
carboxymethyl and methyl groups are preferred. </p>
    <p num="0022">The alkali metal atom represented by M<sup>6</sup>, M<sup>7</sup> or M<sup>8</sup> includes
metal atoms such as Li, Na and K, alkaline earth metal atoms
such as Ca, Mg and Ba, and onium groups such as ammonium (e.g.,
ammonium or tetraethylammonium) and pyridinium. More
preferable M<sup>6</sup>, M<sup>7</sup> or M<sup>8</sup> is a hydrogen atom, an ammonium group
or an alkali metal atom.</p>
    <p num="0023">Some specific examples of the compound represented by
formula (II) of the present invention are listed not for the
purpose of restricting the scope of the present invention thereto.
In the present specification, each exemplary compound
represented by each formula is shown in the acid form (i.e.,
COOH) . However, other forms such as the metal or ammonium salt
are not excluded. <img id="img-00220001" orientation="unknown" wi="132" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00220001.tif" inline="no" he="48"/><img id="img-00220002" orientation="unknown" wi="132" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00220002.tif" inline="no" he="40"/><img id="img-00220003" orientation="unknown" wi="133" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00220003.tif" inline="no" he="37"/><img id="img-00220004" orientation="unknown" wi="134" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00220004.tif" inline="no" he="36"/><img id="img-00220005" orientation="unknown" wi="134" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00220005.tif" inline="no" he="40"/><img id="img-00230001" orientation="unknown" wi="130" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00230001.tif" inline="no" he="37"/><img id="img-00230002" orientation="unknown" wi="130" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00230002.tif" inline="no" he="35"/></p>
    <p num="0024">The compounds represented by formula (II) can be prepared
with reference to the synthetic methods described in <i>Kireto
Kagaku</i> (Chelate Chemistry) (5), edited by Kagehira Ueno and
published by Nankodo Co., Ltd., <i>Inorganic Chemistry,</i> 7, 2405
(1968), <i>Chm. Zvesti</i>., 20, 414 (1966) , and <i>Zhurnal Obshchei Khinii</i>,
49, 659 (1978). Many of the compounds are commercially
available, too.</p>
    <p num="0025">Now, the compound represented by formula (III) is
explained. In formula (III), L<sub>0</sub> represents a divalent alkylene
group having 2 to 8 carbon atoms, and may be straight or branched
with preferably 2 to 4 carbon atoms, more preferably with 2
to 3 carbon atoms. The alkylene group may be substituted by
a hydroxy group or an alkoxy group. In the case where the
substituent is alkoxy, the carbon atom number is 1 to 4,
preferably 1 to 3.</p>
    <p num="0026">M<sup>9</sup> and M<sup>10</sup> have the same meaning as M<sup>6</sup>, M<sup>7</sup> and M<sup>8</sup>, and
preferable groups for M<sup>9</sup> and M<sup>10</sup> are common to those for M<sup>6</sup>,
M<sup>7</sup> and M<sup>8</sup>.</p>
    <p num="0027">In the following, some examples for the compound
represented by formula (III) are exemplified not for the purpose
of restricting the scope of the present invention thereto. <img id="img-00250001" orientation="unknown" wi="128" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00250001.tif" inline="no" he="30"/><img id="img-00250002" orientation="unknown" wi="129" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00250002.tif" inline="no" he="28"/><img id="img-00250003" orientation="unknown" wi="130" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00250003.tif" inline="no" he="33"/><img id="img-00250004" orientation="unknown" wi="130" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00250004.tif" inline="no" he="28"/><img id="img-00250005" orientation="unknown" wi="63" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00250005.tif" inline="no" he="36"/></p>
    <p num="0028">Similarly to those represented by formula (II), the
compounds represented by formula (III) can also be synthesized
with reference to the methods described in <i>KiretoKagaku</i> (Chelate
Chemistry) (5), edited by Kagehira Ueno and published by Nankodo
Co., Ltd., <i>Inorganic Chemistry,</i> 7, 2405 (1968), Chm. <i>Zvesti.,</i>
20, 414 (1966), and <i>Zhurnal Obshchei Khinii</i>, 49, 659 (1978).
Many of the compounds are commercially available, too.</p>
    <p num="0029">Now, the compound represented by formula (IV) is explained.
In formula (IV), X<sub>2</sub>, X<sub>3</sub> and X<sub>4</sub> each represents a methylene group,
an ethylene group, n- and i-propylene groups, each of which
may be substituted with a hydroxy group, a methoxy group or
an ethoxy group. M<sup>11</sup> and M<sup>12</sup> have the same meaning as M<sup>6</sup>, M<sup>7</sup>
and M<sup>8</sup>, and preferable groups for M<sup>11</sup> and M<sup>12</sup> are common to those
for M<sup>6</sup>, M<sup>7</sup> and M<sup>8</sup>.</p>
    <p num="0030">Some specific examples of the compound represented by
formula (IV) are listed below not for the purpose of restricting
the scope of the present invention thereto.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="4"><dt>IV-1</dt><dd>Ethylenediamine-N,N'-diacetic acid</dd><dt>IV-2</dt><dd>Propylenediamine-N,N'-diacetic acid</dd><dt>IV-3</dt><dd>1-Methyl-ethylenediamine-N,N'-diacetic acid</dd><dt>IV-4</dt><dd>Ethylenediamine-N,N'-dipropionic acid</dd><dt>IV-5</dt><dd>Ethylenediamine-N,N'-dilactic acid</dd><dt>IV-6</dt><dd>Propylenediamine-N,N'-dilactic acid</dd><dt>IV-7</dt><dd>2-Hydroxy-propylenediamine-N,N'-diacetic acid</dd><dt>IV-8</dt><dd>2-Methoxy-propylenediamine-N,N'-diacetic acid</dd></dl></p>
    <p num="0031">The compounds represented by formula (IV) are
commercially available.</p>
    <p num="0032">Now, the compound represented by formula (V) is described.
In formula (V) , Z represents a nitrogen-containing heterocyclic
group, which is preferably a nitrogen-containing 5- or
6-membered ring group, and more preferably an aromatic
heterocyclic group. Particularly preferred groups are azoles,
azines and pyridines.</p>
    <p num="0033">Preferable azole rings are pyrrole, pyrroline, pyrazole,
pyrazoline, imidazole, imidazoline, triazole, thiazole,
oxazole, isoxazole and tetrazole.</p>
    <p num="0034">Preferable azine rings are pyrimidine, pyridazine,
oxazine and thiazine.</p>
    <p num="0035">The nitrogen-containing heterocyclic group may be
substituted with an alkyl or alkoxyl group each containing 1
to 4 carbon atoms, a hydroxy group or a carboxymethyl group.</p>
    <p num="0036">In cases where R<sup>4</sup> represents an alkyl group, an alkoxyalkyl
group or a carboxyalkyl group, each of those groups comprises
the same ones as the corresponding group represented by R<sub>1</sub>.
Preferable examples thereof are also common to those of R<sub>1</sub>.</p>
    <p num="0037">M<sup>13</sup> has the same meaning as M<sup>6</sup>, M<sup>7</sup> and M<sup>8</sup>, and its preferable
examples are also common to those for M<sup>6</sup>, M<sup>7</sup> and M<sup>8</sup>.</p>
    <p num="0038">Some specific examples of the compound represented by
formula (V) are listed below not for the purpose of restricting
the scope of the present invention thereto. <dl compact="compact" tsize="3"><dt>V-1</dt><dd>Pyridine-2-carboxylic acid</dd><dt>V-2</dt><dd>Pyrimidine-2-carboxylic acid</dd><dt>V-3</dt><dd>Pyrimidine-5-carboxylic acid</dd><dt>V-4</dt><dd>4-Carboxy-2-imidazole</dd><dt>V-5</dt><dd>4-Carboxy-2-methylimidazole</dd><dt>V-6</dt><dd>N-methylpyridine-2-carboxylic acid</dd><dt>V-7</dt><dd>Pyridine-2,4-dicarboxylic acid</dd><dt>V-8</dt><dd>Pyridine-2,6-dicarboxylic acid</dd></dl></p>
    <p num="0039">The compounds represented by formula (V) can be not only
synthesized by ordinary processes, but are commercially
available.</p>
    <p num="0040">Next, the compound represented by formula (VI) is
described. In formula (VI) , G<sub>1</sub> and G<sub>2</sub> each represents a carboxyl
group, a phosphono group, a sulfo group, a hydroxy group, a
mercapto group, an aryl group, a heterocyclic group, an alkylthio
group, an amidino group, a guanidino group or a carbamoyl group;
L<sub>1</sub>, L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub> each represents a divalent aliphatic or aromatic
group or a divalent linking group comprising a combination
thereof; m and n each represents 0 or 1; X represents a hydrogen
atom, an aliphatic or aromatic group; and M represents a hydrogen
atom or a cation.</p>
    <p num="0041">The aryl (aromatic hydrocarbon) group represented by G1
or G2 may comprise single or bicyclic rings, preferably
containing 5 to 20 carbon atoms. Examples thereof include
phenyl and naphthyl. The substituent which this aryl group 
may have includes an alkyl group (e.g., methyl or ethyl), an
aralkyl group (e.g., phenylmethyl), an alkenyl group (e.g.,
allyl), an alkynyl group an alkoxy group (e.g., methoxy or
ethoxy), an aryl group (e.g., phenyl or p-methylphenyl), an
acylamino group (e.g., acetylamino), a sulfonylamino group
(e.g., methanesulfonylamino), an ureido group, an
alkoxycarbonylamino group (e.g., methoxycarbonylamino), an
aryloxycarbonylamino group (e.g., phenoxycarbonylamino), an
aryloxy group (e.g., phenyloxy), a sulfamoyl group (e.g.,
methylsulfamoyl), a carbamoyl group (e.g., carbamoyl or
methylcarbamoyl), an alkylthio group (e.g., methythio or
carboxymethylthio), an arylthio group (e.g., phenylthio), a
sulfonyl group (e.g., methanesulfonyl) , a sulfinyl group (e.g.,
methanesulfinyl), a hydroxy group, a halogen atom (e.g., Cl,
Br or F), a cyano group, a sulfo group, a carboxy group, a phosphono
group, an aryloxycarbonyl group (e.g., phenyloxy carbonyl), an
acyl group (e.g., acetyl or benzoyl) , an alkoxycarbonyl group
(e.g., methoxycarbonyl), an acyloxy group (e.g., acetoxy), a
nitro group and a hydroxamic acid group.</p>
    <p num="0042">The heterocyclic group represented by G<sub>1</sub> or G<sub>2</sub> is a 3-to
10-membered heterocyclic group containing at least one oxygen
or sulfur atom therein, and may be saturated or unsaturated.
It may further contain a single ring or form a condensed ring
with another aromatic ring or heterocyclic ring. Such
heterocyclic rings, which are 5- or 6-membered unsaturated 
heterocyclic group, include, for example, pyridine, pyrazine,
pyrimidine, pyridazine, triazine, tetrazine, thiophene, furan,
pyran, pyrrole, imidazole, pyrazole, thiazole, isothiazole
oxazole, isoxazole, oxadiazole, thiadiazole, thianthrene,
isobenzofuran, chromene, xanthene, phenoxazine, indolizine,
isoindole, indole, triazole, triazolium, tetrazole,
quinolizine, isoquinoline, quinoline, phthalazine,
naphthylidine, quinoxaline, quinazoline, cinnoline, pterin,
carbazole, carboline, phenanthridine, acrylidine, pteridine,
phenanthroline, phenazine, phenothiazine, phenoxazine,
coumarone, pyrroline, pyrrazoline, indoline, and isoindoline.
Among them, pyridine, pyrazine, pyrimidine, pyridazine,
thiophene, furan, pyrrole, imidazole, pyrazole, thiazole,
isothiazole, oxazole, isoxazole and indole are preferred. More
preferable heterocyclic rings are imidazole and indole.</p>
    <p num="0043">The alkylthio group represented by G<sub>1</sub> or G<sub>2</sub> is represented
by -SR<sub>1</sub> (R<sub>1</sub> represents an alkyl group.). The alkyl group for
R<sub>1</sub> may be straight-chained, branched or cyclic, preferably
containing 1 to 10 carbon atoms. The alkyl group more preferably
comprises a straight-chain containing 1 to 4 carbon. The alkyl
group represented by R<sub>1</sub> may have a substituent group, which
includes the same substituents as those for the aryl group
represented by G<sub>1</sub> or G<sub>2</sub>. Specific examples of the alkylthio
group represented by G<sub>1</sub> or G<sub>2</sub> include, for example, methylthio,
ethylthio, hydroxyethylthio and carboxymethylthio. 
Preferable ones are methylthio and ethylthio.</p>
    <p num="0044">The carbamoyl group represented by G<sub>1</sub> or G<sub>2</sub> may be
substituted, thus being shown as -CONR<sup>1</sup>R<sup>2</sup> wherein R<sup>1</sup> and R<sup>2</sup> each
represents a hydrogen atom, a substituted or unsubstituted alkyl
or aryl group. The alkyl group represented by R<sup>1</sup> and R<sup>2</sup> may
be straight-chained, branched or cyclic, and preferably have
1 to 10 carbon atoms. The aryl group represented by R<sup>1</sup> and R<sup>2</sup>
preferably has 6 to 10 carbon atoms, phenyl being more preferred.
R<sup>1</sup> and R<sup>2</sup> may be connected together to form a ring such as, for
example, morpholine, piperidine, pyrrolidine and piperadine.
Particularly preferred groups as R<sup>1</sup> and R<sup>2</sup> are a hydrogen atom,
a substituted or unsubstituted alkyl group having 1 to 4 carbon
atoms and a phenyl group which may be substituted.</p>
    <p num="0045">Substitutents for the alkyl or aryl group represented
by R<sup>1</sup> and R<sup>2</sup> include those which the aryl group represented by
G<sub>1</sub> or G<sub>2</sub> may have. Specific examples of the carbamoyl group
represented by G<sub>1</sub> or G<sub>2</sub> include, for example, carbamoyl,
N-methyl carbamoyl, N-phenylcarbamoyl and morpholinocarbonyl.</p>
    <p num="0046">The divalent aliphatic group represented by L<sub>1</sub>, L<sub>2</sub> and
L<sub>3</sub> includes a straight-chained, branched or cyclic alkylene
group (preferably of 1 to 6 carbon atoms) , an alkenylene group
(preferably of 2 to 6 carbon atoms), and an alkynylene group
(preferably of 2 to 6 carbon atoms) . These divalent aliphatic
groups may be substituted with, for example, those which the
aryl group represented by G<sub>1</sub> or G<sub>2</sub> may have. Preferable 
substituents include carboxyl and hydroxy, carboxyl being more
preferred.</p>
    <p num="0047">Specific examples of the divalent aliphatic group for
L<sub>1</sub>, L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub> include methylene, ethylene, 1-carboxy-methylene,
1-carboxy-ethylene, 2-hydroxy-ethylene, 2-hydroxy-propylene,
1-phosphono-methylene, 1-phneyl-methylene and
1-carboxy-butylene.</p>
    <p num="0048">As the divalent aromatic group for L<sub>1</sub>, L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub>, divalent
aromatic hydrocarbon (arylene) groups and divaltent aromatic
heterocyclic groups are exemplified. The divalent aromatic
hydrocarbon (arylene) group may comprise a single ring or
bicyclic rings, and preferably contains 6 to 20 carbon atoms,
exemplified by phenylene and naphthylene groups. The divalent
aromatic heterocyclic group is 3- to 10-membered, containing
at least one of a nitrogen, oxygen or sulfur atom, andmay comprise
a single ring or be condensed with another aromatic or
heterocyclic ring. 5- to 6-membered aromatic heterocyclic
groups containing nitrogen as the heteroatom are preferred.
Specific examples of the divalent aromatic heterocyclic group
include the following.
<img id="img-00320001" orientation="unknown" wi="97" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00320001.tif" inline="no" he="33"/><img id="img-00320002" orientation="unknown" wi="55" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00320002.tif" inline="no" he="22"/></p>
    <p num="0049">The divalent aromatic group is preferably arylene
(preferably having 6 to 20 carbon atoms), more preferably
phenylene or naphthylene, particularly preferably being
phenylene. The divalent aromatic group for L<sub>1</sub>, L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub> may
have a substituent that is common to those which the aryl group
represented by G<sub>1</sub> or G<sub>2</sub> may have. Among such groups, carboxyl,
hydroxy and aryl are preferred, carboxyl being more preferred.
L<sub>1</sub>, L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub> each may be a group comprising a divalent aliphatic
group and a divalent aromatic group such as, for example, those
to follow.
<img id="img-00330001" orientation="unknown" wi="137" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00330001.tif" inline="no" he="28"/><img id="img-00330002" orientation="unknown" wi="40" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00330002.tif" inline="no" he="28"/></p>
    <p num="0050">Preferable groups for L<sub>1</sub>, L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub> include an alkylene
or o-phenylene group preferably with 1 to 3 carbon atoms, and
particularly preferable ones are methylene and ethylene.</p>
    <p num="0051">Symbols m and n each represents 0 or 1. Preferably, m
is 1, and n is 0. </p>
    <p num="0052">The aliphatic group represented by X includes a
straight-chained, branched or cyclic alkyl group (preferably
having 1 to 6 carbon atoms) , an alkenyl group (preferably having
2 to 6 carbon atoms), and an alkynyl group (preferably having
2 to 6 carbon atoms) . Among these, an alkyl and alkenyl groups
are preferred. Specific examples are methyl, ethyl, cyclohexyl,
benzyl and allyl. The aromatic group for X includes an aromatic
hydrocarbon (aryl) group or an aromatic heterocyclic group such
as, for example, phenyl, naphthyl, 2-pyridyl and 2-pyrrole.
Among these, an aryl group is preferred, and phenyl is more
preferred. Preferably X is a hydrogen atom, an alkyl group having
1 to 3 carbon atoms, hydrogen being more preferred.</p>
    <p num="0053">The cation represented by M includes ammonium (e.g.,
ammonium and tetraethylammonium) and an alkali metal (e.g.,
Li, K and Na) and pyridinium. The compound represented by
formula (I) may be an ammonium salt (e.g., ammonium salt and
tetraethylammonium salt) , an alkali metal (e.g., Li, K and Na)
salt or an acid salt such as hydrochloric, sulfuric or oxalic
acid salt.</p>
    <p num="0054">The number of the ammonium, alkali metal or acid contained
in the compound is preferably be from 0 to 6 for the isolated
compound (e.g., mono-sodium salt, di-sodium salt, or tri-sodium
salt).</p>
    <p num="0055">Among the compounds represented by formula (VI),
preferable ones are those represented by the following formula 
(VII).
<img id="img-00350001" orientation="unknown" wi="88" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00350001.tif" inline="no" he="39"/></p>
    <p num="0056">L<sub>2</sub>' in formula (VII) has the same meaning as L<sub>2</sub> in formula
(VI). And, G<sub>2</sub>' has the same meaning as G<sub>2</sub> in formula (VI). M'
and M'' each has the same meaning as M in formula (VI).</p>
    <p num="0057">Some specific examples of the compound represented by
formula (VI) are exemplified below not for the purpose of
restricting the scope of the present invention thereto.
<img id="img-00350002" orientation="unknown" wi="140" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00350002.tif" inline="no" he="40"/><img id="img-00350003" orientation="unknown" wi="141" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00350003.tif" inline="no" he="39"/><img id="img-00350004" orientation="unknown" wi="79" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00350004.tif" inline="no" he="41"/><img id="img-00360001" orientation="unknown" wi="140" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00360001.tif" inline="no" he="49"/><img id="img-00360002" orientation="unknown" wi="142" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00360002.tif" inline="no" he="51"/><img id="img-00360003" orientation="unknown" wi="74" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00360003.tif" inline="no" he="46"/><img id="img-00370001" orientation="unknown" wi="126" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00370001.tif" inline="no" he="52"/><img id="img-00370002" orientation="unknown" wi="126" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00370002.tif" inline="no" he="64"/><img id="img-00370003" orientation="unknown" wi="117" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00370003.tif" inline="no" he="61"/><img id="img-00380001" orientation="unknown" wi="118" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00380001.tif" inline="no" he="61"/><img id="img-00380002" orientation="unknown" wi="118" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00380002.tif" inline="no" he="65"/><img id="img-00390001" orientation="unknown" wi="141" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00390001.tif" inline="no" he="50"/><img id="img-00390002" orientation="unknown" wi="143" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00390002.tif" inline="no" he="42"/><img id="img-00390003" orientation="unknown" wi="78" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00390003.tif" inline="no" he="44"/><img id="img-00400001" orientation="unknown" wi="116" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00400001.tif" inline="no" he="44"/><img id="img-00400002" orientation="unknown" wi="142" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00400002.tif" inline="no" he="40"/><img id="img-00400003" orientation="unknown" wi="124" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00400003.tif" inline="no" he="52"/></p>
    <p num="0058">The compound represented by formula (VI) can be prepared
based on the synthetic process described in Japanese Patent
application (Laid-Open) No. 95319/1994, in particular
paragraphs [0036] to [0042] thereof.</p>
    <p num="0059">As the iron (III) complex salt of the compound represented
by formula (VI), those having the stoichiometric ratio of ferric
ion (i.e., iron (III) ion)to the compound of formula (I) of
1:1 is preferred. Further the complex salt may be coordinated
with an amine, a thiocyanate group or a cyanate group as a ligand.
Further, the negative or positive excessive atomic valence is
neutralized with a water-soluble cation or anion. The complex
salt may be hydrated, too. In the following, some examples
for the ion (III) complex of the compound represented by formula
(VI) are exemplified not for the purpose of restricting the
scope of the present invention thereto. <img id="img-00420001" orientation="unknown" wi="122" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00420001.tif" inline="no" he="50"/><img id="img-00420002" orientation="unknown" wi="123" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00420002.tif" inline="no" he="50"/><img id="img-00420003" orientation="unknown" wi="123" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00420003.tif" inline="no" he="49"/><img id="img-00420004" orientation="unknown" wi="123" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00420004.tif" inline="no" he="52"/><img id="img-00430001" orientation="unknown" wi="106" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00430001.tif" inline="no" he="54"/><img id="img-00430002" orientation="unknown" wi="106" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00430002.tif" inline="no" he="65"/><img id="img-00430003" orientation="unknown" wi="105" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00430003.tif" inline="no" he="59"/></p>
    <p num="0060">The ion (III) complex salt of the compound represented
by formulae (I) to (VI) may be in the form of isolated solid
(e.g., powdery, granular or bulky solid), or non-isolated
solution (e.g., aqueous solution).</p>
    <p num="0061">The ion (III) complex salt of the compound represented
by formulae (I) and (VI) can be synthesized by reacting the
compound represented by formulae (I) and (VI) with an iron salt
in a solution. As the compound represented by formulae (I)
and (VI), the ammonium or alkali metal salt (e.g., Li, Na or
K salt) may be used.</p>
    <p num="0062">In cases where the iron chelate compound is used in the
form of solution without compound isolation, unnecessary extra
salts formed in the solution by the reaction are preferably
eliminated. In the present invention, such salts can be
eliminated by ultrafiltration, electro-osmosis, salt
filtration via solvent condensation or salt separation by the
addition of a poor solvent. Among these methods,
electro-osmosis is most preferred. In cases where the solvent
is water, the pH range for the solution of the iron (III) complex
salt of the compound represented by formulae (I) and (VI) is
preferably from 4 to 9, more preferably from 5 to 8, and specially
preferably from 6 to 8. The concentration of the iron complex
salt is preferably from 1 to 80% by weight (i.e., by mass),
more preferably from 1 to 50% by weight, and specially preferably
from 3 to 35% by weight. The solvent for the solution of an 
non-isolated iron chelate compound is preferably water. The
ratio of the compound represented by formulae (I) and (VI) to
the iron ion is preferably not less than 1.0, more preferably
1.05 to 2, and particularly preferably 1.1 to 1.2 in terms of
molar ratio.</p>
    <p num="0063">In the synthesis of the iron chelate of the compound
represented by formulae (I) and (VI) associated with the present
invention, any salt or any metal form of iron can be used as
the iron (III) source, including inorganic salts such as ferric
sulfate, ferric chloride, ferric nitrate, ferric ammonium
sulfate, ferric phosphate, ferrous sulfate, ferrous chloride,
ferrous nitrate, ferrous ammonium sulfate, ferrous phosphate,
iron tritetraoxide, iron sesquioxide and iron hydroxide,
organic salts such as iron acetate. As metallic iron, iron
powder or steel wool can also be used. These ferric ion source
materials may be used individually or in combination of two
or more of them in arbitrary mixing ratios. Any kind of solvent
that is not involved in the reaction may be used as the reaction
solvent, but water is the best.</p>
    <p num="0064">As a preferable embodiment of the present invention, the
compound represented by formulae (I) and (VI) is supplied in
the form of the iron (III) complex salt having been prepared
in advance wherein a foreign compound other than the iron (III)
complex salt is contained in such complex salt at a content
preferably of from 0 to 10% by weight, more preferably from 
0 to 7% by weight, and particularly preferably from 0 to 5%
by weight of the iron (III) complex. More specifically, an
iron complex salt-containing material resulting from the
reaction between the compound represented by formula (I) and
iron sesquioxide, or another iron complex salt-containing
material that is obtained by reacting the compound represented
by formulae (I) and (VI) with ferric chloride followed by
desalting to a pre-determined level can be preferably used.
Here, "foreign compound" indicates any by-product formed by
the reaction between the compound represented by formulae (I)
and (VI) and an iron salt.</p>
    <p num="0065">The bleaching solution of the present invention may be
prepared by adding and dissolving the iron (III) complex salt
that has been prepared in advance by reacting the compound
represented by formulae (I) and (VI) with an iron (III) compound
(e.g., ferric oxide, ferric sulfate, ferric chloride, ferric
bromide or ferric nitrate) . Alternatively, a complex-forming
reaction may be conducted in the bleaching solution by adding
a complex-forming compound and an iron (III) compound (e.g.,
ferric sulfate, ferric chloride, ferric bromide or ferric
nitrate) to form an iron (III) complex salt-containing aqueous
solution. In the latter case, the complex-forming compound
may be used in a quantity slightly larger than the stoichiometric
amount for the ion (III) complex salt formation. In general,
use in excess of 0.01 to 20 mol% is preferred. </p>
    <p num="0066">The compound capable of forming a complex salt with ferric
ion used in the present invention may contain an iron (III)
complex-forming compound other than those represented by
formulae (I) and (VI), but its content is preferably below 50
mol%, more preferable below 20 mol%, the remaining being those
represented by formulae (I) and (VI). Further in the present
invention, the compound represented by formula (I) occupies
30 to 95%, preferably 60 to 90% of the total amount of the
complex-forming compound capable of forming an iron (III)
complex salt in the bleaching solution, while those represented
by formulae (II) to (V) is used in 5 to 70%, preferably 10 to
40%. Such compounds represented by formulae (II) to (V) may
be used individually or in combination of two or more. When
two or more compounds are jointly used, the mixing ratio is
arbitrary. Furthermore, within the scope of the present
invention, iron (III) complex-forming compounds other than
those represented by formulae (I) to (V) may be jointly used.
Such other compounds include EDTA,
diethylentriaminepentaacetic acid, iminodiacetic acid,
methyliminodiacetic acid, N-(2-acetoamido)iminodiacetic acid,
nitrilotriacetic acid,
ethylenediaminetetraquismethylenephosphonic acid,
nitrilotrismethylenephosphonic acid and
diethylenetriaminepentaquismethylenephosphonic acid; still
other compounds can be used. </p>
    <p num="0067">In the present invention, in addition to the
complex-forming compound represented by formulae (I) and (VI)
and, in some cases, the iron (III) complex salt of another
chelating agent described above, an inorganic oxidizing agent
may further be used as the bleaching agent of the bleaching
solution. Such inorganic oxidizing agents include hydrogen
peroxide, hypochlorite salts, persulfate salts and bromate
salts (with alkali metals or alkaline earth metals).
Self-evidently, still other oxidizing compounds can be used.</p>
    <p num="0068">The concentration of the iron (III) complex salt of the
compound represented by formulae (I) and (VI) in the bleaching
solution is appropriately from 0.003 to 3.0 mol/L, preferably
from 0.02 to 1.50 mol/L, and more preferably from 0.05 to 0.50
mol/L. However, with a still more diluted range of from 0.05
to 0.20, the iron (III) complex salt exhibits a superior effect.
In cases where an inorganic oxidizing agent is jointly used,
an iron (III) concentration of from 0.005 to 0.03 mol/L is
preferred.</p>
    <p num="0069">In the bleaching solution of the present invention, a
halogen compound such as chloride, bromide or iodide may be
added as a rehalogenating agent which promotes the oxidation
of silver. Further, instead of the halogen compound, one may
employ an organic legand capable of forming a silver salt
sparingly soluble in water. Such halogen compounds are
preferably incorporated in the form-of an alkali metal salt 
or ammonium salt while such organic legands are preferably
incorporated in the form of the salt of guanidine or amines.
Specific compounds include sodium bromide, potassium bromide,
ammonium bromide, potassium bromide and guanidine
hydrochloride. Among these, ammonium bromide is specially
preferred. The bromide ion concentration in the bleaching
solution is preferably from 0.05 to 2.0 mol/L, more preferably
from 0.5 to 1.5 mol/L. In cases where an inorganic oxidizing
agent is jointly used, the bromide ion concentration is
preferably from 0.05 to 0.1 mol/L.</p>
    <p num="0070">In the bleaching solution associated with the present
invention, the compound represented by the following formula
[A] is preferably contained to enhance the advantages of the
present invention.
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/">A<sub>5</sub>(-COOM<sup>5</sup>)n<sub>51</sub></st32:che></p>
    <p num="0071">In formula [A], A<sub>5</sub> represents an n<sub>51</sub>-valent organic group,
n<sub>51</sub> represents an integer of 1 to 6, and M<sup>5</sup> represents an ammonium
group, an organic ammonium group, an alkali metal (Na, K or
Li), or a hydrogen atom. However, A<sub>5</sub> never represents an
unsubstituted methyl, ethyl or ethylene group.</p>
    <p num="0072">In formula [A] , the n<sub>51</sub>-valent organic group represented
by A<sub>5</sub> includes an alkylene group (e.g., methylene, trimethylene
or tetramethylene), an alkenylene group (e.g., ethenylene),
an alkynylene group (e.g., ethynylene) , a cycloalkylene group
(e.g., 1,4-cyclohexanediyl), an arylene group (e.g., 
o-phenylene or p-phenylene), an alkanetolyl group (e.g.,
1,2,3-propanetolyl), an arenetolyl group (e.g.,
1,2,4-benzentolyl) and an alkyl group (e.g., propyl, butyl,
octyl or cyclohexyl).</p>
    <p num="0073">The n<sub>51</sub>-valent group represented by A<sub>5</sub> includes those
having a substituent (e.g., hydroxy, alkyl or a halogen atom) .
Examples include 1,2-dihydroxyethylene, hydroxyethylene,
2-hydroxy-1,2,3-propanetolyl, methyl-p-phenylene,
1-hydroxy-2-chloroethylene, chloromethylene, and
chloroethenylene. The preferred concrete compounds
represented by formula [A] are shown below.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="6"><dt>(A-1)</dt><dd>HOOCCH<sub>2</sub>C(OH) (COOH)CH<sub>2</sub>COOH</dd><dt>(A-2)</dt><dd>HOOC(CHOH)<sub>2</sub>COOH</dd><dt>(A-3)</dt><dd>HOOCCH(OH)CH<sub>2</sub>COOH</dd><dt>(A-4)</dt><dd>HOOCCH=CHCOOH</dd><dt>(A-5)</dt><dd>Propylene glycolic acid</dd><dt>(A-6)</dt><dd>Butylene glycolic acid</dd><dt>(A-7)</dt><dd>Phthalic acid</dd><dt>(A-8)</dt><dd>Terephthalic acid</dd><dt>(A-9)</dt><dd>Cyclohexane-1,4-dicarboxylic acid</dd><dt>(A-10)</dt><dd>Acetyl-1,2-dicarboxylic acid</dd><dt>(A-11)</dt><dd>2-Methylterephthalic acid</dd><dt>(A-12)</dt><dd>1,1,2,2-tetracarboxyethylene</dd><dt>(A-13)</dt><dd>1,1,2,2-tetracarboxyethane </dd><dt>(A-14)</dt><dd>Aspartic acid</dd><dt>(A-15)</dt><dd>Glutaric acid</dd><dt>(A-16)</dt><dd>HOOCCH<sub>2</sub>COOH</dd></dl></p>
    <p num="0074">Among these exemplary compounds, particularly preferable
ones are (A-3), (A-4), (A-15) and (A-16), (A-3) and (A-16) being
most preferred. Addition of the organic acid represented by
formula [A] improves the stability of the bleaching solution
by suppressing the precipitation or deposition of the ferric
compound. Although the mechanism is not clear, it is probable
that the acid contributes to the improved stability by weakly
coordinating with the iron (III) complex. Besides, the
interference effect to be described later seems to be operating.
Accordingly, with a bleaching solution containing the compound
represented by formula [A], the bath can be kept stable at a
lower pH than the conventional bleaching solution, thus
effectively suppressing stain formation.</p>
    <p num="0075">The organic acid described above may be used in the form
of the metal salt (e.g., Na or K salt) or ammonium salts.</p>
    <p num="0076">The compounds represented by formula [A] is contained
in an amount of preferably 0.01 to 0.25 mol, more preferably
0.02 to 0.15 mol per 1 liter of the processing tank solution.</p>
    <p num="0077">A preferable pH range for the bleaching solution of the
present invention is from 4.0 to 7.0, in particular from 4.2
to 6.0. The pH of the bleaching solution can be adjusted to 
such ranges by using an inorganic or organic acid well known
in the art individually or in combination. Particularly, the
bleaching solution may contain an organic acid having pKa of
2.0 to 5.5 at a concentration of from 0.1 to 2 mol/L. The pKa
value means the absolute value of the reciprocal of acid
dissociation constant determined under the condition of 0.1
mol/L ionic strength at 25°C. The organic acid having a pKa
of 2.0 to 5.5 may not be necessarily the compound represented
by formula [A] above, but other mono-basic or poly-basic acids
may be used, too. The organic acid may be used in the form
of the metal salt (e.g., Na or K salt) or the ammonium salt
thereof. Preferable examples of the organic acid include, in
addition to those represented by formula [A], aliphatic
mono-basic acids such as formic acid, acetic acid,
monochloroacetic acid, monobromoacetic acid, glycolic acid,
propionic acid, monochloropropionic acid, lactic acid, pyruvic
acid, acrylic acid, butyric acid, isobutyric acid, pivalic acid,
aminobutyric acid, valeric acid or isovaleric acid; aminoacid
compounds such as asparagine, alanine, arginine, ethionine,
glycine, glutamine, cysteine, serine, methionine or leucine;
aromatic monobasic acids such as benzoic acid or
mono-substituted benzoic acid including chloro- or
hydroxy-benzoic acid and nicotinic acid; aliphatic dibasic acid
such as tartaric acid, malonic acid, malic acid, maleic acid,
fumaric acid, oxaloacetic acid, glutaric acid or adipic acid; 
aminoacid-based dibasic acids such as aspartic acid, glutamic
acid, cystine and ascorbic acid; aromatic dibasic acids such
as phthlic acid and terephthalic acid; other basic acids such
as citric acid and still other organic acid. In the present
invention, acetic acid and glycolic acid are particularly
preferred for use.</p>
    <p num="0078">In addition to the organic acid having a pKa of 2.0 to
5.5, the bleaching solution of the present invention is
preferably incorporated with a compound selected from
imidazoles at a concentration of from 1 to 50 g/L. Preferable
imidazole compounds may have a substituent selected from alkyl
groups having 1 to 6 carbon atoms, alkenyl groups having 2 to
6 carbon atoms, hydroxyalkyl or carboxyalkyl groups having 1
to 6 carbon atoms, and carboxyl groups at the 1-, 2-, 4- or
5-position. Preferable examples of such imidazole compounds
include imidazole, 2-methylimidazole, 4-methylimidazole,
4-methyl-5-(hydroxymethyl)imidazole and
imidazole-4,5-dicarboxylic acid. Among these compounds,
imidazole, 2-methylimidazole and imidazole-4,5-dicarboxylic
acid are particularly preferred. The concentration of the
imidazole compound is preferably from 1.0 to 30.0 g/L, more
preferably from 1.5 to 5.0 g/L in the bleaching solution.</p>
    <p num="0079">The bleaching solution of the present invention is
reusable when the overflow solution after processing is
collected and appropriately replenished to recover the original 
composition. Such reusing methods are usually called
regeneration, to which reference can be made to paragraphs [0033]
to [0034] of Japanese Patent Application (Laid-Open) No.
303186/1993.</p>
    <p num="0080">The bleaching solution is used at a temperature between
20 and 50°C, preferably between 25 and 45°C. The solution may
contain various types of fluorescent brightening agents,
anti-foaming agents and surfactants.</p>
    <p num="0081">A preferable replenishing amount for the bleaching
solution of the present invention is up to 500 ml, more preferably
up to 300 ml, most preferably up to 200 ml, per 1 m<sup>2</sup> of silver
halide color photographic material. It is noted that, for the
lower replenishing amounts, the advantageous features of the
present invention become the more prominent.</p>
    <p num="0082">In order to activate the bleaching solution of the present
invention, the air or oxygen may be blown in the solution during
processing or in a stock tank of the bleaching solution or a
replenisher, if desired. Alternatively, a suitable oxidizing
agent such as hydrogen peroxide, bromate salts or persulfate
salts may be incorporated.</p>
    <p num="0083">Following the description on the bleaching solution used
in the present invention, the entire procedure of the color
reversal processing according to the present invention will
now be described. In the first place, the black-and-white
(first) development as the first step is explained. </p>
    <p num="0084">In the black-and-white development, the conventionally
known developing agents can be used, such as dihydroxybenzenes
(e.g., hydroquinone or hydroquinone monosulfonate),
3-pyrazolidones (e.g., 1-phenyl-3-pyrazolidone or
1-phenyl-4-methyl-4-hydroxymethyl-3-pyrazolidone),
aminophenols (e.g., N-methyl-p-aminophenol,
N-methyl-3-methyl-p-aminophenol and its derivatives),
ascorbic acid and its isomers and derivatives. These
developing agents may be used individually or in combination.
Preferable developing agents are potassium or sodium
hydroquinone monosulfonate. The developing agent is used at
a concentration of 1 x 10<sup>-5</sup> to 2 mol/L in the developer.</p>
    <p num="0085">The black-and-white developer used in the present
invention can contain a preservative if needed. As the
preservative, a sulfite salt or bisulfite salt is usually used
at a content of 0.01 to 1 mol/L, preferably 0.1 to 0.5 mol/L.
Ascorbic acid, which also acts as a very efficient preservative,
is used at a content of 0.01 to 0.5 mol/L. The hydroxylamines
represented by formula (I) in Japanese Patent Application
(Laid-Open) No. 144446/1991, saccharides, o-hydroxyketones and
hydrazines can also be used. The content of these compounds
is 0.1 mol/L or less. </p>
    <p num="0086">The pH of the black-and-white developer of the present
invention is preferably in the range of 8 to 12, most preferably
9 to 11. A variety of buffering agents can be adopted to maintain
a preferable pH value. Preferable buffering agents include
carbonates, phosphates, borates, 5-sulfosalicylic acid salts,
hydroxybenzoic acid salts, glycine salts, N,N-dimethylglycine
salts, leucine salts, norleucine salts, guanine salts,
3,4-dihydroxyphenylalanine salts, alanine salts, aminobutyric
acid salts, valine salts and lysine salts. From viewpoint of
keeping the above pH range and low cost, carbonates, borates
and 5-sulfosalicylic acid salts are specially preferred. These
buffering agents may be used individually or in combination
of two or more thereof. Furthermore, an acid and/or alkali
may be used together to secure the targeted pH value.</p>
    <p num="0087">As the acid compound, inorganic or organic water-soluble
acids can be preferably used, such as sulfuric, nitric,
hydrochloric, acetic, propionic or ascorbic acid. As the alkali
agent, various hydroxides or ammonium salts can be incorporated
preferably including potassium hydroxide, sodium hydroxide,
aqueous ammonia, triethanolamine and diethanolamine.</p>
    <p num="0088">The black-and-white developer for use in the present
invention preferably contains a silver halide solvent that acts
as development accelerator. Preferable examples include
thiocyan salt, sulfite salts, thiosulfate, 2-methylimidazole
and the thioethers described in Japanese Patent Application 
(Laid-Open) No. 63580/1982. A preferable addition amount of
the silver halide solvent is from 0.005 to 0.5 mol/L.</p>
    <p num="0089">Other development accelerators are quaternary amines,
poly(ethylene oxide)s, 1-phenyl-3-pyrrazolidone and its
derivatives, primary amines and
N,N,N',N'-tetramethyl-p-phenylenediamine.</p>
    <p num="0090">The black-and-white developer for use in the present
invention can further contain not only a dissolution aid such
as diethylene glycol, propylene glycol and other poly (ethylene
glycol)s and various amines including diethanolamine and
triethanolamine, but also a quaternary ammonium salts as a
sensitizing agent. Moreover, a surfactant and a gelatin
hardener may be incorporated.</p>
    <p num="0091">During the black-and-white development, a variety of
anti-foggants may be used for the purpose of preventing
development fog. Suitable anti-foggants include alkali metal
halides such as sodium chloride, potassium chloride, potassium
bromide, sodium bromide and potassium iodide, and organic
anti-foggants. Preferable organic anti-foggants include
nitrogen-containing heterocyclic compounds such as, for
example, benzotriazole, 6-nitrobenzoimidazole,
5-nitroisoindazole, 5-methylbenzotriazole,
5-nitrobenzotriazole, 5-chlorobenzotriazole,
2-thiazolyl-benzimidazole, 2-thiazolylmethyl-benzimidazole
and hydroxyazaindolizine, mercapto-substituted heterocyclic 
compounds such as 1-phenyl-5-mercaptotetrazole,
2-mercaptobenzimidazole and 2-mercaptobenzothiazole, and
mercapto-substituted aromatic compounds such as thiosalicylic
acid. The anti-foggant includes the components eluted from
the color reversal photographic materials during development
to accumulate in the bath.</p>
    <p num="0092">As an anti-foggant, the iodide is incorporated at a
concentration between 5 x 10<sup>-6</sup> and 5 x 10<sup>-4</sup> mol/L. The bromide,
which also preferably acts as an anti-foggant, is incorporated
at a concentration of 0.001 to 0.1 mol/L, and more preferably
0.01 to 0.05 mol/L.</p>
    <p num="0093">To the black-and-white developer for use in the present
invention, a swelling-suppressing agent (e.g., inorganic salts
such as sodium sulfate and potassium sulfate) and/or a hard
water-softener may be incorporated.</p>
    <p num="0094">Preferable hard water-softeners usable in the present
invention include amino-polycarboxylic acids,
amino-polyphosphonic acids, phosphonocarboxylic acids,
organic and inorganic phosphonic acids and the above-described
compounds represented by formula (I) that are associated with
the present invention. Some specific examples are shown below,
but the scope of the present invention is not restricted to
those examples at all. </p>
    <p num="0095">Ethylenediaminetetracetic acid, nitrilotriacetic acid,
hydroxyethyliminodiacetic acid, propylenediaminetetraacetic
acid, diethylentriaminepentaacetic acid,
triethylenetetraminehexaacetic acid,
nitrilo-N,N,N-trimethylenephosphonic acid, ethylenediamine-N,N,N',N'-tetramethylenephosphonic
acid and
1-hydroxyethylidene-1,1-diphosphonic acid. These hard
water-softening agents may be used individually or in
combination of two or more thereof. A preferable range for
the added amount of such a hard water-softening agent is from
0.1 to 20 g/L, more preferably from 0.5 to 10 g/L.</p>
    <p num="0096">The standard processing time of the black-and-white
development is, in most cases, from 4 to 8 min, and mostly 6
min. However, by extending or cutting short the development
time appropriately, the photographic speed of an improperly
exposed photographic material can be shifted to a higher or
lower value. Such process manipultion is called push/shallow
processing altogether. Usually, the photographic speed can
be regulated by changing the processing time between 2 and 18
min. The processing temperature is usually 20 to 50°C,
preferably 33 to 45°C. The replenishing amount of the
black-and-white developer is from 100 to 5000 ml per 1 m<sup>2</sup> of
the processed photographic material, preferably from 200 to
2500 ml per 1 m<sup>2</sup> of the processed photographic material. </p>
    <p num="0097">In the photographic processing of the present invention,
the black-and-white development is followed by rinsing with
water and/or a rinsing solution, if needed. Thereafter,
reversal processing and then color-forming development are
carried out.</p>
    <p num="0098">Though rinsing with water or a rinsing solution may be
carried out with a single bath, it is more preferable to adopt
a multi-stage counter current system using two or more tanks
in order to reduce the replenishing amount. In the rinsing
with water, a relatively large amount of water is replenished.
On the other hand, the rinsing with a rinsing solution is
conducted with a reduced replenishing amount comparable to the
replenishing amount for other processing baths. The
replenishing amount for the rinsing with water is preferably
from 3 to 20 L per 1m<sup>2</sup> of the photographic material. The
replenishing amount for the rinsing with a rinsing solution
is preferably from 50 ml to 2 L, more preferably from 100 ml
to 500 ml per 1 m<sup>2</sup> of the processed photographic material, thus
achieving a marked reduction of water usage compared with the
rinsing with water.</p>
    <p num="0099">The rinsing bath of the present invention may contain
an oxidizing agent, a chelating agent, a buffering agent, an
antiseptic, and a fluorescent brightening agent depending on
need. </p>
    <p num="0100">Then, an image-reversing step or light-fogging is
conducted. In the reversal bath, chemical fogging agents well
known in the art are contained. Useful fogging agents include
stannous ion-containing complex salts such as stannous
ion-organic phosphoric acid complex salts (U.S. Patent
3,617,282), stannous ion-organic phosphonocarboxylic acid
complex salts (Japanese Patent Publication No. 32616/1981) and
stannous ion-amino-polycarboxylic acid complex salts (U.S.
Patent 1,209,050); the stannous ion complex salts represented
by formulae (II) and (III) of Japanese Patent Application
(Laid-Open) No. 109573/1999; boron-containing compounds such
as borohydrides (U.S. Patent 2,984,567) and heterocyclic amine
borane salts (British Patent 1,011,000). The pH of the
reversal bath ranges from an acid to alkaline side depending
on the type of fogging agent used, namely from 2 to 12. More
frequently it ranges from 2.5 to 10, and more preferably from
3 to 9.</p>
    <p num="0101">The stannic ion in the reversal bath has a concentration
between 1 x 10<sup>-3</sup> and 5 x 10<sup>-2</sup> mol/L, preferably between 2 x 10<sup>-3</sup>
and 1.5 x 10<sup>-2</sup> mol/L. In the case where a boron-containing
fogging agent is used in the reversal bath, its concentration
is from 1 x 10<sup>-3</sup> and 5 x 10<sup>-2</sup> mol/L, preferably from 2 x 10<sup>-3</sup>
and 1.5 x 10<sup>-2</sup> mol/L. </p>
    <p num="0102">For the purpose of enhancing the solubility of the tin
(II) chelate, the reversal bath preferably contains propionic
acid, acetic acid or the alkylenedicarboxylic acid compounds
represented by formula (I) of Japanese Patent Application
(Laid-Open) No. 109572/1999. Among these, acetic acid is
particularly preferred. Further, the reversal bath preferably
contains a sorbic acid salt or the quaternary ammonium compound
described in U.S. Patent 5,811,225 as bactricide.</p>
    <p num="0103">The image reversal processing lasts usually for 10 sec
to 3 min, preferably for 20 sec to 2 min, and more preferably
for 30 to 90 sec. The temperature of the reversal bath, which
preferably is in the temperature range for either of the first
development, the subsequent rinsing or the rinsing with water,
and the color-forming development, is usually set at 20 to 50°C,
preferably 33 to 45°C.</p>
    <p num="0104">The replenishing amount for the reversal bath is 10 to
2000 ml, preferably 200 to 1500 ml per 1 m<sup>2</sup> of the processed
photographic material.</p>
    <p num="0105">Since tin (II) chelates and boron-containing fogging
agents are effecttive over a wide range of pH, the addition
of a pH-buffer is not required. However, it nonetheless causes
no harm to add a compound that provides pH-buffering capability.
Such compounds include acids, alkalis or salts exemplified by
organic acids such as citric or malic, inorganic acids such
as boric, sulfuric or hydrochloric, alkali carbonates, caustic 
alkalis, borax or potassium metaborate. If necessary, a hard
water-softening agent such as aminopolycarboxylic acid, a
swelling-suppressing agent such as sodium sulfate or an
anti-oxidant such as p-aminophenol may be added.</p>
    <p num="0106">The photographic material that has been processed with
a reversal bath then proceeds to a color-forming development
step. The color-forming developer for use in the color-forming
development of the present invention is an aqueous alkaline
solution mainly containing a color-forming developing agent
of an aromatic primary amine. As the color-forming developing
agent, p-phenylenediamines are preferably used. Typical
examples of such p-phenylenediamine compounds include
3-methyl-4-amino-N,N-diethylaniline,
3-methyl-4-amino-N-ethyl-N-β-hydroxyethylaniline,
3-methyl-4-amino-N-ethyl-N-β-methanesulfonamideethyl-aniline,
3-methyl-4-amino-N-ethyl-N-β-methoxyethylaniline,
and their salts such as sulfate, hydrochlorate, phosphate,
p-toluenesulfonate, tetraphenylborate,
p- (t-octyl)benzenesulfonate. Two or more compounds may be used
as the developing agent, if needed. A preferable concentration
of the color-forming developing agent is from 0.005 to 0.1 mol/L,
a more preferable one being from 0.01 to 0.05 mol/L.</p>
    <p num="0107">The pH of the color-forming developer for use in the present
invention is preferably 8 to 13, more preferably 10.0 to 12.5.
To keep the pH in the above range, a phosphate salt is used 
as an essential alkali agent in the present invention. Any
of tertiary, secondary or primary phosphates can be used wherein
the counter ion can be an alkali metal such as sodium, potassium
or lithium, ammonium and an organic onium. Among them, the
sodium or potassium salts are preferred. The concentration
of the phosphate salt is preferably 0.05 to 0.25 mol/L, more
preferably 0.05 to 0.15 mol/l in terms of phosphate ion
concentration. An alkali agent and a buffering agent other
than phosphates may be jointly used.</p>
    <p num="0108">Alkali agents and buffering agents which may be used in
combination with a phosphate salt and have a buffering region
of pH 8.0 or more include carbonates, borates,
5-sulfosalicylates, tetraborates, hydroxybenzoates, glycine
salts, N,N-dimethylglycine salts, leucine salts, norleucine
salts, guanine salts, 3,4-dihydroxyphenylalanine salts,
alanine salts, aminobutyrates,
2-amino-2-methyl-1,3-propanediol salts, valine salts, proline
salts, trishydroxyaminomethane salts and lysine salts. Among
these, carbonates and 5-sulfosalicylates are preferred due to
their high solubility and an excellent buffering ability at
a high pH region of 10.0 or more, thus effectively suppressing
the variation of pH by expanding the buffering region secured
by phosphate ion. </p>
    <p num="0109">Specific examples of the alkali agent and the buffering
agent include phosphates such as trisodium phosphate,
tripotassium phosphate, disodium phosphate and dipotassium
phosphate. Alkali agents which may be used in combination
with these include sodium and potassium carbonates, sodium and
potassium bicarbonates, dipotassium 5-sulfosalicylate, sodium
and potassium borate, sodium tetraborate (borax), potassium
tetraborate, sodium o-hydroxybenzoate (sodium salicylate),
potassium o-hydroxybenzoate, potassium
5-sulfo-2-hydroxybenzoate (sodium 5-sulfosalicylate) and
potassium 5-sulfo-2-hydroxybenzoate (potassium
5-sulfosalicylate). Preferable compounds are trisodium or
tripotassium phosphate, disodium or dipotassium phosphate,
dipotassium or disodium 5-sulfosalicylate.</p>
    <p num="0110">In using these buffering agents, one may add a single
phosphate (salt) or two or more in the developer, and can achieve
a targeted pH value by using an acid or an alkali agent.</p>
    <p num="0111">The added amount of the buffering agent in the developer
is preferably not less than 0.05 mol/L, more preferably 0.05
to 0.4 mol/L. In cases where two or more buffering agents are
jointly used, these values hold for the total amount thereof.</p>
    <p num="0112">In practicing the present invention, a various types of
development accelerators may be used according to need. </p>
    <p num="0113">Useful development accelerators include various
pyridinium compounds typically disclosed in U.S. Patent
2648604, and Japanese Patent Publication No. 9503/1969 and U.S.
Patent 3171247 and other cationic compounds; cationic dyes
such as phenosafranine; neutral salts such as thallium nitrate
and potassium nitrate; the poly(ethylene glycol)s and their
derivatives described in Japanese Patent Publication No.
9304/1969, U.S. Patents 2533990, 2531832, 2950970 and 2577127;
nonionic compounds such as polyethylene glycols and
polythioethers; and the thioether compounds described in U.S.
Patent 3201242.</p>
    <p num="0114">Further, depending on need, benzyl alcohol, diethylene
glycol that acts as solvent for benzyl alcohol, triethanolamine
and diethanolamine can be used. However, these compounds is
used as scarcely as possible, since they tend to cause various
problems including the increase of environmental load, solution
stability and the formation of tarry substance.</p>
    <p num="0115">Similarly to the black-and-white developer, a silver
halide solvent may be incorporated such as, for example, the
alkali metal salt of thiocyanic acid, 2-methylimidazole, the
thioether compounds disclosed in Japanese Patent Application
(Laid-Open) No. 63580/1982 and the like. A particularly
preferable compound is 3,6-dithiaoctane-1,8-diol. The
preferable content of the silver halide solvent is common to
that for the black-and-white developer used for the first 
development.</p>
    <p num="0116">Although fog prevention is not necessary for
color-forming development for the present invention, various
anti-foggants may be incorporated in the color-forming
developer for the purpose of maintaining the developer
composition and performance when the development is conducted
along with a constant feeding of color film rolls, i.e., in
the so-called running mode. Preferable anti-foggants used in
development include alkali metal halides such as potassium and
sodium chlorides, potassium and sodium bromide and potassium
iodide, and organic anti-foggants. Organic anti-foggants
include, for example, nitrogen-containing heterocyclic
compounds such as benzotriazole, 6-nitrobenzimidazole,
5-nitroisoindazole, 5-methylbenzotriazole,
5-methylbenzotriazole, 5-nitrobenzotriazole,
5-chlorobenzotriazole, 2-thiazolylbenzimidazole,
2-thiazolylmethylbenzimidazole and hydroxyazaindolizine;
mercapto-substituted heterocyclic compounds such as
1-phenyl-5-mercaptotetrazole, 2-mercaptobenzoimidazole and
2-mercaptobenzothiazole; and mercapto-substituted aromatic
compounds such as thiosalicylic acid. The anti-foggant in the
developer includes the component that is eluted from the
processed color reversal photographic material to accumulate
in the developer. Since the concentration of such anti-foggant
in the developer has little effect on the photographic 
characteristics in the case of color reversal development, any
control thereof is not necessary.</p>
    <p num="0117">Various preservatives can be used in the color-forming
developer for use in the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0118">Typical preservatives are hydroxylamines and sulfite
salts, the latter being more preferred. They are used at a
concentration of from 0 to 0.1 mol/L.</p>
    <p num="0119">The color-forming developer used in the present invention
may contain an organic preservative instead of hydroxyamine
or sulfite ion.</p>
    <p num="0120">The organic preservative means any organic compound
capable of retarding the deterioration of the primary aromatic
amine as the color-forming developing agent; more concretely,
it designates organic compounds having a function of preventing
the oxidation (e.g., by the air) of the color-forming developing
agent. Particularly effective organic preservatives include
hydroxylamine derivatives except hydroxylamine, hydroxamic
acids, hydrazines, hydrazides, phenols, α-hydroxyketones,
α-aminoketones, saccharides, monoamines, diamines, polyamines,
quaternary ammonium salts, nitroxy radicals, alcohols, oximes,
diamide compounds and condensed ring-type amines. These
compounds are described in Japanese Patent Publication No.
30496/1973, Japanese Patent Application (Laid-Open) Nos.
143020/1977, 4235/1988, 30845/1988, 21647/1988, 44655/1988,
53551/1988, 43140/1988, 56654/1988, 58346/1988, 43138/1988, 
146041/1988, 44657/1988 and 44656/1988, U.S. Patents 3,615,503
and 2,494,903, Japanese Patent Application (Laid-Open) Nos.
97953/1989, 186939/1989, 186940/1989, 187557/1989 and
306244/1990. Still other types of preservatives may be used
including the various metals disclosed in Japanese Patent
Application (Laid-Open) Nos. 44148/1982 and 53749/1982, the
salicylic acids disclosed in Japanese Patent Application
(Laid-Open) No. 180588/1984, the amines disclosed in Japanese
Patent Application (Laid-Open) Nos. 239447/1988, 128340/1988,
186939/1989 and 187557/1989, the alkanolamines described in
Japanese Patent Application (Laid-Open) No. 3532/1979, the
polyethyleneimines described in Japanese Patent Application
(Laid-Open) No. 94349/1981 and the aromatic polyhydroxy
compounds described in U.S. Patent 3,746,544 depending on need.
In particular, alkanolamines such as triethanolamine,
dialkylhydroxylamines such as N,N-diethylhydroxylamine and
N,N-di(sulfoethyl)hydroxylamine, hydrazine derivatives
except hydrazine such as N,N-bis(carboxymethyl)hydrazine, or
aromatic polyhydroxy compounds such as sodium
catechol-3,5-disulfonate are preferably added.</p>
    <p num="0121">The addition amount of such an organic preservative is
preferably 0.02 to 0.5 mol/L, more preferably 0.05 to 0.2 mol/L.
If necessary, two or more compounds may be jointly used. </p>
    <p num="0122">The color-forming developer of the present invention
may contain an organic solvent such as diethylene glycol and
triethylene glycol; a dye-forming coupler; a competing coupler
such as citrazinic acid, J-acid or H-acid; a nucleating agent
such as sodium boron hydride; an auxiliary developing agent
such as 1-phenyl-3-pyrrazolidone; a tackifier; a chelating
agent such as an aminopolycarboxylic acid (e.g.,
ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid, nitrilotriacetic acid,
cyclohexanediaminetetraacetic acid,
hydroxyethyliminodiacetic acid, iminodiacetic acid,
N-hydroxymethylethylenediaminetriacetic acid,
diethylenetriamine pentaacetic acid,
triethylenetetraminehexaacetic acid and the compounds
described in Japanese Patent Application (Laid-Open) No.
195845/1983), an organic phosphonic acid (e.g.,
1-hydroxyethylidene-1,1'-diphosphonic acid and those
described in Research Disclosure No. 18170 (1979 May)), an
aminophosphonic acid (e.g., aminotris(methylenephosphonic
acid), and
ethylenediamine-N,N,N',N'-tetramethylenphosphonic acid),
and a phosphonocarboxylic acid (e.g., those described in
Japanese Patent Application (Laid-Open) Nos. 102726/1978,
42730/1978, 121127/1979, 4024/1980, 4025/1980, 126241/1980,
65955/1980 and 65956/1980, and Research Disclosure No. 18170
(1979 May)). These chelating agents, two or more of which may 
be used together depending on need, may be contained at an amount
of 0.05 to 20 g/L, preferably 0.1 to 5 g/L.</p>
    <p num="0123">If necessary, a surfactant may be incorporated. Suitable
compounds include alkylsulfonic acids, arylsulfonic acids,
aliphatic and aromatic carboxylic acids and
polyalkyleneimines.</p>
    <p num="0124">The processing temperature of the color-forming
development applied to the present invention is 20 to 50°C,
preferably 33 to 45°C. The processing time is from 20 sec to
5 min, preferably from 20 sec to 4 min. The replenishing amount,
which is as small as possible within the range of maintaining
developer activity, is appropriately from 100 to 2500 ml,
preferably from 400 to 1200 ml per 1 m<sup>2</sup> of the processed
photographic material.</p>
    <p num="0125">The color reversal photographic material that has been
subjected to color-forming development is then subjected to
a desilvering treatment. The desilvering treatment is carried
out in one of the following procedures.
<sl><li>1. (Color-forming development) - Adjustment - Bleach - Fix</li><li>2. (Color-forming development) - Rinse with water - Bleach -
Fix</li><li>3. (Color-forming development) - Bleach - Fix</li><li>4. (Color-forming development) - Rinse with water - Bleach -
Rinse with water -Fix </li><li>5. (Color-forming development) - Bleach - Rinse with water -Fix</li><li>6. (Color-forming development) - Rinse with water - Blix</li><li>7. (Color-forming development) - Adjustment - Blix</li><li>8. (Color-forming development) - Blix</li><li>9. (Color-forming development) - Rinse with water - Bleach -
Blix</li><li>10. (Color-forming development) - Bleach - Blix</li><li>11. (Color-forming development) - Rinse with water -
Bleach - Blix - Fix</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0126">The "Adjustment" described above is sometimes called
"pre-bleaching".</p>
    <p num="0127">Among the exemplified procedures, No. 1 and No. 3 are
particularly preferred.</p>
    <p num="0128">Replenishment in each procedure may be carried out
individually on each processing bath in the conventional manner.
Alternatively, in Nos. 9 and 10, the solution overflowing from
the bleaching solution may be introduced to the blix bath,
whereby the blix bath is replenished only with the fixing
solution. In No. 11 the overflowing solution of the bleaching
solution is introduced to the blix bath, the overflowing solution
of the fixing solution is introduced to the blix bath by means
of counterflow system, whereby the two introduced solutions
are overflown from the blix bath. </p>
    <p num="0129">In practicing the present invention, a variety of blix
accelerators can be incorporated in the bleaching or blix bath,
or the adjustment bath preceding the bleaching or blix treatment.</p>
    <p num="0130">Examples of such blix accelerators include the various
mercapto compounds disclosed in U.S. Patent 3,893,858, British
1,138,842 and Japanese Patent Application (Laid-Open) No.
141623/1978 ; the disulfide bond-containing compounds described
in Japanese Patent Application (Laid-Open) No. 95630/1978; the
thiazolidine derivatives described in Japanese Patent
Publication No. 9854/1978; the isothiourea derivatives
described in Japanese Patent Application (Laid-Open) No.
94927/1978; the thiourea derivatives described in Japanese
Patent Publication Nos. 8506/1970 and 26586/1974; the thioamide
compounds described in Japanese Patent Application (Laid-Open)
No. 42349/1974; and the dithiocarbamic acid salts described
in Japanese Patent Application (Laid-Open) No. 26506/1970.
Still other examples of blix accelerators include alkylmercapto
compounds unsubstituted or substituted with a hydroxy group,
a carboxyl group, a sulfonic acid group or an amino group. The
amino group may have a substituent such as alkyl or acetoxyalkyl.
Specific compounds are, for example, trithioglycerin,
α,α'-thiodipropionic acid and δ-mercaptobutyric acid. The
compounds described in U.S. Patent 4,552,834 can also be used. </p>
    <p num="0131">In cases where a compound containing a mercapto group
or a disulfide bond in the molecule or a thiazoline derivative
or an isothiourea derivative is contained in the adjustment
or bleaching solution, the content thereof, which depends on
the type of the photographic material to be processed, the
processing temperature and the processing time needed for the
processing in concern, is appropriately 1 x 10<sup>-5</sup> to 10<sup>-1</sup> mol,
preferably 1 x 10<sup>-4</sup> to 5 x 10<sup>-2</sup> mol per 1 liter of the processing
solution.</p>
    <p num="0132">In the adjustment solution, an image-stabilizing agent
is preferably incorporated. In particular, the
formaldehyde-bisulfide adduct described in U.S. Patent
5,037,725 is preferably contained. The secondary amine
described in U.S. Patent 5,523,195 may be incorporated. The
pH of the adjustment solution is usually 3 to 11, preferably
4 to 9, and more preferably 4.5 to 7. The processing time with
the adjustment solution is preferably for 20 sec to 3 min, more
preferably 20 sec to 2 min, and most preferably 30 to 60 sec.
The replenishing amount for the adjustment solution is
preferably from 30 to 2000 ml, particularly preferably from
50 to 1500 ml per 1 m<sup>2</sup> of the processed photographic material.
The temperature for the adjustment processing is preferably
from 20 to 50°C, particularly preferably from 30 to 40°C. </p>
    <p num="0133">The blix (bleach-fix) solution contains as a fixing agent
a water-soluble silver halide solvent including thiosulfate
salts such as sodium or ammonium thiosulfate, thiocyanate salts
such as sodium, ammonium or potassium thiocyanate, thioether
compounds such as ethylenebisthioglycolic acid or
3,6-dithia-1,8-octanediol, and thiourea. These compounds may
be used individually or in combination of two or more thereof.
In some cases, a special blix formulation comprising a fixing
agent and a large amount of a halide such as potassium iodide
as described in Japanese Patent Application (Laid-Open) No.
155354/1980 can be adopted, too. The amount of such a fixing
agent is from 0.1 to 3 mol, preferably from 0.2 to 2 mol per
1 liter of the blix solution.</p>
    <p num="0134">The advantageous effects of the present invention, i.e.,
prevention color restoration failure, stain reduction and
smudge prevention for the processed material are fully achieved
when the bleaching solution having a specific pH value contains
an iron (III) complex salt represented by formula (I) or (II)
together with a carboxylic acid represented by formula [A],
and when the fixing or blix solution contains a compound selected
from imidazoles at a content of 1 to 50 g/L.</p>
    <p num="0135">Preferable imidazoles include unsubstituted imidazole,
those having at the 1-, 2-, 4- or 5-position a substituent
selected from an alkyl group having 1 to 6 carbon atoms, an
alkenyl group having 2 to 6 carbon atoms, a hydroxyalkyl or 
carboxyalkyl group having 1 to 6 carbon atoms or an imidazol
derivatives substituted with a carboxyl group. Specially
preferable imidazole derivatives are imidazole,
2-methylimidazole, 4-methylimidazole,
4-methyl-5-(hydroxymethyl)imidazole and
imidazole-4,5-dicarboxylic acid. Among these, imidazole,
2-methylimidazole and imidazole-4,5-dicarboxylic acid are
still more preferred, imidazole being the most preferred. The
content range for such an imidazole derivative is preferably
1 to 25 g/L, more preferably 1.5 to 10 g/L.</p>
    <p num="0136">In the case where a fixing solution is used in the present
invention, the fixing agent thereof is a water-soluble silver
halide solvent well known in the art, including thiosulfates
such as sodium or ammonium thiosulfate, thiocyanate salts such
as sodium, ammonium or potassium thiocyanate, thioether
compounds such as ethylenebisthioglicolic acid or
3,6-dithia-1,8-octanediol, and thiourea. These compounds may
be individually or in combination of two or more thereof. The
concentration of such a fixing agent is from 0.1 to 3 mol,
preferably 0.2 to 2 mol per 1 L of the fixing solution. In
addition to the various additive described previously, the
solution having a fixing function can contain, as a preservative,
a sulfite salt (e.g., sodium, potassium or ammonium sulfite),
a bisulfite salt, hydroxylamine, hydrazine or an
aldehyde-bisulfite adduct (e.g., acetaldehyde-sodium 
bisulfite). Other effective preservatives include sulfinic
acids (e.g., benzenesulfinic acid) and ascorbic acid. The
solution may further contain a fluorescent brightening agent
of various types, an anti-foaming agent, a surfactant,
polyvinylpyrrolidone, a bactericide, a fungicide or an organic
solvent such as methanol.</p>
    <p num="0137">In the present invention, well-known compounds such as
bistriazinylarylenediamine may be used depending on need. As
other fluorescent brightening agents,
bis(triazinylamino)stylbenesulfonic acid compounds can also
be used, including conventionally known or commercially
available diaminostylbene compounds. Particularly, those
described in Japanese Patent Application (Laid-Open) Nos.
329936/1994, 140625/1995 and 140849/1998 are preferably used.
As for commercially available compounds, descriptions are found
in, for example, <i>Senshoku Nouto</i> (Book on Dyeing) 9th Edition
(published by Irozomesha) , pp. 165 to 168. Among the compounds
described therein, Blankophor BSU liq. and Hakkol BRK are
specially preferred.</p>
    <p num="0138">Though these triazine group-containing compounds may be
incorporated in any processing bath, they are preferably
incorporated in the color-forming developer or the fixing
solution. </p>
    <p num="0139">The replenishing amount for the bleaching, fixing or blix
bath, which can be set arbitrary so as to maintain the function
of each bath, is preferably 30 to 2,000 ml, more preferably
50 to 1,000 ml per 1 m<sup>2</sup> of the processed photographic material.</p>
    <p num="0140">The processing temperature is preferably 20 to 50°C, more
preferably 33 to 45°C, while the processing time is 10 sec to
10 min, preferably 20 sec to 6 min.</p>
    <p num="0141">After desilvered by fixing or blix treatment, the
photographic material is usually subjected to rinsing and/or
stabilizing treatment. The stabilizing bath usually but not
always contains an image stabilizer. Stabilizing baths not
containing stabilizer are called wash-replacing stabilizing
bath to differentiate from stabilizer-containing ones. The
function of such a wash-replacing stabilizing bath is regarded
as substantially the same as that of the rinse bath (washing
bath). Accordingly, in the following, a common explanation
will be given for all the related processing steps except image
stabilizing step.</p>
    <p num="0142">The amount of washing water in the water-washing step
is set in the wide range according to various conditions such
as the characteristics of the photographic material, the use,
the water-washing temperature and the number of washing tank
(the number of stages). </p>
    <p num="0143">The relation between the number of washing tanks and the
quantity of water for a multi-stage counter-current system can
be obtained by the method described in Journal of the Society
of Motion Picture and Television Engineers, 64, pp. 248 to 253
(May, 1955). The number of steps in the multi-stage
counter-current system is preferably between 2 and 15,
particularly preferably between 2 and 10.</p>
    <p num="0144">Although adoption of a multi-stage counter-current system
achieves a remarkable reduction of the amount of washing water,
bacteria propagates in the tanks due to an increased retention
time of water whereby floating matters are formed and tend to
deposit on the photographic material. To solve this problem,
the method of reducing the amount of calcium and magnesium as
described in Japanese Patent Application (Laid-Open) No.
288838/1987 is quite effective. It is also effective to use
the isothiazolones or cyabendazoles described in Japanese
Patent Application (Laid-Open) No. 8542/1983, chlorine-based
bactericides such as chlorinated sodium isocyanurate disclosed
in Japanese Patent Application (Laid-Open) No. 120145/1986,
benzotriazoles described in Japanese Patent Application
(Laid-Open) No. 267761/1986, cupper ion, and the bactericides
described in <i>Bokin, Bobai no Kagaku</i> (Bactericidal and Fungicidal
Chemistry) authored by Hiroshi Horiguchi (1986, Sankyo Shuppan),
<i>Biseibutsu no Mekkin, Sakkin, Bobai Gijutsu</i> (Sterilizing,
Bactericidal and Antifungal Technologies for Microorganism) 
edited by Eisei Gijutsu Kai (Society for Hygiene Technology)
(1982, Kogyo Gijutsu Kai) and Bokin- Bokabi-zai Jiten
(Encyclopedia of Antibacterial and Antifungal Agents) edited
by the Society for Antibacterial and Antifungal Agents, Japan
(1986).</p>
    <p num="0145">Further, aldehydes such as formaldehyde, acetaldehyde
or pyruvinaldehyde, which inactivate remaining magenta
couplers thus preventing dye fading as well as stain formation,
the methylol compounds and hexamethylenetetramine described
in U.S. Patent 4786583, the hexahydrotriazines described in
Japanese Patent Application (Laid-Open) No. 153348/1990, the
formaldehyde-bisulfite adduct described in U.S. Patent .
4921779, and the azolylmethylamines described in European
Patent Application (Laid-Open) Nos. 504609 and 519190 may be
incorporated.</p>
    <p num="0146">As is described in U.S. Patents 4960687, 4975356 and
5037725, it is preferred to incorporate an image stabilizer
or a precursor thereof in the adjusting bath, and not to
incorporate any image stabilizer in the stabilizing bath from
the viewpoint of preventing film surface contamination after
processing and uneven development.</p>
    <p num="0147">In washing water, the stabilizing bath or the rinse
solution, a surfactant as a water-draining agent, EDTA or a
chelating agent such as those represented by formula (II) as
a hard water-softener may be incorporated. </p>
    <p num="0148">Suitable surfactants include nonionic ones of
poly (ethylene glycol) type or polyhydric alcohol type, anionic
ones such as alkylbenzenesulfonic acid salts, sulfuric acid
esters of higher alcohols or alkylnaphthalenesulfonic acid
salts, cationic ones such as quaternary ammonium salts or amine
salts, or amphoteric ones such as amino acid salts or betaines.
Two or more of these surfactants may be used together. The
fluorine-containing surfactants as disclosed in U.S. Patent
5,716,765 or siloxane-type ones may be also used.</p>
    <p num="0149">Among various nonionic surfactants, alkyl poly (ethylene
oxide)s, alkyl phenoxypoly(ethylene oxide)s or alkyl
phenoxypoly(hydroxypropylene oxide)s are preferred. And
particularly preferable anionic surfactants are those
comprising an alkyl-poly(oxyethylene) of 8 to 15 carbon atoms
and an alcohol of 10 to 30 carbon atoms, the most preferable
ones being those comprising an alkyl-poly(oxyethylene) of 8
to 11 carbon atoms and an alcohol of 15 to 25 carbon atoms.</p>
    <p num="0150">In order to enhance the solubility of surfactants, a
solubilizing agent such as amines (e.g., diethanolamine or
triethanolamine) or glycols (e.g., diethylene glycol or
propylene glycol) are preferably incorporated.</p>
    <p num="0151">In the stabilizing or rinse bath, a chelating agent is
preferably incorporated in order to capture heavy metals, thus
improving the solution stability and reducing contamination.
As the chelating agent, one can utilize the same compounds that 
are incorporated in the developer and the bleaching solution
as described hereinabove. The stabilizing or rinse bath
preferably contains a bactericide and a fungicide with the
purpose of preventing the propagation of bacteria and fungi.
Commercially available bactericides and fungicides can be used
for such a purpose. Furthermore, the baths may contain a
surfactant, a fluorescent brightening agent and a hardener.</p>
    <p num="0152">The pH of the stabilizing or rinse bath, and that of the
washing water for use in the present invention is usually between
4 and 9, and preferably between 5 and 8. Ordinary ranges of
the processing temperature and time for these baths are from
15 to 45°C and from 20 sec to 10 min, preferably from 25 to
40°C and from 30 sec to 2 min, though they vary widely depending
on the nature and the application of the photographic material
to be processed. It is noted that the stabilizing or rinse
bath of the present invention exhibits a marked advantageous
effect of contamination prevention in the case where the
photographic material is processed by a desilvering treatment
immediately followed by a treatment with the stabilizing or
rinse bath of the present invention, i.e., without intervening
washing with water after desilvering.</p>
    <p num="0153">The replenishing amount of the stabilizing or rinse bath
of the present invention is preferably 200 to 2,000 ml per 1
m<sup>2</sup> of the processed photographic material. The overflowing
liquid yielded along with the replenishment of the washing water 
and/or the stabilizing solution can be again used in other
processing steps including desilvering.</p>
    <p num="0154">To reduce the use amount of washing water, ion exchange,
reverse osmosis or ultra-filtration is effectively adopted.
Among these methods, ultra-filtration is particularly
preferred. All the processing solutions used to practice the
present invention work at a temperature between 10 and 50°C.
Although the temperature usually is in the range of from 33
to 38°C, one can adopt higher temperatures exceeding the upper
limit to accelerate processing thus curtailing the processing
time, or lower ones below the lower limit to improve image quality
as well as the solution stability.</p>
    <p num="0155">In the case where the stabilization treatment is conducted
without washing with water in the processing of photographic
materials according to the present invention, the methods well
known in the art and described in Japanese Patent Application
(Laid-Open) Nos. 8543/1982, 14834/1983 and 220345/1985 can
be adopted. Alternatively, as preferable embodiments of the
present invention, chelating agents such as
1-hydroxyethylidene-1,1-diphosphonic acid and
ethylenediaminetetramethylenephosphonic acid, or a magnesium
or bismuth compound can be used.</p>
    <p num="0156">The photographic material having been subjected to
washing with water and/or stabilization treatment is then dried.
The material just after leaving the washing bath may be squeezed 
with a squeezing roller or a piece of water-absorbing cloth
to decrease the water content in the image-forming layers and
accelerate drying. To improve the drying efficiency of the
dryer, adoption of higher temperatures or modifying the nozzle
shape to intensify the drying air stream is self-evidently
effective. Film drying can also be accelerated by the
adjustment of the angle at which the drying air is directed
toward the material surface as described in Japanese Patent
Application (Laid-Open) No. 157650/1991.</p>
    <p num="0157">Color photographic materials for use in practicing the
present invention are described hereinbelow. The amount of
developed silver in the present invention indicates the total
of the silver amounts developed by black-and-white and
color-forming developments. Thus, the total amount of
developed silver reaches to 3.0 to 7.0 g/m<sup>2</sup> when the processed
photographic material is a reversal-type color material such
as a reversal color film. While commercially available color
negative photographic materials and reflection-type color
photographic materials such as color photographic paper are
developed only at exposed areas thereof thus giving the amount
of developed silver below 2 g/m<sup>2</sup>, the reversal color photographic
material undergoes development at exposed areas in the first
development, and then color-forming development of the
unexposed, remaining silver halide. This means that more than
90%, substantially 100% of the silver halide contained in the 
photographic material is developed. Hence, the bleaching load
for the reversal material is much higher than those for color
negative films or color papers, thus sometimes resulting in
incomplete bleaching. The present invention exhibits its
advantageous features particularly in the processing of color
reversal films.</p>
    <p num="0158">Usually, silver halide color reversal films comprise a
red-sensitive unit, a green-sensitive unit and a blue-sensitive
unit arranged on a support in this order described from the
support side. Between the red-sensitive unit and the
green-sensitive unit, and/or between the green-sensitive unit
and the blue-sensitive unit, one or more interlayers that do
not form color are provided.</p>
    <p num="0159">In the case where each photosensitive unit comprises three
layers, a low-speed emulsion layer, a medium-speed emulsion
layer and a high-speed emulsion layer are preferably arranged
in this order from the support side. Between these emulsion
layers, a photo-insensitive interlayer that may contain a
photo-insensitive silver halide emulsion may be provided.</p>
    <p num="0160">Although all of the blue-, green- and red-sensitive units
preferably comprise three layers, it is also possible to have
the blue-sensitive unit comprising two layers or less, and the
green- and red-sensitive units comprising three layers. </p>
    <p num="0161">The blue-sensitive layers contain a yellow coupler, the
green-sensitive ones contain a magenta coupler, and the
red-sensitive ones contain a cyan coupler. However, for the
purpose of controlling color reproduction capability, the other
couplers may be mixed in the above combinations.</p>
    <p num="0162">It is preferred to divide the total amount of silver halide
emulsion within the unit to the high-speed layer in 10 to 60%
by weight, to the medium-speed layer in 10 to 50% by weight
and to the low-speed layer in 30 to 70% by weight. The
silver/coupler ratio in each photosensitive layer is preferably
regulated so as to be the largest in the low-speed layer.</p>
    <p num="0163">An interlayer that does not develop color is preferably
provided between the units each being different in spectral
sensitivity. Such a non-color-forming interlayer may contain
a photo sensitive emulsion, a photo-insensitive one or one fogged
in advance.</p>
    <p num="0164">The interlayer may be of monolayer structure or comprise
two to five sub-layers. In the latter case, it is preferred
that a sub-layer placed far from the support contains colloidal
silver particles or a silver halide emulsion that has been
superficially or internally fogged beforehand. In the case
where a silver halide emulsion is incorporated in an interlayer,
the interlayer or the layer adjacent to the interlayer is
preferably contain a color mixing-preventing agent. </p>
    <p num="0165">A more preferable embodiment of the color reversal film
associated with the present invention is described below.</p>
    <p num="0166">On a support are provided a red-sensitive unit, a
green-sensitive unit and a blue-sensitive unit in this order
from the support side wherein at least the red- and
green-sensitive units comprise three photosensitive emulsion
layers. And the three emulsion layers are arranged in the order
of low-speed, medium-speed and high-speed layers from the
support side. The silver/coupler ratio in these photosensitive
layers is preferably from 25 to 150 whereby the medium-speed
layer has a silver/coupler ratio of 5 to 30, and the high-speed
layer has a silver/coupler ratio of 2 to 20.</p>
    <p num="0167">Further, between the red-sensitive unit and the
green-sensitive unit, and between the green-sensitive unit and
the blue-sensitive unit, an interlayer comprising two to five
sub-layers is provided. In the interlayer provided between
the red- and green-sensitive units, the sub-layer adjacent to
the green-sensitive layer may contain colloidal silver
particles or a fogged silver halide emulsion. In the interlayer
provided between the green- and blue-sensitive units, the
sub-layer adjacent to the blue-sensitive layer may contain
colloidal silver particles or a fogged silver halide emulsion.
The thickness of the interlayer (total of all the sub-layer
thickness) is usually 0.5 to 5 µm, preferably 1.0 to 3.0 µm.
The thickness can be readily obtained from the specific gravity 
of each ingredient, or alternatively by examining the
cross-section of the coated product with an electron microscope.</p>
    <p num="0168">It is further preferable to arrange an anti-halation layer
in the support side of the red-sensitive unit, and at least
one protective layer located farther than the blue-sensitive
unit from the support. At least one of protective layer
preferably contains a silver halide emulsion.</p>
    <p num="0169">Various techniques as well as inorganic or organic
materials applicable to the silver halide emulsion and the silver
halide photographic material using the emulsion for use in the
present invention are described in the following parts of
European Patent No. 436938A2 and in the other European Patents
described below.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="left">No.</entry><entry align="left">Item</entry><entry align="left">Reference site</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="left">Layer structure</entry><entry align="left">From p. 146, line 34 to p. 147, line 25.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2</entry><entry align="left">Silver halide emulsion</entry><entry align="left">From p. 147, line 26 to p. 148, line 12.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">Yellow coupler</entry><entry align="left">From p. 137, line 35 to p. 146, line 33, and p. 149, lines 21 to 23.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">Magenta coupler</entry><entry align="left">From p. 149, lines 24 to 12; Eu. P. No. 421,453A1, from p. 3, line 5 to p. 25, line 55.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="left">Cyan coupler</entry><entry align="left">From p. 149, lines 29 to 33; Eu. P. No. 432,804A2, from p. 3, line 28 to p. 40, line 2.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">6</entry><entry align="left">Polymer coupler</entry><entry align="left">From p. 149, lines 34 to 38; Eu. P. No. 435,334A1, from p. 113, line 39 top. 123, line 37.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">7</entry><entry align="left">Colored coupler</entry><entry align="left">From p. 53, line 42 to p. 137, line 34, and from p. 149, lines 39 to 45. </entry></row><row><entry align="left">8</entry><entry align="left">Other functional coupler</entry><entry align="left">From p. 7, line 1 to p. 53, line 41, and from p. 149, line 46 to p. 150, line 3; Eu. P. No. 435,334A2, from p. 3, line 1 to p. 29, line 50.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">9</entry><entry align="left">Antiseptic, preservative</entry><entry align="left">From p. 150, lines 25 to 28.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="left">Formalin scavenger</entry><entry align="left">From p. 149, lines 15 to 17.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">11</entry><entry align="left">Other additives</entry><entry align="left">From p. 153, lines 38 to 47; Eu. P. No. 421,453A1, from p. 75, line 21 to p. 84, line 56.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">12</entry><entry align="left">Dispersing method</entry><entry align="left">From p. 150, lines 4 to 24.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">13</entry><entry align="left">Support</entry><entry align="left">From p. 150, lines 32 to 34.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">14</entry><entry align="left">Layer thickness, physical property of film</entry><entry align="left">From p. 150, lines 35 to 49.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">15</entry><entry align="left">Color-forming development, black-and-white development</entry><entry align="left">From p. 150, line 50 to p. 151, line 47; fogging process of Eu. P. No. 442,323A2, from p. 34, lines 11 to 54, and from p. 27, line 40 to p. 37, line 40.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">16</entry><entry align="left">Desilvering</entry><entry align="left">From p. 151, line 48 to p. 152, line 53.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">17</entry><entry align="left">Automatic processor</entry><entry align="left">From p. 152, line 54 to p.153, line 2.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">18</entry><entry align="left">Washing and stabilizing processes</entry><entry align="left">From p. 153, lines 3 to 37.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLE</u>
    </heading>
    <heading>(Example 1)</heading>
    <p num="0170">The present invention is explained more in detail with
reference to examples, which, however, are not construed to
restrict the scope of the present invention.</p>
    <heading>(1) Preparation of photographic material</heading>
    <heading>Preparation of Sample 101:</heading>
    <p num="0171">On a support comprising a 127 µm-thick cellulose
triacetate film that had been coated with a subbing layer, the
layers of the following compositions were provided to prepare
a multi-layer color photographic material. The resulting
material was designated as Sample 101. In the following
compositions, the numerals indicate the added amount per m<sup>2</sup>.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">First layer: anti-halation layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Black colloidal silver</entry><entry align="center">0.25 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gelatin</entry><entry align="center">2.40 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UV absorber U-1</entry><entry align="center">0.10 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UV absorber U-3</entry><entry align="center">0.10 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UV absorber U-4</entry><entry align="center">0.10 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-1</entry><entry align="center">0.050 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-2</entry><entry align="center">0.050 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-5</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dye D-4</entry><entry align="center">1.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dye D-8</entry><entry align="center">2.5 mg </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fine-crystalline solid dispersion of Dye E-1</entry><entry align="center">0.05 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Second layer: inter-layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gelatin</entry><entry align="center">0.40 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-A</entry><entry align="center">0.2 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-J</entry><entry align="center">1.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-K</entry><entry align="center">3.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-M</entry><entry align="center">0.030 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UV absorber U-6</entry><entry align="center">6.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-3</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-4</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-7</entry><entry align="center">2.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-8</entry><entry align="center">4.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dye D-7</entry><entry align="center">4.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Third layer: inter-layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Yellow colloidal silver</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gelatin</entry><entry align="center">0.50 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-M</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-3</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fourth layer: low-speed red-sensitive emulsion layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Emulsion A</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.20 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Emulsion B</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.20 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Emulsion C</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.15 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gelatin</entry><entry align="center">0.70 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-1</entry><entry align="center">0.050 g </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-2</entry><entry align="center">0.080 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-3</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-6</entry><entry align="center">6.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-9</entry><entry align="center">5.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-11</entry><entry align="center">0.030 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UV absorber U-1</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UV absorber U-2</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-A</entry><entry align="center">1.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-I</entry><entry align="center">0.020 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-J</entry><entry align="center">2.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-2</entry><entry align="center">0.10 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-5</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Additive P-1</entry><entry align="center">0.020 g</entry></row><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1">Fifth layer: medium-speed red-sensitive emulsion layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Emulsion C</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.25 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Emulsion D</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.25 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gelatin</entry><entry align="center">0.60 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-1</entry><entry align="center">0.040 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-2</entry><entry align="center">0.10 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-3</entry><entry align="center">0.020 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-6</entry><entry align="center">7.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-11</entry><entry align="center">0.050 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UV absorber U-1</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UV absorber U-2</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-2</entry><entry align="center">0.10 g </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Additive P-1</entry><entry align="center">0.020 g</entry></row><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1">Fifth layer: high-speed red-sensitive emulsion layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Emulsion E</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.25 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Emulsion F</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.35 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gelatin</entry><entry align="center">1.50 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-1</entry><entry align="center">0.10 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-3</entry><entry align="center">0.060 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-6</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-11</entry><entry align="center">0.020 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UV absorber U-1</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UV absorber U-2</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-2</entry><entry align="center">0. 10 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-9</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-K</entry><entry align="center">1.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-L</entry><entry align="center">1.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-F</entry><entry align="center">0.050 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Additive P-1</entry><entry align="center">0.10 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Seventh layer: inter-layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gelatin</entry><entry align="center">0.70 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Additive P-2</entry><entry align="center">0.10 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-I</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dye D-5</entry><entry align="center">0.020 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dye D-9</entry><entry align="center">6.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-M</entry><entry align="center">0.040 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-O</entry><entry align="center">3.0 mg </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-P</entry><entry align="center">5.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-6</entry><entry align="center">0.050 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Eighth layer: inter-layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Yellow colloidal silver</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gelatin</entry><entry align="center">1.00 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Additive P-2</entry><entry align="center">0.05 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UV absorber U-1</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UV absorber U-3</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-A</entry><entry align="center">0.050 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-M</entry><entry align="center">0.050 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-3</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-6</entry><entry align="center">0.050 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ninth layer: low-speed green-sensitive emulsion layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Emulsion G</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.20 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Emulsion H</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.35 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Emulsion I</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.30 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gelatin</entry><entry align="center">1.50 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-4</entry><entry align="center">0.020 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-7</entry><entry align="center">0.070 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-8</entry><entry align="center">0.070 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-12</entry><entry align="center">0.020 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-13</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-B</entry><entry align="center">0.030 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-D</entry><entry align="center">5.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-E</entry><entry align="center">5.0 mg </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-G</entry><entry align="center">2.5 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-F</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-K</entry><entry align="center">2.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UV absorber U-6</entry><entry align="center">5.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-2</entry><entry align="center">0.15 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-6</entry><entry align="center">0.030 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-4</entry><entry align="center">8.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Additive P-1</entry><entry align="center">5.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1">Tenth layer: medium-speed green-sensitive emulsion layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Emulsion I</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.30 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Emulsion J</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.30 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(An internally fogged silver bromide emulsion (cubic grains with an average equivalent sphere grain diameter of 0.11 µm)</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 5. 0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gelatin</entry><entry align="center">0.70 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-4</entry><entry align="center">0.030 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-8</entry><entry align="center">0.020 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-12</entry><entry align="center">0.020 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-13</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-B</entry><entry align="center">0.030 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-F</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-G</entry><entry align="center">2.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-2</entry><entry align="center">0.050 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-5</entry><entry align="center">6. 0 mg </entry></row><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1">Eleventh layer: high-speed green-sensitive emulsion layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Emulsion K</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.55 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gelatin</entry><entry align="center">0.70 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-3</entry><entry align="center">5.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-4</entry><entry align="center">0.35 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-8</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-12</entry><entry align="center">0.020 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-B</entry><entry align="center">0.050 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-F</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-K</entry><entry align="center">2.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-2</entry><entry align="center">0. 050 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Twelfth layer: inter-layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gelatin</entry><entry align="center">0.30 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-M</entry><entry align="center">0.05 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-3</entry><entry align="center">0.025 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-6</entry><entry align="center">0.025 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dye D-6</entry><entry align="center">5.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Thirteenth layer: yellow filter layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Yellow colloidal silver</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.050 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gelatin</entry><entry align="center">0.70 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-C</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-M</entry><entry align="center">0.030 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-1</entry><entry align="center">0.020 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-6</entry><entry align="center">0.030 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fine-crystalline solid dispersion of Dye E-2</entry><entry align="center">0.030 g </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fourteenth: inter-layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gelatin</entry><entry align="center">0.30 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-Q</entry><entry align="center">0.20 g</entry></row><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1">Fifteenth layer: low-speed blue-sensitive emulsion layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Emulsion L</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.20 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Emulsion M Silver amount</entry><entry align="center">0.20 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gelatin</entry><entry align="center">0.80 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-5</entry><entry align="center">0.30 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-6</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-10</entry><entry align="center">0.030 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-I</entry><entry align="center">8.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-K</entry><entry align="center">1.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-M</entry><entry align="center">5.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UV absorber U-6</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-2</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-3</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1">Sixteenth layer: medium-speed blue-sensitive emulsion layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Emulsion N</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.20 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Emulsion O</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.20 g</entry></row><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1">(An internally fogged silver bromide emulsion: cubic grains</entry></row><row><entry align="left">with an average equivalent sphere grain diameter of 0.11 µm)</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.010 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gelatin</entry><entry align="center">0.90 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-5</entry><entry align="center">0.50 g </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-6</entry><entry align="center">0.020 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-10</entry><entry align="center">0.060 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-N</entry><entry align="center">2.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-2</entry><entry align="center">0.080 g</entry></row><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1">Seventeenth layer: high-speed blue-sensitive emulsion layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Emulsion O</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.20 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Emulsion P</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.25 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gelatin</entry><entry align="center">2.00 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-3</entry><entry align="center">5.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-5</entry><entry align="center">0.20 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-6</entry><entry align="center">0.020 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupler C-10</entry><entry align="center">1.00 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-2</entry><entry align="center">0.10 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-6</entry><entry align="center">0.020 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UV absorber U-6</entry><entry align="center">0.10 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-B</entry><entry align="center">0.020 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-N</entry><entry align="center">5.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Eighteenth layer: first protective layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gelatin</entry><entry align="center">0.80 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UV absorber U-1</entry><entry align="center">0.10 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UV absorber U-2</entry><entry align="center">0.050 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UV absorber U-5</entry><entry align="center">0.20 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-O</entry><entry align="center">5.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-A</entry><entry align="center">0.030 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound Cpd-H</entry><entry align="center">0.20 g </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dye D-1</entry><entry align="center">8.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dye D-2</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dye D-3</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-3</entry><entry align="center">0.10 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Nineteenth layer: second protective layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Colloidal silver</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.11 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fine grain silver iodobromide emulsion with an average grain size of 0.06 µm and AgI content of 1 mol%</entry><entry align="center">Silver amount 0.10 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gelatin</entry><entry align="center">0.70 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UV absorber U-1</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UV absorber U-6</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High boiling point organic solvent Oil-3</entry><entry align="center">0.010 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Twentieth layer: third protective layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gelatin</entry><entry align="center">1.00 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Poly(methyl methacrylate) (average particle size: 1.5 µm)</entry><entry align="center">0.10 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Methyl methacrylate/methacrylic acid copolymer (6:4) (average particle size: 1.5 µm)</entry><entry align="center">0.10 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Silicone oil SO-1</entry><entry align="center">0.10 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Surfactant W-1</entry><entry align="center">3.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Surfactant W-2</entry><entry align="center">8.0 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Surfactant W-3</entry><entry align="center">0.040 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Surfactant W-7</entry><entry align="center">0.015 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0172">In addition to the above-described ingredients, every
emulsion layer was added with additives F-1 to F-8. Further,
each layer was incorporated with gelatin hardener H-1,
surfactants W-3, W-4, W-5 and W-6 as a coating aid or an
emulsifier.</p>
    <p num="0173">Moreover, phenol, 1,2-benzoisothiazoline-3-one,
2-phenoxyethanol, phenethylalcohol or p-butyl benzoate was
added as antiseptic or fungicide.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1">Emulsions used in Sample 101</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Emulsion</entry><entry align="center">Features</entry><entry align="center">Equivalent sphere grain diameter (µm)</entry><entry align="center">Coefficient of variation (%)</entry><entry align="center">AgI content (%)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">A</entry><entry align="left">Monodisperse, tetradecahedral grains</entry><entry align="center">0.13</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">4.5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">B</entry><entry align="left">Monodisperse (111) internal latent image type tabular grains with mean aspect ratio of 2.0</entry><entry align="center">0.25</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">4.8</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C</entry><entry align="left">Monodisperse (111) tabular grains with mean aspect ratio of 2.0</entry><entry align="center">0.30</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">4.0</entry></row><row><entry align="center">D</entry><entry align="left">Monodisperse (111) tabular grains with mean aspect ratio of 3.0</entry><entry align="center">0.35</entry><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="center">4.8</entry></row><row><entry align="center">E</entry><entry align="left">Monodisperse (111) tabular grains with mean aspect ratio of 3.0</entry><entry align="center">0.40</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">F</entry><entry align="left">Monodisperse (111) tabular grains with mean aspect ratio of 4.5</entry><entry align="center">0.55</entry><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="center">2.5 </entry></row><row><entry align="center">G</entry><entry align="left">Monodisperse, cubic grains</entry><entry align="center">0.15</entry><entry align="center">9</entry><entry align="center">3.5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">H</entry><entry align="left">Monodisperse, cubic, internal latent image type grains</entry><entry align="center">0.24</entry><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="center">4.9</entry></row><row><entry align="center">I</entry><entry align="left">Monodisperse (111) tabular grains with mean aspect ratio of 4.0</entry><entry align="center">0.30</entry><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="center">3.5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">J</entry><entry align="left">Monodisperse (111) tabular grains with mean aspect ratio of 5.0</entry><entry align="center">0.45</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry></row><row><entry align="center">K</entry><entry align="left">Monodisperse (111) tabular grains with mean aspect ratio of 5.5</entry><entry align="center">0.60</entry><entry align="center">13</entry><entry align="center">3.5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">L</entry><entry align="left">Monodisperse tetradecahedral grains</entry><entry align="center">0.33</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">4.5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">M</entry><entry align="left">Monodisperse (111) tabular grains with mean aspect ratio of 5.0</entry><entry align="center">0.33</entry><entry align="center">9</entry><entry align="center">6.0</entry></row><row><entry align="center">N</entry><entry align="left">Monodisperse (111) tabular grains with mean aspect ratio of 3.0</entry><entry align="center">0.43</entry><entry align="center">9</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">O</entry><entry align="left">Monodisperse (111) tabular grains with mean aspect ratio of 6.0</entry><entry align="center">0.75</entry><entry align="center">9</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry></row><row><entry align="center">P</entry><entry align="left">Monodisperse (111) tabular grains with mean aspect ratio of 6.0</entry><entry align="center">0.90</entry><entry align="center">8</entry><entry align="center">2.8</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1">Spectral sensitization of Emulsions A to P</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Emulsion</entry><entry align="center">Added spectral sensitizer</entry><entry align="center">Added amount per 1 mol of silver halide (g)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">A</entry><entry align="center">S-1</entry><entry align="center">0.01</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-2</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.35</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-3</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.02</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-8</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.03</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-13</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.015</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-14</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.01</entry></row><row><entry align="center">B</entry><entry align="center">S-2</entry><entry align="center">0.35</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-3</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.02</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-8</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.03</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-13</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.015</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-14</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.01</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C</entry><entry align="center">S-2</entry><entry align="center">0.45</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-3</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.04</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-8</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.04</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-13</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.02</entry></row><row><entry align="center">D</entry><entry align="center">S-2</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-3</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.05</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-8</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.05</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-13</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.015</entry></row><row><entry align="center">E</entry><entry align="center">S-1</entry><entry align="center">0.01</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-2</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.45</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-3</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.05</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-8</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.05</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-13</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.01</entry></row><row><entry align="center">F</entry><entry align="center">S-2</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-3</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.04</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-8</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.04</entry></row><row><entry align="center">G</entry><entry align="center">S-4</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-5</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.05</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-12</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="center">H</entry><entry align="center">S-4</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-5</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.05</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-9</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.15</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-14</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.02</entry></row><row><entry align="center">I</entry><entry align="center">S-4</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-9</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-12</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.1</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1">Spectral sensitization of Emulsions A to P (continued from Table 2)</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Added spectral sensitizer</entry><entry align="center">Added amount per 1 mol of silver halide (g)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">J</entry><entry align="center">S-4</entry><entry align="center">0.35</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-5</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.05</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-12</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="center">K</entry><entry align="center">S-4</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-9</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.05</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-12</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-14</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.02</entry></row><row><entry align="center">L</entry><entry align="center">S-6</entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-10</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-11</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.05</entry></row><row><entry align="center">M</entry><entry align="center">S-6</entry><entry align="center">0.05</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-7</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.05</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-10</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.25</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-11</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.05</entry></row><row><entry align="center">N</entry><entry align="center">S-10</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-11</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.15</entry></row><row><entry align="center">O</entry><entry align="center">S-6</entry><entry align="center">0.05</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-7</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.05</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-10</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.3</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-11</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="center">P</entry><entry align="center">S-6</entry><entry align="center">0.05</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-7</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.05</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-10</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">S-11</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.25</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><img id="img-01040001" orientation="unknown" wi="125" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01040001.tif" inline="no" he="50"/><img id="img-01040002" orientation="unknown" wi="128" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01040002.tif" inline="no" he="49"/><img id="img-01040003" orientation="unknown" wi="110" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01040003.tif" inline="no" he="47"/><img id="img-01040004" orientation="unknown" wi="148" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01040004.tif" inline="no" he="74"/><img id="img-01050001" orientation="unknown" wi="125" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01050001.tif" inline="no" he="56"/><img id="img-01050002" orientation="unknown" wi="125" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01050002.tif" inline="no" he="57"/><img id="img-01050003" orientation="unknown" wi="125" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01050003.tif" inline="no" he="117"/><img id="img-01060001" orientation="unknown" wi="119" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01060001.tif" inline="no" he="41"/><img id="img-01060002" orientation="unknown" wi="118" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01060002.tif" inline="no" he="55"/><img id="img-01060003" orientation="unknown" wi="150" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01060003.tif" inline="no" he="66"/><img id="img-01060004" orientation="unknown" wi="96" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01060004.tif" inline="no" he="69"/><dl compact="compact" tsize="5"><dt>Oil-1</dt><dd>Tri-n-hexyl phosphate</dd><dt>Oil-2</dt><dd>Tricresyl phosphate</dd><dt>Oil-3</dt><dd><img id="img-01070001" orientation="unknown" wi="67" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01070001.tif" inline="no" he="36"/></dd><dt>Oil-4</dt><dd>Tricyclohexyl phosphate</dd><dt>Oil-5</dt><dd>Di-2-ethylhexyl succinate</dd><dt>Oil-6</dt><dd><img id="img-01070002" orientation="unknown" wi="63" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01070002.tif" inline="no" he="47"/></dd><dt>Oil-7</dt><dd><img id="img-01070003" orientation="unknown" wi="48" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01070003.tif" inline="no" he="23"/></dd><dt>Oil-8</dt><dd><img id="img-01070004" orientation="unknown" wi="54" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01070004.tif" inline="no" he="32"/></dd><dt>Oil-9</dt><dd><img id="img-01070005" orientation="unknown" wi="56" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01070005.tif" inline="no" he="42"/></dd></dl><img id="img-01080001" orientation="unknown" wi="113" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01080001.tif" inline="no" he="54"/><img id="img-01080002" orientation="unknown" wi="113" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01080002.tif" inline="no" he="55"/><img id="img-01080003" orientation="unknown" wi="113" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01080003.tif" inline="no" he="47"/><img id="img-01090001" orientation="unknown" wi="112" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01090001.tif" inline="no" he="36"/><img id="img-01090002" orientation="unknown" wi="111" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01090002.tif" inline="no" he="43"/><img id="img-01090003" orientation="unknown" wi="115" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01090003.tif" inline="no" he="36"/><img id="img-01090004" orientation="unknown" wi="100" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01090004.tif" inline="no" he="48"/><img id="img-01090005" orientation="unknown" wi="83" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01090005.tif" inline="no" he="34"/><img id="img-01100001" orientation="unknown" wi="114" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01100001.tif" inline="no" he="35"/><img id="img-01100002" orientation="unknown" wi="115" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01100002.tif" inline="no" he="43"/><img id="img-01100003" orientation="unknown" wi="115" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01100003.tif" inline="no" he="39"/><img id="img-01100004" orientation="unknown" wi="116" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01100004.tif" inline="no" he="43"/><img id="img-01100005" orientation="unknown" wi="116" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01100005.tif" inline="no" he="43"/><img id="img-01110001" orientation="unknown" wi="88" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01110001.tif" inline="no" he="46"/><img id="img-01110002" orientation="unknown" wi="89" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01110002.tif" inline="no" he="42"/><img id="img-01110003" orientation="unknown" wi="90" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01110003.tif" inline="no" he="59"/><img id="img-01110004" orientation="unknown" wi="90" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01110004.tif" inline="no" he="33"/><img id="img-01120001" orientation="unknown" wi="111" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01120001.tif" inline="no" he="41"/><img id="img-01120002" orientation="unknown" wi="112" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01120002.tif" inline="no" he="29"/><img id="img-01120003" orientation="unknown" wi="113" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01120003.tif" inline="no" he="40"/><img id="img-01120004" orientation="unknown" wi="113" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01120004.tif" inline="no" he="37"/><img id="img-01120005" orientation="unknown" wi="114" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01120005.tif" inline="no" he="32"/><img id="img-01120006" orientation="unknown" wi="114" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01120006.tif" inline="no" he="45"/><img id="img-01130001" orientation="unknown" wi="126" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01130001.tif" inline="no" he="42"/><img id="img-01130002" orientation="unknown" wi="126" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01130002.tif" inline="no" he="48"/><img id="img-01130003" orientation="unknown" wi="125" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01130003.tif" inline="no" he="66"/><img id="img-01130004" orientation="unknown" wi="125" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01130004.tif" inline="no" he="41"/><img id="img-01140001" orientation="unknown" wi="130" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01140001.tif" inline="no" he="50"/><img id="img-01140002" orientation="unknown" wi="130" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01140002.tif" inline="no" he="46"/><img id="img-01140003" orientation="unknown" wi="131" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01140003.tif" inline="no" he="51"/><img id="img-01140004" orientation="unknown" wi="131" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01140004.tif" inline="no" he="49"/><img id="img-01150001" orientation="unknown" wi="136" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01150001.tif" inline="no" he="39"/><img id="img-01150002" orientation="unknown" wi="136" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01150002.tif" inline="no" he="41"/><img id="img-01150003" orientation="unknown" wi="137" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01150003.tif" inline="no" he="37"/><img id="img-01150004" orientation="unknown" wi="138" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01150004.tif" inline="no" he="33"/><img id="img-01150005" orientation="unknown" wi="138" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01150005.tif" inline="no" he="40"/><img id="img-01150006" orientation="unknown" wi="138" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01150006.tif" inline="no" he="37"/><img id="img-01160001" orientation="unknown" wi="121" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01160001.tif" inline="no" he="51"/><img id="img-01160002" orientation="unknown" wi="121" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01160002.tif" inline="no" he="48"/><img id="img-01160003" orientation="unknown" wi="121" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01160003.tif" inline="no" he="50"/><img id="img-01160004" orientation="unknown" wi="120" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01160004.tif" inline="no" he="75"/><img id="img-01170001" orientation="unknown" wi="102" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01170001.tif" inline="no" he="46"/><img id="img-01170002" orientation="unknown" wi="103" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01170002.tif" inline="no" he="41"/><img id="img-01170003" orientation="unknown" wi="85" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01170003.tif" inline="no" he="60"/><img id="img-01170004" orientation="unknown" wi="143" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01170004.tif" inline="no" he="40"/><img id="img-01170005" orientation="unknown" wi="142" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01170005.tif" inline="no" he="48"/><img id="img-01180001" orientation="unknown" wi="151" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01180001.tif" inline="no" he="45"/><img id="img-01180002" orientation="unknown" wi="98" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01180002.tif" inline="no" he="50"/><img id="img-01180003" orientation="unknown" wi="109" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01180003.tif" inline="no" he="34"/><img id="img-01180004" orientation="unknown" wi="114" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01180004.tif" inline="no" he="37"/><img id="img-01190001" orientation="unknown" wi="72" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01190001.tif" inline="no" he="23"/><img id="img-01190002" orientation="unknown" wi="102" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01190002.tif" inline="no" he="20"/><img id="img-01190003" orientation="unknown" wi="102" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01190003.tif" inline="no" he="21"/><img id="img-01190004" orientation="unknown" wi="71" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01190004.tif" inline="no" he="35"/><img id="img-01190005" orientation="unknown" wi="79" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01190005.tif" inline="no" he="17"/><st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/">W-7   C<sub>8</sub>F<sub>17</sub>SO<sub>3</sub>Li</st32:che><img id="img-01190006" orientation="unknown" wi="107" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01190006.tif" inline="no" he="22"/><img id="img-01190007" orientation="unknown" wi="110" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01190007.tif" inline="no" he="22"/><img id="img-01190008" orientation="unknown" wi="110" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01190008.tif" inline="no" he="43"/><img id="img-01200001" orientation="unknown" wi="132" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01200001.tif" inline="no" he="69"/><img id="img-01200002" orientation="unknown" wi="117" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01200002.tif" inline="no" he="52"/><img id="img-01200003" orientation="unknown" wi="132" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01200003.tif" inline="no" he="57"/></p>
    <heading>Preparation of dispersion of organic solid dispersion dyes:</heading>
    <p num="0174">Dye E-1 was dispersed by the following process. To 1430
g of a wet cake of dye E-1 containing 30% of methanol, 200 g
of Pluronic F88, (an ethylene oxide-propylene oxide block
copolymer) made by BASF Corp. were added together with water
to give a slurry with a dye content of 6%. Then, an
Ultra-viscomill (UVM-2, a product of Imex Corp.) was charged
with 1700 ml of zirconia beads having a mean diameter of 0.5
mm. The slurry was passed through the mill, and subjected to
grinding for 8 hours at a peripheral speed of about 10 m/sec
and a discharge rate of 0.5 L/min. After the removal of the
beads by filtration, the resulting dispersion was diluted with
water to give a dye concentration of 3%. The diluted dispersion
was then heated at 90°C for 10 hours for stabilization. The
average size of the obtained dye particles was 0.60 µm with
a distribution width of 18% in terms of standard deviation of
(particle size x 100/average particle size).</p>
    <p num="0175">In a similar manner, a solid dispersion of dye E-2 was
prepared having an average particle size of 0.54 µm.</p>
    <heading>(2) Exposure and development processing</heading>
    <p num="0176">The photographic material prepared above (Sample No. 101)
was exposed to a CIE D50 light source through an optical wedge
designed for live scene shooting photographic materials
(neutral color, density gradient of 0.4/cm and density range
of 4.8) ; thereafter the material was processed by the following 
processing procedures (development treatment A)
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Process step</entry><entry align="center">Duration (min)</entry><entry align="center">Temp. (°C)</entry><entry align="center">Tank volume (L)</entry><entry align="center">Replenished amount (ml/m<sup>2</sup>)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">First development</entry><entry align="center">6</entry><entry align="center">38</entry><entry align="center">165</entry><entry align="center">2,200</entry></row><row><entry align="left">First washing</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">38</entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">7,500</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Image reversal</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">38</entry><entry align="center">86</entry><entry align="center">1,100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Color-forming development</entry><entry align="center">6</entry><entry align="center">38</entry><entry align="center">165</entry><entry align="center">2,200</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Pre-bleaching</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">38</entry><entry align="center">65</entry><entry align="center">1,100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Bleaching</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">38</entry><entry align="center">150</entry><entry align="center">220</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fixing</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">38</entry><entry align="center">108</entry><entry align="center">1,100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Second washing</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">38</entry><entry align="center">55</entry><entry align="center">7,500</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Final rinsing</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">44</entry><entry align="center">1,100</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0177">The composition of each processing bath was as follows.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1">[First developer]</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Tank solution</entry><entry align="center">Replenisher</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Nitrilo-N,N,N-trimethylenephosphoric acid pentasodium salt</entry><entry align="center">1.5 g</entry><entry align="center">1.5 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Diethylenetriaminepentaacetic acid pentasodium salt</entry><entry align="center">2.0 g</entry><entry align="center">2.0 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sodium sulfite</entry><entry align="center">28 g</entry><entry align="center">30 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hydroquinone potassium monosulfonate</entry><entry align="center">18 g</entry><entry align="center">20 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Potassium carbonate</entry><entry align="center">20 g</entry><entry align="center">20 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Potassium bicarbonate</entry><entry align="center">15 g</entry><entry align="center">15 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1-Phenyl-4-methyl-4-hydroxymethyl-3-pyrrazolidone</entry><entry align="center">1.5 g</entry><entry align="center">2.0 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Potassium bromide</entry><entry align="center">2.5 g</entry><entry align="center">1.4 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Potassium thiocyanate</entry><entry align="center">1.2 g</entry><entry align="center">1.2 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Potassium iodide</entry><entry align="center">4.0 mg</entry><entry align="center">1.5 mg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Diethylene glycol</entry><entry align="center">15 g</entry><entry align="center">15 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water to make</entry><entry align="center">1000 ml</entry><entry align="center">1000 ml</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PH</entry><entry align="center">9.65</entry><entry align="center">9.70</entry></row><row><entry>The pH was adjusted with sulfuric acid or potassium hydroxide.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1">[Reversal bath]</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">Tank solution</entry><entry align="left">Replenisher</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Nitrilo-N,N,N-trimethylenephosphoric acid pentasodium salt</entry><entry align="center">3.0 g</entry><entry align="left">The same as tank sol.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Stannous chloride dihydrate</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">2.0 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">p-Aminophenol</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">0.001 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sodium hydroxide</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">8 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Acetic acid</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">15 ml</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water to make</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">1000 ml</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PH</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">6.00</entry></row><row><entry>The pH was adjusted with acetic acid or sodium hydroxide.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1">[Color-forming developer]</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">Tank solution</entry><entry align="left">Replenisher</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Nitrilo-N,N,N-trimethylenephosphoric acid pentasodium salt</entry><entry align="center">2.0 g</entry><entry align="center">2.0 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sodium sulfite</entry><entry align="center">7.0 g</entry><entry align="center">7.0 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Trisodium phosphate dodecahydrate</entry><entry align="center">36 g</entry><entry align="center">36 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Potassium bromide</entry><entry align="center">0.7 g</entry><entry align="center">-</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Potassium iodide</entry><entry align="center">40 mg</entry><entry align="center">-</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sodium hydroxide</entry><entry align="center">3.0 g</entry><entry align="center">3.0 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Citrazinic acid</entry><entry align="center">0.5 g</entry><entry align="center">0.5 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">N-ethyl-N-( β-methanesulfoneamide-ethyl)-3-methyl-4-aminoaniline 3/2 sulfuric acid monohydrate</entry><entry align="center">11 g</entry><entry align="center">11 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">3,6-Dithiaoctane-1,8-diol</entry><entry align="center">1.0 g</entry><entry align="center">1.0 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water to make</entry><entry align="center">1000 ml</entry><entry align="center">1000 ml</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PH</entry><entry align="center">11.00</entry><entry align="center">12.10</entry></row><row><entry>The pH was adjusted with sulfuric acid or sodium hydroxide.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1">[Pre-bleaching]</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Tank solution</entry><entry align="center">Replenisher</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid disodium salt dihydrate</entry><entry align="center">8.0 g</entry><entry align="center">8.0 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sodium sulfite</entry><entry align="center">5.0 g</entry><entry align="center">6.0 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1-Thioglycerol</entry><entry align="center">0.4 g</entry><entry align="center">0.5 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Formaldehyde-sodium bisulfite adduct</entry><entry align="center">20 g</entry><entry align="center">25 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water to make</entry><entry align="center">1000 ml</entry><entry align="center">1000 ml</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PH</entry><entry align="center">6.30</entry><entry align="center">6.10</entry></row><row><entry>The pH was adjusted with acetic acid or sodium hydroxide.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1">[Bleaching solution]</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Tank solution</entry><entry align="center">Replenisher</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Bleaching agent (shown in Table 4)</entry><entry align="center">0.15 mol</entry><entry align="center">0.30 mol</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Added compound (shown in Table 4)</entry><entry align="center">0.02 mol</entry><entry align="center">0.04 mol</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound VI Iron (III) complex (shown in Table 4)</entry><entry align="center">0.03 mol</entry><entry align="center">0.06 mol</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Potassium bromide</entry><entry align="center">100 g</entry><entry align="center">200 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ammonium nitrate</entry><entry align="center">10 g</entry><entry align="center">20 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water to make</entry><entry align="center">1000 ml</entry><entry align="center">1000 ml</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PH</entry><entry align="center">5.0</entry><entry align="center">4.8</entry></row><row><entry>The pH was adjusted with nitric acid or ammonium hydroxide.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0178">In the incorporation of the bleaching agent, the
complex-forming compound and the iron compound had been reacted
in advance to form a complex, which was added to the bath along
with the adjustment of the quantity of ammonium nitrate so as
to give the composition shown in Table 4. The pH value in Table
4 indicates that of the tank solution, and the pH value for
the replenisher was set at 0.3 lower than that of the tank
solution. <tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="left">[Fixing solution]</entry><entry align="left">[Tank solution]</entry><entry align="left">[Replenisher]</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ammonium thiosulfate</entry><entry align="left">80 g</entry><entry align="left">The same as tank sol.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sodium sulfite</entry><entry align="left">5.0 g</entry><entry align="left">The same as tank sol.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sodium bisulfite</entry><entry align="left">5.0 g</entry><entry align="left">The same as tank sol.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound (a)</entry><entry align="left">0.05 g</entry><entry align="left">The same as tank sol.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound (b)</entry><entry align="left">0.05 g</entry><entry align="left">The same as tank sol.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water to make</entry><entry align="left">1000 ml</entry><entry align="left">The same as tank sol.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">pH</entry><entry align="left">6.6</entry></row><row><entry>The pH value was adjusted with acetic acid or aqueous ammonia.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><img id="img-01250001" orientation="unknown" wi="153" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01250001.tif" inline="no" he="43"/><img id="img-01250002" orientation="unknown" wi="153" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01250002.tif" inline="no" he="43"/><tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="left">[Stabilizing sol.]</entry><entry align="center">[Tank solution]</entry><entry align="center">[Replenisher]</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1,2-Benzoisothiazoline-3-on</entry><entry align="left">0.06 g</entry><entry align="left">The same as tank sol.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dipropylene glycol</entry><entry align="left">0.3 g</entry><entry align="left">The same as tank sol.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polyoxyethylene-tridecyl ether (average degree of polymerization = 10)</entry><entry align="left">5.0 g</entry><entry align="left">The same as tank sol.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water to make</entry><entry align="left">1000 ml</entry><entry align="left">The same as tank sol.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">pH</entry><entry align="left">7.0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <heading>(2) Evaluation</heading>
    <p num="0179">On each sample obtained by the above processing, the amount
of residual silver, the deposition of ferric compound (i.e.,
iron (III) compound, stain formation and failure of color
restoration were evaluated by the following methods.
Amount of residual silver: the silver amount remaining in the
processed photosensitive material was quantitatively measured
by fluorescent X-ray analysis. By measuring the silver amount
of the sample for which the treatment with a bleaching solution
was omitted and subtracting the weight of the colloidal silver
from the measured value, the amount of developed silver was
determined to be 4.5 g/m<sup>2</sup>.

Failure of color destoration: the photographic characteristic
(HD) curve was obtained for each photosensitive material that
had been processed in the above-described manner with a
transmission densitometer having a measuring optical system 
in conformity with International Standard ISO 5. From the HD
curve thus obtained, the D<sub>max</sub>(R) which indicates the maximum
density measured with red light was read. Separately, a
reference sample for comparison was prepared by repeating the
same processing as above except that the bleaching solution
was replaced to the following reference bleaching solution
having a sufficiently high bleaching activity and that the
bleaching time was changed to 6 min. The corresponding D<sub>max</sub>(R)
was similarly obtained and designated Ref. D<sub>max</sub>(R). Then, the
degree of color restoration failure was defined and evaluated
by the following equation.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">Degree of color restoration failure<st32:break type="required"/>
= [D<st32:sub pos="post">max</st32:sub>(R)/Ref. D<st32:sub pos="post">max</st32:sub>(R)] x 100</st32:df><tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1">[Reference bleaching solution]</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Tank solution</entry><entry align="center">Replenisher</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid disodium salt dihydrate</entry><entry align="center">2.0 g</entry><entry align="center">4.0 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid ferric ammonium salt dihydrate</entry><entry align="center">120 g</entry><entry align="center">240 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Potassium bromide</entry><entry align="center">100 g</entry><entry align="center">200 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ammonium nitrate</entry><entry align="center">10 g</entry><entry align="center">20 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water to make</entry><entry align="center">1000 ml</entry><entry align="center">1000 ml</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PH</entry><entry align="center">5.70</entry><entry align="center">5.50</entry></row><row><entry>The pH was adjusted with nitric acid or ammonium hydroxide.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0180"> Stain formation: After the minimum density of the HD curve
measured with green light (D<sub>min</sub>(G)) was read, the sample was
kept in an atmosphere of 60°C and 70% RH for 2 weeks, and then
D<sub>min</sub>(G) was measured again. By using the two D<sub>min</sub>(G) values before
and after the storage, the magenta stain was defined and
evaluated by the following equation.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">Stain (ΔD<st32:sub pos="post">min</st32:sub>(G)) = D<st32:sub pos="post">min</st32:sub>(G) after storage - D<st32:sub pos="post">min</st32:sub>(G) before storage</st32:df>
Precipitation formation of ferric compound: each bleaching tank
solution after 2 round treatments (One round treatment
corresponds to the processing amount for the replenishing volume
integral equal to the tank volume.) was poured in a beaker,
and the turbidity of the solution was visually inspected. At
the same time, the existence of precipitate on the bottom of
the beaker was checked.

The following evaluation criteria were adopted.
<sl><li>O: No turbidity is observed in the bleaching solution, nor
precipitate is formed at all.</li><li>Δ: Slight turbidity is observed in the bleaching solution but
within an allowable limit, and no precipitate is formed.</li><li>x: Turbidity is obvious, but no precipitate is formed.</li><li>xx: Turbidity is obvious, and precipitate is formed.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0181">Table 4 shows the evaluation results obtained by the
methods described above. In the table, the term "turbidity"
has the same meaning as "precipitate formation".
<tables><table><tgroup cols="9"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Test No.</entry><entry align="center">(I)</entry><entry align="center">Added compound</entry><entry align="center">(VI)</entry><entry align="center">Amount of residual Ag (mg/m<sup>2</sup>)</entry><entry align="center">Color restoration failure (%)</entry><entry align="center">Stain</entry><entry align="center">Turbidity</entry><entry align="center">Note</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">I-8</entry><entry align="left">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">7.0</entry><entry align="center">92</entry><entry align="center">0.28</entry><entry align="center">xx</entry><entry align="center">Compar. example</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">I-8</entry><entry align="left">Compar. comp. (1)</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">6.5</entry><entry align="center">90</entry><entry align="center">0.21</entry><entry align="center">xx</entry><entry align="center">Compar. example</entry></row><row><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">I-8</entry><entry align="left">Compar. comp. (2)</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">15.6</entry><entry align="center">85</entry><entry align="center">0.09</entry><entry align="center">O</entry><entry align="center">Compar. example</entry></row><row><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">I-8</entry><entry align="left">II-1</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">4.4</entry><entry align="center">95</entry><entry align="center">0.03</entry><entry align="center">O</entry><entry align="center">The present invention</entry></row><row><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">I-8</entry><entry align="left">II-3</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">4.1</entry><entry align="center">96</entry><entry align="center">0.02</entry><entry align="center">O</entry><entry align="center">The present invention</entry></row><row><entry align="center">6</entry><entry align="center">I-8</entry><entry align="left">III-1</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">4.9</entry><entry align="center">98</entry><entry align="center">0.03</entry><entry align="center">O</entry><entry align="center">The present invention</entry></row><row><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">I-8</entry><entry align="left">IV-1</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">3.9</entry><entry align="center">98</entry><entry align="center">0.05</entry><entry align="center">O</entry><entry align="center">The present invention</entry></row><row><entry align="center">8</entry><entry align="center">I-8</entry><entry align="left">V-1</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">3.8</entry><entry align="center">99</entry><entry align="center">0.04</entry><entry align="center">O</entry><entry align="center">The present invention</entry></row><row><entry align="center">9</entry><entry align="center">I-8</entry><entry align="left">II-3</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">4.6</entry><entry align="center">97</entry><entry align="center">0.03</entry><entry align="center">O</entry><entry align="center">The present invention</entry></row><row><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">I-8</entry><entry align="left">II-3</entry><entry align="center">VI-1</entry><entry align="center">2.1</entry><entry align="center">99</entry><entry align="center">0.02</entry><entry align="center">O</entry><entry align="center">The present invention</entry></row><row><entry>Comparative compound (1) = iminodiacetic acid

Comparative compound (2) = 1-hydroxyethylidene-1, 1-diphosphonic acid

(I) and (VI) in the top line each indicates the iron (III) complex of the compound represented by formula (I) or (VI) , respectively.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0182">Table 4 indicates the following facts. For the systems
where the conventional iron (III) PDTA (Compounds (1) to (3))
complex salts now in practical use in the market are used as
the bleaching agent, precipitation and stain formation tends
to occur, and the amount of residual silver is comparatively
large when an additive is not used &lt;Test No. 1&gt;. Though the
addition of Comparative Compound (1) is effective to suppress
stain formation, precipitate deposition still takes place &lt;Test
No. 2&gt;. When Comparative Compound (2) was added, both
precipitate and stain formations were suppressed, but the amount
of residual silver further increased &lt;Test No. 3&gt;. In the three
comparative examples (Test Nos. 1 to 3), in particular in Test
No. 3, color development was also incomplete. In a clear
contrast to these results, the examples of the present invention
wherein the compounds represented by formulae (II) to (V) were
incorporated, no precipitate deposition occurred, and
desilvering, stain characteristic and color development were
satisfactorily good. By comparing Test No. 5 with No. 9, one
can conclude that the advantageous features of the present
invention are exhibited even when the bleaching agent is replaced
to the iron (III) complex represented by formula (I). And by
comparing Test No. 5 with No. 10, one can conclude that
desilvering and stain-suppression are further enhanced when
the iron (III) complex represented by formula (VI) was
incorporated in addition to the bleaching agent. </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EFFECT OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0183">According to the present invention wherein a bleaching
solution containing at least one iron (III) complex salt
represented by formula (I) and at least one compound represented
by formulae (II) to (V) is used for the processing of color
photographic materials, precipitate deposition in the
time-elapsed bleaching solution, stain formation and
incomplete color development are difficult to occur even when
a color-forming developer containing phosphate ion at a
concentration of from 0.05 to 0.25 mol/L is used and the
photographic material to be processed is a color reversal
material that develops a large quantity of silver. Hence, such
a bleaching solution can achieve a photographic processing of
desirable developing quality.

Furthermore, by adding the iron (III) complex salt of the
iminocarboxylic acid represented by formula (VI) to the
bleaching solution described above, the advantageous features
of the present invention are enhanced.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A method of processing a silver halide color photographic
Material, wherein the color-forming developer used for the
color-forming development step comprises phosphate ion at a
concentration of from 0.05 to 0.25 mol/L, and the bleaching
solution used for the bleaching step comprises at least one
iron (III) complex salt of the compound represented by the
following formula (I) , and at least one of compounds represented
by the following formulae (II), (III), (IV) and (V):

wherein A1, A2, A3 and A4 may be the same or different, each
represents -CH2OH, -PO3(M2)2 or -COOM1; M1 and M2 each represents
a hydrogen atom, an alkali metal atom, an ammonium group or
an organic ammonium group; X1 represents a straight-chain or
branched-chain alkylene group containing 3 to 6 carbon atoms,
a ring-forming, saturated or unsaturated divalent organic group,
or -(B1O)n5-B2-; n5 represents an integer of 1 to 8; B1 and B2
may be the same or different, each represents an alkylene group
having 1 to 5 carbon atoms; and n1, n2, n3 and n4 may be the
same or different, each represents an integer not more than 10;
wherein R1 represents a hydrogen atom, an alkyl group, a
hydroxyalkyl group, a carboxyalkyl group or an alkoxyalkyl
group; R2 and R3 each represents a hydrogen atom, an alkyl group
or an alkoxyalkyl group; and M6, M7 and M8 each represents a
hydrogen atom, an alkali metal atom, an alkaline earth metal
atom or an onium group;

wherein L0 represents a divalent alkylene group having 2 to
8 carbon atoms, and M9 and M10 each represents a hydrogen atom,
an alkali metal atom, an alkaline earth metal atom or an onium
group;
M11OOC―X2―NH―X3―NH―X4―COOM12
wherein X2, X3 and X4 each represents a substituted or
unsubstituted alkylene group having 1 to 3 carbon atoms, and
M11 and M12 each represents a hydrogen atom, an alkali metal
atom, an alkaline earth metal atom or an onium group; and

wherein Z represents a nitrogen-containing heterocyclic ring;
R4 represents a hydrogen atom, an alkyl group or an alkoxyalkyl
group; M13 represents a hydrogen atom, an alkali metal atom,
an alkaline earth metal atom or an onium group; and m represents
an integer of 1 to 3.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The method of processing a silver halide color
photographic material as in claim 1, wherein the bleaching
solution further contains at least one iron (III) complex salt
of the compound represented by formula (VI):

wherein G1 and G2 each represents a carboxyl group, a phosphono
group, a sulfo group, a hydroxy group, a mercapto group, an
aryl group, a heterocyclic group, an alkylthio group, an amidino
group, a guanidino group or a carbamoyl group; L1, L2 and L3
each represents a divalent aliphatic or aromatic group or a
divalent linking group comprising a combination thereof; m and
n each represents 0 or 1; X represents a hydrogen atom, an
aliphatic or aromatic group; and M represents a hydrogen atom
or a cation.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The method of processing a silver halide color
photographic material as in claim 2, wherein the content ratio
of the iron (III) complex salt of the compound represented by
formula (VI) to the iron (III) complex salt of the compound
represented by formula (I) is in the range of from 0.1 to 0.8.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The method of processing a silver halide color
photographic material as in claim 2 or 3 wherein the compound
represented by formula (VI) is a compound represented by formula
(VII) :

wherein L2' represents a divalent aliphatic or aromatic group
or a divalent linking group comprising a combination thereof;
G2' represents a carboxyl group, a phosphono group, a sulfo
group, a hydroxy group, a mercapto group, an aryl group, a
heterocyclic group, an alkylthio group, an amidino group, a
guanidino group or a carbamoyl group; and M' and M" represents
a hydrogen atom or a cation.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The method of processing a silver halide color
photographic material as in claim 1, wherein the compound
represented by formula (I) is Compound (I-3), Compound (I-4),
Compound (I-8), Compound (I-11) or Compound (I-16).
</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The method of processing a silver halide color
photographic material as in any one of claims 1 to 5, wherein
the compound represented by formula (I) is Compound (I-3).
</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>The method of processing a silver halide color
photographic material as in any one of claims 1 to 6, wherein
the compound represented by formula (II) is selected from the
group consisting of iminodisuccinic acid,
N-carboxymethylaspartic acid and
N,N'-dicarboxymethylaspartic acid.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The method of processing a silver halide color
photographic material as in any one of claims 1 to 7, wherein
the compound represented by formula (III) is
N-(2-hydroxyethyl)aminodiacetic acid.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>The method of processing a silver halide color
photographic material as in any one of claims 1 to 8, wherein
the compound represented by formula (IV) is
ethylenediamine-N,N'-diacetic acid.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>The method of processing a silver halide color
photographic material as in any one of claims 1 to 9, wherein
the compound represented by formula (V) is
pyridine-2-carboxylic acid.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>The method of processing a silver halide color
photographic material as in claim 2, wherein the compound
represented by formula (VI) is N-carboxymethylaspartic acid.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>The method of processing a silver halide color
photographic material as in claim 1, wherein the compound
represented by formula (I) is used in an amount of 30 to 95%
based on the total amount of the complex-forming compound capable
of forming an iron (III) complex salt in the bleaching solution,
and the compounds represented by formulae (II) to (V) are used
in an amount of 5 to 70% based on the total amount of the
complex-forming compound capable of forming an iron (III)
complex salt in the bleaching solution.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>The method of processing a silver halide color
photographic material as in any one of claims 1 to 12, wherein
the bleaching solution further contains a compound represented
by formula [A]:
A5(-COOM5)n51
wherein A5 represents an n51-valent organic group, provided
that A5 never represents an unsubstituted methyl, ethyl or
ethylene group; n51 represents an integer of 1 to 6; and M5
represents an ammonium group, an organic ammonium group, an
alkali metal or a hydrogen atom.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>The method of processing a silver halide color
photographic material as in claim 13, wherein the compound
represented by formula [A] is Compound (A-3), Compound (A-4),
Compound (A-15) or Compound (A-16):
(A-3)HOOCCH (OH) CH2COOH(A-4)HOOCCH=CHCOOH(A-15)Glutaric acid(A-16)HOOCCH2COOH</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>The method of processing a silver halide color
photographic material as in claim 13, wherein the compound
represented by formula [A] is contained in an amount of 0.01
to 0.25 mol per 1liter of the processing tank solution.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>The method of processing a silver halide color
photographic material as in any one of claims 1 to 15, wherein
the black-and-white development is carried out before a color
development.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
