<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1225408-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1225408" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="9907322" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020724">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1225408-A2" status="new" fvid="23524139">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1225408</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20020724</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02250461-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02250461</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020123</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="GB-0101697-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>GB</country>
          <doc-number>0101697</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010123</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F28D   1/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F28D   1/03        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F28F  21/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F28F  21/08        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F28D   1/03L</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F28F  21/08</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Wärmetauscherrohr</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Heat exchanger tube</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Tube d'échangeur de chaleur</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>EMERSON &amp; RENWICK LTD</name>
            <address>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>EMERSON &amp; RENWICK LTD</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Emerson &amp;amp; Renwick Ltd</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Peel Bank Works, Church</street>
              <city>Accrington, Lancashire BB5 4EF</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HARGREAVES COLIN</name>
            <address>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HARGREAVES, COLIN</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>HARGREAVES, COLIN</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Hillrise, 23 Church Lane, Mirfield</street>
              <city>Huddersfield, West Yorkshire WF14 9HU</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Carpenter, David</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>MARKS &amp;amp; CLERK, Alpha Tower, Suffolk Street Queensway</street>
              <city>Birmingham B1 1TT</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A flat, heat exchanger tube formed by rolling metal strip to fold inwardly the
lateral edge regions of the strip to provide a tube (10) having parallel,
spaced, generally planar upper and lower walls (11, 12), one of said lateral
edge regions being bent to define a longitudinally extending partition wall
(16) extending within the tube (10) towards said lower wall (12), and
partition wall (16) including first and second longitudinally extending regions
(16<u style="single">a</u>, 16<u style="single">b</u>) disposed at an angle to one another so as to provide in one face of
the partition wall (16) a longitudinally extending recess receiving the free
edge portion (17) of the other of said lateral edge regions of the strip.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="70"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">This invention relates to tubes and their manufacture, particularly flat tubes
primarily intended for use in heat exchangers.</p>
    <p num="0002">Flat heat exchanger tubes are often used in heat exchangers for use in
automotive vehicles, to carry a first fluid, a second fluid being maintained in
heat exchange relationship with the exterior of the tube so that heat is
transferred between the first and second fluids.</p>
    <p num="0003">It is known to manufacture flat heat exchanger tubes by a cold-rolling process
from coated aluminium strip, the coating providing a "brazing" medium for
sealing and securing abutting walls of the tube, and sometimes also for
securing the tube to other components of the heat exchanger matrix when the
heat exchanger is first manufactured.</p>
    <p num="0004">Flat heat exchange tubes are, in lateral cross-section, relatively wide and
shallow having planar, parallel, upper and lower walls interconnected by
integral curved side walls. It is known to form such a tube by rolling
elongate aluminium strip to raise and bend inwardly the opposite lateral edge
regions of the strip to form the upper wall of the tube. The lateral edge
regions engage one another at the longitudinally extending mid-line of the
upper wall, and it is known from, for example, European patent 0302232, to
bend the free edges of the lateral edge regions inwardly so as to lie within the
tube and to define a partition within the tube extending between the upper and
lower walls of the tube. </p>
    <p num="0005">In accordance with the present invention there is provided a flat heat
exchanger tube formed by rolling metal strip to fold inwardly the lateral edge
regions of the strip to provide a tube having parallel, spaced, generally planar
upper and lower walls, one of said lateral edge regions being bent to define a
longitudinally extending partition wall extending within the tube towards said
lower wall, said partition wall including first and second longitudinally
extending regions disposed at an angle to one another so as to provide in one
face of the partition wall a longitudinally extending recess receiving the free
edge portion of the other of said lateral edge regions of the strip.</p>
    <p num="0006">Preferably said partition wall contacts the inner surface of said lower wall
and said free edge portion of said other of said lateral edge regions of the
strip terminates within said recess of the partition wall.</p>
    <p num="0007">Preferably said first region of said partition wall extends inwardly of the tube
from said upper wall generally at right angles to said upper wall, said second
region commences at the inner edge of the first region and extends at an
oblique angle to said first region, and, said partition wall includes a third
region integral with said second region and commencing at the edge of the
second region remote from the first region, said third region extending from
said second region to contact the inner surface of the lower wall and lying
parallel to said first region but in a plane spaced from the plane of the first
region.</p>
    <p num="0008">Conveniently the angle and extent of said second region, relative to said first
and third regions, is such that said third region plane is spaced from said first
region plane by the thickness of the strip material. </p>
    <p num="0009">Desirably, the partition wall includes a fourth region commencing at the edge
of the third region remote from the second region, said fourth region being a
region of the strip bent through 180°, and thus lying in facial contact with the
face of the partition wall remote from the face of the partition wall engaged
by said free edge portion of said other of said lateral edge regions of the
strip.</p>
    <p num="0010">Alternatively said second region extends at right angles to said first region,
and conveniently said third region terminates in an integral fourth region
extending at right angles to said third region and in facial contact with the
lower wall of the tube</p>
    <p num="0011">Alternatively said first region of said partition wall extends inwardly from
said upper wall of the tube at an acute angle to said upper wall, and said
second region extends at an obtuse angle to said first region so as to contact
the inner surface of said lower wall of the tube generally opposite the root of
said first region at the upper wall.</p>
    <p num="0012">One example of the invention is illustrated in the accompanying drawings
wherein
<sl><li>Figure 1 is a diagrammatic perspective view of a flat, heat exchanger tube,</li><li>Figure 2 is a transverse cross-sectional view, to an enlarged scale, of the tube
of Figure 1,</li><li>Figure 3 is an enlarged view of part of the tube of Figures 1 and 2 illustrating
a modification thereof, and, </li><li>Figures 4, 5, 6, and, 7 are views similar to Figure 3, to a reduced scale,
illustrating four further alternative constructions.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0013">Referring first to Figures 1 and 2 of the accompanying drawings the heat
exchanger tube is formed by a cold-rolling process from aluminium strip.
The aluminium strip is supplied from the manufacturer in coil form and is fed
to the inlet station of the cold-rolling mill or line from a substantially
conventional de-reeler. The strip material is aluminium strip clad on one
face with a "brazing" alloy. Such strip is readily available from companies
such as Alcoa Limited and Finspong Limited. The nature of the strip and the
cladding of "brazing" alloy is not relevant to the invention. It is sufficient to
recognise that the "brazing" alloy cladding is not shed during the cold-rolling
process, and is an alloy which melts at a lower temperature than the base
aluminium strip so that during the manufacture of the heat exchanger the
temperature of the components can be raised to an extent such that the alloy
melts and flows to braze components together, without the aluminium base
material melting.</p>
    <p num="0014">For convenience, throughout this description, it will be assumed that the
cold-rolling process initially raises the lateral edge regions of the strip and
then folds them inwardly. Bearing this in mind, the strip is passed through
the cold-rolling mill with the cladding layer of brazing alloy lowermost so
that as the lateral edge regions of the strip are raised and formed inwardly to
define the upper wall 11 of the tube 10 the cladding layer is outermost, and
the inner surface of the tube is the surface of the aluminium base layer. </p>
    <p num="0015">As is apparent from Figure 1 the flat strip is rolled to raise the lateral edge
regions and to fold them inwardly so that the strip forms a tube which can be
considered to be flat, wide, and relatively shallow. The tube 10 has an upper
wall 11, and a lower wall 12, the walls 11, 12 being parallel, being spaced
apart, and both being generally planar. The upper and lower walls 11, 12 are
interconnected by integral side walls 13 which are part-circular in transverse
cross-section. As can be seen in Figure 1 the aluminium base layer 14 of the
strip is internal to the tube, and the cladding of "brazing" alloy 15 is
external.</p>
    <p num="0016">As is also apparent from Figures 1 and 2 the lateral edge regions of the strip
which form the upper wall 11 abut along the longitudinal mid-line of the
upper wall 11. Moreover, the left-hand lateral edge of the strip (with
reference to the cross-sectional view of the tube in Figure 2) extends beyond
the mid-line of the upper wall 11, and is directed downwardly, within the
tube, to the inner surface of the lower wall 12 to define a partition wall 16
within the tube.</p>
    <p num="0017">The partition wall 16 is of course integral with the upper wall 11, and as is
apparent from Figure 2 includes a first region 16<u style="single">a</u> extending inwardly of the
tube from the upper wall 11 and at right angles to the upper wall 11. Integral
with the lower edge of the first region 16<u style="single">a</u> is a second region 16<u style="single">b</u> inclined at
an obtuse angle to the first region 16<u style="single">a</u>. The angle is not critical, but
conveniently is of the order of 135°. At its lower edge the second region 16<u style="single">b</u>
has integral therewith the commencement of a third region 16<u style="single">c</u> of the
partition wall 16, the region 16<u style="single">c</u> extending parallel to the region 16<u style="single">a</u> and, at
its free edge, abutting the inner surface of the lower wall 12. The angle and
the extent of the second region 16<u style="single">b</u> of the partition wall is such that the plane 
of the third region 16<u style="single">c</u> is spaced from an equivalent plane of the first region
16<u style="single">a</u> by approximately the thickness of the strip material. As it is the left-hand
lateral edge region of the strip which defines the partition wall 16 it will
be recognised that the cladding layer of the region of the strip which defines
the partition wall 16 is facing to the right in Figure 2. Moreover, the
displacement of the second region relative to the first and third regions is
such that the plane of the third region is spaced to the right of the plane of the
first region.</p>
    <p num="0018">For the avoidance of doubt, the partition wall 16 extends through the full
length of the tube 10 and the formation, and shaping, of the partition wall 16
is achieved by the cold-rolling process. The nature of the cold-rolling
process is not of particular relevance to the invention, and the manner in
which a strip is converted, in a series of stages, by consecutive roll stands of
a cold-rolling mill, into a closed tube, will be well understood by those
familiar with cold-rolling.</p>
    <p num="0019">It will be recognised that the shaping of the partition wall 16 defines a recess
in the right-hand face of the partition wall 16. As can be seen in Figure 2,
the edge portion of the right-hand lateral edge region of the strip is also bent
downwardly to lie within the interior of the tube, but the in-turned portion 17
of the right-hand lateral edge region of the strip is shorter than the partition
wall 16, and terminates well short of the lower wall 12 of the tube. In fact,
the in-turned portion 17 is seated within the recess of the right-hand face of
the partition wall 16, and terminates at the shoulder defined by the second
region 16<u style="single">b</u> of the partition wall. It will also be recognised that the cladding
15 is the left-hand face of the portion 17 and thus the cladding of the portion
17 abuts the cladding of the first region 16<u style="single">a</u> of the partition wall 16. </p>
    <p num="0020">The tube 10, which is formed as a continuous length, is cut into
predetermined lengths at the exit of the cold-rolling mill, by any convenient
cutting mechanism, for example a "flying" shear. Conveniently the cut
lengths of tube are not heated at this stage to cause brazing, and instead the
tubes are assembled with "fin" material, and other components of the heat
exchanger, to define a heat exchanger matrix which is then heated to cause
the cladding of the strip material to flow and thus braze the various
components of the heat exchanger together. During this process the cladding
of the partition wall 16 and the portion 17 flows so that the mid-line join in
the upper wall 11 is sealed by brazing alloy, the partition 17 and region 16<u style="single">a</u>
are brazed together and moreover the free edge of the partition wall is brazed
to the inner surface of the lower wall 12 of the tube.</p>
    <p num="0021">Figure 3 illustrates a modification of the arrangement illustrated in Figures 1
and 2 in which the portion of the strip which forms the partition wall 16 is
somewhat longer, and the edge portion of the third region 16<u style="single">c</u> of the partition
wall is turned back on itself (to the left in Figure 3) to double the thickness of
the partition wall 16 adjacent the lower wall 13 of the tube. In effect the
fourth region 16<u style="single">d</u> of the partition wall, defined by bending the free edge of
the partition wall through 180°, ensures that the thickness of the lower region
of the partition wall matches the thickness of the partition wall where the
portion 17 is brazed to the first region 16<u style="single">a</u> of the wall. Thus the portion 17
terminates at the top of the "knee" defined by the second region 16<u style="single">b</u> of the
wall 16 and the upwardly extending fourth region 16<u style="single">d</u> of the wall terminates
beneath the "knee". It will be understood that by bending the strip material
to the left (as in Figure 3) to define the fourth region 16<u style="single">d</u>, the cladding layer
15 lies at the outside of the bend and thus contacts the inner surface of the 
aluminium base of the wall 12, thus enhancing the bonding of the partition
wall to the lower wall of the tube when brazing takes place.</p>
    <p num="0022">Figure 4 illustrates a simplification of the partition wall structure. In the
simplified construction the first region 16<u style="single">a</u> of the partition wall 16 extends
inwardly from the upper wall 11 at an acute angle, the region 16<u style="single">a</u> having
been bent relative to the wall 11 through more than 90. The region 16<u style="single">a</u>
extends approximately half the depth of the tube, between the walls 11, 12,
and the remainder of the depth of the tube is occupied by the second region
16<u style="single">b</u> of the partition wall. The region 16<u style="single">b</u> is bent in the opposite direction
relative to the region 16<u style="single">a</u> so that the free edge of the region 16<u style="single">b</u> contacts the
wall 12 substantially opposite the point at which the region 16<u style="single">a</u> merges with
the upper wall 11. In essence therefore the angle subtended between the
region 16<u style="single">a</u> and the region 16<u style="single">b</u> is double the angle subtended between the
region 16<u style="single">a</u> and the associated part of the upper wall 11. Similarly the portion
17, which lies in facial contact with the right-hand face of the region 16<u style="single">a</u> lies
at an obtuse angle to the associated region of the wall 11, the angle subtended
between the portion 17 and the wall 11 being the compliment of the angle
subtended between the first region 16<u style="single">a</u> and the wall 11. Again therefore it
can be seen that the portion 17 is received within the recess defined between
the first and second regions of the partition wall.</p>
    <p num="0023">Figure 5 illustrates a modification of the arrangement shown in Figure 4 in
which the angle between the first region 16<u style="single">a</u> and its associated part of the
wall 11 is more acute, and thus the angle subtended between the regions 16<u style="single">a</u>,
16<u style="single">b</u> is reduced closer to a right angle. The angle of the portion 17 is adjusted
accordingly. While the recess in the partition wall 16 of the Figure 5
arrangement is deeper, and thus provides a greater locking action supporting 
the portion 17 against inward displacement, the greater bend radius between
the wall 11 and the first region 16<u style="single">a</u> of the partition wall 16 generates a larger
gap in the upper wall 11 along the mid-line of the wall 11 than is the case
with the less tight bend radius of Figure 4. The larger gap may prove
problematic if capillary action draws too much of the brazing alloy, when
molten, to fill the gap, and thus starves the interface of the portion 17 and the
region 16<u style="single">a</u>. It will be recognised therefore that there is a balance to be
achieved between the size of the gap produced, and the depth of the recess,
and therefore the efficiency of the mechanical "locking" of the portion 17
within the recess. In many respects the arrangement of Figures 2 and 3 is
preferable in this regard since the bend radius is minimised, but there is
nevertheless a good locking action where the free edge of the portion 17 seats
on the "knee" defined by the second region 16<u style="single">b</u> of the partition wall.
Moreover the arrangement of Figures 2 and 3 is believed to be strong in use,
the partition wall being strong in compression (normal to the plane of the
tube) and resistant to lateral deformation as could occur as a result of
pressure differential between the passages on opposite sides respectively of
the wall. The provision of the region 16<u style="single">d</u> of the wall ensures that the tube
cross-section is effectively symmetrical thus facilitating the assembly of the
tube ends into corresponding apertures punched in the walls of the associated
header tanks and the like without the need to orient the tube in a single
rotational position relative to the aperture.</p>
    <p num="0024">In each of the examples illustrated in Figures 2 to 5 of the drawings it can be
seen that the free edge of the portion 17 is chamfered at an angle
corresponding to the angle of the region 16<u style="single">b</u> which it abuts. The chamfer of
the edge of the portion 17 is formed during the cold rolling process in one of
the early stands of the rolling mill. </p>
    <p num="0025">In the modifications of Figure 2 illustrated in Figures 6 and 7 the second
region 16<u style="single">b</u> of the partition wall 16 extends generally parallel to the upper and
lower walls 11, 12 of the tube and thus lies generally at right angles to the
parallel first and third regions 16<u style="single">a</u>, 16<u style="single">c</u> of the partition wall 16. The turned
in portion of the right-hand lateral edge region of the strip includes a first
region 17<u style="single">a</u> abutting, in facial contact with, the partition wall first region 16<u style="single">a</u>,
and an integral second region 17<u style="single">b</u> bent at right angles to the first region 17<u style="single">a</u>
and abutting, in facial contact with, the partition wall second region 16<u style="single">b</u>. In
addition in the example illustrated in Figure 7 the partition wall 16 includes a
fourth region 16<u style="single">d</u> bent at right angles to the third region 16<u style="single">c</u> and abutting, in
facial contact with, the inner surface of the wall 12 of the tube. As with the
foregoing examples it can be seen that the partition wall 16 of the tubes of
Figures 6 and 7 are shaped to define a recess receiving the portion 17 of the
tube. The efficiency of mechanical "locking" of the portion 17 in the recess
is high given the right angle orientation of the "knee" and the designs are
strong in compression, and exhibit minimal gap at the interface of the regions
16<u style="single">a</u> and 17<u style="single">a</u>.</p>
    <p num="0026">It will be recognised that tubing formed in the manner described above can be
used in environments other than automobile heat exchangers. Moreover,
although the formation is particularly advantageous where the material is an
aluminium strip clad with a brazing alloy, similar forms could be produced
from other strip materials including aluminium strip clad on one side with a
"brazing" alloy and clad on its opposite side with an erosion and/or corrosion
resistant layer. </p>
    <p num="0027">It is to be recognised that the invention in this application also resides in a
method of manufacturing a flat tube from strip material by using a cold-rolling
process to convert the strip into a closed tubular form having upper
and lower parallel walls and an internal partition wall having a "knee" or
recess therein receiving an edge portion of the opposite lateral edge region of
the strip. The invention also resides in a method of manufacturing a heat
exchanger utilising such tubes in which the assembled heat exchanger is
subjected to a heating process to fuse brazing alloy provided as a cladding on
the strip material from which the tubes are manufactured.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A flat, heat exchanger tube formed by rolling metal strip to fold
inwardly the lateral edge regions of the strip to provide a tube (10) having
parallel, spaced, generally planar upper and lower walls (11, 12), one of said
lateral edge regions being bent to define a longitudinally extending partition
wall (16) extending within the tube (10) towards said lower wall (12), and the
tube being characterised in that said partition wall (16) includes first and
second longitudinally extending regions (16a, 16b) disposed at an angle to
one another so as to provide in one face of the partition wall (16) a
longitudinally extending recess receiving the free edge portion (17) of the
other of said lateral edge regions of the strip.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A flat, heat exchanger tube as claimed in claim 1 characterised in that
said partition wall (16) contacts the inner surface of said lower wall (11) and
said free edge portion (17) of said other of said lateral edge regions of the
strip terminates within said recess of the partition wall (16).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A flat, heat exchanger tube as claimed in claim 1 or claim 2
characterised in that said first region (16a) of said partition wall extends
inwardly of the tube from said upper wall (11) generally at right angles to
said upper wall, said second region (16b) commences at the inner edge of the
first region and extends at an oblique angle to said first region, and, said
partition wall (16) includes a third region (16c) integral with said second
region and commencing at the edge of the second region remote from the
first region, said third region extending from said second region to contact
the inner surface of the lower wall (12) and lying parallel to said first region
but in a plane spaced from the plane of the first region.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A flat, heat exchanger tube as claimed in claim 1 or claim 2
characterised in that said first region (16a) of said partition wall extends
inwardly of the tube from said upper wall (11) generally at right angles to
said upper wall, said second region (16b) commences at the inner edge of the
first region and extends generally at right angles to said first region, and, said
partition wall includes a third region (16c) integral with said second region
and commencing at the edge of the second region remote from the first
region, said third region (16c) extending from said second region to contact
the inner surface of the lower wall (12) and lying parallel to said first region
but in a plane spaced from the plane of the first region.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A flat, heat exchanger tube as claimed in claim 3 characterised in that
the angle and extent of said second region (16b), relative to said first and
third regions 16a, 16c), is such that said third region plane is spaced from
said first region plane by the thickness of the strip material.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A flat, heat exchanger tube as claimed in claim 3 or claim 5,
characterised in that, the partition wall (16) includes a fourth region (16d)
commencing at the edge of the third region (16c) remote from the second
region (16b), said fourth region being a region of the strip bent through
180°, and thus lying in facial contact with the face of the partition wall (16)
remote from the face of the partition wall engaged by said free edge portion
(17) of said other of said lateral edge regions of the strip.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A flat, heat exchanger tube as claimed in claim 1 characterised in that
said first region (16a) of said partition wall extends inwardly from said upper
wall (11) of the tube at an acute angle to said upper wall, and said second
region (16b) extends at an obtuse angle to said first region so as to contact the
inner surface of said lower wall (12) of the tube generally opposite the root of
said first region(16a) at the upper wall (11).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A flat, heat exchanger tube as claimed in claim 4 characterised in that
said free edge portion (17) of said other of said lateral edge regions of the
strip includes a first region (17a) engaging said first region (16a) of said
partition wall and a second region (17b) at right angles to said first region
(17a) and engaging said second region (16b) of said partition wall.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>A flat, heat exchanger tube as claimed in claim 4 or claim 8
characterised in that said third region (16c) of said partition wall (16)
terminates in an integral fourth portion (16d) extending at right angles to said
third portion in a direction towards the plane of the first portion (16a) and
making facial contact with said tube lower wall (12)</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
