<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1234988-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1234988" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="18907558" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020828">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1234988-A2" status="new" fvid="23544027">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1234988</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20020828</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02003849-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02003849</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020220</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001045835-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001045835</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010221</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F16C   3/02        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F16C   3/02        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F16C  17/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F16C  17/10        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F16C  23/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F16C  23/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F16C  25/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F16C  25/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F16C  33/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F16C  33/04        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F16C  33/24        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F16C  17/10</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F16C  23/04</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F16C  25/04</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F16C  33/04C</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Besonderer Typ von Lagervorrichtung</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Special type bearing device</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Dispositif de palier d'un type particulier</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MINEBEA KK</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MINEBEA CO., LTD.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Minebea Co., Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>4106-73 Miyota, Miyota-machi</street>
              <city>Kitasaku-gun, Nagano-ken 3849-2100</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HOKKIRIGAWA KAZUO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>OBARA RIKURO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HOKKIRIGAWA, KAZUO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>OBARA, RIKURO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>HOKKIRIGAWA, KAZUO</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>3-1-21, Matsugamisaki</street>
              <city>Yonezawa-shi, Yamagata-ken 992-0053</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Obara, Rikuro, c/o Minebea Co., Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Karuizawa Manu., Unit 4106-73 Miyota, Miyota-machi</street>
              <city>Kitasaku-gun, Nagano-ken 3849-2100</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Goddar, Heinz J., Dr.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>FORRESTER &amp;amp; BOEHMERT Pettenkoferstrasse 20-22</street>
              <city>80336 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>The invention provides a special type bearing device that
is insusceptible to damage, is light in weight, has a long service
life, and excellent wear resistance, is insusceptible to the effect
of change in temperature, is easy to fabricate, and has little
offensiveness towards mating members. Further, the same is
capable of sufficiently retaining a lubricant such as oil and
grease, and retaining the lubricant for a long period of time
without the need of supplying oil during operation, thereby
rendering it maintenance-free. That is, the special type
bearing device as described above comprises an axis (1), a pair
of rotating bodies fixedly attached to the axis (1), and a
supporting body with which the rotating bodies are in contact,
wherein any one of the axis (1), the rotating bodies, and the
supporting body is made of RB ceramic or CRB ceramic.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="74" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="101"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a special type bearing
device making use of a new type of high-tech eco-material
(state-of-the-art material excellent in ecological adaptability)
which is different from conventional industrial material in that
biomass resources is utilized.</p>
    <p num="0002">For conventional special type bearing devices, copper
based or iron based sintered alloy, polymer resin material
(nylon, Teflon, other synthetic resin, and so forth), and non-ferrous
material, such as phosphor bronze, brass and so forth,
have been in widespread use, however, these materials have
each its own problem.</p>
    <p num="0003">Conditions required of special type bearing devices
include small friction coefficient, small insusceptibility to the
effect of temperature, easiness with which to fabricate, low cost,
and little offensiveness towards mating members.</p>
    <p num="0004">None of the various conventional materials described
above can satisfy all these conditions as required.</p>
    <p num="0005">For example, the copper based sintered alloy is soft in
hardness, and has large friction coefficient, so that it is
susceptible to the effect of change in temperature while its
wear resistance is less than satisfactory depending on its
application.</p>
    <p num="0006">The iron based sintered alloy has problems in that it is
inferior in affinity and conformability with mating members, is
incapable of raising its oil retention ratio to a sufficiently high
level, and has high expansion coefficient and so forth. </p>
    <p num="0007">As for the polymer resin material, it is in principle
intended for use in the case of dry friction where no lubricating
oil is used, and its application is limited to the cases of use
under a light load, use in a dry condition, and so forth.
Further, it has problems such as limitations to enhancement of
friction coefficient as well as wear resistance besides a problem
of thermal expansion.</p>
    <p num="0008">Meanwhile, the non-ferrous material described above can
exhibit a function of satisfactory lubrication in its application
under a high load, at low revolution and so forth, however, it is
not necessarily satisfactory in respect of friction coefficient,
and wear resistance.</p>
    <p num="0009">Now, an attempt to obtain a porous carbonaceous
material by utilizing rice bran, produced in quantity of 900,
000 tons a year in Japan and in as much as 33 million tons a
year throughout the world, has been well known by researches
carried out by Mr. Kazuo HOEKIRIGAWA, the first inventor of
the present invention (refer to "Functional Material", May
issue, 1997, Vol. 17, No. 5, pp. 24 ∼ 28).</p>
    <p num="0010">Herein are disclosed a carbonaceous material (referred to
hereinafter as RB ceramic) obtained by mixing degreased bran
derived from rice bran with a thermosetting resin before
kneading, drying a formed kneaded mixture obtained by
pressure-forming a kneaded mixture, and subsequently, firing
the formed kneaded mixture as dried in an inert gas, and a
method of producing the carbonaceous material.</p>
    <p num="0011">With such a method as described above, however, it has
been practically difficult to form the formed kneaded mixture
with high precision because there occurs discrepancy in
dimensions by as much as 25% in terms of a contraction ratio of 
the dimensions of a finished formed product obtained after
firing in the inert gas to those of the formed kneaded mixture
prepared by pressure-forming.</p>
    <p num="0012">It is therefore an object of the invention to solve
drawbacks of the conventional special type bearing units
described above, and to provide a special type bearing device
capable of satisfying all the requirements as described, that is,
a special type bearing device that is insusceptible to damage, is
light in weight, has a long service life and excellent wear
resistance, is insusceptible to the effect of variation in
temperature, is easy to fabricate, and has little offensiveness
towards mating members, the special type bearing device
further being capable of sufficiently retaining a lubricant such
as oil and grease, and retaining the lubricant for a long period
of time without the need of supplying oil during operation,
thereby being rendered maintenance-free.</p>
    <p num="0013">A new class of ceramic (CRB ceramic) as described later,
representing further improvement on RB ceramic, is a ceramic
material friendly to nature, obtained by using rice bran as a
raw material, and by mixing degreased bran derived from the
rice bran with a thermosetting resin before firing. CRB
ceramic has the following excellent features:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>very high hardness</li><li>very small expansion coefficient</li><li>porous organization structure</li><li>good electric conductivity</li><li>small specific gravity and light weight</li><li>very small friction coefficient</li><li>excellent wear resistance </li><li>easy to mold or to form in a die</li><li>a small contraction ratio of the dimensions of a finished
product to those of a formed workpiece</li><li>ceramic material having varying features can be produced by
mixing with a variety of resins</li><li>the raw material being rice bran, little adverse effect on
global environment, leading to conservation of natural
resources</li></ul></p>
    <p num="0014">Accordingly, it can be said that this ceramic material has
conditions suitable for application to a special type bearing
device, such as insusceptibility to damage, light weight, a long
service life, capability of retaining oil and grease for a long
period of time, and so forth.</p>
    <p num="0015">The ceramic (CRB ceramic) described above is an
improved material of RB ceramic, that is, a black resin or
porous ceramic,

obtained by mixing degreased bran derived from rice bran with
a thermosetting resin before kneading, subjecting a kneaded
mixture thus obtained to a primary firing in an inert gas at a
temperature in a range of 700 to 1000°C, pulverizing the
kneaded mixture after the primary firing into carbonized
powders passing through a 100-mesh sieve, mixing the
carbonized powders with a thermosetting resin before
kneading, pressure-forming a kneaded mixture at pressure in a
range of 20 to 30 MPa, and subjecting a formed workpiece thus
obtained again to a heat treatment in an inert gas atmosphere
at a temperature in a range of 100 to 1100°C. CRB ceramic
differs largely from RB ceramic in that in contrast with RB
ceramic having a contraction ratio of the dimensions of a
finished product thereof to those of a formed workpiece at as 
high as 25%, CRB ceramic has a very small contraction ratio at
not more than 3%, rendering it superior to RB ceramic.</p>
    <p num="0016">The inventor has discovered that special type bearing
devices having a variety of features can be fabricated with ease
by applying CRB ceramic as material for at least a part of the
respective special type bearing devices.</p>
    <p num="0017">In another aspect of the present invention, the
dimensions of a workpiece already formed of RB ceramic can be
properly adjusted by shaving the same although the
conventional RB ceramic has a contraction ratio of the
dimensions of a finished product thereof to those of the
workpiece already formed at as high as 25%, and therefore, the
invention does not exclude embodiments thereof, using RB
ceramic. Because RB ceramic has substantially the same
property as that of CRB ceramic except in respect of the
dimensions of the finished product thereof, the invention does
not exclude embodiments thereof, using RB ceramic, in this
regard either.</p>
    <p num="0018">In carrying out the invention, however, it is preferable to
use mainly CRB ceramic because a product of high-precision
dimensions can be obtained through one forming process in
this case.</p>
    <p num="0019">Further, it has been discovered that special type bearing
devices having a variety of features can be fabricated by
introducing novel configurations to contact parts of the system
as well as by suitable combination of material used for a
conventional special type bearing device made of synthetic
resin with material used for a conventional special type
bearing device made of steel based metal.</p>
    <p num="0020">More specifically, the invention provides a special type 
bearing device comprising an axis, a rotating body or rotating
bodies, fixedly attached to the axis or formed integrally
therewith, and a supporting body with which the rotating body
or the rotating bodies are in contact, wherein at least a part of
the axis, the rotating body or the rotating bodies, and the
supporting body is made of RB ceramic or CRB ceramic.
<sl><li>Fig. 1 is a sectional view of an example of a special type
bearing device according to the invention;</li><li>Fig. 2 is a schematic illustration of a hemisphere of the
special type bearing device shown in Fig. 1;</li><li>Fig. 3 is a sectional view of another example of a special
type bearing device according to the invention;</li><li>Fig. 4 is a sectional view of still another example of a
special type bearing device according to the invention;</li><li>Fig. 5 is a sectional view of a further example of a special
type bearing device according to the invention;</li><li>Fig. 6 is a sectional view of a still further example of a
special type bearing device according to the invention;</li><li>Fig. 7 is a sectional view of an yet further example of a
special type bearing device according to the invention;</li><li>Fig. 8 is a sectional view showing an example of a spindle
motor, incorporating the special type bearing device shown in
Fig. 1;</li><li>Fig. 9 is a sectional view showing an example of a pivot
assembly (hereinafter referred to as ass'y). for an HDD,
incorporating the special type bearing device shown in Fig. 1;</li><li>Fig. 10 is a sectional view of another example of a special
type bearing device according to the invention;</li><li>Fig. 11 is a sectional view showing an example of a special 
type bearing device according to the invention, comprising a
bearing of a single structure; and</li><li>Fig. 12 is a sectional view showing another example of a
special type bearing device according to the invention,
comprising a bearing of a single structure.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0021">RB ceramic or CRB ceramic material for use in a special
type bearing device according to the invention is made of
degreased bran derived from rice bran for use as a main raw
material, and a thermosetting resin.</p>
    <p num="0022">The degreased bran may be of either a local origin or a
foreign origin regardless of the kind of rice.</p>
    <p num="0023">Further, any thermosetting resin may be used as long as
it has thermosetting property, and typical examples thereof
include phenol resin, diaryl phthalate resin, unsaturated
polyester resin, epoxy resin, polyimide resin, and triazine resin.
In particular, phenol resin is preferably used.</p>
    <p num="0024">Furthermore, a thermoplastic resin, such as a polyamide
and so forth, can be used in combination with a thermosetting
resin provided that it is used without departing from the spirit
and scope of the invention.</p>
    <p num="0025">A mixing ratio of the degreased bran to a thermosetting
resin is 50 to 90 : 50 to 10 by weight, however, the mixing ratio
of 70 to 80 : 30 to 20 is preferably adopted.</p>
    <p num="0026">A method of producing the RB ceramic material has been
well known by researches carried out by Mr. Kazuo
Horikirikawa, the first inventor of the present invention
(reference: "Functional Material", May issue, 1997, Vol. 17, No.
5, pp. 24 ∼ 28).</p>
    <p num="0027">That is, described therein are a carbonaceous material 
obtained by mixing degreased bran derived from rice bran with
a thermosetting resin before kneading, drying a formed
kneaded mixture obtained by pressure-forming a kneaded
mixture, and subsequently, firing the formed kneaded mixture
as dried in an inert gas atmosphere, and a method of producing
the same.</p>
    <p num="0028">Now, a method of producing the CRB ceramic material is
briefly described hereinafter. The method comprises the steps
of mixing degreased bran derived from rice bran with a
thermosetting resin before kneading, subjecting a kneaded
mixture thus obtained to a primary firing in an inert gas at a
temperature in a range of 700 to 1000°C, pulverizing the
kneaded mixture after the primary firing into carbonized
powders, mixing the carbonized powders with a thermosetting
resin before kneading, pressure-forming a kneaded mixture
thus obtained at a pressure in a range of 20 to 30 MPa, and
subjecting a formed workpiece thus obtained again to a heat
treatment at a temperature in a range of 100 to 1100°C in an
inert gas atmosphere.</p>
    <p num="0029">A thermosetting resin in a liquid state, having a
relatively small molecular weight, is desirable as the
thermosetting resin for use in the primary firing.</p>
    <p num="0030">A rotary kiln is normally used in carrying out the primary
firing, and a firing time is for a duration in a range of 40 to 120
min. A mixing ratio of the carbonized powders obtained by
the primary firing to the thermosetting resin is 50 to 90 : 50 to
10 by weight, however, the mixing ratio of 70 to 80 : 30 to 20 is
preferably adopted.</p>
    <p num="0031">The kneaded mixture of the carbonized powders and the
thermosetting resin is pressure-formed at a pressure in a range 
of 20 to 30 MPa, preferably, in a range of 21 to 25 MPa. A die
used is preferably at a temperature of about 150°C.</p>
    <p num="0032">For the heat treatment, a well controlled electric furnace
is employed, and heat treatment time is in a range of about 60
to 360 min.</p>
    <p num="0033">A heat treatment temperature is preferably in a range of
600 to 1100°C, and a warming rate up to the heat treatment
temperature is required to be relatively moderate up to 500°C.
In terms of more specific values, the warming rate is in a range
of 0.5 to 2°C / min, and is preferably 1°C / min.</p>
    <p num="0034">Further, in lowering the temperature of the formed
workpiece after baked by the heat treatment, a relatively
moderate cooling rate is required until reaching 500°C. Upon
the temperature dropping below 500°C, the formed workpiece
is left to cool by itself. In terms of more specific values, the
cooling rate is in a range of 0.5 to 4°C / min, and is preferably
1°C / min.</p>
    <p num="0035">Further, the inert gas for use at the time of the primary
firing and the heat treatment may be any gas selected from the
group consisting of helium, argon, neon, and nitrogen gas,
however, nitrogen gas is preferably used.</p>
    <p num="0036">Further, the RB ceramic or CRB ceramic used in carrying
out the invention is preferably dehydrated at a temperature
not lower than 100°C after formed.</p>
    <p num="0037">With the special type bearing device according to the
invention, the RB ceramic or the CRB ceramic is used for a
part or the whole of a rotating body or rotating bodies, a
supporting body, and an axis.</p>
    <p num="0038">The RB ceramic or the CRB ceramic can be used in, for
example, a part or the whole of the axis, the rotating body or 
bodies, and the supporting body. The RB ceramic or the CRB
ceramic, impregnated with a lubricating oil, is preferably used.</p>
    <p num="0039">Synthetic resin and steel based metal, in common use as
material for conventional special type bearing units, can be
combined with the RB ceramic or the CRB ceramic as
appropriate.</p>
    <p num="0040">For the synthetic resin, any synthetic resin selected from
the group consisting of polyolefin, such as hard polyethylene,
and polypropylene, polyamide, such as nylon - 6, 6,
polycarbonate, and so forth may be used provided that it is
hard to a degree and strong.</p>
    <p num="0041">For the steel based metal, any metal such as an alloy of
steel combined with nickel, chromium, molybdenum, etc. may
be used provided that it is hard and insusceptible to rust. A
stainless steel is a type of material which is preferably used.</p>
    <p num="0042">Further, a steel with its surface plated such as chromium
plated steel may be used.</p>
    <p num="0043">With the special type bearing device according to the
invention, the rotating body and the supporting body can be
configured into a variety of shapes.</p>
    <p num="0044">The shape of the rotating body is preferably a hemisphere,
a cone, a sphere, a ring or a disc, and so forth.</p>
    <p num="0045">Examples of the sphere include a proper sphere and an
oval.</p>
    <p num="0046">With the special type bearing device according to the
invention, a contact condition between the rotating body and
the supporting body will be surface contact or line contact.</p>
    <p num="0047">Examples of line contact include a case where the rotating
body is a hemisphere, and the supporting body has a tapered
face. Cited as such a case is one where, for example, a pair of 
hemispheres whose spherical surfaces are opposed to each
other are provided integrally with an axis, or fixedly attached
to the axis by adhesion, bonding. or so forth so as to be in
contact with a tapered sleeve having a conical surface
expanding inward on both sides thereof as seen in section
between the hemispheres (refer to Figs. 1, 4, and 5).</p>
    <p num="0048">Another example of line contact is a case where the
rotating body is a sphere, and the supporting body has a
conical surface. For example, a sphere is provided integrally
with an axis, or fixedly attached to the axis by adhesion,
bonding, or so forth so as to be in contact with a tapered sleeve
having a conical surface caving in on both the inner sides
thereof as seen in section in such a way as to surround the
sphere. In this case, oscillation of the axis while in rotation is
enabled (refer to Fig. 7).</p>
    <p num="0049">Examples of surface contact include a case where the
rotating body is a cone and a supporting body is a cone having
a conical surface expanding inward on both sides thereof as
seen in section. Cited as such a case is one where, for example,
a pair of rotating bodies whose conical surfaces are opposed to
each other are provided integrally with an axis, or fixedly
attached to the axis by adhesion, bonding, or so forth so as to
be in contact with a tapered sleeve having a conical surface
expanding inward on both sides thereof as seen in section
(refer to Fig. 3).</p>
    <p num="0050">Another example of surface contact is a case where each
of a pair of rotating bodies is a side ring, and a supporting body
is a sleeve (refer to Fig. 6).</p>
    <p num="0051">Still another example of surface contact is a case where a
rotating body is a sphere having a convex surface, and is in 
contact with a supporting body having a concave spherical
surface so as to be partially surrounded by the latter. In this
case, oscillation of the axis while in rotation is enabled (refer to
Fig. 10).</p>
    <p num="0052">Further, in the case of surface contact, one or more than
one grooves are preferably provided on a fitting face of the
supporting body or a contact face of the side ring. With such a
construction as described, friction trouble can be avoided by
allowing wear powder or other foreign matters such as dust to
be removed from friction faces. The grooves are preferably
configured into an annular shape, spiral shape, or radial
shape.</p>
    <p num="0053">With the special type bearing device according to the
invention, the rotating body or the supporting body may be
preloaded or energized. In this way, preload is constantly
applied to contact parts of these bodies, so that new contact
parts are automatically come to be formed to cope with
elements such as wear, occurring to friction parts of both the
bodies, in contact with each other.</p>
    <p num="0054">Such preload or energization may be applied from one
direction, or from two directions opposite to each other. For
example, the preload or energization may be applied from one
side in the direction parallel to the axial direction, or from both
sides in the direction parallel to the axial direction.</p>
    <p num="0055">Further, the supporting body may be divided into parts,
and the preload or energization may be applied in a gap
therebetween. In the case of the rotating body being a sphere,
the supporting body can be pressurized or energized by the
agency of spacers.</p>
    <p num="0056">The preload or energization may normally be applied by 
use of a spring, such as a metal spring, rubber spring, and so
forth, in such a way as to cause the rotating body or the
supporting body to be pushed out or to undergo contraction.</p>
    <p num="0057">The special type bearing device according to the invention
is applicable to driving equipment in general, such as a
miniature motor and so forth, as a bearing with improved
performance in various respects in place of a conventional
sleeve bearing made of sintered material, and a conventional
bearing made of polymer resin. Examples of such a product to
which the special type bearing device is applied include the
following:
<sl><li>1. spindle motor for an HDD</li><li>2. spindle motor for an FDD</li><li>3. polygon mirror</li><li>4. miniature motor for the automobile</li><li>5. miniature motor for office automation equipment
including, for example, a copying machine, printer, facsimile
machine, and so forth</li><li>6. HDD swing arm applied to a pivot bearing</li><li>7. miniature stepping motor</li><li>8. fan motor for use in a blower, and so forth</li><li>9. motor for a sawing machine</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0058">In particular, the special type bearing device according to
the invention is preferably assembled into a miniature motor,
for example, a spindle motor, a pivot ass'y. bearing for an HDD,
and so forth.</p>
    <p num="0059">Embodiments of the invention are summed up as follows:
<sl><li>(1) a special type bearing device comprising an axis, a pair of
rotating bodies fixedly attached to the axis, and a supporting
body with which the rotating bodies are in contact, wherein 
any one of the axis, the rotating bodies, and the supporting
body is made of RB ceramic or CRB ceramic.</li><li>(2) a special type bearing device as set forth under item (1)
above, wherein the rotating bodies, and the whole or only
contact parts of the supporting body are made of RB ceramic or
CRB ceramic.</li><li>(3) a special type bearing device as set forth under item (1) or
(2) above, wherein each of the rotating bodies is in the shape of
a hemisphere or a cone, and the supporting body has a conical
surface suitable for accommodating the rotating bodies .</li><li>(4) a special type bearing device as set forth under item (3)
above, wherein one or more than one grooves are provided on
contact faces of the supporting body, in contact with each of the
rotating bodies .</li><li>(5) a special type bearing device as set forth under item (4)
above, wherein the groove or grooves are configured into an
annular shape, spiral shape, or radial shape.</li><li>(6) a special type bearing device as set forth under any one of
items (1) to (5) above, wherein any one of the pair of the
rotating bodies is kept out of contact with the axis, and is
preloaded in the direction towards the other of the rotating
bodies.</li><li>(7) a special type bearing device as set forth under any one of
items (1) to (5) above, wherein both of the pair of the rotating
bodies are kept out of contact with the axis, and are preloaded
from two directions opposite to each other, respectively.</li><li>(8) a special type bearing device as set forth under any one of
items (1) to (7) above, wherein the supporting body is divided
into two parts so as to be preloaded.</li><li>(9) a sleeve bearing device comprising an axis, a pair of side 
rings fixedly attached to the axis, and a sleeve, wherein any
one of the axis, the side rings, and the sleeve is made of RB
ceramic or CRB ceramic.</li><li>(10) a sleeve bearing device as set forth under item (9) above,
wherein one or more than one grooves, configured into an
annular shape, spiral shape, or radial shape, are provided on a
contact face of each of the side rings.</li><li>(11) a spherical special type bearing comprising an axis, a
rotating body fixedly attached to the axis, and a supporting
body, the rotating body being a spherical body while the
supporting body supporting the spherical body in such a way as
to surround the latter at four points, wherein any one of the
axis, the rotating body, and the supporting body is made of RB
ceramic or CRB ceramic.</li><li>(12) a spherical special type bearing as set forth under item
(11) above, wherein the spherical body is either a proper sphere
or an oval.</li><li>(13) a spherical special type bearing as set forth under item
(11) or (12) above, wherein the quartered parts of the
supporting body are integrally joined together with spacers
and are kept energized.</li><li>(14) a spherical special type bearing comprising an axis, a
rotating body in the shape of a sphere having a convex surface,
fixedly attached to the axis, and a supporting body having a
concave spherical surface, the sphere having the convex
surface being in surface contact with the supporting body
having the concave spherical surface across the entire surface
thereof, wherein any one of the axis, the rotating body, and the
supporting body is made of RB ceramic or CRB ceramic.</li><li>(15) a special type bearing device as set forth under any one of 
items (1) to (14) above, wherein any one of the axis, the
rotating body, and the supporting body is made of RB ceramic
or CRB ceramic, and the RB ceramic or the CRB ceramic is
impregnated with a lubricating oil.</li><li>(16) a miniature motor incorporating the special type bearing
device as set forth under any one of items (1) to (15) above.</li><li>(17) a spindle motor incorporating the special type bearing
device as set forth under any one of items (1) to (15) above.</li><li>(18) a pivot ass'y for an HDD, incorporating the special type
bearing device as set forth under any one of items (1) to (15)
above.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0060">Now, various examples of the special type bearing device
according to the invention are described hereinafter with
reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
    <p num="0061">Fig. 1 shows an example of a special type bearing device
according to the invention as (R - A).</p>
    <p num="0062">The special type bearing device (R - A) is fabricated as
follows.</p>
    <p num="0063">More specifically, a hemisphere 3 - 1, made of RB ceramic
or CRB ceramic, is fixedly attached to a shaft (an axis) 1 by
bonding in a press fit or by other means such as a mechanical
method, and is inserted into the bore of a tapered sleeve 2 as
far as the hemisphere 3 - 1 comes into contact with a tapered
part of the tapered sleeve 2, on the side of one end thereof (up
to contact points P as seen in section). Subsequently, a
hemisphere 3 - 2 is fitted into the bore of the tapered sleeve 2
from the side of the other end of the shaft 1 as far as the
hemisphere 3 - 2 comes into contact with a tapered part of the
tapered sleeve 2, on the other side thereof (up to contact points
P' as seen in section) while applying preload thereto, thereby 
fixedly attaching the hemisphere 3 - 2 to the shaft 1 by bonding
in a press fit or by other means such as a mechanical method.</p>
    <p num="0064">As shown in Fig. 2, the hemispheres 3 - 1, 3 - 2 are
fabricated by processing a sphere A prepared by firing CRB
ceramic in a die to a high degree of sphericity, slicing the
sphere A crosswise into equal parts, that is, hemispheres B, B
and subsequently, boring a hole in the respective hemispheres
B, B for fitting the same onto the shaft 1.</p>
    <p num="0065">Alternatively, a hole may be bored in the sphere A as it is
before slicing the same crosswise, and the hemispheres may be
impregnated with oil for lubrication at a high temperature or
in a vacuum after the fabrication of the hemispheres.</p>
    <p num="0066">Further, the tapered sleeve 2 is made of steel, and has
high hardness as a result of a hardening process applied
thereto as necessary, so that the tapered sleeve 2 is finished
with high precision in terms of respective dimensions thereof,
and in particular, the tapered parts on both sides are finished
to high-precision dimensions.</p>
    <p num="0067">Further, the hemispheres 3 - 1, 3 - 2 may be made of steel,
RB ceramic or CRB ceramic, and the tapered sleeve 2 may be
made of RB ceramic or CRB ceramic.</p>
    <p num="0068">The RB ceramic or CRB ceramic is preferably
impregnated sufficiently with a lubricating oil.</p>
    <p num="0069">In the case of a sphere made of steel or other ceramic, the
sphere is not normally impregnated with lubricating oil.</p>
    <p num="0070">In any case, with such a bearing structure as described
above, load will be borne on contact lines (where P and P' are
present), constituting contact points between the respective
hemispheres and the respective tapered parts of the tapered
sleeve 2. </p>
    <p num="0071">The special type bearing device (R - A) shown in Fig. 1 has
the following features:
<sl><li>Case A where the hemispheres are made of RB ceramic or
CRB ceramic, and the tapered sleeve is made of steel:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>less rotational deflection of the shaft after assembled
due to spherical contact</li><li>small friction coefficient and high wear resistance.
These features are further enhanced when the hemispheres
are impregnated with a lubricating oil.</li><li>variation in the dimensions of the hemispheres
themselves, dependent on variation in temperature, becomes
negligible due to small expansion coefficient of the
hemispheres, and because the shaft 1 and the tapered sleeve 2
are made of an iron based material, variation in the
dimensions thereof, dependent on variation in temperature,
can be held down to the minimum. In particular, due to this
feature, variation in the positions of the contact lines (points P,
P' in Fig. 1) can be reduced, thereby enabling the effect of
variation (increase / decrease) of backlash occurring due to an
increase in temperature to be lessened.</li><li>this being the case of line contact instead of surface
contact as in the case of a conventional type bearing, a sliding
friction torque is small, fluctuation in torque is small, and heat
generation is also small.</li><li>reduction in the weight of the special type bearing
device is possible due to a low specific gravity thereof</li><li>the special type bearing device can be utilized as an
electric conductor</li><li>if there is provided a structure wherein preload is
continuously applied from either the hemisphere 3 - 1 or the 
hemisphere 3 - 2 by the urging of a spring as shown in Fig. 5,
automatic correction against wear can be implemented in case
that wear occurs on the contact lines passing the points P, P',
respectively, because this will cause contact between respective
spheres and tapered surfaces</li><li>there is no need of applying a heat treatment in order to
increase the hardness of the shaft 1</li><li>the special type bearing device is provided in the form of
a completed unit, so that it can be assembled into equipment
with ease.</li></ul></li><li>Case B where the hemispheres are made of steel, and the
tapered sleeve is made of RB ceramic or CRB ceramic:
<sl><li>The special type bearing device in this case has
substantially the same features as those for the case A as
described above.</li></sl></li></sl></p>
    <p num="0072">Fig. 3 shows another example of a special type bearing
device according to the invention as (R - B).</p>
    <p num="0073">This special type bearing device is the same in
construction as the previously described example (R - A) except
that the hemispheres made of RB ceramic or CRB ceramic are
configured into the shape of a cone, thereby rendering the
construction thereof suitable for use under a high load and at a
low speed.</p>
    <p num="0074">With the special type bearing device, a cone 4 - 1, made of
RB ceramic or CRB ceramic, is fixedly attached to a shaft (an
axis) 1 by bonding in a press fit or by other means, and is
inserted into the bore of a conical sleeve 5 as far as the conical
surface of the cone 4 - 1 comes into contact with the conical
surface of the conical sleeve 5. Subsequently, a cone 4 - 2 is
fitted into the bore of the conical sleeve 5 from the other end of 
the shaft 1 as far as the cone 4 - 2 comes into contact with the
conical surface of the conical sleeve 5, on the other side thereof
while applying preload thereto, thereby fixedly attaching the
cone 4 - 2 to the shaft 1 by bonding in a press fit or by other
means such as a mechanical method.</p>
    <p num="0075">The conical sleeve 5 is made of steel, and has high
hardness as a result of a hardening process applied thereto as
necessary, so that the conical sleeve 5 is finished with high
precision in terms of respective dimensions thereof, and in
particular, the conical surfaces on both sides are finished to
high-precision dimensions.</p>
    <p num="0076">Further, grooves 6 are provided on the conical surface of
the conical sleeve 5 as necessary in order to allow wear powder
or other foreign matters such as dust to be removed from
friction faces thereof, thereby avoiding friction trouble. The
grooves are configured into an annular shape, spiral shape, or
radial shape.</p>
    <p num="0077">With this bearing device, the cones 4 - 1, 4 - 2 may be
made of steel, RB ceramic or CRB ceramic, and the conical
sleeve 5 may be made of RB ceramic or CRB ceramic.</p>
    <p num="0078">Further, with this bearing device as well, the RB ceramic
or CRB ceramic is preferably impregnated sufficiently with a
lubricating oil.</p>
    <p num="0079">In any case, with such a bearing structure as described
above, load will be borne by surface contact parts between the
conical surfaces of the cones and the conical surface of the
conical sleeve, so that this bearing device based on surface
contact has enhanced load resistance in contrast with the
special type bearing device (R - A) shown in Fig. 1, based on
line contact. </p>
    <p num="0080">The special type bearing device (R - B) has the following
features:
<sl><li>Case A where the cones are made of RB ceramic or CRB
ceramic, and the conical sleeve is made of steel:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>small friction coefficient and high wear resistance.
This feature is further enhanced when the cones are
impregnated with a lubricating oil.</li><li>because of small friction coefficient, a friction torque is
small, and heat generation is also small.</li><li>suitable for use under a high load because load is borne
through surface contact on the conical surface.</li><li>variation in the dimensions of the cones themselves,
dependent on variation in temperature, becomes negligible due
to small expansion coefficient of the cones, and because the
shaft 1 and the conical sleeve 5 are made of an iron based
material, variation in the dimensions thereof, dependent on
variation in temperature, can be held down to the minimum.
In particular, due to this feature, variation in the position of
impingement on contact surfaces can be reduced, thereby
enabling the effect of variation (increase / decrease) of backlash
occurring due to an increase in temperature to be lessened.</li><li>reduction in the weight of the special type bearing
device is possible due to a low specific gravity thereof.</li><li>the special type bearing device can be utilized as an
electric conductor.</li><li>if there is provided a structure wherein preload is
continuously applied from either the cone 4 - 1 or the cone 4 - 2
by the urging of a spring, automatic correction for wear on both
the conical surfaces can be implemented</li><li>there is no need of applying a heat treatment in order to 
increase the hardness of the shaft 1.</li><li>the special type bearing device is provided in the form of
a completed unit, so that it can be assembled into equipment
with ease.</li></ul></li><li>Case B where the cones are made of steel, and the conical
sleeve is made of RB ceramic or CRB ceramic:
<sl><li>The special type bearing device in this case has
substantially the same features as those for the case A.</li></sl></li></sl></p>
    <p num="0081">Fig. 4 shows still another example of a special type
bearing device according to the invention as (R - C).</p>
    <p num="0082">This special type bearing represents a special type
bearing device featuring a constitution wherein the tapered
sleeve 2 as for the special type bearing device (R - A) of a
hemisphere type, constructed as shown in Fig. 1, is divided into
two equal parts, and springs are provided therebetween for
preloading.</p>
    <p num="0083">This special type bearing device is constructed such that
springs 8 are assembled in-between a tapered sleeve 2 - 1 and a
tapered sleeve 2 - 2, formed by dividing a tapered sleeve into
two, so as to constantly apply preload to a contact line between
a hemisphere 3 - 1 and the tapered sleeve 2 - 1 (contact points
P are present on the contact line) as well as a contact line
between a hemisphere 3 - 2 and the tapered sleeve 2 - 2
(contact points P' are present on the contact line), so that
automatic correction of backlash due to wear, and so forth,
occurring to friction parts in contact with each other, is
enabled.</p>
    <p num="0084">As with the other examples, the special type bearing
device (R - C) has such different constitutions as follows:
<sl><li>a case A where the hemispheres are made of RB ceramic or 
CRB ceramic, and the tapered sleeves are made of steel; and</li><li>a case B where the hemispheres are made of steel, and the
tapered sleeves are made of RB ceramic or CRB ceramic</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0085">With the special type bearing device (R - C) as well, the
RB ceramic or CRB ceramic is preferably impregnated
sufficiently with a lubricating oil.</p>
    <p num="0086">Further, this method of dividing the tapered sleeve into
two equal parts is similarly applicable to the special type
bearing device (R - B) of a cone type, constructed as shown in
Fig. 3.</p>
    <p num="0087">Fig. 5 shows a further example of a special type bearing
device according to the invention as (R - D).</p>
    <p num="0088">The special type bearing device (R - D) is the same as the
special type bearing device (R - A) of the hemisphere type,
constructed as shown in Fig. 1, except that it is constructed
such that preload is constantly applied to a hemisphere 3 - 2 on
the bottom side thereof by the urging of a spring 9, the
hemisphere 3 - 2 on the bottom side is out of contact with a
shaft 1, and slidable in the axial direction of the shaft 1 while
mechanically restrained against rotation in the direction of
rotation of the shaft 1, and the spring 9 is installed so as to be
interjacent between a flat face of the hemisphere 3 - 2, in
contact with one end thereof, and a snap ring 7 fitted into a
groove 10 provided at the rear end of the shaft 1, in contact
with the other end thereof, so that preload is constantly
applied to a contact line (contact points P' in Fig. 5) by the
urging of the spring 9.</p>
    <p num="0089">A receptacle structure for the other end of the spring 9 is
not limited to that of a snap ring type, and other mechanical
type may be adopted instead. </p>
    <p num="0090">With such a construction as described, automatic
correction of backlash due to wear, and. so forth, occurring to
friction parts (contact points P, P' in Fig. 4), can be
implemented as with the case of the special type bearing device
(R - C), constructed as shown in Fig. 4,</p>
    <p num="0091">In this case as well, a hemisphere 3 - 1, and the
hemisphere 3 - 2 may be made of steel, RB ceramic or CRB
ceramic, and a tapered sleeve 2 may be made of RB ceramic or
CRB ceramic as with the case of the special type bearing device
(R - A), constructed as shown in Fig. 1.</p>
    <p num="0092">With the special type bearing device (R - D) as well, the
RB ceramic or CRB ceramic is preferably impregnated
sufficiently with a lubricating oil.</p>
    <p num="0093">Fig. 6 shows a still further example of a special type
bearing device according to the invention as (R - E).</p>
    <p num="0094">The bearing (R - E) represents the special type bearing
device of a construction using a special type bearing made of
RB ceramic or CRB ceramic, wherein a side ring 11 made of
steel or other material is fixedly attached to a shaft 1 in a press
fit, or formed integrally with the shaft 1, the shaft 1 is inserted
into the bore of a sleeve bearing 14 with a fitting clearance
adequate for slidable rotation, and a side ring 12 also made of
steel or other material is fitted onto the shaft 1 from the other
end thereof while applying preload so as to be fixedly attached
to the shaft 1 in a pressurized state by bonding or by other
means such as a mechanical method.</p>
    <p num="0095">Grooves 13 are formed on a friction face of the side rings
11, 12, respectively, in contact with the sleeve bearing 14, as
necessary, in order to allow wear powder or other foreign
matters such as dust to be removed from the friction faces, 
thereby avoiding friction trouble. The grooves 13 are
configured into an anular shape, spiral shape, radial shape, or
so forth.</p>
    <p num="0096">The RB ceramic or CRB ceramic is preferably
impregnated sufficiently with a lubricating oil.</p>
    <p num="0097">As with the special type bearing device (R - D) constructed
as shown in Fig. 5, this special type bearing device may also be
constructed such that preload is constantly applied to the side
ring 11 by the urging of a spring.</p>
    <p num="0098">Fig. 7 shows an yet further example of a special type
bearing device according to the invention as (R - F).</p>
    <p num="0099">The bearing (R - F) represents a spherical special type
bearing device. With the spherical special type bearing device
(R - F), a sphere 16 made of RB ceramic or CRB ceramic is
fitted onto a shaft 1 to be fixedly attached thereto, and is
sandwiched between respective tapered parts of a tapered
sleeve 2 - 1, and a tapered sleeve 2 - 2, both made of steel, and
assembled together with dimensions set in such a way as to
enable adequate preload to be applied to contact lines (contact
points P, P' are present on the respective contact lines) by the
agency of spacers 15. Further, the spherical special type
bearing device (R - F) in whole is assembled into a housing 22.</p>
    <p num="0100">The spherical special type bearing device (R - F) may
adopt a reverse constitution such that the sphere 16 is made of
steel while the tapered sleeve 2 - 1 and the tapered sleeve 2 - 2
are made of RB ceramic or CRB ceramic.</p>
    <p num="0101">With the spherical special type bearing device (R - F) as
well, the RB ceramic or CRB ceramic is preferably impregnated
sufficiently with a lubricating oil.</p>
    <p num="0102">The special type bearing device (R - F) is simpler in 
construction, and lower in production cost in comparison with
those bearings currently available in the market.</p>
    <p num="0103">Fig. 8 shows an example of a spindle motor incorporating
the special type bearing device R of the hemisphere type shown
in Fig. 1 in the axial core part thereof as X.</p>
    <p num="0104">Fig. 9 shows an example of a pivot ass'y bearing for an
HDD, incorporating the special type bearing device R of the
hemisphere type shown in Fig. 1 as Y.</p>
    <p num="0105">The pivot ass'y bearing Y is fabricated by assembling the
special type bearing device R into a sleeve 19 of a pivot ass'y
bearing for a swing arm of an HDD, and mounting a seal cover
18 on the sleeve 19 for sealing to prevent leakage of oil.</p>
    <p num="0106">Assembling of the sleeve 19 into an assembling part of
equipment for various applications will suffice to set up this
pivot ass'y bearing</p>
    <p num="0107">The pivot ass'y. bearing Y may be used in the same way
as for common bearings of various types (sleeve bearing, ball
bearing, and so forth).</p>
    <p num="0108">Fig. 10 shows another example of a special type bearing
device according to the invention as (R - G).</p>
    <p num="0109">With the special type bearing device (R - G), a shaft 1 is
inserted in a press fit into a hole at the center of a sphere made
of steel to be fixedly attached thereto, a sphere of a spherical
inner race 20 is slidably fitted to an outer race 21 to be
assembled with each other, and the outer periphery of the
outer race 21 is fitted into a housing 22 to be fixed thereto by
swaging.</p>
    <p num="0110">Thus, the special type bearing device (R - G) is a bearing
constructed so as to enable the shaft 1 to oscillate at an angle of
 while in rotation. </p>
    <p num="0111">Fig. 11 shows still another example of a special type
bearing device according to the invention as (R - H).</p>
    <p num="0112">The special type bearing device (R - H) is a bearing
employing only one of the hemispheres in the special type
bearing device (R - A) constructed as shown in Fig. 1,
comprising a tapered sleeve 2, a hemisphere 3, and a shaft (not
shown) fixedly attached to the hemisphere 3.</p>
    <p num="0113">The tapered sleeve 2 is in line contact with the
hemisphere 3, and by applying preload to a contact line
therebetween, automatic correction of backlash due to wear
and so forth, occurring to friction parts (points P in Fig. 4) can
be implemented as with the case of the special type bearing
device (R - C) constructed as shown in Fig. 4.</p>
    <p num="0114">In this case as well, the hemisphere 3 may be made of
steel, RB ceramic or CRB ceramic, and the tapered sleeve 2
may be made of RB ceramic or CRB ceramic as with the case of
the special type bearing device (R - A) constructed as shown in
Fig. 1.</p>
    <p num="0115">With the special type bearing device (R - H) as well, the
RB ceramic or CRB ceramic is preferably impregnated
sufficiently with a lubricating oil.</p>
    <p num="0116">Further, it is possible to employ two units of the special
type bearing devices (R - H), disposed so as to face each other.
It is also possible to employ a plurality of units of these,
overlaid one after another, as necessary. Furthermore, the
special type bearing device (R - H) may be employed in
combination with a special type bearing device (R - I) as shown
in Fig. 12.</p>
    <p num="0117">Fig. 12 shows a further example of the special type
bearing device according to the invention as (R - I). </p>
    <p num="0118">This special type bearing device represents a bearing of a
single structure, comprising only one of the same rotating
bodies made of RB ceramic or CRB ceramic as employed in the
special type bearing device (R - B) so as to be suitable for use
under a high load and at a low speed.</p>
    <p num="0119">With the special type bearing device (R - I), a cone 4.
made of RB ceramic or CRB ceramic, is fixedly attached to a
shaft (an axis) 1 (not shown) by bonding in a press fit or by
other means, and is inserted into the bore of a conical sleeve 5
as far as the conical surface of the cone 4 comes into contact
with the conical surface of the conical sleeve 5.</p>
    <p num="0120">The conical sleeve 5 is made of steel, and has high
hardness as a result of a hardening process applied thereto as
necessary, so that the conical sleeve 5 is finished with high
precision in terms of respective dimensions thereof, and in
particular, the conical surfaces thereof on both sides as seen in
section are finished to high-precision dimensions.</p>
    <p num="0121">Further, grooves 6 are provided on the conical surface of
the conical sleeve 5 as necessary in order to allow wear powder
or other foreign matters such as dust to be removed from
friction faces, thereby avoiding friction trouble. The grooves are
configured into an annular shape, spiral shape, or radial
shape.</p>
    <p num="0122">Further, with this bearing, the cone 4 may be made of
steel, RB ceramic or CRB ceramic, and the conical sleeve 5 may
be made of RB ceramic or CRB ceramic.</p>
    <p num="0123">With this bearing as well, the RB ceramic or CRB ceramic
is preferably impregnated sufficiently with a lubricating oil.</p>
    <p num="0124">In any case, with such a bearing structure as described
above, load will be borne on surface contact parts between the 
conical surface of the cone and the conical surface of the conical
sleeve, so that the special type bearing device R - I, based on
surface contact, has its load resistance improved in contrast
with the special type bearing device (R - H) of the hemisphere
type, shown in Fig. 11, which is based on line contact.</p>
    <p num="0125">The special type bearing device (R - I) has the same
features as those of the special type bearing device (R - B).</p>
    <p num="0126">Further, it is possible to employ two units of the special
type bearing devices (R - I), disposed so as to face each other.
It is also possible to employ a plurality of units of the special
type bearing devices (R - I), overlaid one after another, or
disposed so as to face each other, as required. Furthermore,
the special type bearing device (R -I) may be employed in
combination with the special type bearing device (R - H) as
shown in Fig. 11.</p>
    <p num="0127">Now, the special type bearing device according to the
invention exhibits particular effects unachievable by
conventional bearing devices in that it is insusceptible to
damage, is light in weight, has a long service life and excellent
wear resistance, is insusceptible to the effect of change in
temperature, is easy to fabricate, and has little offensiveness
towards mating members, and further, the same can exhibit a
pronounced advantageous effect in that, due to its porosity, it
is capable of sufficiently retaining a lubricant such as oil and
grease, and thereafter, retaining the lubricant for a long period
of time without the need of supplying oil during operation,
thereby rendering it maintenance-free. In particular, the
special type bearing device according to the invention, using
CRB ceramic, has an advantage of a small contraction ratio of
the dimensions of a finished product to those of a formed 
workpiece, thereby enabling a high-precision product to be
fabricated with ease.</p>
    <p num="0128">The features disclosed in the foregoing description,
in the claims and/or in the accompanying drawings may, both
separately and in any combination thereof, be material for
realising the invention in diverse forms thereof.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A special type bearing device comprising an axis (1), a
pair of rotating bodies fixedly attached to the axis, and a
supporting body with which the rotating bodies are in contact,
wherein any one of the axis (1), the rotating bodies, and the
supporting body is made of RB ceramic or CRB ceramic.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A special type bearing device as set forth in claim 1,
wherein the rotating bodies, and the whole or only contact
parts of the supporting body are made of RB ceramic or CRB
ceramic.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A special type bearing device as set forth in claim 1 or
claim 2, wherein each of the rotating bodies is in the shape of a
hemisphere (3-1, 3-2) or a cone (4-1, 4-2), and the supporting
body has a conical surface suitable for accommodating the
rotating bodies .</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A special type bearing device as set forth in claim 3,
wherein one or more than one grooves (6) are provided on
contact faces of the supporting body, in contact with each of the
rotating bodies.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A special type bearing device as set forth in claim 4,
wherein the groove (6) or the grooves (6) are configured into an
annular shape, spiral shape, or radial shape.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A special type bearing device as set forth in any one of
claims 1 to 5, wherein any one of the pair of the rotating bodies
is kept out of contact with the axis (1), and is preloaded in the
direction towards the other of the rotating bodies .</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A special type bearing device as set forth in any one of
claims 1 to 5, wherein both of the pair of the rotating bodies are
kept out of contact with the axis (1), and are preloaded from
two directions opposite to each other, respectively.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A special type bearing device as set forth in any one of
claims 1 to 7, wherein the supporting body is divided into two
parts (2-1, 2-2) so as to be preloaded.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>A sleeve bearing device comprising an axis (1), a pair of
side rings (11, 12) fixedly attached to the axis (1), and a sleeve
bearing (14), wherein any one of the axis (1), the side rings (11,
12), and the sleeve bearing (14) is made of RB ceramic or CRB
ceramic.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>A sleeve bearing device as set forth in claim 9,
wherein one or more than one grooves (13), configured into an
annular shape, spiral shape, or radial shape, are provided on a
contact face of each of the side rings (11, 12).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>A spherical special type bearing device comprising an
axis (1), a rotating body fixedly attached to the axis (1), and a
supporting body, the rotating body being a spherical body (16)
while the supporting body supporting the spherical body (16) in
such a way as to surround the latter at four points, wherein
any one of the axis (1), the rotating body, and the supporting
body is made of RB ceramic or CRB ceramic.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>A spherical special type bearing device as set forth in
claim 11, wherein the spherical body is either a proper sphere
or an oval.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>A spherical special type bearing device as set forth in
claim 11 or claim 12, wherein quartered parts of the supporting
body are integrally joined together with spacers (15) and are
kept energized.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>A spherical special type bearing device comprising an
axis (1), a rotating body in the shape of a sphere having a
convex surface, fixedly attached to the axis, and a supporting
body having a concave spherical surface, the sphere having the
convex surface being in surface contact with the supporting
body having the concave spherical surface across the entire
surface thereof, wherein any one of the axis, the rotating body,
and the supporting body is made of RB ceramic or CRB
ceramic.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>A special type bearing device as set forth in any one of
claims 1 to 14, wherein any one of the axis (1), the rotating
body or bodies, and the supporting body is made of RB ceramic
or CRB ceramic, and the RB ceramic or the CRB ceramic is
impregnated with a lubricating oil.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>A miniature motor incorporating the special type
bearing device as set forth in any one of claims 1 to 15.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>A spindle motor incorporating the special type bearing
device as set forth in any one of claims 1 to 15.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="18">
      <claim-text>A pivot ass'y for an HDD, incorporating the special
type bearing device as set forth in any one of claims 1 to 15.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="19">
      <claim-text>A special type bearing device of a single structure,
comprising an axis (1), a single rotating body fixedly attached
to the axis, and a supporting body with which the single
rotating body is in contact, wherein any one of the axis (1), the
rotating body, and the supporting body is made of RB ceramic
or CRB ceramic.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="20">
      <claim-text>A special type bearing device of a single structure as
set forth in claim 19, wherein the rotating body is in the shape
of a hemisphere (3) or a cone (4), and the supporting body has a
conical surface suitable for accommodating the rotating body.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="21">
      <claim-text>A special type bearing device of a single structure as
set forth in claim 19 or claim 20, wherein one or more than one
grooves (6), configured into an annular shape, spiral shape, or
radial shape, are provided.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
