<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1238744-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1238744" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="26610011" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020911">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1238744-A1" status="new" fvid="23537521">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1238744</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20020911</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02004122-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02004122</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020225</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001048756-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001048756</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010223</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001381889-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001381889</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20011214</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B23K  26/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B23K  26/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B23K  26/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B23K  26/03        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B23K  26/24        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B23K  26/32        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G01N  21/88        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G01N  21/88        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B23K  26/03</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B23K  26/24B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B23K  26/32A</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L23K103:04</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren und Vorrichtung zur Überwachung der Schweissqualität einer Laserschweissverbindung</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Laser weld quality monitoring method and system</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Méthode et appareil de contrôle de la qualité du soudage d' un joint soudé par laser</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NISSAN MOTOR</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NISSAN MOTOR CO., LTD.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>NISSAN MOTOR CO., LTD.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>2 Takara-cho, Kanagawa-ku</street>
              <city>Yokohama-shi Kanagawa-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MORI KIYOKAZU</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TAKEMURA SHINSUKE</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TARUI TAISHI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MORI, KIYOKAZU</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TAKEMURA, SHINSUKE</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TARUI, TAISHI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>MORI, KIYOKAZU</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>2-3-2-306, Okada</street>
              <city>Atsugi-shi, Kanagawa-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>TAKEMURA, SHINSUKE</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>4164-3, Shimotsuruma</street>
              <city>Yamato-shi, Kanagawa-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>TARUI, TAISHI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>3-24-10-502, Katasekaigan</street>
              <city>Fujisawa-shi, Kanagawa-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Weber, Joachim, Dr.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Hoefer, Schmitz, Weber &amp;amp; Partner Patentanwälte Gabriel-Max-Strasse 29</street>
              <city>81545 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>Infrared reflection of a laser beam (LB3) irradiated on a welding part (WP) of
work (5) is detected by a sensor (6a) high of elevation angle, where it is converted into
an electrical signal, which is processed by a measuring circuit (MC) to be input to a
quality monitor (QM), where it is stored as a data in a memory (7g), which data is
processed by way of a spectral analysis, which calculates a spectral distribution of
electrical signal, and a signal power sum in a particular frequency band, to be compared
with a threshold value for decision on occurrence of a significant porous state.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="142" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="102"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <b>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a laser weld quality monitoring method and
system. In particular, the invention relates to a laser weld quality monitoring method
and system adapted to monitor a quality of a YAG laser weld, such as for an occurrence
of a porous, under-filled, or non-welded status.</p>
    <p num="0002">The welding of very thin steel sheets, such as for a vehicle body, is performed
by a laser welding. In comparison with a spot welding, the laser welding has many
advantages such that it is applicable to a one-side welding without the need of clamping
steel sheets from both obverse and reverse, and that it allows an easy welding even at an
inside of a complicate narrow groove. However, as a disadvantage, it tends to suffer a
degradation of welding quality caused by a failed lapping accuracy between steel sheets
or accrued suddenly at a stained welding part.</p>
    <p num="0003">Therefore, the monitoring of a laser weld is performed by predicting a weld
quality in a real-time manner. Japanese Patent Application Laying-Open Publication
No. 2000-271768 has disclosed techniques of using a pair of sensors having their
detection angles different from each other, for sensing intensities of light from a plume
occurring at a keyhole of a weld by a YAG (Yttrium Aluminum Garnet) laser and
reflection of light of the YAG laser, to detect variations of output, welding, and inter-sheet
gap as welding conditions, thereby performing a real-time prediction of a quality
of the laser weld.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0004">For the conventional method of monitoring a quality of laser weld, it is
possible to detect occurrences of a significant grooved state of weld (hereafter
sometimes referred to as "under-filled" state or simply "under-fill") and a non-conforming
state of weld significantly deviated from a specified welding condition
(hereafter sometimes referred to as "non-conforming" state or simply "non-conformity").
It however is difficult to detect an occurrence of a significant porous state of weld
(hereafter sometimes referred to as "porous" state or simply "porosity" or "pore").</p>
    <p num="0005">The difficulty in detection of an occurrence of porous state in the conventional
weld quality monitoring method resides in that a decision on quality is made of a state
of weld based on the intensity of light emitted from a melt (with a "keyhole") irradiated
by a laser beam, irrespective of the fact that the porous state is caused by a mixing of
zinc vapor inside the keyhole, which mixing seldom imparts significant variations in the 
intensity of emitted light from the keyhole.</p>
    <p num="0006">Moreover, in a lap welding, if the inter-sheet gap is too great, there occurs an
incomplete welding as a failure of weld between lapped steel sheets (hereafter
sometimes referred to as "non-welded" state or "failed lap weld"), of which detection
also is difficult in the conventional weld quality monitoring method.</p>
    <p num="0007">Furthermore, in the conventional weld quality monitoring method, occurrences
of the porous state, weld state such as an under-filled excepting a non-welded, and non-conforming
state can be detected in different manners depending on the weld state, so
that their detection needs a very complicate calculation process, with a commensurate
great burden to be imposed on a CPU (central processing unit) for the calculation
process.</p>
    <p num="0008">Still more, in the conventional weld quality monitoring method which allows a
facilitated detection of an occurrence of a porous state, weld state such as an under-filled
excepting a non-welded, or non-conforming state over an entire welding region, if
the occurrence of such a state is localized merely in part of the welding region, it also is
uneasy to detect this state.</p>
    <p num="0009">The present invention is made with such points in view. It therefore is an
object of the invention to provide a laser weld quality monitoring method and system
allowing for an ensured detection of occurrences of weld states such as a porous, under-filled,
and non-welded, without an undesirable increase of burden imposed on a
processing capacity of CPU, as well as for that of localized occurrences of weld states
such as a porous, under-filled, and non-welded, in a welding region by a YAG laser.</p>
    <p num="0010">As a solution to achieve the object, according to an aspect of the present
invention, there is provided a laser weld quality monitoring method comprising:
welding a part of work with a laser beam irradiated thereon from a YAG laser; detecting
a varying intensity of light reflected from the welding part to provide a detection signal;
determining a value of signal power of a frequency spectrum in a specified frequency
band of the detection signal; and making a decision for a porous state of the welding
part to be significant as the value of signal power exceeds a threshold of weld quality,
and to be insignificant as the value of signal power does not exceed the threshold of
weld quality.</p>
    <p num="0011">According to another aspect of the present invention, there is provided a laser
weld quality monitoring method comprising: irradiating a laser beam from a YAG laser
to a welding part of work; detecting light reflected from the welding part; calculating a
frequency distribution from a set of data of the detected light within a interval of time;
calculating, from the frequency distribution, a first signal power sum in one of a first 
frequency band for detecting an under-filled state and a second frequency band for
detecting a porous state, and a second signal power sum in a third frequency band for
detecting a non-welded state; mapping a combination of calculated values of the first
and second signal power sums, in a region defined by a combination of a first axis
representing the first signal power sum and a second axis representing the second signal
power sum, including a sub-region representing a non-conforming state as one of the
under-filled state, the porous state, and the non-welded state; and making a decision for
the welding part to have the non-conforming state, as the combination of calculated
values is mapped in the sub-region.</p>
    <p num="0012">Further, to achieve the object described, according to another aspect of the
present invention, there is provided a laser weld quality monitoring system comprising:
a welder configured to weld a part of work with a laser beam irradiated thereon from a
YAG laser; a detector configured to detect a varying intensity of light reflected from the
welding part to provide a detection signal; a value determiner configured to determine a
value of signal power of a frequency spectrum in a specified frequency band of the
detection signal; and a decision-maker configured to make a decision for a porous state
of the welding part to be significant as the value of signal power exceeds a threshold,
and to be insignificant as the value of signal power does not exceed the threshold.</p>
    <p num="0013">According to another aspect of the present invention, there is provided a laser
weld quality monitoring system comprising: a laser welder configured to irradiate a
laser beam from a YAG laser to a welding part of work; a detector configured to detect
light reflected from the welding part; a calculator configured to calculate a frequency
distribution from a set of data of the detected light within a interval of time; a calculator
configured to calculate, from the frequency distribution, a first signal power sum in one
of a first frequency band for detecting an under-filled state and a second frequency band
for detecting a porous state, and a second signal power sum in a third frequency band
for detecting a non-welded state; an operator configured to map a combination of
calculated values of the first and second signal power sums, in a region defined by a
combination of a first axis representing the first signal power sum and a second axis
representing the second signal power sum, including a sub-region representing a non-conforming
state as one of the under-filled state, the porous state, and the non-welded
state; and a decision-maker configured to make a decision for the welding part to have
the non-conforming state, as the combination of calculated values is mapped in the sub-region. </p>
    <heading>
      <b>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE ACCOMPANYING DRAWINGS</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0014">The above and further objects and novel features of the present invention will
more fully appear from the following detailed description when the same is read in
conjunction with the accompanying drawings, in which:
<sl><li>Fig. 1 is a fragmentary side view of a weld quality monitoring system
according to an embodiment of the invention, as it is applied to a YAG laser welder of a
welding system;</li><li>Fig. 2 is an illustrated conceptual constitution of the welding system equipped
with the weld quality monitoring system of Fig. 1;</li><li>Fig. 3 is a block diagram of a combination of a diffraction system and a pair of
photo-diodes connected thereto in a P(photo)-E(electric) converting sensor of a
measuring system of the weld quality monitoring system;</li><li>Fig. 4 is a block diagram of a combination of the diffraction system, a signal
processing line configured with a photo-diode and a measuring circuit connected thereto
in the measuring system, and a quality monitor of the weld quality monitoring system;</li><li>Fig. 5 is a sectional view of a lap welding part of work;</li><li>Fig. 6 is a perspective sectional view of a porous weld of a lapped portion of
work;</li><li>Fig. 7 is a perspective sectional view of an under-filled weld of a lapped
portion of work;</li><li>Fig. 8 is a flowchart of processes for monitoring a quality of weld to be free of
significant porous or under-filled state;</li><li>Fig. 9 is a set of waveform graphs of data on intensities of filtered infrared rays
of light from a welding part observed by a pair of P-E converting sensors under
reference welding conditions;</li><li>Fig. 10 is a set of waveform graphs of data on intensities of visible rays of light
from the welding part observed by the pair of sensors under the reference welding
conditions;</li><li>Fig. 11 is a set of waveform graphs of spectral power distributions of infrared
components of light detected by one sensor high of observation angle;</li><li>Fig. 12 is a graph showing typical distributions of Marharanobis distances over
a range of signal power for porous, fine porous, conforming, and under-filled parts;</li><li>Fig. 13 is a graph showing a relationship between a sheet thickness sum and a
frequency to be effective for a decision of porous state;</li><li>Fig. 14 is a graph showing a relationship between a welding speed and a
frequency to be effective for a decision of porous state, for different sheet thickness 
sums;</li><li>Fig. 15 is an exemplary table stored in a memory of the quality monitor in the
measuring system;</li><li>Fig. 16 is a sectional view describing a mechanism of variation of effective
frequency band at a welding part;</li><li>Fig. 17 is a perspective sectional view of a non-welded state of a lapped
portion of work;</li><li>Fig. 18 is a flowchart of processes for monitoring a quality of weld by a weld
quality monitoring system according to another embodiment of the invention;</li><li>Fig. 19 is a set of waveform graphs each respectively of an electrical detection
signal representing varying intensities of infrared rays of reflected light of YAG laser
beam in a welding accompanied by a conforming state or a non-welded state under
reference welding conditions;</li><li>Fig. 20 is a set of waveform graphs each respectively of an electrical detection
signal representing varying intensities of infrared rays of reflected light of YAG laser
beam in a welding accompanied by an under-filled state or a porous state under the
reference welding conditions;</li><li>Fig. 21 is a set of waveform graphs representing spectral signal power after
FFT operations of signal intensities of the electrical detection signals of Fig. 19 and Fig.
20;</li><li>Fig. 22 is a graph illustrating respective distributions of signal power sum data
associated with the under-filled state, porous state, non-welded state, and conforming
state;</li><li>Fig. 23 is a graph having a region of two-axis coordinate system mapped
thereon and divided into sub-regions covering respective sets of signal power sum data
associated with the under-filled state, porous state, non-welded state, and conforming
state;</li><li>Fig. 24 is a graph having the region of two-axis coordinate system mapped
thereon with a boundary region covering mixed signal power sum data;</li><li>Fig. 25 is an illustration describing a procedure of a decision to be again made
of whether the quality of weld under observation is conforming or not; and</li><li>Fig. 26 is an illustration of a vibration model of a melt region at a welding part
of a lap weld.</li></sl></p>
    <heading>
      <b>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0015">There will be detailed below the preferred embodiments of the present 
invention with reference to the accompanying drawings. Like members are designated
by like reference characters.</p>
    <heading>(First Embodiment)</heading>
    <p num="0016">Fig. 1 shows an essential portion of a weld quality monitoring system QMS
according to an embodiment of the invention, as it is applied to a YAG laser welder 100
of a welding system WS for a vehicle body fabrication line of an automobile factory,
Fig. 2 illustrates a conceptual constitution of the welding system WS equipped with the
weld quality monitoring system QMS, Fig. 3 shows a combination of a diffraction
system DS1 and a pair of photo-diodes 8a, 9a connected thereto in a P-E converting
sensor of a measuring system MS of the weld quality monitoring system QMS, and
Fig.4 shows a combination of the diffraction system DS1, a signal processing line PL1a
configured with one 8a of the pair of photo-diode and a measuring circuit 71a connected
thereto in the measuring system MS, and a quality monitor QM of the weld quality
monitoring system QMS.</p>
    <p num="0017">The welding system WS includes the YAG laser welder 100 and a YAG laser
oscillator 1. As shown in Fig. 1, the laser welder 100 is assembled as a combination of
a laser gun 101, a paint blast nozzle 102 (or protective gas discharge nozzle or electric
welder), and a paint supply system 103 (or gas supply system or welding transformer),
which are held in their cooperative positions by a common holder 104. In the Figures,
the laser welder 100 is set in a vertical position, where the laser gun 101 has, at a top
part 101a (as an input end) thereof, an optical fiber cable 2 connected thereto for
introducing, into the welder 100, a laser beam LB1 optically conducted (as flux of light
with a diverging tendency) from the laser oscillator 1. The laser gun 101 has, between
the above-noted top part 101a and a bottom part 101b (as an output end) thereof, an
intermediate lance part 101c configured as a light converging optical system COS (Fig.
2) for converging the introduced laser beam LB1.</p>
    <p num="0018">More specifically, the optical system COS has a collimator lens 3 for
collimating the diverging laser beam LB1 into a collimated laser beam LB2 as parallel
flux of light, and a light converging lens 4 for converging the collimated laser beam
LB2 to be focused as a converged laser beam LB3 on a focal point F to be set in
accurate position to a welding part WP of work 5 (as a lapped combination of vehicle
body panel members 5a, 5b) to be lap welded. It is noted that the welding part WP is a
part (of melt region + associated weld) under observation (i.e. monitoring), with a laser-irradiated
welding point inclusive, and has a length (e.g. 30 mm as in Fig. 25)
corresponding to an interval of bead (hereinafter sometimes called "bead section" or
simply "bead", when re-solidified) for which a prediction of weld quality is made on the 
basis of observation (i.e. by the monitoring). At the welding part WP, its constituent
materials are once melt by energy of the laser beam LB3, before solidification of the
melt by which the work 5 is to be lap welded at the part WP.</p>
    <p num="0019">The weld quality monitoring system QMS is constituted with the measuring
system MS (Figs. 2-4) and the quality monitor QM (Figs. 2, 4) communicating
therewith. The measuring system MS includes a pair of photoelectric sensors 6a, 6b
(Figs. 1-4, 6) and a set of four measuring circuits 71a, 71b, 72a, 72b (hereafter
sometimes collectively referred to as "MC", Figs. 2, 4) electrically connected thereto.
As illustrated in Fig. 1, the pair of sensors 6a, 6a are disposed, by use of a common
bracket 104b angularly adjustably fastened by bolts 104, 104e to a yoke 104a of the
common holder 104 of the laser welder 100, in their relatively fixed positions (90 - 1
= 30 degrees and 90 - 2 = 80 degrees relative to an optical axis OA) at a lateral side
of the bottom part 101b of the laser gun 101, such that one sensor 6a functions as a
reflected light detector in a first position at a first angle 1 of elevation to be 60
degrees relative to a concerned surface Sf of work 5, and the other sensor 6b functions
as a plasmatic light detector in position at a second angle 2 of elevation to be 10
degrees relative to the surface Sf of work 5. As illustrated in Fig. 2, the former sensor
6a makes a detection of such portion L1 (Figs. 2, 3, 5) of light of the laser beam LB3
that is reflected, and not absorbed, by (a front periphery 26f of a melt region 26, Fig. 5,
in) the welding part WP where the beam LB3 is irradiated. The latter sensor 6b makes
a detection of such portion L2 (Figs. 2, 3, 6) of light emitted from a plume 28 (hot metal
plasma, Fig. 5) developed in the welding part WP.</p>
    <p num="0020">In the weld quality monitoring system QMS, there is made a real-time decision
on the quality of weld at the welding part WP, based on that portion L1 of reflected
light which is detected by the sensor 6a and that portion L2 of plasmatic light which is
detected by the sensor 6b. It is noted the sensor 6a is essential to the present
embodiment which employs reflection of laser beam for detection of a porous state of
weld to be significant in porosity.</p>
    <p num="0021">The sensor 6a positioned at the first angle 1 of elevation is adapted as a P-E
converter for converting instantaneous varying intensities of respective diffracted light
L11, L12 (Fig. 3) of the detected portion L1 of reflected light of the laser beam LB3
into corresponding electrical signals E11, E12 (Figs. 2-4) with instantaneous amplitudes
proportional to the intensities of the diffracted light L11, L12, respectively. The
sensor 6b positioned at the second angle 2 of elevation is adapted as a P-E converter
for converting instantaneous varying intensities of diffracted light L21, L22 (Fig. 3) of
the detected portion L2 of emitted light from the plasmatic plume 28 into corresponding 
electrical signals E21, E22 (Figs. 2-4) with instantaneous amplitudes proportional to the
intensities of the diffracted light L21, L22, respectively.</p>
    <p num="0022">More specifically, as shown in Fig. 3, the reflected light sensor 6a is configured
with: a diffraction system DS1 (Figs. 3, 4), which has an input path D1 for inputting a
portion L1 of reflected light available for detection, a diffracter D10 for diffracting the
input light L1 into diffracted light L11, L12 (as flux of finally diffracted components of
the input light L1), and first and second output paths D11, D12 for conducting the
diffracted light L11, L12; and first and second photo-diodes 8a, 9a installed in the
output paths D11, D12 for detecting the intensities of diffracted light L11, L12,
respectively. Likewise, the plasmatic light sensor 6b is configured with: a diffraction
system DS2 (Figs. 3, 4), which has an input path D2 for inputting a portion L2 of
plasmatic light available for detection, a diffracter D20 for diffracting the input light L2
into diffracted light L21, L22 (as flux of finally diffracted components of the input light
L2), and first and second output paths D21, D22 for conducting the diffracted light L21,
L22; and first and second photo-diodes 8b, 9b installed in the output paths D21, D22 for
detecting the intensities of diffracted light L21, L22, respectively.</p>
    <p num="0023">The diffracter D10 (or D20 vice versa) has a dichroic mirror 10 installed at a
branching point between the input and output paths D1 (D2) and D11, D12 (D21, D22).
This mirror 10 serves: for transmitting, toward the first output path D11 (D21), flux of
such components of input light L1 (L2) that have longer wavelengths than a specified
wavelength (500 nm in this exampple), as initially diffracted light L10 (L20); and for
reflecting, toward the second output path D12 (D22), flux of such visible components of
the input light L1 (L2) that have wavelengths not exceeding the specified wavelength
(500 nm), as the diffracted light L12 (L22) to be input to the second photo-diode 9a (9b),
where its intensity is converted into the electrical signal E12 (E22) to be output to a
corresponding measuring circuit 71a (72a). Further, the diffractor D10 (D20) has, at
the end of its optical path D13 (D23) connected to the first output path D11 (D21), an
interference filter 11 for transmitting, toward this output path D11 (D21), mere flux of
such components of the initially diffracted light L10 (L20) that have wavelengths within
a specified range (1064± 10 nm corresponding to YAG laser of 1.06 µm, in this
example), as the diffracted light L11 (L21) to be input to the first photo-diode 8a (8b),
where its intensity is converted into the electrical signal E11 (E21) to be output to a
corresponding measuring circuit 71b (72b).</p>
    <p num="0024">In other words, at the sensor 6a (or 6b vice versa), first, light L1 (L2) striking
thereto (at the left end in Fig. 3) from the welding part WP is separated by the dichroic
mirror 10 in a wavelength selecting manner, so that, on the one hand, flux of visible 
rays of light L12 (L22) having wavelengths not exceeding 500 nm are reflected by the
mirror 10 and conducted (as a set of plasmatic components of light) to the photo-diode
9a (9b), where its varying intensity is converted into the electrical signal E12 (E22).
On the other hand, of the striking light L1 (L2) from the welding part WP, flux of
infrared rays of light L10 (L20) having passed the dichroic mirror 10 further strikes the
interference filter 11, where flux of mere such components of light that reside within the
above-noted wavelength range corresponding to light of YAG laser having a 1.06
µm wavelength is transmitted to be conducted to the photo-diode 8a (8b), where its
varying intensity is converted into the electrical signal E11 (E21) to be output to the
measuring circuit 71a (72a). It is noted that the photo-diode 8a and the measuring
circuit 71a cooperatively constitute a first signal processing line PL1a (Fig. 4) in the
measuring system MS, which line Plla is employed for detection of an occurrence of
significant porosity in the weld to be monitored by use of reflection of the laser beam
LB3 in this embodiment.</p>
    <p num="0025">More specifically, in the weld quality monitoring system QMS, the measuring
system MS has two diffraction systems DS1 and DS2, four photo-diodes 8a, 9a and 8b,
9b, and four measuring circuits 71a, 71b and 72a, 72b. As described, the first signal
processing line PL1a is constituted as a combination of the photo-diode 8a connected to
the diffraction system DS1 and the measuring circuit 71a. Likewise, a combination of
the photo-diode 9a connected to the diffraction system DS1 and the measuring circuit
71b constitutes a second signal processing line PL1b; a combination of the photo-diode
8b connected to the diffraction system DS2 and the measuring circuit 72a constitutes a
third signal processing line PL2a; and a combination of the photo-diode 9b connected to
the diffraction system DS2 and the measuring circuit 72b constitutes a fourth signal
processing line PL2b.</p>
    <p num="0026">As shown for the first signal processing line PL1a in Fig. 4, the measuring
circuit 71a (or 71b; or 72a or 72b, vice versa) is configured with: a pre-stage amplifier
7a for amplifying the electrical signal E11 (E12; E21, E22) from the photo-diode 8a
(8b; 9a, 9b) into an electrical analog signal Ea having a necessary level for subsequent
processing; and a pair of signal processing circuits 73, 74 of which one 73 is formed by
an A/D (analog-to-digital) converter 7b for converting the analog signal Ea output from
the amplifier 7a into a corresponding digital signal Eb, and the other 74 is formed as a
combination of a band-pass filter 7c for passing a set of such signal components of the
analog signal Ea that reside within a specified frequency band, as a band-pass-filtered
analog signal Ec, and an A/D converter 7d for converting the analog signal Ec into a
corresponding digital signal Ed. In the measuring circuit 71a (71b; 72a, 72b, Fig. 4), 
designated by reference characters OP1 and OP2 are operational amplifiers, R1 to R6
are resistors, and C1 is a capacitor.</p>
    <p num="0027">The quality monitor QM is configured with a PC (personal computer) 7e
connected to the signal processing circuits 73, 74 of each signal processing line PL, a
touch-panel type display 7f connected to the PC, and an internal or external memory 7g
provided for the PC. The PC 7e is adapted, by programs to be read therein from the
memory 7g, for necessary functions to execute various processes described herein,
including those for calculating a frequency distribution of harmonic components of
input signal (Eb), calculating a value of signal power in a specified frequency band of
input signal (Eb or Ed), and making a decision on a quality of weld at the welding part
(WP), with a porous state of the weld inclusive. The display 7f indicates various
image frames sent from the PC, including that of a resultant decision on the weld
quality. The memory 7g includes ROM (read only memory) and RAM (random
access memory) for storing various programs and data, as necessary for the monitoring
described herein.</p>
    <p num="0028">Fig. 5 describes why the quality of lap weld 24 at a welding part WP of work 5
is predictable by analysis of light L1, L2 from the welding part WP. Fig. 6 illustrates a
porous state of re-solidified lap weld 24 of the work 5, and Fig. 7 illustrates an under-filled
state of re-solidified lap weld 24 of the work 5. It is noted that Fig. 5 is a section
along a welding direction WD of work 5, and Figs. 6 and 7 are perspective sectional
views. In this embodiment, the work 5 is supposed as a lapped combination of two
vehicle body panel members 5a, 5b, that is, a pair of steel sheets 22, 22 each
respectively formed with Zn (zinc) layers 21, 21 plated on both sides thereof.</p>
    <p num="0029">In Fig. 5, as a converged high-power density laser beam LB3 from the YAG
laser welder 100 is radiated on a welding part WP of a lapped portion 20 of the work 5,
the irradiated welding part WP is caused to melt, by energy transmitted thereto from the
laser beam LB3, so that, at a leading or front end 24a of a bead section of re-solidified
lap weld 24, a melt region 26 has a (substantially semi-spherical, parabolic, or
columnar) keyhole 25 formed therethrough by a plume 28 of high-pressure high-temperature
metal (Fe) plasma developed therethrough. The Zn layers 21 plated on
the steel sheet 22 as a base material have a far lower melting point than the steel sheet
22, and are vaporized when the steel sheets 22 melt, so that vaporized Zn (confined
under pressure) between the lapped sheets 22 may burst forth, in the form of Zn vapor
jets 27, through a (substantially quadrisect-spheroidal, half-paraboloidal, or half-tubular)
melting front periphery 26f of the melt region 26, into the plume 28 and a
(substantially quadrisect-spheroidal, half-paraboloidal, or half-tubular) solidification-starting 
rear periphery 26r of the melt region 26, causing the melt region 26 to vibrate.
As a result, the lap weld 24 may have a porous state 23 with non-conforming traces of
Zn vapor jets 27 left in the rear periphery 26r, such as significant pores (blowholes),
when this periphery 26 is re-solidified, as illustrated in Fig. 6.</p>
    <p num="0030">It is noted that, as will be discussed later with reference to Fig. 26, the melt
region 26 exposed to the plume 28 is forced to vibrate, depending on variations of
plasma pressure, as well as on how and when Zn vapor bursts. It also is noted that, as
the welding part WP advances in the welding direction WD, the (melting) front
periphery 26f of a current melt region 26 constitutes the (solidification-starting) rear
periphery 26r of a subsequent melt region 26 and, as used herein, "re-solidification of a
melt region 26" (to be observed within a significant time period) actually means or
includes "solidification at a boundary of a rear periphery 26r of the melt region 26" (to
be observed within a shorter time period).</p>
    <p num="0031">The beam LB3 of YAG laser has a wavelength about 1.06 µm, which is short
so that YAG laser rays are substantially transmitted through the plume 28 (i.e. with little
reflection on or in the plume 28 which is transparent to the laser rays), thus striking on
an inside 26g of the front periphery 26f of vibrating melt region 26, where they are
partially absorbed, thereby supplying thermal energy to the vicinity of an outside 26h of
the front periphery 26f as a melting frontier of the bead section 24, and the rest of laser
beam (as well as part of radiation of the plume 28) is reflected at the inside 26g of the
front periphery 26f. As the inside 26g is vibrated in a complicated manner, the flux of
light reflected therefrom also has a varying density. This density can be detected as a
varying intensity of light observed at a fixed angle, which intensity can be processed by
way of a spectral analysis to obtain significant data on a current state of the melt region
26, that is substantially associated with a state of re-solidified weld to be predicted for
use in decision on a quality of the weld.</p>
    <p num="0032">As the weld quality now in concern is a porosity of a bead section of the weld
24 (Fig. 6), the data to be obtained will be most significant, when the varying intensity
of light is observed at an observation angle that looks the mid of keyhole 25, or more
preferably, at such an observation angle that looks a wall part 26i at the inside 26g of
the front periphery 26f of melt region 26 corresponding in vertical position to the plated
Zn layer 21 between the steel sheets 22 of work 5. Accordingly, the first sensor 6a
employed for use in decision on a porous state of weld 24 is set at a higher or greater
angle of elevation (1) than the elevation angle (2) of the second sensor 6b. The
elevation (1) of the first sensor 6a may preferably be set within an angle range of 45
degrees to 70 degrees, where reflection representing variations in motion of the front 
periphery 26f of melt region 26 can be caught without interference with radiation of the
laser beam LB3 focused on the welding part WP. More preferably, it (1) may be
optimally set at an angle about 60 degrees, with considerations taken of associated
welding conditions such as sheet thickness, inter-sheet gap, laser beam's power and
focal point. It is noted that the second sensor 6b, which is set lower in elevation than
the first sensor 6a, looks a top 26j of the melt region 26 and an upper part 28a of the
transparent plume 28 developed thereabove, and that this sensor 6b is unable to catch
such vibrations of melt that are so fast and unique (to the melt part 26i) as to be
responsible for the decision of a significant porous state 23 to occur or not when re-solidified.</p>
    <p num="0033">Fig. 7 shows an under-filled state 31 of weld 24, in which the pair of panel
members 5a, 5b of Zn-plated steel sheet work 5 have therebetween a lap-welded portion
20 with a greater inter-sheet distance or gap 30 (looser contact) than required for
conformity, where part (26k) of the melt region (26 under the condition of Fig. 5) was
filled, causing a surface (26m) of the melt region (26) to be over-recessed, after which
the melt region (26) has been re-solidified, providing the weld 24. Such an under-filled
state 31 of weld 24 is preferably predictable by spectral analysis of light detected
at the second sensor 6b.</p>
    <p num="0034">Fig. 8 is a flowchart of processes (in the computer 7e) for monitoring a quality
of lap-weld (to be free of significant porous or under-filled state) in accordance with an
embodiment of the invention. Fig. 9 to Fig. 12 illustrate data obtained for spectral
analyses of light detected by the first and second sensors 6a, 6b under the following
reference welding conditions: YAG laser output, 3 kw at the welding part WP; panel
members 5a, 5b, Zn-plated steel sheets 0.8 mm thick each; and welding speed, 4.5
m/min.</p>
    <p num="0035">As the YAG laser beam LB3 is irradiated to a frontier of the welding part WP
in the lapped portion 20 of the panel members 5a, 5b as Zn-plated steel sheets, the
frontier of the welding part WP is melt with thermal energy of the laser beam LB3, so
that the welding part WP has a melt region 26 with a keyhole 25, which (25) is formed
by a plume 28 developed therethrough and defined by the combination of a front
periphery 26f as a melting part of the melt region 26 and a rear periphery 26r as a part
of the melt region 26 to be re-solidified. The plume 28 and wall of the keyhole 25 (as
a combination of the front periphery 26f and a front part of the rear periphery 25r) are
very hot, and radiate visible rays of light and infrared rays, which are detected by the
first and second sensors 6a and 6b (Fig. 1) of the weld quality monitoring system QMS,
together with such rays of laser beam LB3 that are reflected from the wall of keyhole 25. </p>
    <p num="0036">In the monitoring system QMS, those rays of light detected by the first and
second sensors 6a and 6b, i.e., optical signals L1 (at the sensor 6a) and L2 (at the sensor
6b) enter the diffraction systems DS1 and DS2 (Fig. 3) in the sensors 6a and 6b, where
they are diffracted into four optical analog detection signals L11 (YAG laser light
1.06µm, in L1), L12 (visible light under 500 nm, in L1) and L21 (YAG laser light
1.06µm, in L2), L22 (visible light under 500 nm, in L2), which are processed by the
signal processing lines PL (PL1a, PL1b and PL2a, PL2b) (Fig. 4) to provide four sets of
electrical digital detection signals Eb, Ed to be processed in the computer 7e of the
quality monitor QM for monitoring qualities of re-solidified weld 24 (Fig. 6, Fig. 7) at
the current welding part WP (Fig. 5) by way of prediction. In the signal processing
lines PL (Fig. 4), the optical detection signals L11, L12 and L21, L22 strike on the
photo-diodes 8a, 9a and 8b, 9b of the sensors 6a and 6b, respectively, where they are
converted into four electrical analog detection signals E11, E12 and E21, E22 (Fig. 3),
which are input to the measuring circuits MC (71a, 71b and 72a, 72b) (Fig. 2), where
they are amplified by corresponding amplifiers 7a (Fig. 4), then amplified detection
signals Ea are processed, on the one hand, by four processing circuits 73 respectively
including A/D converters 7b to provide a group of four digital detection signals Eb
(whole spectral components), and on the other hand, by four processing circuits 74
respectively including band-pass filters 7c and A/D converters 7d to provide another
group of four digital detection signals Ed (exclusive spectral components).</p>
    <p num="0037">At a step S1 (Fig. 8), four sets of thus obtained signals Eb, Ed are sampled in
order by the computer 7e, and stored in the memory 7g, as four sets of digital data on
respective waveforms of analog detection signals L11, L12 and L21, L22 (or E11, E12
and E21, E22), which represent varying intensities (as densities of flux) of such
diffracted components of detected light L1 and L2 that reside in wavelength bands (&lt;
500 nm; ≈ 1.06µm) defined by combination of dichroic mirror 10 and interference
filter 11 (Fig. 3). It is noted that, among a total of eight types of digital signals Eb (for
L11, L12 and L21, L22) and Ed (for L11, L12 and L21, L22), selected one (for example,
Ed for L11) or more may preferably have a priority (or priorities) to be sampled, as
necessary for monitoring a concerned quality (for example, absence of significant
porosity) or in consideration of an available memory capacity.</p>
    <p num="0038">Fig. 9 is a set of waveform graphs (by .txtPpk or .txtPp) of stored data (item
nos. 40962B and 40962) on intensities of filtered infrared rays of light from the welding
part WP, i.e., on electrical detection signals (Eb for L11 and L21) obtained from
reflection substantially of YAG laser beam LB3 (at the wall part 26i in keyhole 25 and
the top 26j of melt region 26, and though a little, radiation from the plume 28 and melt 
region 26) under the above-noted reference welding conditions (for beads of article), as
the data are sampled in the computer 7e at a sampling frequency of 20 kHz. In the
waveform graphs, the ordinate and abscissa represent a signal intensity (amplitude) and
a lapse time, respectively, and reference characters YH and YL denote data on temporal
variations of infrared reflection intensities caught by the first sensor 6a high of
observation angle and the second sensor 6b low of observation angle, respectively. In
Fig. 9, shown by graphs at the left are data of a bead section (LH6810) with a
conforming quality of weld (OK WAVEFORM), central ones are data of a bead section
(LH#15) with a significant porous state (B8 BLOW NG), and right ones are data of a
bead section (RH#15) with an under-filled state (B5Under). In the case of under-filled
bead section, its YH and YL waveforms are apparently different from those of
conforming bead section, so that the decision for an under-filled state can be easily
made. However, in the case of porous bead section, of which YH and YL waveforms
appear little different from those of conforming bead section, it is difficult for a simple
comparison of the former with the latter to give an ensured decision for the former to be
porous.</p>
    <p num="0039">Fig. 10 is a set of waveform graphs (by .txtPpk or .txtPp) of stored data (item
nos. 4096B and 4096) on intensities of visible rays of light from the welding part WP,
i.e., on electrical detection signals (Eb for L12 and L22) obtained from radiation
substantially from the plume 28 and melt region 26 (and though a little, reflection at the
wall part 26i in keyhole 25 and the top 26j of melt region 26) under the above-noted
reference welding conditions (for the beads of article), as the data are sampled in the
computer 7e at a sampling frequency of 20 kHz. In these waveform graphs, the
ordinate and abscissa represent a signal intensity (amplitude) and a lapse time,
respectively, as described, but reference characters PH and PL denote data on temporal
variations of visible radiation intensities caught by the first sensor 6a high of
observation angle and the second sensor 6b low of observation angle, respectively. In
Fig. 9, shown by graphs at the left are data of the bead section (LH6810) with a
conforming quality of weld (OK WAVEFORM), central ones are data of the bead
section (LH#15) with a significant porous state (B8 BLOW NG), and right ones are data
of the bead section (RH#15) with an under-filled state (B5Under). In the case of
under-filled bead section, its PH and PL waveforms are apparently different from those
of conforming bead section, so that the decision for an under-filled state can be easily
made. However, in the case of porous bead section, of which PH and PL waveforms
appear little different from those of conforming bead section, it is difficult for a simple
comparison of the former with the latter to give an ensured decision for the former to be 
porous.</p>
    <p num="0040">Like this, it is difficult for a simple examination of temporal intensity
variations of reflected light and visible light detected by the sensors 6a and 6b to
conclude a distinction between conforming bead section and porous bead section.
Therefore, at a step S2 of the flowchart of Fig. 8, among waveform data stored in the
memory 7g, data on YH waveforms (Eb for L11 of 40962B and 40962) as temporal
variations of infrared reflection caught by the first sensor 6a high of observation angle
are read in the computer 7e, where they are processed by a programmed operator for
calculating an FFT (high-speed Fourrier transform) of their signal intensities to provide
frequency characteristics of the YH waveforms, each as a spectral distribution of signal
power over a specified frequency range (0 to 2000 x 50 Hz).</p>
    <p num="0041">Fig. 11 shows a set of power distribution waveform graphs of thus obtained
data (FFT of YH). In the waveform graphs, the ordinate and abscissa represent a level
of relative signal power and a frequency, respectively. The relative signal power
(sometimes simply called "signal power", as used herein) is a dimensionless index
indicating how much the integration of power of signal components amounts within an
associated quantization slot of frequency. As will be apparent from comparison
between left and central graphs of Fig. 11, the FFT operation of signal intensity
provides a distribution of relative signal power which has a significant difference even
between conforming bead section (LH6810) and porous bead section (LH#15). More
specifically, the power distribution of conforming bead section has significant peaks of
relative signal power within a frequency range of 100 Hz to 500 Hz, while that of
porous bead section has significant peaks of relative signal power within a frequency
range of 0 Hz to 1000 Hz. In this embodiment, such a difference of power distribution
is evaluated for the weld quality monitoring to be ensured, in the following manner.</p>
    <p num="0042">At a step S3 of the flowchart of Fig. 8, there is calculated, for a respective bead
section of weld in concern, a sum of signal power of components within a range
between 605 Hz and 650 Hz by using waveform data after the FFT transform of signal
intensities. Then, at a step S4, a decision is made of whether or not the above-noted
sum exceeds a reference value 170,000. If the sum exceeds the reference value (YES),
the control flow goes to a step S5, where a decision is made for the porosity to be
excessive (in the sense of significance). Unless it exceeds the reference value (NO),
the control flow goes to a step S6, where a decision is made for the porosity to be within
a normal range. The result of such a decision is indicated on the display 7f.</p>
    <p num="0043">It is noted that, for calculation of the relative signal power as a dimensionless
index (x<sub>ijk</sub>) for an i-th one of I frequency bands, for a j-th one of J bead sections of weld, 
and for a k-th one of K observed articles, where "I", "J", and "K" are specified integers,
and "i", "j", and "k" are arbitrary integers not exceeding I, J, and K, respectively, the
FFT operator has once determined or is given a combination of data on a standard
average vector {m<sub>jk</sub>; k=0}, a standard deviation vector {σ<sub>jk</sub>; k=0}, and a standard data
vector {x<sub>ijk</sub>; k = 0} as a set of I normalized indices x<sub>ij0</sub> of signal power, for a respective
one of J conforming bead sections of weld of a reference article (article no. k = 0), so
that the index (x<sub>ijk</sub>) can be determined as a normalized dimensionless value, such that
x<sub>ijk</sub> = (y<sub>ijk</sub> - m<sub>j0</sub>)/σ<sub>j0</sub>, where y<sub>ijk</sub> is a level of absolute signal power at an i-th frequency
band of a waveform of a j-th bead section of a k-th observed article. Further, for the j-th
bead section of the k-th observed article, a set {x<sub>ijk</sub>} of associated dimensionless
indices x<sub>ijk</sub> is processed together with a corresponding set {x<sub>ij0</sub>} of standard data x<sub>ij0</sub> to
determine an (m x m) correlation matrix R(r<sub>mm</sub>) therebetween and an (m x m) inverse
matrix A(a<sub>mm</sub>) of the correlation matrix R(r<sub>mm</sub>), where "m" is an integer equivalent to I.
The reference bead section may preferably be a conforming one of observed bead
sections, so that data of this bead section can be conveniently re-used.</p>
    <p num="0044">Next, at a step S7, on the basis of dimensionless index set {x<sub>ijk</sub>} and inverse
matrix A(a<sub>mn</sub>) for j-th bead section of k-th observed article, there is calculated a
corresponding value of a standardized dispersion in terms of a Maharanobis distance
D<sub>jk</sub>, such that D<sub>jk</sub><sup>2</sup> = [{x<sub>ijk</sub>}][A(a<sub>mn</sub>)][{x<sub>ijk</sub>}]<sup>t</sup> (e.g. for a j of k corresponding to any of
item nos. 40962B and 40962) by processing a corresponding set of resultant data of the
FFT operation, that is, a data set of characteristic quantities as levels of relative signal
power of a spectral waveform in Fig. 11. The Maharanobis distance in terms of D<sub>kj</sub> or
D<sub>kj</sub><sup>2</sup> is an algebraic distance representing how far a set of characteristic quantity of the
FFT signal power waveform at a current welding part of a bead section under
observation (e.g. 40962) is spaced from that of the reference bead section, in a vector
filed normalized relative to the set of characteristic quantities of signal power waveform
of the reference bead section. Fig. 12 is a graph of which ordinate and abscissa
represent the sum of FFT signal power and the Marharanobis distance in logarithmic
representation, and on which four typical sets of Maharanobis distances (at
corresponding welding parts of porous, fine porous, conforming, and under-filled bead
sections) are mapped to show their distributions that depend on respective sets of
characteristic quantities of associated signal power waveforms.</p>
    <p num="0045">At a step S8 of the flowchart of Fig. 8, there is made a decision based on such a
distribution of Maharanobis distances, as to whether or not the bead section under
observation has at the current welding part a Maharanobis distance exceeding a
threshold or reference value 1000. If the Maharanobis distance is in excess (YES), the 
control flow goes to a step S9, where a decision is made for an under-filled state to
occur. Unless it is so, the flow goes to a step S10, where a decision is made for no
under-filled state to occur.</p>
    <p num="0046">In the embodiment described, as to whether or not the porosity is excessive,
there is made a decision in dependence on the sum of signal power within a particular
frequency range. It however is noted that, as will be seen from the distribution in Fig.
12, Maharanobis distances of porous bead section reside within a region defined by
combination of a range of Maharanobis distance under 2 and a range of signal power
sum over 170000, the decision as to whether or not the porosity is excessive may
preferably be made, on basis of a set of characteristic quantities of a signal power
waveform of Fig. 11 resulted from the FFT operation of signal intensities, by
calculating an associated Maharanobis distance and signal power sum within a
particular frequency band to know which region this combination of distance and sum
belongs to, like the case of a decision to be made for an under-filled state to occur.</p>
    <p num="0047">Moreover, this embodiment is described of the case of welding conditions on
sheet thickness to be 0.8 mm and welding speed to be 4.5 m/min. It will be understood
that a weld quality monitoring method or system according to this invention is
applicable also to welding speed and/or sheet thickness else than described. In the
case of welding conditions different from above in welding speed and/or sheet thickness,
the particular frequency band associated with the decision for a porous state to occur
may preferably be varied. This is because, along with variation of welding speed
and/or sheet thickness, the particular frequency band to be effective for decision of
porous state varies. In order for the decision of porous state to have a maintained
accuracy, an optimal frequency band therefor is selected, as it varies in dependence on
welding speed and/or sheet thickness.</p>
    <p num="0048">In order to keep the decision of porous state always accurate, it was examined
how the particular frequency band should be changed in consideration of varied welding
speed and/or sheet thickness, in an experimental manner, as follows: As work, two
Zn-plated steel sheets 0.8 mm and 1.0 mm thick were lapped to be welded. Welding
speed was varied between 3.0 m/min to 5.0 m/min. YAG laser power was set to 3 kW
at the welding part.</p>
    <p num="0049">Description is now made of a case in which the sheet thickness was changed.
In this experiment, welding speed was set to 3.5 m/min, while the two sheets had a sum
of thickness thereof (as a nominal, i.e., assuming no inter-sheet gap) changed between
1.6 mm to 2.4 mm. In case of a sheet thickness sum of 2.4 mm, for example, an
occurrence of porous state accompanied a tendency for the signal power to rise within a 
frequency band of 0 Hz to 50 Hz. As the sheet thickness sum decreased, the signal
power tended to rise within an enlarged frequency band. Fig. 13 shows a result of this
experiment.</p>
    <p num="0050">As shown in Fig. 13, the signal power rose high in a frequency band of 0 Hz to
1000 Hz for a sheet thickness sum of 1.6 mm, a frequency band of 0 Hz to 800 Hz for a
sheet thickness sum of 1.8 mm, a frequency band of 0 Hz to 700 Hz for a sheet
thickness sum of 2.0 mm, and a frequency band of 0 Hz to 500 Hz for a sheet thickness
sum of 2.4 mm. Accordingly, for a decision of porous state, depending on what mm
the sheet thickness sum is, it is determined which frequency band to be selected. It is
noted that the quality monitor QM of measuring system MS (Fig. 4) has stored in the
memory 7g such a relationship between sheet thickness sum and frequency as shown in
Fig. 13.</p>
    <p num="0051">Description is now made of a case in which the welding speed was changed.
In this experiment, the change of welding speed was between 3.5 m/min to 5.0 m/min
for a sheet thickness sum of 1.6 mm, and between 3.0 m/min to 4.0 m/min for a sheet
thickness sum of 2.0 mm. For either sheet thickness sum, as the welding speed
increased, the signal power tended to rise within a narrower frequency band. Fig. 14
shows a result of this experiment.</p>
    <p num="0052">As shown in Fig. 14, for the sheet thickness sum 1. 6 mm, the signal power
rose high in a frequency band of 0 Hz to 1000 Hz at a welding speed of 3.5 m/min, a
frequency band of 0 Hz to 800 Hz at a welding speed of 4.0 m/min, a frequency band of
0 Hz to 700 Hz at a welding speed of 4.5 m/min, and a frequency band of 0 Hz to 600
Hz at a welding speed of 5.0 m/min.</p>
    <p num="0053">For the sheet thickness sum 2.0 mm, the signal power rose high in a frequency
band of 0 Hz to 800 Hz at a welding speed of 3.0 m/min, a frequency band of 0 Hz to
700 Hz at a welding speed of 3.5 m/min, and a frequency band of 0 Hz to 600 Hz at a
welding speed of 4.0 m/min.</p>
    <p num="0054">Accordingly, for a decision of porous state, depending on what m/min the
welding speed is, it is determined which frequency band to be selected. It is noted that
the quality monitor QM of measuring system MS (Fig. 4) has stored in the memory 7g
such a relationship between sheet thickness sum and frequency as shown in Fig. 13, and
such a relationship between welding speed and frequency as shown in Fig. 14 for
various sheet thickness sums, as a set of data listed in the form of a Table-1 shown in
Fig. 15. The Table-1 has various welding speeds listed in a matrix of addresses
defined by combination of a row of different thickness t1 (Fig. 16) of upper sheet 5a and
a column of different thickness t2 (Fig. 16) of lower sheet 5b, each for access to a stored 
frequency to be effective for a decision of porous state. For example, an address of
welding speed 3.5 m/min defined by combination of an upper sheet thickness t1 of 1.2
mm and a lower sheet thickness t2 of 0.8 mm leads to a frequency band of 0 Hz to 800
Hz to be effective for use at the welding speed 3.5 m/min for a sheet thickness sum of
2.0 mm, as shown in Fig. 14. Likewise, an address of welding speed 5.0 m/min
defined by combination of an upper sheet thickness t1 of 0.8 mm and a lower sheet
thickness t2 of 0.8 mm leads to a frequency band of 0 Hz to 600 Hz to be effective for
use at the welding speed 5.0 m/min for a sheet thickness sum of 1.6 mm, as shown in
Fig. 14.</p>
    <p num="0055">Like this, the frequency to be effective for a decision of porous state varies in
dependence on variations of nominal sheet thickness and welding speed, which may
well be associated with a difference in configuration of the melt region 26 or keyhole 25
(Fig. 5) in analysis of weld quality.</p>
    <p num="0056">Fig. 16 describes this mechanism. Upon irradiation of YAG laser beam,
lapped sheets 5a, 5b have a melt region 26 with keyhole, of which the configuration
varies in dependence on an apparent sheet thickness sum and welding speed, so that it
has a greater depth H (i.e. elongated or increased in an aspect ratio H/D relative to its
width D), as the sheet thickness sum increases, or has a smaller width D (i.e. elongated
either, but decreased in the aspect ratio H/D), as the welding speed increases. It is
noted that the apparent sheet thickness sum equals to a sum of t1 + t2 + g (an inter-sheet
gap), i.e., the nominal sheet thickness sum (t1 + t2) + the inter-sheet gap (g). In
calculation of the aspect ratio H/D, the depth H equals to the apparent sum. However,
for designation of address in Table-1, the nominal sum is used, as the stored data is for a
typical welding, where the inter-sheet gap is properly set.</p>
    <p num="0057">As described with reference to Fig. 13 and Fig. 14, the frequency to be
effective for a decision of porous state is lowered, either when the sheet thickness (sum)
increases or when the welding speed increases. This is partly because of an increased
aspect ratio H/D due either to an increased sheet thickness (sum) or an increased
welding speed, accompanying a melt region with keyhole to be elongate with a lowered
resonance frequency, thus resulting in a reduced frequency band where the signal power
tends to rise.</p>
    <p num="0058">It may thus be preferable to recognize, by use of a CCD camera or the like, a
melt region with keyhole as a configuration model to be based on for determination of
aspect ratio H/D, to thereby determine an effective frequency for a decision of porous
state.</p>
    <heading>(Second Embodiment)</heading>
    <p num="0059">There will be described below a weld quality monitoring method and system
according to an embodiment of the invention, which allows an ensured decision on a
quality of weld that may be under-filled or non-welded, and is different from the first
embodiment in which a decision is made for a porous state to occur.</p>
    <p num="0060">The weld quality monitoring system and an associated welding system in the
second embodiment are identical to those (QMS and WS in Figs. 1 to 4) of the first
embodiment, providing that a personal computer 7e is adapted, by programs to be read
therein from a memory 7g, for necessary functions to execute various processes
described herein, including: in addition to functions in the first embodiment, a function
for calculating a value of signal power in a respective one of three frequency bands, that
is, a first frequency band for detecting an under-filled state, a second frequency band for
detecting a porous state, and a third frequency band for detecting a non-welded state; a
function for making a decision for a respective one of a conforming state, an under-filled
state, a porous state, and a non-welded state to occur; and a function for dividing
(a region covering) a set of data on time-dependant variations of electrical detection
signals stored for a respective welding part, into a plurality of (sub-regions covering)
subsets thereof in the form of a temporal sequence.</p>
    <p num="0061">There will be described below various functions of the quality monitoring
system QMS according to the present embodiment of the invention, with reference to
Fig. 1 to Fig. 7 and Fig. 17 to Fig. 25. Fig. 18 is a flowchart of processes (in the
computer 7e) for monitoring a quality of lap-weld to be free of significant under-filled,
porous, or non-welded state. Fig. 19 to Fig. 21 illustrate data obtained for spectral
analyses of light detected by first and second sensors 6a, 6b under the following
reference welding conditions: YAG laser output, 3 kw at a welding part WP; panel
members 5a, 5b, Zn-plated steel sheets 0.8 mm thick each; and welding speed, 4.5
m/min.</p>
    <p num="0062">It is noted that the present embodiment is adapted also for detection of a non-welded
state, which is a non-conforming state of weld unable to provide a required weld
strength. Fig. 17 shows a typical non-welded state between a pair of upper and lower
panel members (i.e. Zn-plated steel sheets) 5a, 5b lapped to be welded. The non-welded
state is caused by an excessive inter-sheet gap 40, which obstructs sufficient
heat transmission to the lower member 5b, resulting in an insufficient melting at the
welding part.</p>
    <p num="0063">As described with reference to Fig. 5, as a YAG laser beam LB3 is irradiated to
a welding part WP in a lapped portion 20 of panel members 5a, 5b, the welding part WP
has a melt region 26 with a keyhole 25 formed by a plume 28 developed therethrough. 
The plume 28 and wall of the keyhole 25 are very hot, and radiate visible rays of light
and infrared rays, which are detected by the first and second sensors 6a and 6b, together
with such rays of laser beam LB3 that are reflected from the wall of keyhole 25.
Detected rays of light are converted into four electrical analog detection signals E11,
E12 and E21, E22 (Fig. 3), which are processed in measuring circuits MC (71a, 71b and
72a, 72b) (Fig. 2), to provide a group of four digital detection signals Eb (whole spectral
components), and another group of four digital detection signals Ed (exclusive spectral
components). At a step S21 of the flowchart of Fig. 18, four sets of thus obtained
signals Eb, Ed are sampled in order by the computer 7e, and stored in the memory 7g.</p>
    <p num="0064">Fig. 19 and Fig. 20 are waveform graphs of stored data on intensities of filtered
infrared rays of light from the welding part WP, i.e., on electrical detection signals (Eb
for L11 and L21) obtained from reflection substantially of YAG laser beam under the
above-noted reference welding conditions. The data are sampled in the computer 7e at
a sampling frequency of 20 kHz. In the waveform graphs, the ordinate and abscissa
represent a signal intensity (amplitude in voltage) and a lapse time, respectively.
There are shown time-dependant variations of infrared reflection intensities caught by
the first sensor 6a high of observation angle. In Fig. 19, upper and lower graphs show
waveforms of signal intensity for a "conforming bead section" that has a conforming
quality of weld and a "non-welded bead section" that has an incomplete weld,
respectively. In Fig. 20, upper and lower graphs show waveforms of signal intensity
for an "under-filled bead section" that has an under-filled weld and a "porous bead
section" that is significant in porosity of weld, respectively. As is apparent from
comparison of those graphs, the under-filled bead section is different in waveform from
any other bead section, so that the decision for an under-filled state can be easily made.
However, the non-welded and porous bead sections appear little different in waveform
from the conforming bead section, so that it is difficult to see through weld qualities of
the former bead sections by observation of their waveforms.</p>
    <p num="0065">Like this, it is difficult for a simple examination of temporal intensity
variations of reflected light to conclude a distinction between conforming bead section
and non-welded bead section, as well as between conforming bead section and porous
bead section. Therefore, at a step S22 of the flowchart of Fig. 18, among waveform
data stored in the memory 7g, data on waveforms representing temporal variations of
such infrared rays of light that are reflected at a current welding part and caught by the
first sensor 6a high of observation angle are read in the computer 7e, where they are
processed by a programmed operator for calculating an FFT of their signal intensities.</p>
    <p num="0066">Fig. 21 shows a set of power distribution waveform graphs of data obtained by 
applying the FFT operator to the waveforms shown in Fig. 19 and Fig. 20. In the
waveform graphs, the ordinate and abscissa represent a level of relative signal power
and a frequency, respectively. The relative signal power is given as a dimensionless
quantity (area) representing how many signal components of associated frequency are
contained.</p>
    <p num="0067">As will be apparent from Fig. 21, the FFT operation of signal intensity
provides a distribution of relative signal power which has a significant difference
among conforming bead section, non-welded bead section, under-filled bead section,
and porous bead section. In this embodiment, such a difference of power distribution
is evaluated for the weld quality monitoring to be ensured, in the following manner.</p>
    <p num="0068">In waveform graphs of Fig. 21 obtained by FFT operation of signal intensities,
there is set for detection of under-filled state a first frequency band ranging 0 to 1000
Hz, and, likewise, for detection of porous state a second frequency band ranging 0 to
1000 Hz. The setting of such frequency bands is based on experimental results that
show occurrences of under-filled state and porous state can be clearly detected in those
frequency bands. Although the first and second frequency bands are set to be identical
in this embodiment, the (second) frequency band to be effective for detection of a
porous state needs to be changed in dependence on sheet thickness (sum) and welding
speed, as described in the first embodiment. For a certain sheet thickness or welding
speed, therefore, the second frequency band for detection of porous state may preferably
be changed, for example, to a range of 0 - 600 Hz.</p>
    <p num="0069">In addition, for detection of a non-welded state, there is set a third frequency
band ranging 3000 Hz to 6000 Hz. As is apparent from Fig. 21, when non-welded
state occurs, signal power of this frequency band tends to go higher than signal power
when under-filled state or porous state occurs. The setting of this frequency band also
is based on experimental results that show occurrences of non-welded state can be
clearly detected there.</p>
    <p num="0070">Signal power sum of those frequency bands are determined and mapped on an
imaginary two-axis coordinate system, as illustrated in Fig. 22. In the imaginary
coordinate system, the ordinate and abscissa represent signal power sums in the (first
and second) frequency bands ranging 0 Hz to 1000 Hz, and a signal power sum in the
(third) frequency band ranging 3000 Hz to 6000 Hz, respectively.</p>
    <p num="0071">For example, in the case of an under-filled bead section which provides such a
waveform as shown in an upper right graph of Fig. 21, there is determined a
combination of an area defined by a waveform within the frequency band ranging 0 Hz
to 1000 Hz and an area defined by a waveform of the frequency band ranging 3000 Hz 
to 6000 Hz, and this combination is mapped on a coordinate of which the ordinate and
abscissa correspond to those areas. By such mapping, it is observed that under-filled
bead sections (triangular mark) tend to be distributed within a sub-region that is
relatively small of signal power sums of ordinate and abscissa of the two-axis
coordinate system. Likewise, porous bead sections (square mark) tend to be
distributed within a sub-region that is relatively small of signal power sum of ordinate
and relatively large of signal power sum of abscissa of the two-axis coordinate system,
and non-welded bead sections (rhombus mark) tend to be distributed within a sub-region
that is relatively large of signal power sum of ordinate and extends over an entire
section of axis of abscissa of the two-axis coordinate system. Further, it is observed
that conforming bead sections (round mark) tend to be distributed within a sub-region
that is relatively small of signal power sum of ordinate and extends over an intermediate
section of axis of abscissa of the two-axis coordinate system.</p>
    <p num="0072">An investigation was made of a multiplicity of welded bead sections to know
how under-filled bead sections, porous bead sections, non-welded bead sections, and
conforming bead sections thereof are distributed in a region of two-axis coordinate
system, with an observed result that they are distributed within such separate sub-regions
as shown in Fig. 23. It is supposed that if under-filled state, porous state,
and/or non-welded state occur in combination at a single welding part of bead, they
should be distributed in a vicinity of a boundary between associated sub-regions.
Therefore, in this embodiment, as illustrated in Fig. 24, there is provided a complex or
mixing sub-region difficult of discrimination of a type of weld quality. Accordingly,
in the imaginary region of two-axis coordinate system, there exist an under-filled sub-region,
a conforming sub-region, a porous sub-region, a non-welded sub-region, and a
mixing sub-region. It is noted that the term "sub-region" is for relative expression and
may well be read simply "region". It may depend on a result of practice how wide the
width of mixing sub-region should be set.</p>
    <p num="0073">It also is noted that the imaginary region of two-axis coordinate system is
prepared in the computer 7e, and those sub-regions are in no way given as actual two-dimensional
planes. Although, after respective FFT operations of signal intensities,
their results are mapped on the imaginary region of two-axis coordinate system, such a
mapping is not actually made on a two-dimensional plane. Signal power sums
constituting respective sub-regions have their numerical ranges, which are stored in the
memory 7g, allowing for the computer 7e to make a prompt decision as to whether a
non-conforming state occurs or whether an observed bead section is conforming,
depending on which sub-region the result of operation belongs to. </p>
    <p num="0074">Referring again to the flowchart of Fig. 18, at a step S23, on the basis of data
given, while welding, on such a waveform as shown in Fig. 21, there are calculated
signal power sums in frequency bands ranging 0 Hz to 1000 Hz and 3000 Hz to 6000
Hz, respectively. Then, at a step S24, it is decided that a combination of coordinates in
two-axis coordinate system, as it is defined by a combination of signal power sums
calculated between 0 Hz to 1000 Hz and between 3000 Hz to 6000 Hz, resides in which
sub-region shown in Fig. 24.</p>
    <p num="0075">In decision at the step S24, if the combination of coordinates belongs to a
preset conforming sub-region (YES), the control flow goes to a step S25, it is decided
that the welding at a welding part under observation has a conforming state (conforming
bead section). On the other hand, at the step S24, unless the combination of
coordinates belongs to the preset conforming sub-region (NO), the control flow goes to
a step S26, where it is decided whether or not the combination of coordinates belongs to
one of an under-filled sub-region, a porous sub-region, and a non-welded sub-region, as
they are preset.</p>
    <p num="0076">In decision at the step S26, if the combination of coordinates belongs to one of
the under-filled sub-region, the porous sub-region, and the non-welded sub-region
(YES), there should have occurred a weld state of associated sub-region, and the control
flow goes to a step S27, where it is decided that the welding part under observation has
a non-conforming weld quality. It is noted that the decision for a conforming bead
section as well as decision for any non-conforming state of weld is indicated by a
display 7f. With the foregoing process complete, an entire decision on a welding part
under observation goes to an end.</p>
    <p num="0077">On the other hand, in decision at the step S26, unless the combination of
coordinates belongs to one of the under-filled sub-region, the porous sub-region, and the
non-welded sub-region (NO), that is, if it belongs to such a mixing sub-region as shown
in Fig. 24, then it becomes necessary to divide the welding part under observation into a
plurality of sub-sections, as shown in Fig. 25, to again make a decision on each sub-section
as to whether its weld quality is conforming or not.</p>
    <p num="0078">The decision to be again made of whether the weld quality is conforming or not
is performed in the following procedure:</p>
    <p num="0079">As described, for a single welding part under observation, the electrical
detection signal E1 output from the first sensor 6a has time-dependant variations
associated therewith, of which data is stored in the memory 7g of quality monitor QM,
which is read in the computer 7e, where a field of the data representing the time-dependant
variations of the electrical detection signal E1 is divided into a plurality of 
sub-sections of the field as a temporal sequence. For example, assuming that a
welding part under observation represents a section of bead 30 mm in length, as shown
in Fig. 25, the bead section under observation is divided into five sub-sections each
having a 6 mm length, and a decision is made of a respective one of the sub-sections,
for which quality of weld to occur or if it is conforming, in a manner quite identical to
an upper part of the flowchart of Fig. 18.</p>
    <p num="0080">As this division of a data section is applied to a stored data of the electrical
signal E1, it takes a time interval of 0.4 sec to weld the 30 mm bead section by a
welding speed to be 4.5 m/sec in this embodiment, which means that the bead section
under observation is represented by a length of stored data corresponding to a fraction
of 0.4 sec of the electrical signal. As this data is divided into five sub-sections, the
fraction of 0.4 sec of electrical signal is divided into a temporal sequence of sub-fractions
of electrical signal each corresponding to a time slot of 0.08 sec. This
division provides, for the bead section under observation, a sequence of data on sub-fractions
of electrical signal appearing in a first sub-interval of time ranging 0 sec to
0.08 sec, a second sub-interval of time ranging 0.08 sec to 0.16 sec, a third sub-interval
of time ranging 0.16 sec to 0.24 sec, a fourth sub-interval of time ranging 0.24 sec to
0.32 sec, and a fifth sub-interval of time ranging 0.32 sec to 0.4 sec. Although it is
preferable to set the bead section within a length range of about 1 mm to about 8mm,
this length may well be varied, as necessary, depending a configuration of the bead
section and the accuracy of weld quality decision to be desirable.</p>
    <p num="0081">Data on sub-fractions of electrical signal corresponding to sub-intervals of time
are stored in the memory 7g. At a step S28 of the flowchart of Fig. 18, those data are
read one by one in the computer 7e, where their waveforms of signal intensities are
processed by the FFT operator. As a result, at a step S29, there are calculated a
combination of signal power sums within the frequency bands ranging 0 Hz to 1000 Hz
and 3000 Hz to 6000 Hz, respectively. Then, at a step S30, it is decided in which one
of sub-regions of two-axis coordinate system shown in Fig. 24 a coordinate
corresponding to the combination of signal power sums in the frequency bands of 0 Hz
to 1000 Hz and 3000 Hz to 6000 Hz resides. At this stage of process, such a decision
is made that, for example, as shown in Fig. 25, there appears a non-welded state in a
sub-section (the leftmost one in Fig. 25) of bead section corresponding to the first sub-interval
of time, another non-welded state in a sub-section (neighboring to the right of
the leftmost one) of bead section corresponding to the second sub-interval of time, and a
conforming state in each of the remaining sub-sections (up to the rightmost one) of bead
section corresponding to the third to fifth sub-intervals of time. </p>
    <p num="0082">Next, at a step S31, there is calculated a conforming proportion of the bead
section under observation. In the above-noted case, two of five sub-sections are each
non-conforming in quality of weld, with the rest conforming, so that the conforming
proportion is 60 %.</p>
    <p num="0083">Then, at a step S32, if the number of sub-sections decided to be conforming
exceeds a preset proportion (e.g. 70%) of conforming sub-section relative to the number
of divided sub-sections (YES), the control flow goes to a step S33, where it is
concluded that the re-examined bead section is conforming as a whole. This is
because the bead section actually corresponds to a length of continuous bead preset to
be longer than a required length for a sufficient weld strength, which means the actual
bead section includes an allowance for probable occurrences of non-conformity, such as
an under-filled, porous, and/or non-welded points. Therefore, if a section of bead
under observation has a calculated conforming length exceeding the required length, the
bead section may well be considered to be conforming as a whole.</p>
    <p num="0084">On the other hand, at the step S32, unless the number of sub-sections decided
to be conforming exceeds the preset proportion (e.g. 70%) of conforming sub-section
relative to the number of divided sub-sections (NO), the control flow goes to a step S34,
where it is concluded that the re-examined bead section has under-filled, porous, and/or
non-welded parts, so that it is non-conforming as a whole. It is noted that the display
7f indicates the conclusion of re-examined bead section to be conforming or non-conforming
as a whole.</p>
    <p num="0085">Like this, in this embodiment, even if an entirety of bead section as a welding
part is once decided to be problematic in weld quality, the bead section is re-examined
to know whether the conforming proportion is sufficient, so that the resultant conclusion
has an increased accuracy, assuring an enhanced proportion of conforming bead without
problem.</p>
    <p num="0086">The foregoing monitoring process is performed in a real-time manner, that is,
substantially at the same time as the welding. Even if the re-examination of a current
welding part is performed, the conclusion is given before entering the monitoring of a
subsequent welding part. If a welding part is finally concluded to be problematic in
weld quality, then the welding part is marked by blasting a paint thereto. Although a
fabricated vehicle body panel may have tens of welding parts, the paint marking
facilitates a final inspection in a post-process. In the final inspection, paint-marked
parts of any panel may well be again visually checked for non-conformity in weld
quality. If a vehicle panel is concluded to be problematic in weld quality, this panel is
transferred to a back-up process, where it is repaired. </p>
    <p num="0087">In the foregoing process of this embodiment, the sheet thickness sum or
welding speed is kept constant. However, though depending on the sheet thickness
sum, welding speed, or aspect ratio, there inherently is an optimal frequency for
decision on an occurrence of porous state, as described in the first embodiment.
Therefore, like the first embodiment, the second embodiment may also have a
frequency (i.e. the second frequency band) varied in dependence on the sheet thickness
sum, welding speed, or aspect ratio.</p>
    <p num="0088">In the second embodiment, respective decisions for occurrences of porous,
under-filled, and non-welded states can be processed by a single operation program,
without providing various complicate operation programs for detection of different
kinds of non-conformity of weld quality. Therefore, associated CPU is allowed to
have a quite decreased burden imposed thereon for such operation.</p>
    <p num="0089">Further, in this embodiment, by decision after subdivision of a bead section,
even a part of the bead section can also be monitored with ease for any state of weld
quality, allowing for an enhanced accuracy of decision on a degree of kind of weld
quality to occur.</p>
    <p num="0090">Fig. 26 is an illustration of a vibration model of a melt region 26 formed with a
keyhole 25, at a laser welding part of a lap weld between steel sheets 22 with Zn plating
21. The vibration model is configured like an eye drop extending upstream the
welding direction in plan, and has a height equivalent to an apparent thickness sum of
work (i.e. Zn-plated steel sheets 22). The lobe of a basic vibration of the model is
open (for free vibrations) at both top and bottom surfaces of the work, and close (with
forced vibrations) at a vertical center where vaporized metal of inter-sheet layers of the
Zn-plating 21 is discharged as jets.</p>
    <p num="0091">While preferred embodiments of the present invention have been described
using specific terms, such description is for illustrative purposes, and it is to be
understood that changes and variations may be made without departing from the scope
of the following claims.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A laser weld quality monitoring method comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>welding a part (WP) of work (5) with a laser beam (LB3) irradiated thereon
from a YAG laser (1);</claim-text><claim-text>detecting a varying intensity of light (L1) from the welding part (WP) to
provide a detection signal (Eb, Ed);</claim-text><claim-text>determining (S3) a value of signal power of a frequency spectrum in a
specified frequency band of the detection signal (Eb, Ed); and</claim-text><claim-text>making a decision (S4, S5, S6) for a porous state of the welding part (WP)
   to be significant as the value of signal power exceeds a threshold of
weld quality, and
   to be insignificant as the value of signal power does not exceed the
threshold of weld quality.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A laser weld quality monitoring method according to claim 1, wherein the
detection signal comprises a varying electrical signal (Eb, Ed) representing the varying
intensity of the light (L1) from the welding part (WP), and the determining the value of
signal power comprises calculating (S2) a set of frequency spectra of the varying
electrical signal.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A laser weld quality monitoring method according to claim 1, wherein the
specified frequency band is varied depending on one of a thickness (H) of the work (5),
a welding speed, and an aspect ratio (H/D) of a keyhole (25) at the welding part (WP).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A laser weld quality monitoring method according to claim 1, wherein the
determining the value of signal power comprises one of passing the electrical signal
(Ea) to a band-pass filter (7c) and applying a Fourrier transform to data of the electrical
signal (Ed).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A laser weld quality monitoring method comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>irradiating a laser beam (LB3) from a YAG laser (1) to a welding part (WP) of
work (5);</claim-text><claim-text>detecting light (L1) reflected from the welding part (WP);</claim-text><claim-text>calculating (S22) a frequency distribution from a set of data of the detected
light (L1) within a interval of time;</claim-text><claim-text>calculating (S23), from the frequency distribution, a first signal power sum in
one of a first frequency band for detecting an under-filled state and a second frequency
band for detecting a porous state, and a second signal power sum in a third frequency
band for detecting a non-welded state;</claim-text><claim-text>mapping (Fig. 22, Fig. 23, Fig. 24) a combination of calculated values of the
first and second signal power sums, in a region defined by a combination of a first axis
representing the first signal power sum and a second axis representing the second signal
power sum, including a sub-region representing a non-conforming state as one of the
under-filled state, the porous state, and the non-welded state; and</claim-text><claim-text>making a decision (S24, S25, S26, S27) for the welding part to have the non-conforming
state, as the combination of calculated values is mapped in the sub-region.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A laser weld quality monitoring method according to claim 5, wherein the
calculating the frequency distribution comprises converting the detected light (L1) into
an electrical signal (Eb, Ed), storing data on time-dependant variations of the electrical
signal (Eb, Ed), and calculating the frequency distribution from the stored data.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A laser weld quality monitoring method according to claim 5, wherein the
region includes sub-regions representing the under-filled state, the porous state, and the
non-welded state, respectively.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A laser weld quality monitoring method according to claim 5, wherein the
region (Fig. 23) includes a sub-region representing a conforming state of the work.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>A laser weld quality monitoring method according to claim 5, wherein the
region (Fig. 24) includes a sub-region representative of at least tow of the under-filled
state, the porous state, and the non-welded state.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>A laser weld quality monitoring method according to claim 5, further
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>calculating (S29), from a subset of the set of data, a subsidiary frequency
distribution of the detected light within a sub-interval of the interval of time;</claim-text><claim-text>calculating (S30), from the subsidiary frequency distribution, a first subsidiary
signal power sum in one of a first subsidiary frequency band for detecting an under-filled
state in a sub-section of the welding part corresponding to the sub-interval and a
second subsidiary frequency band for detecting a porous state in the sub-section, and a
second subsidiary signal power sum in a third subsidiary frequency band for detecting a
non-welded state in the sub-section;</claim-text><claim-text>mapping (Fig. 23, Fig. 24) in the region a combination of calculated subsidiary
values of the first and second subsidiary signal power sums;</claim-text><claim-text>making a decision (S30) for the sub-section of the welding part to have the
non-conforming state, as the combination of calculated subsidiary values is mapped in
the sub-region; and</claim-text><claim-text>concluding (S31, S32, S33, S34) a weld quality of the welding part based on
the decision for the sub-section.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>A laser weld quality monitoring method according to claim 10, wherein
the concluding the weld quality depends on a conforming proportion (S32) of the sub-section
to the welding part.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>A laser weld quality monitoring method according to claim 10, wherein
one of the first, second, and third subsidiary frequency bands is varied depending on
one of a thickness (H) of the work (5), a welding speed, and an aspect ratio (H/D) of a
keyhole (25) at the sub-section of the welding part (WP).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>A laser weld quality monitoring system comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a welder (100) configured to weld a part (WP) of work (5) with a laser beam
(LB3) irradiated thereon from a YAG laser (1);</claim-text><claim-text>a detector (MS) configured to detect a varying intensity of light (L1) reflected
from the welding part (WP) to provide a detection signal (Eb, Ed);</claim-text><claim-text>a value determiner (S2, S3) configured to determine a value of signal power of
a frequency spectrum in a specified frequency band of the detection signal (Eb, Ed); and</claim-text><claim-text>a decision-maker (S4, S5, S6) configured to make a decision for a porous state
of the welding part (WP)
   to be significant as the value of signal power exceeds a threshold of
weld quality, and
   to be insignificant as the value of signal power does not exceed the
threshold of weld quality.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>A laser weld quality monitoring system comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>welding means (100) for welding a part (WP) of work (5) with a laser beam
(LB3) irradiated thereon from a YAG laser (1);</claim-text><claim-text>detecting means (MS) for detecting a varying intensity of light (L1) reflected
from the welding part (WP) to provide a detection signal (Eb, Ed);</claim-text><claim-text>value determining means (S2, S3) for determining a value of signal power of a
frequency spectrum in a specified frequency band of the detection signal (Eb, Ed); and</claim-text><claim-text>decision-making means (S4, S5, S6) for making a decision for a porous state of
the welding part
   to be significant as the value of signal power exceeds a threshold of
weld quality, and
   to be insignificant as the value of signal power does not exceed the
threshold of weld quality.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>A laser weld quality monitoring system comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a laser welder (100) configured to irradiate a laser beam (LB3) from a YAG
laser (1) to a welding part (WP) of work (5);</claim-text><claim-text>a detector (MS) configured to detect light (L1) reflected from the welding part
(WP);</claim-text><claim-text>a calculator (S22) configured to calculate a frequency distribution from a set of
data of the detected light within a interval of time;</claim-text><claim-text>a calculator (S23) configured to calculate, from the frequency distribution, a
first signal power sum in one of a first frequency band for detecting an under-filled state
and a second frequency band for detecting a porous state, and a second signal power
sum in a third frequency band for detecting a non-welded state;</claim-text><claim-text>an operator (Fig. 22, Fig. 23, Fig. 24) configured to map a combination of
calculated values of the first and second signal power sums, in a region defined by a
combination of a first axis representing the first signal power sum and a second axis
representing the second signal power sum, including a sub-region representing a non-conforming
state as one of the under-filled state, the porous state, and the non-welded
state; and</claim-text><claim-text>a decision-maker (S24, S25, S26, S27) configured to make a decision for the
welding part to have the non-conforming state, as the combination of calculated values
is mapped in the sub-region.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>A laser weld quality monitoring system comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>laser welding means (100) for irradiating a laser beam (LB3) from a YAG laser
(1) to a welding part (WP) of work (5);</claim-text><claim-text>detecting means (MS) for detecting light (L1) reflected from the welding part
(WP);</claim-text><claim-text>calculating means (S22) for calculating a frequency distribution from a set of
data of the detected light within a interval of time;</claim-text><claim-text>calculating means (S23) for calculating, from the frequency distribution, a first
signal power sum in one of a first frequency band for detecting an under-filled state and
a second frequency band for detecting a porous state, and a second signal power sum in
a third frequency band for detecting a non-welded state;</claim-text><claim-text>operator means (Fig. 22, Fig. 23, Fig. 24) for mapping a combination of
calculated values of the first and second signal power sums, in a region defined by a
combination of a first axis representing the first signal power sum and a second axis
representing the second signal power sum, including a sub-region representing a non-conforming
state as one of the under-filled state, the porous state, and the non-welded
state; and</claim-text><claim-text>decision-making means (S24, S25, S26, S27) for making a decision for the
welding part to have the non-conforming state, as the combination of calculated values
is mapped in the sub-region.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
