<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1245629-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1245629" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="23069504" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021002">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1245629-A2" status="new" fvid="23562432">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1245629</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021002</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02252318-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02252318</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020328</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="US-27956001-P" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>27956001</doc-number>
          <kind>P</kind>
          <date>20010329</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   8/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   8/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   5/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   5/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/098       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/14        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   9/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   9/02        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  15/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  15/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F02K   9/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F02K   9/34        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08F   8/04</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08K   5/098+L15/00B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08K   5/14+L15/00B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  15/00B+B2B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F02K   9/34L</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Kautschukzusammensetzung mit hoher Festigkeit und daraus hergestellte Abscherschicht</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">High strength rubber formulations, and shear ply made from the same</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition de caoutchouc à haute résistance et couche de cisaillement fabriqué à partir de cette composition</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ALLIANT TECHSYSTEMS INC</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ALLIANT TECHSYSTEMS INC.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>ALLIANT TECHSYSTEMS INC.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>5050 Lincoln Drive</street>
              <city>Edina, Minnesota 55436</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ELLERTSON JOHN W</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HARVEY ALBERT R</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ELLERTSON, JOHN W.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HARVEY, ALBERT R.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>ELLERTSON, JOHN W.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>225 East, 200 South</street>
              <city>Brigham City, Utah 84302</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>HARVEY, ALBERT R.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>112 Ashe Circle</street>
              <city>Brigham City, Utah 84302</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Stuttard, Garry Philip</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Urquhart-Dykes &amp;amp; Lord Tower House Merrion Way</street>
              <city>Leeds LS2 8PA</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>IT</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>Disclosed are a precursor composition, a rubber component and a shear
ply prepared from the precursor composition, and methods for making and
using the same. The precursor composition includes:
<sl><li>(a) a first hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer modified
by a metal salt unsaturated carboxylic acid ester, wherein the hydrogenated
nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer is derived from a first ethylenically
unsaturated nitrile and a first conjugated diene;</li><li>(b) a second hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer
derived from a second ethylenically unsaturated nitrile and a second
conjugated diene; and</li><li>(c) a curing agent.</li></sl></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <b>RELATED APPLICATION</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0001">This application claims the benefit of priority of provisional
patent application 60/279,560 filed in the U.S. Patent &amp; Trademark Office on
March 29, 2001, the complete disclosure of which is incorporated herein by
reference.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</b>
    </heading>
    <heading>
      <b>1. Field of the Invention</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0002">The present invention pertains to the field of high strength
elastomers. More particularly, the present invention pertains to high strength
elastomers suited for use in high temperature shear ply applications, such as for
transferring loads from the pressure vessel of either a stand-alone composite
rocket motor or strap-on composite booster to a rocket skirt.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>2. Description of Related Art</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0003">Although there are many variations to the configuration and
construction of a rocket motor, rocket motors generally comprise an outer motor
casing for housing an energetic fuel or propellant. In the case of a solid rocket
motor, the outer motor casing houses a solid propellant formulated to undergo
combustion while contributing to the production of adequate thrust for attaining
propulsion of the rocket motor. Other types of rocket motors, such as hybrid,
reverse-hybrid motors, and bi-liquid motors, make use of a liquid oxidizer and/or
liquid fuel. A rubber insulation layer and a liner positioned between the casing
and the propellant serve to protect the rocket motor casing from high
temperature combustion products generated as the propellant burns. </p>
    <p num="0004">Rocket motor casings are generally made of metal, a composite
material, or a combination of metal and composite materials. Composite
materials are typically prepared by winding a resin-impregnated fiber on a
mandrel to shape the rocket motor casing. The resin may be a curable resin, and
is normally either an epoxy or phenolic resin. The fibers are usually carbon
graphite fibers or aramid fibers.</p>
    <p num="0005">The aft end portion of the rocket motor casing is directed to a
rocket skirt. Typically, an outer surface portion of a composite rocket motor
casing is covered with a shear ply layer for coupling the rocket motor casing to
the skirt. High strength rubber compositions are often used for the forming
shear ply layers that connect the rocket skirt with the composite rocket motor
casing.</p>
    <p num="0006">Silica-filled nitrile polybutadiene rubber (NBR) compositions are
presently used to form shear ply layers that connect a rocket skirt with a stand-alone
composite rocket motor casing. The conventional NBR compositions have
been found generally to exhibit a tensile strength and ultimate elongation on the
order of 20,684 kPa (3000 psi) and 700 percent, respectively. Although these
properties are adequate for stand-alone motor applications, new developments in
rocketry call for the use of strap-on boosters across a wide temperature range.
The strap-on design imparts higher loads to the shear ply than a stand-alone
rocket motor. These higher load designs encountered in strap-on booster
applications have created a perceived need for a novel shear ply material that
possesses a higher tensile strength and improved high temperature properties
compared to conventional silica-filled NBR compositions. </p>
    <heading>
      <b>OBJECTS OF THE INVENTION</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0007">It is therefore one of the objects of this invention to provide a
precursor composition that, upon curing, forms a high strength rubber that can
have sufficient flexion, strength, and high temperature properties for use, by way
of example, in a shear ply for rocketry applications.</p>
    <p num="0008">Another object of the invention is to provide a rubber material
that may have sufficient flexion, strength, and high temperature properties for
use in a shear ply for rocketry applications. It is especially preferred by this
object that the rubber material have a tensile strength and ultimate elongation
that are sufficient for the intended preferred application of a shear ply.</p>
    <p num="0009">It is another object of this invention to provide a rocket motor
assembly comprising a shear ply constructed and arranged for transferring loads
between a coupled casing and skirt of the rocket motor assembly.</p>
    <p num="0010">Yet another object of the invention is to provide corresponding
methods for making the high strength rubber material from the precursor
composition, as well as methods of making and applying shear ply articles using
the high strength rubber composition.</p>
    <p num="0011">Additional objects and advantages of the invention will be set
forth in the description that follows, and in part will be apparent from the
description, or may be learned by practice of the invention. The objects and
advantages of the invention may be realized and obtained by means of the
instrumentalities and combinations pointed out in the appended claims. </p>
    <heading>
      <b>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0012">To achieve the foregoing objects, and in accordance with the
purposes of the invention as embodied and broadly described in this document,
according to one aspect of this invention there is provided a precursor
composition that is curable into a rubber component and comprises:
<sl><li>(a) a first hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer modified by
a metal salt unsaturated carboxylic acid ester, wherein the hydrogenated nitrile
conjugated-diene copolymer is derived from a first composition comprising a first
ethylenically unsaturated nitrile and a first conjugated diene;</li><li>(b) a second hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer derived
from a second composition comprising a second ethylenically unsaturated nitrile
and a second conjugated diene; and</li><li>(c) a curing agent,</li></sl>
   wherein (a) and (b) are intermixed.</p>
    <p num="0013">In accordance with another aspect of this invention, there is
provided a rubber component formed from the precursor composition.</p>
    <p num="0014">In accordance with still another aspect of this invention, a
method is provided in which components (a) and (b) of the precursor composition
are mixed together to form a blend, and the blend is cured with a curing agent,
such as a peroxide curing agent, to form the rubber component.</p>
    <p num="0015">In accordance with a further aspect of this invention, there is
provided a method for coupling a skirt to a composite rocket motor case of a
rocket motor engine. This aspect of the invention involves providing a rubber
shear ply comprising the rubber component of this invention, and interposing the 
rubber shear ply between a skirt and a composite rocket motor case of a rocket
motor assembly.</p>
    <p num="0016">The present invention overcomes the problems that are outlined
above, addresses the above and other objects, and advances the art by providing
a high strength rubber composition having improved strength across a broad
temperature range for use in various applications. These applications include,
but are not limited to, rocketry applications, especially in the context of forming
shear ply layers. As used herein, the term "rubber" is defined to encompass both
synthetic and natural elastomers. The rubber composition, in its various
embodiments and methodologies, can facilitate the use of stronger rocket motors,
as well as new types of motors.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0017">The accompanying drawings are incorporated in and constitute a
part of the specification. The drawings, together with the general description
given above and the detailed description of the preferred embodiments and
methods given below, serve to explain the principles of the invention. In such
drawings:</p>
    <p num="0018">Fig. 1 is a graph depicting spectrophotometrically estimated
temperature dependant dynamic mechanical properties of a presently preferred
rubber composition illustrating the present invention;</p>
    <p num="0019">Fig. 2 is a graph showing comparative information with respect to
that shown in Fig. 1, but where the data was obtained from the best available
prior art material for use in making shear ply layers; </p>
    <p num="0020">Fig. 3 is a bar graph showing the relative shear strengths of prior
art silica filled rubber compositions at 22°C (72°F) versus a presently preferred
material illustrating the present invention; and</p>
    <p num="0021">Fig. 4 is a comparative bar graph identical to Fig. 3, but showing
data obtained from identical specimens at 38°C (100°F).</p>
    <heading>
      <b>DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS AND METHODS OF THE INVENTION</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0022">Reference will now be made in detail to the presently preferred
embodiments and methods of the invention as elaborated upon by the
accompanying drawings. It should be noted, however, that the invention in its
broader aspects is not limited to the specific details, representative devices and
methods, and illustrative examples shown and described in this section in
connection with the preferred embodiments and methods. The invention
according to its various aspects is particularly pointed out and distinctly claimed
in the attached claims read in view of this specification, and appropriate
equivalents.</p>
    <p num="0023">The precursor composition according to an embodiment of this
invention comprises a first hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer
modified by a metal salt unsaturated carboxylic acid ester, and a second
hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer not modified with the metal salt
unsaturated carboxylic acid ester. Each of the hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene
copolymers is derived from a respective composition comprising at least one
respective ethylenically unsaturated nitrile and at least one respective
conjugated diene. The ethylenically unsaturated nitriles of the first and second
hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene copolymers may be the same or different. 
Representative ethylenically unsaturated nitriles are acrylonitrile and
methacrylonitrile, with acrylonitrile currently being preferred. As referred to
herein, ethylenically unsaturated means the presence of at least one carbon-carbon
double bond.</p>
    <p num="0024">The conjugated dienes of the first and second hydrogenated nitrile
conjugated-diene copolymers may be the same or different. Representative
conjugated dienes for use in this invention include, for example, one or more
members selected from the group consisting of butadiene, isoprene,
dimethylbutadiene, 1,3-pentadiene, and piperylene. Of these, butadiene is
currently preferred.</p>
    <p num="0025">The metal salt unsaturated carboxylic acid ester is derived from
an ethylenically unsaturated carboxylic acid, which is preferably an α,β-ethylenically
unsaturated carboxylic acid having at least one carboxyl group.
The ethylenically unsaturated carboxylic acid may comprise at least one
unsaturated monocarboxylic acid selected from the group consisting of acrylic
acid, methacrylic acid, crotonic acid, and 3-butenic acid. Alternatively, the
ethylenically unsaturated carboxylic acid may comprise at least one unsaturated
dicarboxylic acid selected from the group consisting of maleic acid, fumaric acid,
and itaconic acid. It is also possible to use combinations of monocarboxylic and
dicarboxylic acids.</p>
    <p num="0026">Representative metals for the metal salt unsaturated carboxylic
acid ester include zinc, magnesium, calcium, and aluminum, and combinations
thereof. The metal salt unsaturated carboxylic acid ester may be derived from a
metallic compound, such as a metal oxide, especially zinc oxide. The currently 
preferred metal salt unsaturated carboxylic acid ester comprises zinc
dimethacrylate.</p>
    <p num="0027">According to one example of the invention, the weight ratio of
component (a) to component (b) in the precursor composition may be in a range of
85:15 to 30:70.</p>
    <p num="0028">The amount and type of curing agent demonstrates appreciable
effects upon the strength of the finished rubber composition. For example, a
peroxide curing agent may constitute from 1 weight percent to 2 weight percent
of the total weight of the precursor composition. The curing agent is preferably
dispersed in a clay or other carrier that itself comprises from 1 weight percent to
3 weight percent of the total weight of the precursor composition. The peroxide
curing agent is typically heated to an activation temperature whereupon the
agent cleaves at the peroxide to form a pair of free-radicals that initiate the
polymerization reaction. An especially preferred peroxide curing agent is 2,2'-bis(t-butylperoxy)diisopropyl
benzene, which is preferably heated to an activation
temperature of about 149°C (300°F) to 160°C (320°F) to initiate polymerization.
Other conventional peroxide curing agents may be used to initiate at different
temperatures as a matter of design choice. Alternatively, other initiators, e.g.,
nitrobenzyl photoinitiators, may be used to initiate polymerization.</p>
    <p num="0029">In addition to providing a finished rubber composition having
excellent mechanical properties, the precursor has various rheological properties
that facilitate related manufacturing processes using the precursor. Various
precursor formulations that are described above have demonstrated the following
rheological properties: <ul list-style="bullet"><li>a Mooney viscosity ranging between 60 and 80 determined as ML1 +
4 at 100°C (212°F),</li><li>a TS2 ranging between 3.0 and 4.5 minutes determined by
oscillating disk rheometer at 160°C (320°F) over a 5° arc,</li><li>a minimum torque (ML) ranging from 0.45 to 1.13 N·m (4.0 to 10.0
in-lb) determined by oscillating disk rheometer at 160°C (320°F)
over a 5° arc,</li><li>a maximum torque (MH) after 2 hours ranging between 4.5 to 7.9
N·m (40 and 70 in-lb),</li><li>an Mc(90) ranging between 4.0 to 6.8 N·m (35 and 60 in-lb)
determined by oscillating disk rheometer at 160°C (320°F) over a 5°
arc, and</li><li>a tc(90) ranging from 20 and 45 minutes determined by oscillating
disk rheometer at 160°C (320°F) over a 5° arc.</li></ul></p>
    <p num="0030">Preferred precursors also contain an antioxidant in an amount
ranging from 2 weight percent to 3 weight percent of the total weight of the
precursor composition. The antioxidant preferably comprises an amine, and is
most preferably selected from the group consisting of di-n-butylamine and
phenyl-β-naphylamine. An imidazole antioxidant may be used in synergistic
combination with the amine antioxidant, and the imidazole preferably comprises
zinc 2-percaptotoluolimidazole. </p>
    <p num="0031">In its further aspects, the invention pertains to a cured rubber
composition that is derived from the precursor. According to the broad ranges of
ingredient weight percentages that are described above, the rubber composition
may be formulated to provide an average shear strength in the finished rubber
product greater than 17,237 kPa (2500 psi) when tested between 21°C (70°F) and
38°C (100°F) by single-lap shear specimens of structural rubber bonded to a
graphite/fiber epoxy composite with a cross head rate of 0.051 cm/min (0.02
in/min). The 17,237 kPa (2500 psi) shear strength is approximately equal to the
shear strength that is obtainable from the best silica-filled compositions available
in the prior art. Even so, the shear strength is normally greater than about
20,684 kPa (3000 psi), and shear strengths of 24,132 kPa (3500) psi are
frequently obtained from finished shear ply materials that are formed of the
rubber compositions described above.</p>
    <p num="0032">Other structural properties of the finished rubber composition
may include one or more of the following properties, where the temperature is at
about 21°C (70°F) unless otherwise specified:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>a specific gravity in a range of 1.07 to 1.14,</li><li>a Shore A hardness in a range of 60 to 75,</li><li>a 100 percent modulus in a range from 2413 kPa (350 psi) to 5861
kPa (850 psi),</li><li>a tensile strength in a range from 37,921 kPa (5500 psi) to 44,126
kPa (6400 psi),</li><li>an elongation percent in a range of 423 to 564, and </li><li>a tear resistance in a range of 1896 kPa (275 psi) and 2586 kPa (375
psi).</li></ul></p>
    <p num="0033">The precursor and finished rubber composition are, in presently
preferred but merely illustrative embodiments of the invention, essentially free of
silica, where the term "essentially" is hereby defined to mean free from all but
trace elements of silica or as comprising less than 1% silica.</p>
    <p num="0034">In still further aspects, the invention pertains to a method of
making the rubber composition by blending components (a) and (b) into a
mixture, and adding a crosslinking agent. Suitable blenders include
conventional rubber mixing equipment, such as the BRABENDER and
RELIABLE brand mixers. Mixing is preferably performed in a two-pass
procedure, with the crosslinker and any cure catalysts or accelerants added in
the second pass.</p>
    <p num="0035">Yet another aspect includes a method of making a shear ply
material using the rubber composition and precursor. The aforementioned
method of making the rubber composition may be modified to include making a
shear ply for use in connecting a skirt to a rocket motor. This method includes
the step of obtaining a precursor mixture as described above, adding a curing
agent, activating the curing agent to polymerize the mixture, forming a laminate
using the mixture; and adapting the laminate for use as a shear ply connecting a
skirt with a rocket motor. The step of forming a laminate preferably includes
forming a laminate made of the mixture and a fibrous material, such as a
graphite fiber/epoxy composite. </p>
    <p num="0036">This invention will not be described further with reference to the
following examples, which should be considered as exemplary, not exhaustive, of
the scope of the invention.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>EXAMPLES 1-4</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0037">The following ingredients shown in Table 1 were purchased from
commercial vendors and combined into precursors for use in making structural
rubber compositions. The materials were placed in a BRABENDER internal
mixer to form 300 gram batch sizes for evaluation.</p>
    <p num="0038">ZSC 2295™ and Zetpol 2020™ were purchased from Zeon
Chemicals of Louisville, Kentucky. The Zetpol 2020 product contains amine-stabilized
butadiene in an amount ranging from 62.5 weight percent to 65.1
weight percent and acrylonitrile ranging from 34.9 weight percent to 37.5 weight
percent of the product, where the product is hydrogenated to 91% saturation.
Agerite Stalite S was purchased from the B.F. Goodrich Corporation of New
York, New York. Agerite Stalite S functions as an amine antioxidant. Vanox
ZMTI was purchased from the R.T. Vanderbilt Company, Inc. of New York, New
York. Vanox ZMTI contains zinc 2-percaptotoluolimidazole, which functions as
an imidazole antioxidant that is known to act synergistically with Agerite Stalite
S to prolong the life of finished rubber products. Vul-Cup 40KE was purchased
from Hercules Incorporated Corporation of Wilmington, Delaware. Vul-Cup
40KE contains 2,2'-bis(t-butylperoxy)diisopropyl benzene, which is dispersed in a
clay carrier to a 40 percent by weight concentration.</p>
    <p num="0039">The examples were each prepared by a two-pass procedure. In
the first pass, all ingredients other than the curative were added to a
BRABENDER mixer at 25-40 rpm. This batch was dumped at 93°C (200°F). The 
second pass was performed at the same mixing speed, and dumped at 71°C
(160°F).
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1"><b>STRUCTURAL RUBBER FORMULATIONS (Parts By Weight)</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Commercial Product</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Example 1</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Example 2</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Example 3</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Example 4</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">ZSC 2295</entry><entry align="center">60.00</entry><entry align="center">60.00</entry><entry align="center">50.00</entry><entry align="center">50.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Zetpol 2020</entry><entry align="center">40.00</entry><entry align="center">40.00</entry><entry align="center">50.00</entry><entry align="center">50.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Agerite Stalite S</entry><entry align="center">1.50</entry><entry align="center">1.50</entry><entry align="center">1.50</entry><entry align="center">1.50</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Vanox ZMTI</entry><entry align="center">1.00</entry><entry align="center">1.00</entry><entry align="center">1.00</entry><entry align="center">1.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Vul-Cup 40KE</entry><entry align="center">5.00</entry><entry align="center">3.00</entry><entry align="center">5.00</entry><entry align="center">3.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Total</b></entry><entry align="center">107.50</entry><entry align="center">105.50</entry><entry align="center">107.50</entry><entry align="center">105.50</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0040">Accordingly, Table 1 shows the weight percentages of ingredients
according to each mixture.</p>
    <p num="0041">The respective mixtures were each subjected to rheological
measurements at 100°C to determine their suitability for use in manufacturing
processes, then heated to a temperature of 160°C (320°F) for activation of the
peroxide curing agent for physical property testing. The results are shown in
Table 2.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1"><b>RHEOLOGICAL CHARACTERISTICS</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Property</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Example 1</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Example 2</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Example 3</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Example 4</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Mooney viscosity, ML 1 + 4 at 100°C (212 F)</entry><entry align="center">66.8</entry><entry align="center">69.4</entry><entry align="center">68.4</entry><entry align="center">72.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">The following properties were determined by oscillating disk </entry></row><row><entry align="left">rheometer, 160°C (320°F), 5-degree arc</entry></row><row><entry align="left">ts2,min.</entry><entry align="center">3.2</entry><entry align="center">3.7</entry><entry align="center">3.3</entry><entry align="center">3.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">ML, in.-lb.</entry><entry align="center">5.2</entry><entry align="center">4.8</entry><entry align="center">4.8</entry><entry align="center">8.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MH (after 2 hours), in.-lb.</entry><entry align="center">60.0</entry><entry align="center">47.5</entry><entry align="center">52.5</entry><entry align="center">45.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Mc(90), in.-lb.</entry><entry align="center">54.5</entry><entry align="center">43.2</entry><entry align="center">47.7</entry><entry align="center">41.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">tc (90), min.</entry><entry align="center">26.1</entry><entry align="center">28.4</entry><entry align="center">27.1</entry><entry align="center">37.5</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0042">The 300 gram batch rubber formulations from Table 1 were
subjected to evaluation for purposes of determining strength and flexibility
properties. Table 3 summarizes the physical properties of the rubber
formulations.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1"><b>PHYSICAL PROPERTIES OF THE STRUCTURAL RUBBERS AFTER THERMAL ACTIVATION OF CURING AGENT AT 160°C</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Property</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Example 1</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Example 2</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Example 3</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Example 4</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Specific gravity</entry><entry align="center">1.1207</entry><entry align="center">1.1118</entry><entry align="center">1.0938</entry><entry align="center">1.0851</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Shore A hardness</entry><entry align="center">71.2</entry><entry align="center">67.0</entry><entry align="center">66.3</entry><entry align="center">63.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">100 percent modulus, psi</entry><entry align="center">766</entry><entry align="center">527</entry><entry align="center">547</entry><entry align="center">372</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tensile strength, psi</entry><entry align="center">6140</entry><entry align="center">6100</entry><entry align="center">6000</entry><entry align="center">5940</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Elongation, percent</entry><entry align="center">423</entry><entry align="center">539</entry><entry align="center">442</entry><entry align="center">564</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tear resistance, psi</entry><entry align="center">317</entry><entry align="center">347</entry><entry align="center">296</entry><entry align="center">312</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0043">From these measurements, the rubber that resulted from
Example 2 was determined to have the best properties for use in a shear ply
layer for rocketry applications. However, all of the rubbers tested demonstrated
sufficient properties of flexion and strength for use in these applications.</p>
    <p num="0044">Testing of solid rubber compositions determined that Example 2 
had superior properties of strength, flexibility and adhesion, so a scaled-up batch
of Example 2 was produced in a 3000 gram batch size. A two-pass procedure was
again used, with mixing speeds of 40 rpm in a RELIABLE brand mixer. Dump
temperatures were 104°C (220°F) and 68°C (155°F) for the first and second
passes, respectively.</p>
    <p num="0045">The scaled-up batch had the following rheological properties and
physical properties shown in Tables 4 and 5, respectively.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1"><b>PROCESSING CHARACTERISTICS AND CURING PROPERTIES OF THE SCALED UP VERSION OF EXAMPLE 2</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Property</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Example 2 (Scale Up)</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Mooney viscosity,

ML 1 + 4 at 100°C (212°F)</entry><entry align="center">65.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">The following properties were determined by oscillating disk rheometer,

160°C (320°F), 5-degree arc</entry></row><row><entry align="left">ts2, min.</entry><entry align="center">3.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">ML, in.-lb.</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MH (after 2 hours), in.-lb.</entry><entry align="center">49.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Mc(90), in.-lb.</entry><entry align="center">44.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">tc(90), min.</entry><entry align="center">36.0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1"><b>PHYSICAL PROPERTIES OF THE SCALED UP VERSION OF EXAMPLE 2</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Property</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Example 2 (Scale Up)</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Specific gravity</entry><entry align="center">1.1058</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Shore A hardness</entry><entry align="center">72.6 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">100 percent modulus, psi</entry><entry align="center">540</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tensile strength psi</entry><entry align="center">5440</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Elongation, percent</entry><entry align="center">460</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tear resistance, psi</entry><entry align="center">347</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0046">Fig. 1 provides a graph of data that was obtained from the scale
up formulation of Example 2 using a Rheometrics Dynamic Spectrometer at a
frequency of 1 radian/second and at a strain of 0.2 percent. The temperature at
which the peak in the loss modulus G" is understood to approximate the glass
transition temperature of an elastomer. The peak occurred at -27.1°C for
Example 2. By way of comparison, a prior art silica filled NBR rubber
composition that Thiokol Propulsion currently uses in its shear ply layers
provided the results shown in Fig. 2, where the glass transition temperature is
estimated at -31.5°C. This data shows that the low temperature performance
characteristics of the two rubber compositions are nearly the same with flexion of
the prior art silica-filled composition being slightly better in terms of minimum
temperature performance. The transition for Example 2 is much steeper, which
indicates that Example 2 loses flexion over a narrower temperature range.
Furthermore, the storage modulus G' of Example 2 falls well below the storage
modulus of the prior art silica-filled composition at -10°C. These measurements
show that Example 2, while having improved strength characteristics, has a
flexion-temperature performance that is comparable to the prior art formulation.</p>
    <p num="0047">According to another aspect of the invention, a precursor as
previously described was used to make a shear ply layer. The load bearing
structural capacity of a shear ply layer including the solid rubbed composition
was tested by curing a rubber sample, laminating the rubber sample to a
graphite fiber/epoxy composite, then curing the composite. Similar laminates 
were made and tested using the prior art silica-filled composition. The samples
were tested at 22°C (72°F) and 38°C (100°F) using a conventional lap shear
testing machine at a cross-head rate of 0.051 cm/minute (0.02 inches/minute).
Fig. 3 provides a comparison of the shear strength values for samples including
an "NBR Control" for the silica-filled composition (left bar on graph), as well as a
historical average for numerous silica-filled samples based upon Thiokol
Propulsion quality control procedures involving the silica-filled composition
(middle bar on graph). These values do not exceed 17,327 kPa (2500 psi) and are
compared to 25,924 kPa (3760 psi) for the Example 2 sample (right bar on graph).</p>
    <p num="0048">Fig. 4 provides an identical comparison to that shown in Fig. 3,
except the results shown in Fig. 4 were obtained at 38°C (100°F). The silica-filled
specimens show a shear strength performance reduction to less than 13,789 kPa
(2000 psi), while Example 2 continued to demonstrate performance in excess of
17,237 kPa (2500 psi).</p>
    <p num="0049">The foregoing detailed description of the preferred embodiments
of the invention has been provided for the purposes of illustration and
description, and is not intended to be exhaustive or to limit the invention to the
precise embodiments disclosed. The embodiments were chosen and described in
order to best explain the principles of the invention and its practical application,
thereby enabling others skilled in the art to understand the invention for various
embodiments and with various modifications as are suited to the particular use
contemplated. It is intended that the scope of the invention cover various
modifications and equivalents included within the spirit and scope of the
appended claims.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A precursor composition having a total weight and curable into
a rubber component, the precursor composition comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) a first hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer modified
by a metal salt unsaturated carboxylic acid ester, wherein the hydrogenated
nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer is derived from a first composition
comprising a first ethylenically unsaturated nitrile and a first conjugated
diene;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) a second hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer
derived from a second composition comprising a second ethylenically
unsaturated nitrile and a second conjugated diene; and</claim-text><claim-text>(c) a curing agent,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein (a) and (b) are intermixed.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A precursor composition according to claim 1, wherein the first
and second ethylenically unsaturated nitriles are identical or different, and
are each selected to comprise at least one member selected from the group
consisting of acrylonitrile and methacrylonitrile.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A precursor composition according to claim 1, wherein the first
and second ethylenically unsaturated nitriles each comprise acrylonitrile.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A precursor composition according to claim 1, wherein the first
and second conjugated dienes are identical or different, and are each selected
to comprise at least one member selected from the group consisting of
butadiene, isoprene, dimethylbutadiene, 1,3-pentadiene, and piperylene.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A precursor composition according to claim 1, wherein the first
and second conjugated dienes each comprise butadiene.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A precursor composition according to claim 1, wherein the metal
salt unsaturated carboxylic acid ester is derived from at least one
ethylenically unsaturated monocarboxylic acid and at least one member
selected from the group consisting of a metal and metallic compound, and
wherein the ethylenically unsaturated monocarboxylic acid comprises at least
one member selected from the group consisting of acrylic acid, methacrylic
acid, crotonic acid, and 3-butenic acid.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A precursor composition according to claim 1, wherein the metal
salt unsaturated carboxylic acid ester is derived from at least one
ethylenically unsaturated dicarboxylic acid and at least one member selected
from the group consisting of a metal and metallic compound, and wherein the
ethylenically unsaturated dicarboxylic acid comprises at least one member
selected from the group consisting of maleic acid, fumaric acid, and itaconic
acid.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A precursor composition according to claim 1, wherein the metal
salt comprises at least one element selected from the group consisting of zinc,
magnesium, calcium, and aluminum.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>A precursor composition according to claim 1, wherein the metal
salt unsaturated carboxylic acid ester comprises zinc dimethacrylate.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>A precursor composition according to claim 1, wherein the
curing agent comprises a peroxide curing agent.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>A precursor composition according to claim 1, wherein the
curing agent comprises 2,2'-bis(t-butylperoxy)diisopropyl benzene.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>A precursor composition according to claim 1, wherein the
curing agent is dispersed in a clay carrier.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>A precursor composition according to claim 1, wherein the
precursor composition is essentially free of silica.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>A precursor composition according to claim 1, wherein (a) and
(b) are formulated and present in an effective ratio to provide:
<claim-text><claim-text>a Mooney viscosity in a range of 60 to 80 determined as ML1+4 at
100°C;</claim-text><claim-text>a TS2 ranging in a range of 3.0 to 4.5 minutes determined by
oscillating disk rheometer at 160°C over a 5° arc;</claim-text><claim-text>a ML ranging in a range of 4.0 to 10.0 in.-lb determined by oscillating
disk rheometer at 160°C over a 5° arc;</claim-text><claim-text>a MH after 2 hours in a range of 40.0 to 70 in.-lb;</claim-text><claim-text>an Mc(90) in a range of 35 to 60 in.-lb determined by oscillating disk
rheometer at 160°C over a 5° arc; and</claim-text><claim-text>a tc(90) in a range of 20 to 45 minutes determined by oscillating disk
rheometer at 160°C over a 5° arc.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>A precursor composition according to claim 1, wherein (a), (b),
and (c) are formulated and present in effective ratios to provide, upon curing
of the precursor composition into the rubber component, an average shear
strength in the rubber product greater than 24,132 kPa when tested at 21°C
by single-lap shear specimens of the rubber product bonded to a
graphite/fiber epoxy composite with acrosshead rate of 0.0508 cm/min.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>A precursor composition according to claim 1, wherein (a), (b),
and (c) are formulated and present in effective ratios to provide, upon curing
of the precursor composition into the rubber component, an average shear
strength in the rubber product greater than 17237 kPa when tested at 38°C
by single-lap shear specimens of the rubber product bonded to a
graphite/fiber epoxy composite with acrosshead rate of 0.0508 cm/min.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>A precursor composition according to claim 1, wherein (a), (b),
and (c) are formulated and present in effective ratios to provide, upon curing
of the precursor composition into the rubber component, as determined at
21°C,
   a specific gravity in a range of 1.07 to 1.14,
   a Shore A hardness in a range of 60 to 75,
   a 100 percent modulus in a range of 2413 kPa to 5861 kPa,
   a tensile strength in a range of 37,921 kPa to 44,126 kPa,
   an elongation percent in a range of 400 to 575, and
   a tear resistance in a range of 1896 kPa to 2586 kPa.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="18">
      <claim-text>A precursor composition according to claim 1, wherein carbon-carbon
double bonds in each of the first hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene
copolymer and the second hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene
copolymer are hydrogenated to 85% to 95% of saturation.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="19">
      <claim-text>A precursor composition according to claim 1, wherein carbon-carbon
double bonds in each of the first hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene
copolymer and the second hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene
copolymer are hydrogenated to 90% to 92% of saturation.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="20">
      <claim-text>A rubber component having a total weight, the rubber
component being formed from a precursor composition comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) a first hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer modified
by a metal salt unsaturated carboxylic acid ester, wherein the hydrogenated
nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer is derived from a first composition
comprising a first ethylenically unsaturated nitrile and a first conjugated
diene;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) a second hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer
derived from a second composition comprising a second ethylenically
unsaturated nitrile and a second conjugated diene; and</claim-text><claim-text>(c) a curing agent,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein (a) and (b) are intermixed.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="21">
      <claim-text>A rubber component according to claim 20, wherein the first and
second ethylenically unsaturated nitriles are identical or different, and are
each selected to comprise at least one member selected from the group
consisting of acrylonitrile and methacrylonitrile.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="22">
      <claim-text>A rubber component according to claim 20, wherein the first and
second ethylenically unsaturated nitriles each comprise acrylonitrile.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="23">
      <claim-text>A rubber component according to claim 20, wherein the first and
second conjugated dienes are identical or different, and are each selected to
comprise at least one member selected from the group consisting of
butadiene, isoprene, dimethylbutadiene, 1,3-pentadiene, and piperylene.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="24">
      <claim-text>A rubber component according to claim 20, wherein the first and
second conjugated dienes each comprise butadiene.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="25">
      <claim-text>A rubber component according to claim 20, wherein the metal
salt unsaturated carboxylic acid ester is derived from at least one
ethylenically unsaturated monocarboxylic acid and at least one member
selected from the group consisting of a metal and metallic compound, and
wherein the ethylenically unsaturated monocarboxylic acid comprises at least
one member selected from the group consisting of acrylic acid, methacrylic
acid, crotonic acid, and 3-butenic acid.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="26">
      <claim-text>A rubber component according to claim 20, wherein the metal
salt unsaturated carboxylic acid ester is derived from at least one
ethylenically unsaturated dicarboxylic acid and at least one member selected
from the group consisting of a metal and metallic compound, and wherein the
ethylenically unsaturated dicarboxylic acid comprises at least one member
selected from the group consisting of maleic acid, fumaric acid, and itaconic
acid.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="27">
      <claim-text>A rubber component according to claim 20, wherein the metal
salt comprises at least one element selected from the group consisting of zinc,
magnesium, calcium, and aluminum.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="28">
      <claim-text>A rubber component according to claim 20, wherein the metal
salt unsaturated carboxylic acid ester comprises zinc dimethacrylate.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="29">
      <claim-text>A rubber component according to claim 20, wherein the curing
agent comprises a peroxide curing agent.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="30">
      <claim-text>A rubber component according to claim 20, wherein the curing
agent comprises 2,2'-bis(t-butylperoxy)diisopropyl benzene.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="31">
      <claim-text>A rubber component according to claim 20, wherein the curing
agent is dispersed in a clay carrier.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="32">
      <claim-text>A rubber component according to claim 20, wherein the rubber
component is essentially free of silica.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="33">
      <claim-text>A rubber component according to claim 20, wherein (a), (b), and
(c) are formulated and present in effective ratios to provide the rubber
component with an average shear strength in the rubber product greater
than 24,132 kPa when tested at 21°C by single-lap shear specimens of the
rubber product bonded to a graphite/fiber epoxy composite with acrosshead
rate of 0.0508 cm/min.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="34">
      <claim-text>A rubber component according to claim 20, wherein (a), (b), and
(c) are formulated and present in effective ratios to provide the rubber
component with an average shear strength in the rubber product greater
than 17237 kPa when tested at 38°C by single-lap shear specimens of the
rubber product bonded to a graphite/fiber epoxy composite with acrosshead
rate of 0.0508 cm/min.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="35">
      <claim-text>A rubber component according to claim 20, wherein (a), (b), and
(c) are formulated and present in effective ratios to provide the rubber
component with, as determined at 21°C,
   a specific gravity in a range of 1.07 to 1.14,
   a Shore A hardness in a range of 60 to 75,
   a 100 percent modulus in a range of 2413 kPa to 5861 kPa,
   a tensile strength in a range of 37,921 kPa to 44,126 kPa,
   an elongation percent in a range of 400 to 575, and
   a tear resistance in a range of 1896 kPa to 2586 kPa.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="36">
      <claim-text>A rubber component according to claim 20, wherein carbon-carbon
double bonds in each of the first hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene
copolymer and the second hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene
copolymer are hydrogenated to 85% to 95% of saturation.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="37">
      <claim-text>A rubber component according to claim 20, wherein carbon-carbon
double bonds in each of the first hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene
copolymer and the second hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene
copolymer are hydrogenated to 90% to 92% of saturation.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="38">
      <claim-text>A method of making a rubber component, the method
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) providing a first hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene
copolymer modified with a metal salt unsaturated carboxylic acid ester,
wherein the hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer is derived from
a first composition comprising a first ethylenically unsaturated nitrile and a
first conjugated diene;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) providing a second hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene
copolymer derived from a second composition comprising a second
ethylenically unsaturated nitrile and a second conjugated diene;</claim-text><claim-text>(c) blending components provided by (a) and (b) to form a blend;
and</claim-text><claim-text>(d) curing the blend with a curing agent to form the rubber
component.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="39">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 38, wherein the first and second
ethylenically unsaturated nitriles are identical or different, and are each
selected to comprise at least one member selected from the group consisting
of acrylonitrile and methacrylonitrile.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="40">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 38, wherein the first and second
ethylenically unsaturated nitrites each comprise acrylonitrile.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="41">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 38, wherein the first and second
conjugated dienes are identical or different, and are each selected to comprise
at least one member selected from the group consisting of butadiene,
isoprene, dimethylbutadiene, 1,3-pentadiene, and piperylene.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="42">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 38, wherein the first and second
conjugated dienes each comprise butadiene.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="43">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 38, wherein the metal salt
unsaturated carboxylic acid ester is derived from at least one ethylenically
unsaturated monocarboxylic acid and at least one member selected from the
group consisting of a metal and metallic compound, and wherein the
ethylenically unsaturated monocarboxylic acid comprises at least one
member selected from the group consisting of acrylic acid, methacrylic acid,
crotonic acid, and 3-butenic acid.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="44">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 38, wherein the metal salt
unsaturated carboxylic acid ester is derived from at least one ethylenically
unsaturated dicarboxylic acid and at least one member selected from the
group consisting of a metal and metallic compound, and wherein the
ethylenically unsaturated dicarboxylic acid comprises at least one member
selected from the group consisting of maleic acid, fumaric acid, and itaconic
acid.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="45">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 38, wherein the metal salt
comprises at least one element selected from the group consisting of zinc,
magnesium, calcium, and aluminum.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="46">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 38, wherein the metal salt
unsaturated carboxylic acid ester comprises zinc dimethacrylate.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="47">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 38, wherein the curing agent
comprises a peroxide curing agent.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="48">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 38, wherein the curing agent
comprises 2,2'-bis(t-butylperoxy)diisopropyl benzene.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="49">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 38, wherein the curing agent is
dispersed in a clay carrier.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="50">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 38, wherein the rubber component
is essentially free of silica.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="51">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 38, wherein the rubber component
is formulated to provide an average shear strength in the rubber product
greater than 24,132 kPa when tested at 21°C by single-lap shear specimens
of the rubber product bonded to a graphite/fiber epoxy composite with
acrosshead rate of 0.0508 cm/min.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="52">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 38, wherein the rubber component
is formulated to provide an average shear strength in the rubber product
greater than 17237 kFa when tested at 38°C by single-lap shear specimens of
the rubber product bonded to a graphite/fiber epoxy composite with
acrosshead rate of 0.0508 cm/min.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="53">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 38, wherein the rubber component
is formulated to provide, as determined at 21°C,
   a specific gravity in a range of 1.07 to 1.14,
   a Shore A hardness in a range of 60 to 75,
   a 100 percent modulus in a range of 2413 kPa to 5861 kPa,
   a tensile strength in a range of 37,921 kPa to 44,126 kPa,
   an elongation percent in a range of 400 to 575, and
   a tear resistance in a range of 1896 kPa to 2586 kPa.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="54">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 38, wherein carbon-carbon double
bonds in each of the first hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer
and the second hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer are
hydrogenated to 85% to 95% of saturation.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="55">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 38, wherein carbon-carbon double
bonds in each of the first hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer
and the second hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer are
hydrogenated to 90% to 92% of saturation.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="56">
      <claim-text>A method of transferring loads between a skirt and a composite
rocket motor case of a rocket motor assembly, the method comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) providing a first hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene
copolymer modified with a metal salt unsaturated carboxylic acid ester,
wherein the hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer is derived from
a first composition comprising a first ethylenically unsaturated nitrile and a
first conjugated diene, wherein the metal salt unsaturated carboxylic acid
ester is derived from an ethylenically unsaturated carboxylic acid having at
least one carboxyl group and at least one member selected from the group
consisting of a metal and metallic compound;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) providing a second hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene
copolymer derived from a second composition comprising a second
ethylenically unsaturated nitrile and a second conjugated diene;</claim-text><claim-text>(c) blending components (a) and (b) to form a blend;</claim-text><claim-text>(d) curing the blend with a curing agent to form a rubber shear ply;
and</claim-text><claim-text>(e) interposing the rubber shear ply between the skirt and the
composite rocket motor case.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="57">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 56, wherein the first and second
ethylenically unsaturated nitriles are identical or different, and are each
selected to comprise at least one member selected from the group consisting
of acrylonitrile and methacrylonitrile.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="58">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 56, wherein the first and second
ethylenically unsaturated nitriles each comprise acrylonitrile.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="59">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 56, wherein the first and second
conjugated dienes are identical or different, and are each selected to comprise
at least one member selected from the group consisting of butadiene,
isoprene, dimethylbutadiene, 1,3-pentadiene, and piperylene.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="60">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 56, wherein the first and second
conjugated dienes each comprise butadiene.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="61">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 56, wherein the metal salt
unsaturated carboxylic acid ester is derived from at least one ethylenically
unsaturated monocarboxylic acid and at least one member selected from the
group consisting of a metal and metallic compound, and wherein the
ethylenically unsaturated monocarboxylic acid comprises at least one
member selected from the group consisting of acrylic acid, methacrylic acid,
crotonic acid, and 3-butenic acid.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="62">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 56, wherein the metal salt
unsaturated carboxylic acid ester is derived from at least one ethylenically
unsaturated dicarboxylic acid and at least one member selected from the
group consisting of a metal and metallic compound, and wherein the
ethylenically unsaturated dicarboxylic acid comprises at least one member
selected from the group consisting of maleic acid, fumaric acid, and itaconic
acid.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="63">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 56, wherein the metal salt
comprises at least one element selected from the group consisting of zinc,
magnesium, calcium, and aluminum.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="64">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 56, wherein the metal salt
unsaturated carboxylic acid ester comprises zinc dimethacrylate.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="65">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 56, wherein the curing agent
comprises a peroxide curing agent.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="66">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 56, wherein the curing agent
comprises 2,2'-bis(t-butylperoxy)diisopropyl benzene.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="67">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 56, wherein the curing agent is
dispersed in a clay carrier.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="68">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 56, wherein the rubber shear ply is
essentially free of silica.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="69">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 56, wherein the rubber shear ply is
formulated to provide an average shear strength in the rubber product
greater than 24,132 kPa when tested at 21°C by single-lap shear specimens
of the rubber product bonded to a graphite/fiber epoxy composite with
acrosshead rate of 0.0508 cm/min.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="70">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 56, wherein the rubber shear
component is formulated to provide an average shear strength in the rubber
product greater than 17237 kPa when tested at 38°C by single-lap shear
specimens of the rubber product bonded to a graphite/fiber epoxy composite
with acrosshead rate of 0.0508 cm/min.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="71">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 56, wherein the rubber shear ply is
formulated to provide, as determined at 21°C,
   a specific gravity in a range of 1.07 to 1.14,
   a Shore A hardness in a range of 60 to 75,
   a 100 percent modulus in a range of 2413 kPa to 5861 kPa,
   a tensile strength in a range of 37,921 kPa to 44,126 kPa,
   an elongation percent in a range of 400 to 575, and
   a tear resistance in a range of 1896 kPa to 2586 kPa.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="72">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 56, wherein carbon-carbon double
bonds in each of the first hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer
and the second hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer are
hydrogenated to 85% to 95% of saturation.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="73">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 56, wherein carbon-carbon double
bonds in each of the first hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer
and the second hydrogenated nitrile conjugated-diene copolymer are
hydrogenated to 90% to 92% of saturation.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
