<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1251313-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1251313" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="18971357" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021023">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1251313-A2" status="new" fvid="23590954">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1251313</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021023</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02008510-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02008510</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020415</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001121498-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001121498</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010419</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F02C   7/16        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F02C   7/18        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23M  13/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23M  13/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23R   3/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23R   3/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23R   3/04        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23R   3/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23R   3/10        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23R   3/30        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23R   3/30        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F23M  13/00B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F23R   3/00C</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F23R   3/06</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">R23D211:00</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Gasturbinenverbrennungsanlage</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">A gas turbine combustor</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Chambre de combustion de turbine à gaz</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MITSUBISHI HEAVY IND LTD</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MITSUBISHI HEAVY INDUSTRIES, LTD.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Mitsubishi Heavy Industries, Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>5-1, Marunouchi 2-chome, Chiyoda-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>AOYAMA KUNIAKI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>IKEDA KAZUFUMI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MANDAI SHIGEMI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SUENAGA KIYOSHI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TANAKA KATSUNORI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>AOYAMA, KUNIAKI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>IKEDA, KAZUFUMI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MANDAI, SHIGEMI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SUENAGA, KIYOSHI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TANAKA, KATSUNORI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Aoyama, Kuniaki, Takasago Research &amp;amp; Dvt. Center</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Mitsubishi Heavy Ind.Ltd, 2-1-1, Arai-cho Shinhama</street>
              <city>Takasago, Hyogo-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Ikeda, Kazufumi, Takasago Research &amp;amp; Dvt. Center</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Mitsubishi Heavy Ind.Ltd, 2-1-1, Arai-cho Shinhama</street>
              <city>Takasago, Hyogo-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Mandai, Shigemi, Takasago Research &amp;amp; Dvt. Center</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Mitsubishi Heavy Ind.Ltd, 2-1-1, Arai-cho Shinhama</street>
              <city>Takasago, Hyogo-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Suenaga, Kiyoshi, Takasago Research &amp;amp; Dvt. Center</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Mitsubishi Heavy Ind.Ltd, 2-1-1, Arai-cho Shinhama</street>
              <city>Takasago, Hyogo-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Tanaka, Katsunori, c/o Takasago Machinery Works</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Mitsubishi Heavy Ind.Ltd, 2-1-1, Arai-cho Shinhama</street>
              <city>Takasago, Hyogo-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Henkel, Feiler, Hänzel &amp;amp; Partner</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Möhlstrasse 37</street>
              <city>81675 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A gas turbine combustor includes a side wall, for
defining a combustion volume, having upstream and
downstream ends, a pilot nozzle, disposed adjacent the
upstream end of the side wall, for discharging a pilot
fuel to form a diffusion flame in the combustion volume,
and a plurality of main nozzles, provided around the
pilot nozzles, for discharging a fuel-air mixture to form
premixed flames in the combustion volume. Film air is
supplied into the combustion volume downstream of the
main nozzles along the inner surface of the side wall to
reduce the fuel-air ratio in a region adjacent the inner
surface of the side wall and to restrain a combustion-driven
oscillation in the combustion volume.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="63" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="116"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <heading>1. Field of the Invention</heading>
    <p num="0001">The invention relates to a gas turbine
combustor.</p>
    <heading>2. Description of the Related Art</heading>
    <p num="0002">Conventional gas turbine utilizes a two-stage
combustor which includes a pilot nozzle for forming a
diffusion flame, as a pilot flame, along the axis of the
combustor, and a plurality of main nozzles for
discharging a fuel-air mixture to form premixed flames as
the main combustion around the diffusion flame.</p>
    <p num="0003">In the conventional gas turbine combustor, the
premixed flames complete the combustion process in a
short length in the axial direction of the combustor
which may result in short flames or a rapid combustion
adjacent a wall. When the combustion process is
completed within a small volume, the volumetric density
of the energy released by the combustion or the
combustion intensity in the combustor becomes high so
that a combustion-driven oscillation can easily be
generated within a plane perpendicular to the axis or in
the peripheral direction. The combustion-driven
oscillation is self-excited oscillation generated by the
conversion of a portion of the thermal energy to the
oscillation energy. The larger the combustion intensity
in a section of a combustor, the larger the exciting
force of the combustion-driven oscillation to promote the
generation of the combustion-driven oscillation.</p>
    <heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0004">The invention is directed to solve the prior art
problems, and to provide a gas turbine combustor which is
improved to reduce a combustion-driven oscillation.</p>
    <p num="0005">According to the invention, a gas turbine combustor
comprises a side wall for defining a combustion volume, 
having upstream and downstream ends, a pilot nozzle,
disposed adjacent the upstream end of the side wall, for
discharging a pilot fuel to form a diffusion flame in the
combustion volume, and a plurality of main nozzles,
provided around the pilot nozzles, for discharging a
fuel-air mixture to form premixed flames in the
combustion volume. Film air is supplied into the
combustion volume downstream of the main nozzles along
the inner surface of the side wall to reduce the fuel-air
ratio in a region adjacent the inner surface of the side
wall and to restrain a combustion-driven oscillation in
the combustion volume.</p>
    <p num="0006">According to another feature of the invention, a gas
turbine combustor comprises a side wall for defining a
combustion volume the side wall having upstream and
downstream ends, a pilot nozzle, disposed adjacent the
upstream end of the side wall, for discharging a pilot
fuel to form diffusion flame in the combustion volume,
and a plurality of main nozzles, provided.around the
pilot nozzles, for discharging a fuel-air mixture to form
premixed flames in the combustion volume. The side wall
includes a plurality of oscillation damping orifices
which are defined in a region downstream of the main
nozzles and extend radially through the side wall.</p>
    <heading>DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
    <p num="0007">These and other objects and advantages and further
description will now be discussed in connection with the
drawings in which:
<sl><li>Figure 1 is a sectional view of A gas turbine
combustor according to a preferred embodiment of the
present invention;</li><li>Figure 2 is an enlarged section of a portion
indicated by "A" in Figure 1;</li><li>Figure 3 is a partial side view of a combustor tail
tube in the direction of III in Figure 2, showing steam
passages and a plurality of oscillation damping orifices;</li><li>Figure 4 is another section of the portion indicated 
by "A" in Figure 1;</li><li>Figure 5 is a partial section of the combustor tail
tube along a plane perpendicular to the axis of the gas
turbine combustor, showing liner segments forming an
acoustic liner of the invention;</li><li>Figure 6A is a partial section of the combustor tail
tube along a plane perpendicular to the axis of the gas
turbine combustor, showing liner segments according to
another embodiment;</li><li>Figure 6B is a partial section similar to Figure 6A,
showing liner segments according to another embodiment;</li><li>Figure 6C is a partial section similar to Figures 6A
and 6B, showing liner segments according to another
embodiment;</li><li>Figure 7A is a partial section of the combustor tail
tube along a plane including the axis of the gas turbine
combustor, showing liner segments according to another
embodiment; and</li><li>Figure 7B is an enlarged section of the liner
segment shown in Figure 7A.</li></sl></p>
    <heading>Description of the Preferred Embodiments</heading>
    <p num="0008">With reference to the drawings, a preferred
embodiment of the present invention will be described
below.</p>
    <p num="0009">A gas turbine 100 according to the embodiment
includes a compressor (not shown), an expander (not
shown) connected to the compressor by a shaft, a casing
102 and 104 for enclosing the compressor and the
expander, and a combustor 10 fixed to the casing 102 and
104. The air compressed by the compressor is supplied to
the combustor 10 through a compressed air chamber 106
defined by the casing 102 and 104.</p>
    <p num="0010">The combustor 10 has cylindrical a combustor tail
tube 12 and an inner tube 30. A pilot nozzle 14 is
provided at the center of the inner tube 30 around which
a plurality of main nozzles 16 are disposed. A fuel, for
example natural gas, is supplied as a pilot fuel to the 
pilot nozzle 14 through a pilot fuel supply conduit 26.
The pilot nozzle 14 discharges the pilot fuel into the
combustor tail tube 12 to form a diffusion flame. A
fuel, for example natural gas, is supplied as a main fuel
through a main fuel supply conduit 28 so that the main
fuel is mixed with air, supplied from the compressed air
chamber 106, in a volume upstream of the main nozzles 16.
The main nozzles 16 discharge the fuel-air mixture into
the inner tube 12 to form premixed flames.</p>
    <p num="0011">With reference to in particular Figure 2, the inner
tube 30 has an outer diameter smaller than the inner
diameter of the combustor tail tube 12 so that a gap "d"
is defined between the inner tube 30 and the combustor
tail tube 12. The inner tube 30 is inserted into the
combustor tail tube 12 by a predetermined length "L".
This configuration allows the high pressure air in the
compressed air chamber 106 to flow into the combustor
tail tube 12 through the gap "d" as a film air along the
inner surface of the combustor tail tube 12. When the
film air flows along the inner surface of the combustor
tail tube 12, it is mixed with the main fuel-air mixture
or the premixed flames discharged through the main
nozzles 16. Therefore, the fuel-air ratio of the
premixed flames is reduced in the region adjacent the
inner surface of the combustor tail tube 12 so that a
rapid combustion is restrained in the region adjacent the
inner surface of the combustor tail tube 12. This
reduces oscillation energy to restrain the combustion-driven
oscillation.</p>
    <p num="0012">In this embodiment, the combustor tail tube 12
defines a plurality of axially extending steam passages
12a (shown in Figures 2 and 3) into which cooling steam
is supplied through a steam header 18 from an external
steam source and may be, for example steam extracted from
an intermediate pressure turbine to cool the casing. The
steam which has passed through the steam passage 12a to
cool the combustor tail tube 12 is recovered by a steam 
recovery apparatus, for example a low pressure turbine.</p>
    <p num="0013">An acoustic liner 24 is preferably attached to the
combustor tail tube 12 so that the acoustic liner 24
encloses the outer surface adjacent the rear end of the
combustor tail tube 12 to define an acoustic buffer
chamber 25 between the acoustic liner 24 and the outer
surface of the combustor tail tube 12. A plurality of
orifices 12b, which radially extend through the wall of
the combustor tail tube 12 to fluidly communicate the
internal volume of the combustor tail tube 12 with the
acoustic buffer chamber 25, are defined as oscillation
damping orifices. With reference to in particular Figure
3, in this embodiment, the orifices 12b are disposed in
lines between respective sets of four steam passages 12a.
When a combustion-driven oscillation, in particular
oscillation within a plane perpendicular to the axis of
the combustor tail tube 12 or peripheral and/or radial
oscillation is generated in a region adjacent the
proximal end portion of the combustor tail tube 12, the
orifices 12b allow the combustor 10 to restrain the
combustion-driven oscillation by reducing the pressure of
the fuel-air mixture moving through the orifices 12b to
reduce the oscillation energy.</p>
    <p num="0014">The preferred embodiment of the present invention
has been described. The invention, however, is not
limited to the embodiment and can be varied and modified
within the scope of the invention.</p>
    <p num="0015">For example, a plurality of orifices 24a can be
provided as air cooling orifices in the acoustic liner 24
for introducing the air from the compressed air chamber
106 into the acoustic buffer chamber 25. The provision
of the air cooling orifices 24a allows the wall portions
between the adjoining orifices 12b of the combustor tail
tube 12 to be cooled by the air through the air cooling
orifices 24a. The air cooling orifices 24a are
preferably disposed in lines aligned over the
corresponding lines of the orifices 12b and axially 
offset relative to the orifices 12b so that the air
cooling orifices 24a are axially positioned
intermediately between the adjoining orifices 12b. The
above-described disposition of the air cooling orifices
24a allows the air to flow into the acoustic buffer 25
through the air cooling orifices 24a as impingements jet
relative to the wall of the combustor tail tube 12 and to
effectively cool the wall portions between the adjoining
orifices 12b of the combustor tail tube 12.</p>
    <p num="0016">Further, the acoustic liner 24 is not required to
comprise an integral single body enclosing the proximal
end portion of the combustor tail tube 12. The acoustic
liner 24 can comprise a plurality of liner segments 124
disposed around the combustor tail tube 12, as shown in
Figure 5. The configuration of the acoustic liner 24
composed of the liner segments 124 allows the thermal
stress generated in the acoustic liner 24 to be reduce by
the temperature difference between the acoustic liner 24
and the combustor tail tube 12.</p>
    <p num="0017">Further, a bellows portion, for reducing thermal
stress, may be provided in the liner segments. With
reference to Figure 6A, a liner segment 246 has lateral
bellows portions 246c disposed between side wall portions
246a, attached to the side wall of the combustor tail
tube 12, and peripheral wall portion 246b, substantially
parallel to the side wall of the combustor tail tube 12.
The lateral bellows portions 246c allows the liner
segment 246 to deform, between the side wall portions
246a and the peripheral wall portion 246b, mainly in the
direction shown by arrow "a", parallel to the side wall
of the combustor tail tube 12.</p>
    <p num="0018">In another embodiment shown in Figure 6B, liner
segment 346 has a lateral bellows portion 346c, provided
in the peripheral wall portion 346b other than between
the side wall portions 346a, attached to the side wall of
the combustor tail tube 12, and the peripheral wall
portion 346b, substantially parallel to the side wall of 
the combustor tail tube 12, as in the embodiment of
Figure 6A. The lateral bellows portion 346c allows the
liner segment 346 to deform in the direction of arrow "a"
and parallel to the side wall of the combustor tail tube
12.</p>
    <p num="0019">In another embodiment shown in Figure 6C, liner
segment 446 has perpendicular bellows portions 446c
disposed between side wall portions 446a, attached to the
side wall of the combustor tail tube 12, and the
peripheral wall portion 446b, substantially parallel to
the side wall of the combustor tail tube 12. The
perpendicular bellows portions 446c allow the liner
segment 446 to deform in the radial direction of arrow
"r" perpendicular to the side wall of the combustor tail
tube 12.</p>
    <p num="0020">Further, in an embodiment shown in Figures 7A and
7B, the liner segment 546 has side walls 546a terminated
by outwardly extending engagement portions 546b. Catches
13, which have Z-shaped section, are attached to the
outer surface of the side wall of the combustor tail tube
12. Engaging the engagement portions 546b with the
catches 13 allows the liner segments 546 to be attached
to, but movable relative to, the combustor tail tube 12.
By movably attaching the liner segment to the combustor
tail tube 12, the thermal stress due to the temperature
difference therebetween can be reduced or prevented.
Further, sealing members 548 may be disposed between the
engagement portions 546b and the catches 13 or combustor
tail tube 12. The sealing members 548 may comprise a
thermally resistive 0-ring, a thermally resistive C-ring,
a thermally resistive E-ring, a thermally resistive wire
mesh, or a thermally resistive brush seal.</p>
    <p num="0021">It will also be understood by those skilled in the
art that the forgoing description describes preferred
embodiments of the disclosed device and that various
changes and modifications may be made without departing
from the spirit and scope of the invention.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A gas turbine combustor comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a side wall for defining a combustion volume, the side
wall having upstream and downstream ends;</claim-text><claim-text>a pilot nozzle, disposed adjacent the upstream end of
the side wall, for discharging a pilot fuel to form diffusion
flame in the combustion volume;</claim-text><claim-text>a plurality of main nozzles, provided around the pilot
nozzles, for discharging a fuel-air mixture to form premixed
flames in the combustion volume; and</claim-text><claim-text>means for supplying film air into the combustion volume
downstream of the main nozzles along the inner surface of the
side wall to reduce the fuel-air ratio in a region adjacent
the inner surface of the side wall and to restrain a
combustion-driven oscillation in the combustion volume.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A gas turbine combustor, according to claim 1, wherein
the side wall includes a plurality of oscillation damping
orifices which are defined in a region downstream of the main
nozzles and extend radially through the side wall.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A gas turbine combustor comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a side wall for defining a combustion volume, the side
wall having upstream and downstream ends;</claim-text><claim-text>a pilot nozzle, disposed adjacent the upstream end of
the side wall, for discharging a pilot fuel to form diffusion
flame in the combustion volume;</claim-text><claim-text>a plurality of main nozzles, provided around the pilot
nozzles, for discharging a fuel-air mixture to form premixed
flames in the combustion volume; and</claim-text><claim-text>the side wall including a plurality of oscillation
damping orifices which are defined in a region downstream of
the main nozzles and extend radially through the side wall.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A gas turbine combustor according to claim 2 or 3,
further comprising an acoustic liner attached to the outer
surface of the side wall in a region where the oscillation
damping orifices are defined.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A gas turbine combustor according to claim 4, wherein
the acoustic liner comprises a plurality of liner segments
attached to the outer surface of the side wall.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A gas turbine combustor according to claim 5, wherein
the liner segments include bellows portions for reducing
thermal stress due to the temperature difference between the
side wall of the gas turbine combustor and the respective
liner segments.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A gas turbine combustor according to claim 5 or 6,
further comprising catches attached to the outer surface of
the side wall; and
   the liner segments including engagement portions for
engaging the catches whereby the engagement of the engaging
portions with the catches allows the liner segments to be
attached to the outer surface of the side wall.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A gas turbine combustor according to claim 7, further
comprising sealing members provided between the engaging
portions and the catches or the side wall.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>A gas turbine combustor according to any one of claims 1
to 8, wherein the side wall includes a plurality of steam
passages for allowing cooling steam to flow therethrough; and
   the oscillation damping orifices being disposed in lines
between the steam passages.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>A gas turbine combustor according to claim 9, wherein
the acoustic liner includes a peripheral wall facing the side
wall of the combustor and a plurality of air cooling orifices
defined in the peripheral wall disposed in lines aligned over
the lines of the oscillation damping orifices.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>A gas turbine combustor according to claim 10, wherein
the air cooling orifices are disposed to face the wall
portions between the adjoining oscillation damping orifices.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
