<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1246173-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1246173" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="18948217" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021002">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1246173-A2" status="new" fvid="23561791">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1246173</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021002</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02006197-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02006197</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020319</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001093941-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001093941</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010328</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B   7/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B   7/004       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B   7/0045      20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B   7/007       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B   7/007       20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B   7/125       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B   7/125       20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B   7/24        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B   7/24        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G11B   7/0045</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G11B   7/125C</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Optisches Aufzeichnungsmedium, optische Aufzeichnungsvorrichtung und optisches Aufzeichnungsverfahren</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Optical recording medium, optical recording device and optical recording method</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Support d'enregistrement optique, dispositif d'enregistrement optique et procédé d'enregistrement optique</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TDK CORP</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TDK CORPORATION</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>TDK Corporation</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1-13-1, Nihonbashi, Chuo-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo 103-8272</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>FUKUZAWA NARUTOSHI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TSUKAMOTO SYUJI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>FUKUZAWA, NARUTOSHI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TSUKAMOTO, SYUJI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>FUKUZAWA, NARUTOSHI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>c/o TDK Corporation, 1-13-1, Nihonbashi, Chuo-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo 103-8272</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>TSUKAMOTO, SYUJI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>c/o TDK Corporation, 1-13-1, Nihonbashi, Chuo-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo 103-8272</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Wagner, Karl H., Dipl.-Ing.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>WAGNER &amp;amp; GEYER Patentanwälte Gewürzmühlstrasse 5</street>
              <city>80538 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A laser beam is directed to an optical recording medium
such as a DVD-R to successively form thereon marks of a
length corresponding to data with a spacing disposed
therebetween. A Q value or the amount of reduction in time
causes the rise time of laser irradiation to be delayed
with respect to the scheduled rise time at least after a
spacing equal in length to the mark of the shortest length
employed for recording. The Q value satisfies the
following equation (1) expressed in terms of the
relationship between the recording speed n and an asymmetry.
That is,
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">(0.54×Asymmetry-1.1)/n≦Q≦ (0.54×Asymmetry-0.1)/n</st32:df>
where the asymmetry is the ratio of an amplitude of the
shortest mark to that of the longest mark of the recorded
marks.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="81"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to an optical recording
medium such as a DVD-R, and to a device and method for
optical recording information onto the optical recording
medium.</p>
    <p num="0002">In a high density optical recording medium such as a DVD-R,
laser pulses are directed to the recording layer, made of
organic dye or the like, in response to data to be recorded
thereon such that marks having a length corresponding to
the data are successively formed with a spacing disposed
between the marks. To accomplish high density recording on
such an optical recording medium, it is necessary to reduce
the marks and the spacing disposed therebetween as much as
possible.</p>
    <p num="0003">Laser pulses are directed to the recording layer at a
predetermined recording speed as mentioned above. The
energy of the laser pulses is accumulated in the marks
adjacent to each other along the direction of recording and
a spacing disposed therebetween, causing thermal
interference between a mark and the spacing. </p>
    <p num="0004">For example, to avoid the thermal interference, the
conventional DVD-R recording methods (strategies) include
dividing laser pulses, directed to a DVD-R to form marks
thereon, into a top pulse having a large pulse width and
multi-pulses repeated at short time intervals, thereby
preventing heat from being accumulated upon completion of
irradiation of the laser pulses.</p>
    <p num="0005">In addition to this, the recording strategy is changed
because of the following reasons to thereby control the
thermal interference.</p>
    <p num="0006">For example, consider two combinations: a combination of a
mark, a long spacing, and a mark; another combination of a
mark, a short spacing, and a mark. In these cases,
recording these combinations by the same recording strategy
would cause different amounts of heat to be accumulated in
each mark and different recording mark lengths to be
produced in the same duration of laser pulse irradiation
due to the difference in length of spacings disposed
between the recording marks. This would ultimately lead to
a difference in total jitter. Here, the total jitter means
the jitter of a recording mark/spacing produced along the
time axis and normalized with channel clocks. </p>
    <p num="0007">Suppose that a mark has been formed and is followed by a
short spacing. In this case, the amount of heat generated
during the formation of the mark would affect the mark
subsequent to the spacing, resulting in an elongated mark
and a shortened spacing.</p>
    <p num="0008">In the case of a DVD-R, such a thermal interference has a
serious effect on a combination of a 3T spacing disposed
between marks, the spacing having 3T (3 channel bit length)
equal in length to the shortest mark of the DVD.</p>
    <p num="0009">For this reason, such a recording strategy has been
conventionally employed for recording in which the start of
a laser top pulse subsequent to a predetermined short
spacing is delayed so as to shorten the length of an
emitted pulse than in other cases.</p>
    <p num="0010">The mark subsequent to a 3T spacing or the shortest spacing
would be seriously affected by the thermal interference.
Therefore, such a laser pulse delay time for shortening the
length of the mark and the amount of time reduction Q(ns)
after the 3T spacing are effective to prevent total jitter.</p>
    <p num="0011">As described above, Q can be used to form a mark subsequent
at least to a spacing equal in length to the shortest mark 
provided for recording. In any combinations of a mark, the
shortest spacing, and a mark or of a mark, a long spacing,
and a mark, this allows the lengths of the last marks (or
spacings) to be aligned with each other irrespective of the
length of the spacings, thereby reducing the total jitter.</p>
    <p num="0012">It has been conventionally practiced upon recording to
determine the optimum Q value based on an asymmetry
obtained by a signal after the recording or on a fixed
value employed for roughly expecting the power of the
asymmetry. However, different recorders provide different
expectation values and thus provide different asymmetries
upon recording the same optical recording medium, thereby
making it impossible to determine the optimum Q value in a
fixed manner.</p>
    <p num="0013">The present invention has been developed in view of the
aforementioned conventional problems. It is therefore an
object of the present invention to provide an optical
recording method, an optical recording device, and an
optical recording medium which find the relationship
between the asymmetry (recording power) and the optimum Q
value affected greatly by the asymmetry to provide total
jitter controlled in a good manner. </p>
    <p num="0014">The inventor has made intensive studies on optical
recording methods, optical recording devices, and optical
recording media. Consequently, the inventor found it
possible to provide the optimum Q value at least after a
spacing equal in length to the shortest mark employed for
recording by controlling the value in response to the power
and the recording speed of the laser beam upon recording.</p>
    <p num="0015">Accordingly, the aforementioned object can be accomplished
with the present invention described below.
<sl><li>(1) An optical recording method for successively forming
and thereby recording marks with a spacing disposed
therebetween by directing a laser beam in response to data
at a predetermined recording speed onto a recording layer
of an optical recording medium, the marks having a length
corresponding to the data to be recorded, the optical
recording medium comprising at least the recording layer
and an optical reflective layer on an optical transparent
substrate, the method comprising the step of: controlling,
in response to a power and a recording speed of the laser
beam upon recording, an amount of time reduction for
delaying a start time of a laser beam irradiation with
respect to a scheduled start time to shorten duration of
the laser beam irradiation at least after the spacing equal 
in length to a shortest mark employed for recording.</li><li>(2) An optical recording method for successively forming
and recording marks with a spacing disposed therebetween by
directing a laser beam in response to data at a
predetermined recording speed n onto a recording layer of
an optical recording medium, the marks having a length
corresponding to the data to be recorded, the optical
recording medium comprising at least the recording layer
and an optical reflective layer on an optical transparent
substrate, wherein an amount of time reduction Q(ns) for
delaying a start time of a laser beam irradiation with
respect to a scheduled start time to shorten duration of
the laser beam irradiation at least after the spacing equal
in length to a shortest mark employed for recording, the
recording speed n, and an asymmetry satisfy the following
equation (1),
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">(0.54×Asymmetry-1.1)/n≦Q≦(0.54×Asymmetry-0.1)/n</st32:df>
where the asymmetry is a ratio of an amplitude of the
shortest mark to that of a longest mark of recorded marks
and has a value of 0% or greater.</li><li>(3) An optical recording device for successively forming
and recording marks with a spacing disposed therebetween by
directing a laser beam in response to data at a 
predetermined recording speed onto a recording layer of an
optical recording medium, the marks having a length
corresponding to the data to be recorded, the optical
recording medium comprising at least the recording layer
and an optical reflective layer on an optical transparent
substrate, wherein an amount of time reduction for delaying
a start time of a laser beam irradiation with respect to a
scheduled start time to shorten duration of the laser beam
irradiation at least after the spacing equal in length to a
shortest mark employed for recording is controlled in
response to values of a power and the recording speed of
the laser beam upon recording.</li><li>(4) An optical recording device for successively forming
and recording marks with a spacing disposed therebetween by
directing a laser beam in response to data at a
predetermined recording speed n onto a recording layer of
an optical recording medium, the marks having a length
corresponding to the data to be recorded, the optical
recording medium comprising at least the recording layer
and an optical reflective layer on an optical transparent
substrate, wherein an amount of time reduction Q(ns) for
delaying a start time of a laser beam irradiation with
respect to a scheduled start time to shorten duration of
the laser beam irradiation at least after the spacing equal 
in length to a shortest mark employed for recording, the
recording speed n, and an asymmetry satisfy the following
equation (1),
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">(0.54×Asymmetry-1.1)/n≦Q≦(0.54×Asymmetry-0.1)/n</st32:df>
where the asymmetry is a ratio of an amplitude of the
shortest mark to that of a longest mark of recorded marks
and has a value of 0% or greater.</li><li>(5) An optical recording medium for successively forming
and recording marks thereon with a spacing disposed
therebetween by directing a laser beam in response to data
at a predetermined recording speed n onto a recording layer
of the optical recording medium comprising at least the
recording layer made of dye and an optical reflective layer
on an optical transparent substrate, the marks having a
length corresponding to the data to be recorded, wherein
an amount of time reduction Q(ns) for delaying a start time
of a laser beam irradiation with respect to a scheduled
start time to shorten duration of the laser beam
irradiation at least after the spacing equal in length to a
shortest mark employed for recording, the recording speed n,
and an asymmetry satisfy the following equation (1),
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">(0.54xAsymmetry-1.1)/n≦Q≦(0.54×Asymmetry-0.1)/n</st32:df>
where the asymmetry is a ratio of an amplitude of the
shortest mark to that of a longest mark of recorded marks 
and has a value of 0% or greater.</li><li>(6) An optical recording medium according to (5), in which
an optical constant k of the dye is 0.01 to 0.1 at a write
frequency of the laser beam.</li><li>(7) An optical recording medium for successively forming
and recording marks thereon with a spacing disposed
therebetween by directing a laser beam in response to data
at a predetermined recording speed n onto a recording layer
of the optical recording medium comprising at least the
recording layer and an optical reflective layer on an
optical transparent substrate, the marks having a length
corresponding to the data to be recorded, wherein
information on the optical strategy is pre-recorded on a
pre-recorded region, and the optical strategy is the method
comprising the step of: controlling, in response to a power
and a recording speed of the laser beam upon recording, an
amount of time reduction for delaying a start time of a
laser beam irradiation with respect to a scheduled start
time to shorten duration of the laser beam irradiation at
least after the spacing equal in length to a shortest mark
employed for recording.</li><li>(8) The optical recording medium according to (7), in which 
the optical recording medium is provided with a plurality
of grooves disposed at a predetermined pitch in the width
direction, a land is disposed between the grooves in
parallel to the grooves, and the pre-recorded region
includes at least one of a groove wobbling formed by
wobbling the grooves at a predetermined amplitude and space
frequency and an isolated pit disposed on top of the land
in accordance with a pre-specified rule.</li><li>(9) An optical recording medium for successively forming
and recording marks thereon with a spacing disposed
therebetween by directing a laser beam in response to data
at a predetermined recording speed n onto a recording layer
of the optical recording medium comprising at least the
recording layer and an optical reflective layer on an
optical transparent substrate, the marks having a length
corresponding to the data to be recorded, wherein
information on the optical strategy is pre-recorded on a
pre-recorded region, and in the optical strategy, an amount
of time reduction Q(ns) for delaying a start time of a
laser beam irradiation with respect to a scheduled start
time to shorten duration of the laser beam irradiation at
least after the spacing equal in length to a shortest mark
employed for recording, the recording speed n, and an
asymmetry satisfy the following equation (1), <st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">(0.54×Asymmetry-1.1)/n≦Q≦(0.54×Asymmetry-0.1)/n</st32:df>
where the asymmetry is a ratio of an amplitude of the
shortest mark to that of a longest mark of recorded marks
and has a value of 0% or greater.</li><li>(10) The optical recording medium according to (9), wherein
the optical recording medium is provided with a plurality
of grooves disposed at a predetermined pitch in a width
direction, a land is disposed between the grooves in
parallel to the grooves, and the pre-recorded region
includes at least one of a groove wobbling formed by
wobbling the grooves at a predetermined amplitude and space
frequency and an isolated pit disposed on top of the land
in accordance with a pre-specified rule.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0016">In the present invention, the optimum Q value at least
after a spacing equal in length to the shortest mark
employed for recording is controlled in accordance not only
with the combination of record marks and a spacing but also
with the recording power and speed upon recording.
Furthermore, the relationship between an asymmetry or the
ratio of the amplitude of the shortest recording mark to
that of the longest recording mark and the Q value is
defined, thereby giving the equation that provides good
total jitter. </p>
    <p num="0017">In the equation, n is expressed in [(channel bit
length) × (channel bit rate upon recording)]/reference speed,
and the reference speed is equal to channel bit length ×
reference channel bit rate.</p>
    <p num="0018">For a DVD, the channel bit length is 0.133µm, and the
channel bit rate is 26.16MHz.</p>
    <p num="0019">These and other objects, features and advantages of the
present invention will become more apparent upon a reading
of the following description and appended drawings.</p>
    <p num="0020">These and other objects and advantages of the present
invention will become clear from the following description
with reference to the accompanying drawings, wherein:
<sl><li>Fig. 1 is a partially exploded perspective view
illustrating the main portion of an optical recording
medium according to an embodiment of the present invention;</li><li>Fig. 2 is a block diagram illustrating an optical recording
device for implementing an optical recording method
according to an embodiment of the present invention; </li><li>Fig. 3 is a diagram illustrating a recording strategy
employed for the optical recording method according to the
present invention;</li><li>Fig. 4 is a diagram illustrating the definition of
variables in an equation for an asymmetry employed for the
optical recording method according to the present
invention;</li><li>Fig. 5 is a diagram illustrating the relationship between
the asymmetry and the power of laser beams provided for
optical recording operations;</li><li>Fig. 6 is a diagram illustrating the relationship between
the Q value and the asymmetry, employed to derive the
aforementioned equation;</li><li>Fig. 7 is a diagram illustrating the relationship between
the asymmetry, the total jitter, and the Q value;</li><li>Fig. 8 is an enlarged schematic view illustrating a pre-recorded
region where information on the recording strategy
according to the method of the present invention is prestored
on the optical recording medium; </li><li>Fig. 9 is a diagram illustrating the relationship between
the marks of 3T to 14T after the spacing of 3T and all
marks in terms of optical reflectivity along time axis with
the Q value being equal to 0 and the asymmetry being equal
to 5%;</li><li>Fig. 10(A) is the same diagram as Fig. 9, with the
asymmetry being equal to 5% and the Q value being equal to
+0.10T;</li><li>Fig. 10(B) is the same diagram as Fig. 9, with the
asymmetry being equal to 9% and the Q value being equal to
+0.10T;</li><li>Fig. 11(A) is the same diagram as Fig. 9, with the
asymmetry being equal to 6% and the Q value being equal to
+0.50T; and</li><li>Fig. 11(B) is the same diagram as Fig. 9, with the
asymmetry being equal to 10% and the Q value being equal to
+0.50T.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0021">Now, the present invention will be explained below in more
detail with reference to the accompanying drawings in
accordance with the embodiments. </p>
    <p num="0022">As shown in Fig. 1, an optical recording medium 10
according to an embodiment of the present invention is a
DVD-R having a recording layer 12 made of dye, and
comprises a substrate 14 made of a transparent base
material. The optical recording medium 10 also comprises
the recording layer 12 made of the dye that is applied to
cover grooves 16. The grooves 16 are formed on a surface
of the substrate 14 (on the upper surface in Fig. 1) to
guide a laser beam. the optical recording medium 10
further comprises a reflective film 18 that is made of gold,
silver, aluminum or the like and formed on top of the
recording layer 12 through sputtering or the like, and a
protective layer 20 for covering the outer surface of the
reflective film 18.</p>
    <p num="0023">The recording layer 12 is made of an organic dye, having an
optical constant k of 0.01 to 0.1, such as poly methine
cyanine or metal azo complex dye. The substrate 14 is made
of polycarbonate or polyolefin macromolecular polymer.</p>
    <p num="0024">An optical recording device 30 shown in Fig. 2 performs
optical recording operations on the optical recording
medium 10. </p>
    <p num="0025">The optical recording device 30, a DVD-R recorder in this
embodiment, actuates a spindle motor 32 via a spindle servo
31 to rotate the optical recording medium (DVD-R disk) 10
at a constant recording rate n. The optical recording
device 30 then allows a laser device 36 to emit a laser
beam directed to the recording layer 12 corresponding to
data being recorded, thereby successively forming marks
(recording marks) having a length corresponding to the data
with a spacing disposed therebetween.</p>
    <p num="0026">The laser device 36 emits a controlled number of laser
pulses according to the data to be recorded, the number of
laser pulses being controlled by a laser driver 38.</p>
    <p num="0027">There is provided a recording optical system, shown
generally by reference numeral 42 in Fig. 2, which includes
an objective lens 42A and a half mirror 42B. The objective
lens 42A is subjected to focus tracking control in a manner
such that a focus tracking servo 44 allows the laser beam
to be focused on the recording layer 12. In addition, the
objective lens 42A and the half mirror 42B are subjected to
the control of a feed servo 46 so as to move from the inner
to the outer circumference in synchronization with the
rotation of the optical recording medium 10. </p>
    <p num="0028">The spindle servo 31, the laser driver 38, the focus
tracking servo 44, and the feed servo 46 are controlled by
a controller 50. The data (information) to be recorded on
the recording layer 12 is delivered to the controller 50.</p>
    <p num="0029">Now, explained below is a recording strategy of optical
recording data onto the optical recording medium 10 or a
DVD-R using the optical recording device 30.</p>
    <p num="0030">In principle, as shown in Fig. 3, this recording strategy
is designed as follows. That is, the laser device 36 is
activated so as to launch a top pulse Ttop having an
elongated duration in time upon initiating the recording of
the data to be recorded, followed by multi-pulses (of a
pulse width Tmp) repeated at short time intervals. For
example, as shown at the center in Fig. 3, suppose that the
data to be recorded Twd is equal to 8T. In this case, the
recording strategy is performed using multi-pulses
consisting of the top pulse Ttop and five pulses (of Tmp)
repeated at short time intervals.</p>
    <p num="0031">On the other hand, to record the shortest data of 3T, the
recording strategy is performed using only the top pulse
Ttop. </p>
    <p num="0032">To form a mark of 3T or data of 3T, the preceding spacing
Tsp is set at 3T only in this case.</p>
    <p num="0033">In Fig. 3, it is seen that the start of the top pulse Ttop
is delayed with respect to that of the data to be recorded.
This is to avoid generating excessive heat due to the
presence of the heat accumulated as described above.</p>
    <p num="0034">In practice, the start of the top pulse Ttop is delayed by
Q(ns) with respect to the scheduled timing that is shown by
the solid line in Fig. 3.</p>
    <p num="0035">The value of Q after the spacing of 3T is operated in the
controller 50 as follows, and then controlled via the laser
driver 38.</p>
    <p num="0036">In this embodiment, the relationship between the optimum
asymmetry and the optimum Q value after the spacing of 3T
is defined by the following equation (1) to provide a good
total jitter. That is,
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">(0.54×Asymmetry-1.1)/n≦Q≦(0.54×Asymmetry-0.1)/n</st32:df>
where n is the recording speed. At n=1 or normal speed,
the recording speed is equal to 3.49m/s, while at n=2 or
double speed, the recording speed is 6.98m/s. The
asymmetry represents the ratio of the amplitude of the 
shortest mark to that of the longest mark (spacing), shown
by the following equation (2) according to the DVD
standards. That is,
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">Asymmetry=[(I14H+I14L)-(I3H+I3L)/[2*(I14H-I14L)]*100</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0037">In the above equation (2), it is assumed that I14 is the
amplitude width of the read signal for reading the longest
mark and I3 is the amplitude width of the read signal for
reading the shortest mark. Then, as shown in Fig. 4, by
definition, I14 has the peak height of I14H and the lowest
height of I14L, while I3 has the peak height of I3H and the
lowest height of I3L, each being measured from the zero
level.</p>
    <p num="0038">As shown in Fig. 5, the asymmetry and the power of the
light emitted from the laser device 36 are generally
proportional to each other irrespective of the recording
speed (excluding the region of the saturated amplitude of
I14).</p>
    <p num="0039">The preferably asymmetry is 0 to 12% and more preferably on
the order of 0 to 10%.</p>
    <p num="0040">The slope of the graph shown in Fig. 5 may conceivably be
varied or offset due to the thermal conductivity of the 
material of the recording layer 12, the thickness and
thermal conductivity of the reflective film 18, the amount
of heat generated upon decomposition of the dye of the
recording layer 12 upon recording (when irradiated with a
laser beam) and so forth. However, in practice, the
asymmetry and the power of the laser beam are always
proportional to each other. This proportionality is hardly
dependent on the value of Q which has been mentioned above.</p>
    <p num="0041">Here, in the equation (1), the recording speed n is the
reference speed of 3.49m/s at n=1 (1T = 38.15ns upon
recording at normal speed).</p>
    <p num="0042">The equation (1) shown above has been derived from the
relationships between the Q value and the asymmetry, and
between the total jitter, the asymmetry, and the Q value,
as shown in Figs. 6 and 7.</p>
    <p num="0043">It is necessary to pre-record the information on the
recording strategy onto the optical recording medium 10
before the medium is optical recorded. The information may
be recorded on the pre-recorded region 52 shown in Fig. 8.</p>
    <p num="0044">That is, the optical recording medium is provided with the
plurality of grooves 16 at a predetermined pitch in their 
width direction. Between the grooves 16, lands 54 are
disposed in parallel to the grooves 16. The pre-recorded
region 52 includes one of or both a wobbling portion 56 and
an isolated pit 58, where information on the recording
strategy is pre-recorded. Here, the wobbling portion 56 is
formed by wobbling the groove 16 at a predetermined
amplitude and space frequency, and the isolated pit 58 is
disposed on top of the land 54 in accordance with a pre-specified
rule.</p>
    <p num="0045">The above equation (1) was derived through the following
example and comparative example.</p>
    <p num="0046">An optical recording medium that was compatible with the
General Standards for DVD-R's was used for recording at
normal speed (n=1).</p>
    <p num="0047">The Asymmetry (hereinafter referred to as Asymm.) and Q
value were varied to measure deviations in the total jitter,
the marks after 3T spacing (3T to 11T and 14T), and all
marks.</p>
    <p num="0048">The recording strategy was employed so that 3Ttop is 1.65T,
4Ttop is 1.65T, Ttop after 5T is 1.70T, and Tmp is 0.7T. </p>
    <p num="0049">In Figs. 9 to 11, the vertical axis represents the
frequency of the marks formed and the horizontal axis
represents time at each point such as 3T mark and 4T mark.
The solid line represents each mark and the dashed line
represents the case of all marks. The frequency of the
marks has a Gaussian distribution preferably with a reduced
standard deviation and a reduced shift of a mark (solid
line) after a 3T spacing with respect to all marks (dashed
line).</p>
    <p num="0050">1. The reference recording speed was set at 3.49m/s and the
laser power was adjusted such that the Asymm. was 5% to
perform recording with the Q value of the write signal
after a 3T spacing being changed.</p>
    <p num="0051">The results were +1.6ns (+0.042T), +2.1ns (+0.055T), and
+2.6ns (+0.068T), at an Asymm. of 5%.</p>
    <p num="0052">As shown in Fig. 9 and Table 1, at the Q value equal to
zero, the comparison between the 3T mark (solid line) after
a 3T spacing and all marks (dashed line) tells that the 3T
mark after a 3T spacing is selectively shifted toward the
longer side with respect to all marks. The total jitter
was found to be 8.4% because of an increased heat
accumulation under these conditions as mentioned above and 
a shortened 3T spacing caused by the absence of a Q value
(see Fig. 9).</p>
    <p num="0053">At the Q value equal to +0.05T (=1.9ns), the lengths of the
3T mark after a 3T spacing and all marks generally match
with each other, with the total jitter being equal to 7.7%
(Fig. 11(A)).</p>
    <p num="0054">At the Q value equal to +0.06T (=2.3ns), the lengths of the
3T mark after a 3T spacing and all marks generally match
with each other, with the total jitter being equal to 7.6%.</p>
    <p num="0055">At the Q value equal to +0.10T (=3.8ns), the comparison
between the 3T mark after a 3T spacing and all marks tells
that the 3T mark after a 3T spacing is selectively shifted
toward the shorter side with respect to all marks. This is
because of a decreased heat accumulation under these
conditions and a shortened 3T spacing after a 3T spacing
caused by an elongated Q value. The total jitter was found
to be 8.2% (Fig. 10(A)).</p>
    <p num="0056">2. The reference recording speed was set at 3.49m/s and the
laser power was adjusted such that the Asymm. was 9% to
perform recording with the Q value of the write signal
after a 3T spacing being changed. </p>
    <p num="0057">The results were +3.8ns (+0.10T), +4.3ns (+0.11T), and
+4.8ns (+0.13T), at an Asymm. of 9%.</p>
    <p num="0058">At the Q value equal to +0.05T (=1.9ns), the comparison
between the 3T mark (solid line) after a 3T spacing and all
marks (dashed line) tells that the 3T mark after a 3T
spacing is selectively shifted toward the longer side with
respect to all marks. This shift took place because of the
aforementioned heat accumulation. The total jitter was
found to be 8.5% (Fig. 11(B)).</p>
    <p num="0059">At the Q value equal to +0.10T (=3.8ns), the lengths of the
3T mark after a 3T spacing and all marks generally match
with each other, with the total jitter being equal to 7.8%
(Fig. 10(B)).</p>
    <p num="0060">At the Q value equal to +0.12T (=+4.6ns), the lengths of
the 3T mark after a 3T spacing and all marks generally
match with each other, with the total jitter being equal to
8.0%.</p>
    <p num="0061">At the Q value equal to +0.15T (=+5.7ns), the comparison
between the 3T mark after a 3T spacing and all marks tells
that the 3T mark after a 3T spacing is selectively shifted 
toward the shorter side with respect to all marks. This is
because of a decreased heat accumulation under these
conditions and a shortened 3T spacing after a 3T spacing
caused by an elongated Q value. The total jitter was found
to be 9.8%.</p>
    <p num="0062">3. The reference recording speed was set at 3.49m/s and the
laser power was adjusted such that the Asymm. was 0% to
perform recording with the Q value of the write signal
after a 3T spacing being changed.</p>
    <p num="0063">At the Q value equal to -0.02T, the lengths of the 3T mark
after a 3T spacing and all marks generally match with each
other, with the total jitter being equal to 8.0%.</p>
    <p num="0064">At the Q value equal to -0.01T, the lengths of the 3T mark
after a 3T spacing and all marks generally match with each
other, with the total jitter being equal to 8.0%.</p>
    <p num="0065">At the Q value equal to 0.03T (=+1.1ns), the comparison
between the 3T mark after a 3T spacing and all marks tells
that the 3T mark after a 3T spacing is selectively shifted
toward the shorter side with respect to all marks. This is
because of a decreased heat accumulation under these
conditions and a shortened 3T spacing after a 3T spacing 
caused by an elongated Q value. The total jitter was found
to be 8.3%.</p>
    <p num="0066">At the Q value equal to 0.05T (=+1.9ns), the comparison
between the 3T mark after a 3T spacing and all marks tells
that the 3T mark after a 3T spacing is selectively shifted
toward the shorter side with respect to all marks. This is
because of a decreased heat accumulation under these
conditions and a shortened 3T spacing after a 3T spacing
caused by an elongated Q value. The total jitter was found
to be 8.7%.</p>
    <p num="0067">From the results in the foregoing, the relationship between
the optimum Q value and Asymm., which gives a target total
jitter value, is derived in the form of the aforementioned
equation (1). (Here, the target total jitter value of 8.0%
or less was defined as an acceptable result.)</p>
    <p num="0068">To measure the total jitter values and the mark lengths,
TA320 made by Yokogawa Electric Corporation was employed as
a measuring device. The asymmetry was measured using an
analog oscilloscope made by Iwatsu Electric Co., Ltd.</p>
    <p num="0069">The foregoing results are summarized in Table 1. <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center" namest="1">Asymm 5%</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">Q value Range</entry><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="3">(T):0.42T∼0.68T</entry></row><row><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="3">(ns):1.60∼2.60</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">-</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">Q value(ns)</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">Total Jitter</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">Drawing referenced</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">0T</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.0</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">8.4</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">Fig. 9</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">0.05T</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">1.9</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">7.7</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">Fig. 11(A)</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">0.06T</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">2.3</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">7.6</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">Fig. 11(B)</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">0.1T</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">3.8</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">8.2</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">Fig. 10(A)</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1">Asymm 9%</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">Q value Range</entry><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="3">(T) :0.099T∼0.125T</entry></row><row><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="3">(ns) :3.76∼4.76</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">-</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">Q value(ns)</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">Total Jitter</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">Drawing referenced</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">0.05T</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">1.9</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">8.5</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">Fig. 11(B)</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">0.1T</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">3.8</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">7.8</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">Fig. 10(B)</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">0.12T</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">4.6</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">8</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">0.15T</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">5.7</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">9.8</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1">Asymm 0%</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">Q value Range</entry><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="3">(T) :-0.029T∼-0.003T</entry></row><row><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="3">(ns) :-1.1∼-0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">-</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">Q value(ns)</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">Total Jitter</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">Drawing referenced</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">-0.02T</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">-0.8</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">8</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">-0.01T</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.4</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">8</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">0.03T</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">1.1</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">8.3</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">0.05T</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">1.9</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">8.7</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0070">The present invention, configured as described above,
allows an optimum Q value to be obtained at least after a
spacing equal in length to the shortest mark employed for
recording, thereby realizing an improved effect of reducing
the total jitter.</p>
    <p num="0071">Having now fully described the invention, it will be
apparent to one of ordinary skill in the art that many
changes and modifications can be made thereto without
departing from the spirit and scope of the invention as set
forth herein.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>An optical recording method for successively forming
and thereby recording marks with a spacing disposed
therebetween by directing a laser beam in response to data
at a predetermined recording speed onto a recording layer
of an optical recording medium, the marks having a length
corresponding to the data to be recorded, the optical
recording medium comprising at least the recording layer
and an optical reflective layer on an optical transparent
substrate, the method comprising the step of:
<claim-text><claim-text>controlling, in response to a power and a recording
speed of the laser beam upon recording, an amount of time
reduction for delaying a start time of a laser beam
irradiation with respect to a scheduled start time to
shorten duration of the laser beam irradiation at least
after the spacing equal in length to a shortest mark
employed for recording.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>An optical recording method for successively forming
and recording marks with a spacing disposed therebetween by
directing a laser beam in response to data at a
predetermined recording speed n onto a recording layer of
an optical recording medium, the marks having a length
corresponding to the data to be recorded, the optical
recording medium comprising at least the recording layer
and an optical reflective layer on an optical transparent
substrate, wherein
   an amount of time reduction Q(ns) for delaying a
start time of a laser beam irradiation with respect to a
scheduled start time to shorten duration of the laser beam
irradiation at least after the spacing equal in length to a
shortest mark employed for recording, the recording speed n,
and an asymmetry satisfy the following equation (1),
(0.54×Asymmetryl-1.1)/n≦Q≦(0.54×Asymmetry-0.1)/n
where the asymmetry is a ratio of an amplitude of the
shortest mark to that of a longest mark of recorded marks
and has a value of 0% or greater.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>An optical recording device for successively forming
and recording marks with a spacing disposed therebetween by
directing a laser beam in response to data at a
predetermined recording speed onto a recording layer of an
optical recording medium, the marks having a length
corresponding to the data to be recorded, the optical
recording medium comprising at least the recording layer
and an optical reflective layer on an optical transparent
substrate, wherein
   an amount of time reduction for delaying a start time
of a laser beam irradiation with respect to a scheduled
start time to shorten duration of the laser beam
irradiation at least after the spacing equal in length to a
shortest mark employed for recording is controlled in
response to values of a power and the recording speed of
the laser beam upon recording.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>An optical recording device for successively forming
and recording marks with a spacing disposed therebetween by
directing a laser beam in response to data at a
predetermined recording speed n onto a recording layer of
an optical recording medium, the marks having a length
corresponding to the data to be recorded, the optical
recording medium comprising at least the recording layer
and an optical reflective layer on an optical transparent
substrate, wherein
   an amount of time reduction Q(ns) for delaying a
start time of a laser beam irradiation with respect to a
scheduled start time to shorten duration of the laser beam
irradiation at least after the spacing equal in length to a
shortest mark employed for recording, the recording speed n,
and an asymmetry satisfy the following equation (1),
(0.54×Asymmetry-1.1)/n≦Q≦(0.54×Asymmetry-0.1)/n
where the asymmetry is a ratio of an amplitude of the
shortest mark to that of a longest mark of recorded marks
and has a value of 0% or greater.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>An optical recording medium for successively forming
and recording marks thereon with a spacing disposed
therebetween by directing a laser beam in response to data
at a predetermined recording speed n onto a recording layer
of the optical recording medium comprising at least the
recording layer made of dye and an optical reflective layer
on an optical transparent substrate, the marks having a
length corresponding to the data to be recorded, wherein
   an amount of time reduction Q(ns) for delaying a
start time of a laser beam irradiation with respect to a
scheduled start time to shorten duration of the laser beam
irradiation at least after the spacing equal in length to a
shortest mark employed for recording, the recording speed n,
and an asymmetry satisfy the following equation (1),
(0.54×Asymmetry-1.1)/n≦Q≦(0.54×Asymmetry-0.1)/n
where the asymmetry is a ratio of an amplitude of the
shortest mark to that of a longest mark of recorded marks
and has a value of 0% or greater.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The optical recording medium according to claim 5,
wherein
   an optical constant k of the dye is 0.01 to 0.1 at a
write frequency of the laser beam.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>An optical recording medium for successively forming
and recording marks thereon with a spacing disposed
therebetween by directing a laser beam in response to data
at a predetermined recording speed n onto a recording layer
of the optical recording medium comprising at least the
recording layer and an optical reflective layer on an
optical transparent substrate, the marks having a length
corresponding to the data to be recorded, wherein
   information on the optical strategy is pre-recorded
on a pre-recorded region, and the optical strategy is the
method comprising the step of:
<claim-text><claim-text>controlling, in response to a power and a recording
speed of the laser beam upon recording, an amount of time
reduction for delaying a start time of a laser beam
irradiation with respect to a scheduled start time to
shorten duration of the laser beam irradiation at least
after the spacing equal in length to a shortest mark
employed for recording.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The optical recording medium according to claim 7,
wherein
   the optical recording medium is provided with a
plurality of grooves disposed at a predetermined pitch in a
width direction,
   a land is disposed between the grooves in parallel to
the grooves, and
   the pre-recorded region includes at least one of a
groove wobbling formed by wobbling the grooves at a
predetermined amplitude and space frequency and an isolated
pit disposed on top of the land in accordance with a pre-specified
rule.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>An optical recording medium for successively forming
and recording marks thereon with a spacing disposed
therebetween by directing a laser beam in response to data
at a predetermined recording speed n onto a recording layer
of the optical recording medium comprising at least the
recording layer and an optical reflective layer on an
optical transparent substrate, the marks having a length
corresponding to the data to be recorded, wherein
   information on the optical strategy is pre-recorded
on a pre-recorded region, and in the optical strategy, an
amount of time reduction Q(ns) for delaying a start time of
a laser beam irradiation with respect to a scheduled start
time to shorten duration of the laser beam irradiation at
least after the spacing equal in length to a shortest mark
employed for recording, the recording speed n, and an
asymmetry satisfy the following equation (1),
(0.54×Asymmetry-1.1)/n≦Q≦(0.54×Asymmetry-0.1)/n
where the asymmetry is a ratio of an amplitude of the
shortest mark to that of a longest mark of recorded marks
and has a value of 0% or greater.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>The optical recording medium according to claim 9,
wherein
   the optical recording medium is provided with a
plurality of grooves disposed at a predetermined pitch in a
width direction,
   a land is disposed between the grooves in parallel to
the grooves, and
   the pre-recorded region includes at least one of a
groove wobbling formed by wobbling the grooves at a
predetermined amplitude and space frequency and an isolated
pit disposed on top of the land in accordance with a pre-specified
rule.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
