<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1264978-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1264978" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="19015660" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021211">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1264978-A2" status="new" fvid="23640553">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1264978</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021211</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02011883-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02011883</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020528</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001174365-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001174365</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010608</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F01N   3/08        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F01N   3/08        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F01N   3/20        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F01N   3/20        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F01N   3/28        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F01N   3/28        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F02D  41/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F02D  41/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F02D  45/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F02D  45/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F02D  41/02C4D1A</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">R01N3:08B6D</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">R01N570:04</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">De-Sulfatierung eines NOx-Speicherkatalysators</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Desulphating of nitrogen oxide trapping catalyst</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Désulfuration d'un piège catalytique de NOx</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NISSAN MOTOR</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NISSAN MOTOR CO., LTD.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Nissan Motor Co., Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>2 Takara-cho, Kanagawa-ku</street>
              <city>Yokohama-shi, Kanagawa</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ISHIZUKA YASUJI</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NISHII SATOSHI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SATO KENICHI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ISHIZUKA, YASUJI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NISHII, SATOSHI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SATO, KENICHI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>ISHIZUKA, YASUJI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>7359 Meadowridge Circle</street>
              <city>West Bloomfield, MI 48322</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>NISHII, SATOSHI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>D101, Green Terrace, 1692, Hazawa-cho, Kanagawa-ku</street>
              <city>Yokohama-shi, Kanagawa</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>SATO, KENICHI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>162-16, Gumisawa-cho, Totsuka-ku</street>
              <city>Yokohama-shi, Kanagawa</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Grünecker, Kinkeldey, Stockmair &amp;amp; Schwanhäusser Anwaltssozietät</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Maximilianstrasse 58</street>
              <city>80538 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>Sulphur oxides in the exhaust gas of a vehicle engine (1) are trapped by a
nitrogen oxide trapping catalyst (5A). A controller (6) calculates the sulphur oxide
poisoning amount of the trapping catalyst (5A) from the running condition of the
vehicle (S13), and desulphating the sulphur oxides by a removing mechanism (3,
4, 14). The release amount of sulphur oxides per unit time due to desulphating is
set as a parameter based on the sulphur oxide poisoning amount (S11), and by
integrating the calculated release amount using the parameter, the current poisoning
amount is calculated, and the release completion timing is precisely found.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="151" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="104"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0001">This invention relates to desulphating of a nitrogen oxide (NOx) trapping
catalyst for an internal combustion engine.</p>
    <heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0002">Tokkai 2000-73744 published by the Japanese Patent Office in 2000
discloses an exhaust purification device provided with a trapping catalyst which
prevents nitrogen oxides (NOx) contained in the exhaust gas from being released
into the atmosphere, when running the internal combustion engine at a lean
air-fuel ratio.</p>
    <p num="0003">The NOx trapping catalyst traps NOx contained in the exhaust gas of
the engine when it is run at a lean air-fuel ratio, and releases the trapped NOx
when the engine is run at a rich air-fuel ratio. The NOx released by the catalyst is
reduced by reducing agents in the exhaust gas such as hydrocarbons (HC) and
carbon monoxide (CO) that are generated due to combustion of a fuel mixture of a
rich air-fuel ratio, and is discharged into the atmosphere as nitrogen (N<sub>2</sub>).</p>
    <p num="0004">When the NOx trapping catalyst traps the NOx in the exhaust gas at
a lean air-fuel ratio, it also traps sulfur oxides (SOx) in the exhaust gas. The
sulfur oxides poisons the catalyst, and the NOx trapping performance declines the 
more the poisoning by SOx increases.</p>
    <p num="0005">In the prior art device, the trapped amount of SOx by the catalyst is
computed, and when the computed amount reaches an upper limit, the air-fuel
ratio of the air-fuel mixture supplied to engine is temporarily enriched and the
exhaust gas temperature is increased. Due to the increase of temperature of the
exhaust gas, the SOx trapped by the NOx trapping catalyst is released, and the
NOx trapping performance of the NOx trapping catalyst is recovered. This operation
is termed desulphating of the NOx trapping catalyst.</p>
    <heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0006">In the prior art device, the SOx release amount during desulphating of
the NOx trapping catalyst is calculated based on the assumption that the SOx
amount is released from the NOx trapping catalyst at a fixed rate. Desulphating
is performed until the trapped SOx amount decreases to a predetermined lower
limiting value.</p>
    <p num="0007">However, the inventors discovered experimentally that the SOx release
rate was not fixed, and differed according to the trapped amount. Therefore, if the
SOx release amount of the NOx trapping catalyst is calculated by setting the SOx
release rate constant, gross errors will arise in the calculation result and the
desulphating of the NOx trapping catalyst will not be performed correctly. Unless
desulphating is performed correctly, the NOx trapping performance of the NOx
trapping catalyst will not necessarily be recovered as desired. Moreover, as 
desulphating is accompanied by an enriching of the air-fuel ratio, desulphating of
low precision brings about an increase of engine fuel consumption.</p>
    <p num="0008">It is therefore an object of this invention to calculate the SOx release
amount during desulphating of a NOx trapping catalyst, correctly.</p>
    <p num="0009">In order to achieve the above object, this invention provides an exhaust
gas purification device for a vehicle engine. The device comprises a nitrogen oxide
trapping catalyst which traps nitrogen oxides in exhaust gas and the engine
comprises a mechanism which removes sulphur oxides which have poisoned the
nitrogen oxide trapping catalyst from the nitrogen oxide trapping catalyst.</p>
    <p num="0010">The device further comprises a sensor which detects a running condition
of the vehicle, and a programmable controller programmed to calculate a sulphur
oxide poisoning amount of the nitrogen oxide trapping catalyst from the running
condition of the vehicle, start operation of the mechanism when the sulphur oxide
poisoning amount reaches a predetermined amount, set a decrease amount per
unit time of the sulphur oxide poisoning amount during operation of the mechanism
as a parameter based on the sulphur oxide poisoning amount, calculate the
sulphur oxide poisoning amount during operation of the mechanism based on an
integral value of the decrease amount per unit time, and after operation of the
mechanism has started, stop operation of the mechanism when the sulphur oxide
poisoning amount has decreased to a predetermined desulphating completion
equivalent value. </p>
    <p num="0011">This invention also provides an exhaust gas purification method for
such a vehicle engine that comprises a nitrogen oxide trapping catalyst which
traps nitrogen oxides in exhaust gas, a mechanism for removing sulphur oxides
which have poisoned the nitrogen oxide trapping catalyst from the nitrogen oxide
trapping catalyst.</p>
    <p num="0012">The method comprises detecting a running condition of the vehicle,
calculating a sulphur oxide poisoning amount of the nitrogen oxide trapping
catalyst from the running condition of the vehicle, starting operation of the
removing mechanism when the sulphur oxide poisoning amount reaches a
predetermined amount, setting a decrease amount per unit time of the sulphur
oxide poisoning amount during operation of the removing mechanism as a parameter
based on the sulphur oxide poisoning amount, calculating the sulphur oxide
poisoning amount during operation of the removing mechanism based on an
integral value of the decrease amount per unit time, and stopping, after operation
of the removing mechanism has started, operation of the removing mechanism
when the sulphur oxide poisoning amount has decreased to a predetermined
desulphating completion equivalent value.</p>
    <p num="0013">The details as well as other features and advantages of this invention
are set forth in the remainder of the specification and are shown in the accompanying
drawings.</p>
    <heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
    <p num="0014">FIG. 1 is a schematic diagram of an internal combustion engine
provided with an exhaust purification device according to this invention.</p>
    <p num="0015">FIG. 2 is a flowchart describing a desulphating routine of a NOx
trapping catalyst performed by a controller according to this invention.</p>
    <p num="0016">FIG. 3 is a diagram showing a relation between the duration of SOx
desulphating and a SOx cumulative amount found experimentally by the inventors.</p>
    <p num="0017">FIG. 4 is a diagram describing the characteristics of a desulphating
constant table stored by the controller.</p>
    <p num="0018">FIGs. 5A-5D are timing charts describing the desulphating operation
performed by the controller.</p>
    <p num="0019">FIG. 6 is a flowchart describing an air-fuel ratio control subroutine
performed by the controller according to a second embodiment of this invention.</p>
    <p num="0020">FIG. 7 is a diagram describing the characteristics of a map of an
excess air factor stored by the controller according to the second embodiment of
this invention.</p>
    <heading>DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
    <p num="0021">Referring to FIG. 1 of the drawings, a multi-cylinder four-stroke cycle 
direct injection gasoline engine 1 for a vehicle comprises an intake passage 2
which aspirates air to a combustion chamber 1A formed in each cylinder, and an
exhaust passage 9 which discharges the exhaust gas from the combustion chamber
1A.</p>
    <p num="0022">The intake passage 2 is connected to the combustion chamber 1A via
a collector 21 and intake manifold 22. An air flow meter 7 which detects the
intake air amount, and a throttle 8 which regulates the intake air amount, are
provided in the intake passage 2. A fuel injector 3 injects fuel into the air
aspirated into the combustion chamber 1A and generates an air-fuel mixture. The
air-fuel mixture burns due to a spark plug 4 provided in the combustion chamber
1A which ignites the air-fuel mixture.</p>
    <p num="0023">The exhaust gas due to combustion of the air-fuel mixture is discharged
into the atmosphere via a catalytic converter 5 disposed midway along the exhaust
passage 9. Part of the exhaust gas is returned to the intake air through an
exhaust gas recirculation (EGR) passage 12 which connects the collector 21 with
the exhaust passage 9. The EGR passage 12 is provided with an EGR valve 14
which regulates the exhaust gas recirculation amount.</p>
    <p num="0024">The nitrogen oxide (NOx) contained in the exhaust gas of the air-fuel
mixture having a lean air-fuel ratio is trapped by a NOx trapping catalyst 5A
contained in the catalytic converter 5. The NOx trapping catalyst 5A releases the
trapped NOx and promotes the reduction thereof when it meets the exhaust gas
generated from an air-fuel mixture having a rich air-fuel ratio. A controller 6 
controls the fuel injection timing and injection period of the fuel injector 3,
ignition timing of the spark plug 4, and the opening of the EGR valve 14 by
signals.</p>
    <p num="0025">The controller 6 comprises a microcomputer provided with a central
processing unit (CPU), a read-only memory (ROM), a random access memory
(RAM) and an input/output interface (I/O interface). The controller 6 may also
comprise plural microcomputers.</p>
    <p num="0026">For this control, signals are input to the controller 6 from a throttle
opening sensor 18 which detects the opening of the throttle 8, an engine rotation
sensor 19 which detects a rotation speed of the engine 1, a vehicle speed sensor 20
which detects a running speed of the vehicle, a water temperature sensor 15 which
detects a cooling water temperature of the engine 1, and a universal exhaust gas
oxygen sensor 10 which detects the air -fuel ratio of the air -fuel mixture burnt by
the engine 1 from the exhaust gas composition of the exhaust passage 2, respectively.</p>
    <p num="0027">In the steady state of the engine 1, by controlling the fuel injection
amount of the fuel injector 3, the controller 6 burns an air-fuel mixture having a
lean air-fuel ratio with less fuel than the stoichiometric air-fuel ratio. The NOx
trapping catalyst of the catalytic converter 5 traps the NOx contained in the
exhaust gas of the engine 1 in this state. On the other hand, if the NOx trapping
catalyst traps a predetermined amount of NOx, by controlling the fuel injection
amount of the fuel injector 3, the controller 6 burns an air-fuel mixture having a
rich air-fuel ratio with more fuel than the stoichiometric air-fuel ratio, and 
regenerates the NOx trapping catalyst by releasing the NOx trapped by the NOx
trapping catalyst and reducing NOx by HC and CO, which are reducing agents
contained in exhaust gas generated under a rich air-fuel ratio.</p>
    <p num="0028">Apart from the NOx trapping and regeneration of this catalyst, the
controller 6 calculates a SOx cumulative amount of the NOx trapping catalyst in
the catalytic converter 5. The SOx cumulative amount is calculated by accumulating
a NOx trap amount of the catalyst per unit time.</p>
    <p num="0029">If the SOx cumulative amount reaches a predetermined amount, the
controller 6 performs desulphating. Here, desulphating is a general term for three
kinds of control, i.e., making the air -fuel ratio of the air-fuel mixture burnt in the
engine 1 richer by controlling the fuel injection amount of the fuel injector 3,
delaying the ignition timing of the spark plug 4, and stopping EGR by controlling
the EGR valve 4. The enrichment of the air-fuel ratio promotes reduction of SOx
released from the NOx trapping catalyst. The delay of ignition timing and stopping
of EGR bring about a rise of exhaust temperature required to make the NOx
trapping catalyst release SOx.</p>
    <p num="0030">The controller 6 calculates the SOx cumulative amount of the NOx
trapping catalyst as follows during desulphating. The SOx release amount per
unit time released by desulphating is calculated, and the SOx cumulative amount
per unit time is calculated by deducting the SOx release amount per unit time
from the SOx trap amount per unit time. As the SOx release amount per unit
time exceeds the SOx trap amount per unit time during desulphating, the SOx 
cumulative amount per unit time is a negative value that makes the SOx cumulative
amount decrease. The controller 6 terminates desulphating when the SOx cumulative
amount becomes zero. The SOx release amount per unit time in this calculation
process, i.e., the SOx release rate, is not fixed.</p>
    <p num="0031">Referring to FIG. 3, according to the research of the inventors, the
variation in the SOx cumulative amount with respect to the length of the SOx
desulphating operation can be represented by a curve as shown in the drawing.
This curve is obtained at a constant vehicle speed at which the SOx trapping rate
of the NOx trapping catalyst is constant. The slope of the curve in this drawing is
therefore considered to represent the SOx release rate. The curve shows that the
SOx release rate is larger, the larger the SOx cumulative amount becomes, and
the SOx release rate is large in the early stages of the SOx desulphating operation.
Unless the calculation of the variation in the SOx cumulative amount is performed
correctly, the completion of desulphating cannot be determined correctly.
Consequently, if desulphating is terminated before desulphating is completed, the
NOx trapping performance of the NOx trapping catalyst will not fully recover. On
the other hand, if desulphating is continued even after desulphating is completed,
the fuel consumption of the engine 1 will increase.</p>
    <p num="0032">The controller 6 calculates a SOx release amount per unit time <i>RSMILE,</i>
i.e., a SOx release rate, using equation (1), considering the characteristics of the
SOx release rate as mentioned above.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center"><st32:italic>RSMILE</st32:italic> = <st32:italic>SOXMILE</st32:italic><st32:sub pos="post">-1</st32:sub> · <st32:italic>RSMILE1</st32:italic> + <st32:italic>RSMILE2</st32:italic></st32:df> 
   where, <i>SOXMILE<sub>-1</sub></i> = the SOx cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE</i> one unit

time ago, and

   <i>RSMILE1</i>, <i>RSMILE2=</i> coefficients.</p>
    <p num="0033">The coefficients <i>RSMILE1</i>, <i>RSMILE2</i> are set experimentally beforehand.
The SOx release rate <i>RSMILE</i> is equal to the slope of the curve of the variation in
the SOx cumulative amount shown in FIG. 3. Equation (1) calculates the SOX
release rate <i>RSMILE</i> at the point X in FIG. 3, by calculating the slope of the
straight line connecting the points X and Y separated by the unit time. As shown
in FIG. 3, the SOx release rate is larger, the larger the SOX cumulative amount
<i>SOXMILE</i> becomes.</p>
    <p num="0034">If the coefficients <i>RSMILE1 and RSMILE2</i> are defined, it is possible
to summarize a table showing the relation between the SOx cumulative amount
<i>SOXMILE</i> and the SOx release rate <i>RSMILE</i> in FIG. 4. In this table, the SOx
cumulative amount is divided into five regions by four boundary values, <i>SXMIL1 -
SXMIL4,</i> and the SOx release rate <i>RSMILE</i> is set as five fixed values, <i>RSML1 -
RSML5</i>, according to the region.</p>
    <p num="0035">Here, <i>SXMIL1 &gt; SXMIL2 &gt; SXMIL3 &gt; SXMIL4 &gt; SXMIL5,</i> and <i>RSML1
&gt; RSML2 &gt; RSML3 &gt; RSML4 &gt; RSML5.</i></p>
    <p num="0036">That is, the SOx release rate <i>RSMILE is</i> larger the SOx cumulative
amount <i>SOXMILE</i> becomes. This table or a map specifying the same characteristics
is stored beforehand in the memory of the controller 6, and the controller 6 can 
also obtain the SOx decreasing rate <i>RSMILE</i> from the SOx cumulative amount
<i>SOXMILE</i> by looking up the prestored table or map.</p>
    <p num="0037">Now, if the exhaust temperature exceeds 650°C even when desulphating
is not performed, the NOx trapping catalyst will release trapped SOx. Therefore, if
this temperature condition holds, the controller 6 calculates the SOx cumulative
amount considering the variation characteristics of the SOx cumulative amount
in the same way as when desulphating is performed, even if desulphating is not
performed.</p>
    <p num="0038">Next, the desulphating routine performed for the above control by the
controller 6 will be described, referring to FIG. 2. This routine is performed at an
interval of ten milliseconds during the running of the engine.</p>
    <p num="0039">The controller 6 reads the vehicle speed <i>V</i> detected by the vehicle
speed sensor 20 in a step S1.</p>
    <p num="0040">In a following step S2, the SOX cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE<sub>-1</sub></i>
calculated on the immediately occasion when the routine was performed, is compared
with an upper limiting value <i>SOXFUL</i>. The upper limiting value <i>SOXFUL</i> is a
value for determining whether desulphating of the NOx trapping catalyst is performed,
and is set as a value equivalent to ten percent of the physical upper limiting value
of the SOx trap or poisoning of the NOx trapping catalyst.</p>
    <p num="0041">The SOx cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE</i> in this routine while 
desulphating is not performed is converted into and expressed in mileage of vehicle
travel. Correspondingly, the upper limiting value <i>SOXFUL</i> is expressed in mileage.
Therefore, if the physical upper limiting value of the SOx cumulative amount of
the NOx trapping catalyst is 8000km, the upper limiting value <i>SOXFUL</i> is 800km.</p>
    <p num="0042">Now, in the step S2, if the SOX cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE<sub>-1</sub></i>
calculated on the immediately occasion when the routine was performed does not
exceed the upper limiting value <i>SOXFUL</i>, the controller 6 determines whether or
not the desulphating flag <i>FLS1 is</i> unity in a step S4. The desulphating flag <i>FLS1</i>
is a flag which is set to unity when the SOX poisoning amount S<i>OXMILE<sub>-1</sub></i>
calculated on the immediately occasion when the routine was performed exceeds
the upper limiting value <i>SOXFUL,</i> and it is reset to zero when desulphating is
completed. Therefore, when the desulphating flag <i>FLS1</i> is zero, it shows that the
desulphating operation is not required. When the desulphating flag <i>FLS1</i> is unity,
it shows that the desulphating operation is required.</p>
    <p num="0043">When the desulphating flag <i>FLS1</i> is unity in the step S4, the controller
6 processes a step S5. When the desulphating flag <i>FLS1</i> is not unity, i.e., in the
case of zero, the controller 6 determines whether or not the vehicle speed <i>V</i> has
reached the predetermined speed <i>VSP2</i> in a step S8.</p>
    <p num="0044">As mentioned above, the NOx trapping catalyst releases SOx when the
exhaust gas is at a high temperature of 650°C or more even if desulphating is not
performed. As the exhaust gas temperature is higher the faster the vehicle runs,
according to this routine, it is determined whether or not the exhaust gas temperature 
exceeds 650°C by determining whether or not the vehicle speed <i>V</i> exceeds the
predetermined speed <i>VSP2.</i> The predetermined speed <i>VSP2 is</i> therefore a vehicle
speed corresponding to the exhaust temperature of 650°C, for example, 110-120
km/hr. Here, the predetermined speed <i>VSP2</i> is set to 110 km/hr. The predetermined
speed <i>VSP2</i> is preferably determined experimentally beforehand.</p>
    <p num="0045">If the vehicle speed <i>V</i> does not exceed the predetermined speed <i>VSP2</i>
in the step S8, the NOx trapping catalyst does not release SOx. In this case, the
controller 6 performs the processing of a step S12 after setting the SOx release
rate <i>RSMILE</i> to zero in a step S9. When the vehicle speed <i>V</i> exceeds the
predetermined speed <i>VSP2</i> in the step S8, the NOx trapping catalyst releases
SOx. In this case, the controller 6 processes the step S11.</p>
    <p num="0046">Now, in the step S2, when the SOX cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE<sub>-1</sub></i>
exceeds the upper limiting value <i>SOXFUL</i>, desulphating is required. In this case,
in the step S3, the controller 6 sets the desulphating operation flag <i>FLS1</i> to
unity.</p>
    <p num="0047">In a following step S5, it is determined whether or not the vehicle
speed <i>V</i> has reached the predetermined speed <i>VSP1.</i> The predetermined velocity
<i>VSP1 is</i> a value for determining whether or not the minimum exhaust temperature
required to release SOx is obtained by performing desulphating of the NOx trapping
catalyst. As mentioned above, from the relation between exhaust gas temperature
and vehicle speed <i>V</i>, if the vehicle speed has reached the predetermined speed
<i>VSP1</i>, it is determined that the NOx trapping catalyst can release SOx by 
desulphating. On the other hand, if the vehicle speed <i>V</i> has not reached the
predetermined speed <i>VSP1</i>, it is determined that the NOx trapping catalyst does
not release SOx even if desulphating is performed.</p>
    <p num="0048">Here, the predetermined speed <i>VSP1 is</i> determined as follows.</p>
    <p num="0049">That is, it is determined taking consideration of whether the temperature
of the NOx trapping catalyst reaches the SOx release temperature of 650°C by
performing desulphating. In other words, the vehicle speed equivalent to a
temperature obtained by deducting a temperature rise part due to desulphating
from 650°C, is <i>VSP1</i>. Although the temperature rise due to desulphating changes
with the specification of the exhaust purification device or engine, it is considered
to be from 70°C to 100°C. As a result, if the exhaust temperature is 550°C to
580°C, the exhaust gas temperature will reach 650°C by desulphating. The vehicle
speed equivalent to the exhaust gas temperature of 550°C-580°C is, for example,
90-100 km/hr. Here, the predetermined vehicle speed <i>VSP1</i> is set to 90 km/hr. It
is desirable to set the predetermined vehicle speed <i>VSP1</i> by determining it
experimentally beforehand.</p>
    <p num="0050">Now, in the step S5, if the vehicle speed <i>V</i> has reached the predetermined
speed <i>VSP1</i>, the controller 6 will perform desulphating in the step S10. Desulphating
means three operations, i.e. enrichment of the air-fuel ratio of the air-fuel mixture
by increasing the fuel injection amount of the fuel injector 3, delay of ignition
timing of the spark plug 4, and closing of the EGR valve 4 as mentioned above. </p>
    <p num="0051">These operations are performed by signals output from the controller 6
to the fuel injector 3, spark plug 4 and EGR valve 14.</p>
    <p num="0052">As seen from the flowcharts, desulphating is performed in the step
S10 if it is determined that the SOx cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE<sub>-1</sub></i> exceeds the
upper limiting value <i>SOXFUL</i> in the step S2, or desulphating is continuing in the
step S4, in addition to the condition that the exhaust gas temperature represented
by the vehicle speed <i>V</i> is in a region suitable for desulphating.</p>
    <p num="0053">After desulphating, in a step S11, the controller 6 calculates the SOx
release rate <i>RSMILE</i> using the above-mentioned equation (1).</p>
    <p num="0054">As the NOx trapping catalyst releases SOx when the vehicle speed <i>V</i>
exceeds the predetermined speed <i>VSP2</i> in the step S8, even if desulphating is not
performed, the SOx release rate <i>RSMILE is</i> calculated in the step S11 also in that
case. The controller 6 processes the step S12 after the processing of the step S11.</p>
    <p num="0055">On the other hand, if the vehicle speed <i>V</i> has not reached the
predetermined speed <i>VSP1</i> in the step S5, the controller 6 sets the SOx release
rate <i>RSMILE</i> to zero in the step S6.</p>
    <p num="0056">In the following step S7, the controller 6 stops desulphating by a
signal output to the fuel injector 3, spark plug 4 and EGR valve 14. The controller
6 processes the step S12 after the processing of the step S7. </p>
    <p num="0057">In the step S12, the controller 6 calculates a SOx trap amount Δ<i>V</i> per
unit time. The SOx amount trapped by the NOx trapping catalyst has an intimate
relation with the mileage of the vehicle. The mileage is obtained by integrating the
vehicle speed <i>V.</i> Here, the cumulative amount SOxΔ<i>V</i> per unit time corresponding
to the execution interval of the routine, is calculated as a difference of an integral
<i>Vx</i> of the vehicle speed <i>V,</i> and an integral <i>Vx<sub>-1</sub></i> on the immediately preceding
occasion when the routine was performed. In other words, the SOx trap amount
Δ<i>V</i> per unit time is represented by the mileage achieved per unit time.</p>
    <p num="0058">In the following step S13, the controller 6 calculates the SOx cumulative
amount <i>SOXMILE</i> by the next equation (2) using the SOx release rate <i>RSMILE</i>
which were set in the steps S6, S9 or S11, and the SOx trap amount <i>ΔV</i> per unit
time.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center"><st32:italic>SOXMILE</st32:italic> = <st32:italic>SOXMILE</st32:italic><st32:sub pos="post">-1</st32:sub> + Δ<st32:italic>V</st32:italic> - <st32:italic>RSMILE</st32:italic></st32:df>
   where, <i>SOXMILE<sub>-1</sub> = SOXMILE</i> calculated on the immediately

      preceding occasion the routine was executed.</p>
    <p num="0059">In the following step S14, it is determined whether the SOx cumulative
amount <i>SOXMILE</i> is zero. This is a step which determines whether or not SOx
desulphating was completed. When the SOX cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE is</i>
zero, the controller 6 resets the desulphating flag <i>FLS1</i> to zero in a step S15.</p>
    <p num="0060">In a following step S16, the controller 6 stops desulphating as in the
processing of the step S7 by signals output to the fuel injector 3, spark plug 4 and 
the EGR valve 14. The engine 1 is therefore run at an air-fuel ratio, ignition
timing and exhaust gas recirculation amount which are usually applied to normal
running. The controller 6 processes the step S17 after the processing of the step
S16.</p>
    <p num="0061">In the step S14, when the SOx cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE</i> is not
zero, steps S15 and S16 are skipped and the step S17 is processed.</p>
    <p num="0062">In the step S17, after storing the mileage <i>Vx</i> and the SOx cumulative
amount <i>SOXMILE</i> in a memory as <i>Vx<sub>-1</sub></i>, <i>SOXMILE<sub>-1</sub></i>, respectively, the controller 6
terminates the routine.</p>
    <p num="0063">In the step S14, it is determined whether or not desulphating is
complete by determining whether or not the SOX cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE is</i>
zero, but whether or not desulphating is complete can also be determined by
setting a minimum valve of the SOx cumulative amount at which the NOx
trapping catalyst effectively completes SOx release, and comparing this minimum
value with the SOx cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE.</i></p>
    <p num="0064">Next, the variation of the SOx cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE</i> of the
NOx trapping catalyst in the aforesaid routine will be described referring to FIGs.
5A-5D.</p>
    <p num="0065">The SOx cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE</i> of the NOx trapping catalyst
increases with the vehicle running distance. If the vehicle speed <i>V</i> exceeds the 
predetermined speed <i>VSP2</i> during a run as shown in section A of FIG. 5B, the
NOx catalyst temperature will rise above 650°C, and the NOx trapping catalyst
will release SOx. Consequently, as shown in FIG. 5A, the SOx cumulative
amount <i>SOXMILE</i> decreases.</p>
    <p num="0066">If the section in which the vehicle speed <i>V</i> does not exceed the
predetermined vehicle speed <i>VSP2</i> continues for some time, the SOx cumulative
amount <i>SOXMILE</i> of the NOx trapping catalyst continues to increase, and eventually
exceeds the upper limiting value <i>SOXFUL</i> shown by the point B of FIG. 5A.
Consequently, the desulphating flag <i>FLS1 changes</i> from zero to unity as shown in
FIG. 5C. However, if the vehicle speed <i>V</i> at this time does not exceed the
predetermined speed <i>VSP1,</i> the controller 6 does not perform desulphating.</p>
    <p num="0067">When the desulphating flag <i>FLS1</i> is unity, and the vehicle speed <i>V</i>
exceeds the predetermined velocity <i>VSP1</i> as shown by the point C of FIG. 5B, the
controller 6 performs desulphating as shown by FIG. 5D, and release of SOx from
the NOx trapping catalyst is promoted due to enrichment of the air fuel ratio and
rise in temperature of the exhaust gas. As a result, the SOx cumulative amount
<i>SOXMILE</i> decreases and eventually becomes zero as shown by the point F in FIG.
5A. When the SOx cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE</i> becomes zero, the controller 6
stops desulphating as shown by FIG. 5D.</p>
    <p num="0068">As can be seen from FIG. 5A, the decrease of the SOx cumulative
amount <i>SOXMILE</i> of the NOx trapping catalyst is not linear, but the decrease
rate increases the larger the SOX poisoning amount <i>SOXMILE</i> becomes, and in 
the latter half of SOx release, the decrease rate of the SOx cumulative amount
<i>SOXMILE</i> gradually becomes smaller. In this case, if it was assumed that the
SOx release rate <i>RSMILE is</i> a fixed value, and the SOx cumulative amount
<i>SOXMILE</i> is calculated based on the constant release rate, the timing when the
SOx desulphating procedure is completed will be largely different from the timing
when the SOx desulphating procedure is actually completed.</p>
    <p num="0069">In this exhaust gas purification device, as shown by the step S11 of
the routine of FIG. 2, the controller 6 calculates the SOx release amount <i>RSMILE</i>
using a coefficient <i>RSMILE1</i> set according to the elapsed time from the start of
desulphating, and a coefficient <i>RSMILE2</i> set based on the SOx cumulative amount
<i>SOXMILE.</i> The SOx cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE</i> can therefore -precisely trace
the actual variation in the SOx cumulative amount of the NOx trapping catalyst.</p>
    <p num="0070">Therefore, desulphating is performed not too much and not too little,
and release of SOx can be completed in a short time without wastage. The
increase of fuel consumption due to desulphating can also be suppressed to the
lowest limit. Further, the fact that completion of SOx release can be precisely
known has a desirable effect on the determining precision of desulphating on the
next occasion.</p>
    <p num="0071">On the other hand, even during the desulphating period when the
desulphating flag <i>FLS1</i> is unity, when the vehicle speed <i>V</i> is less than the
predetermined vehicle speed <i>VSP1,</i> as the exhaust gas temperature is too low, the
NOx trapping catalyst cannot release SOx even if desulphating is performed. In 
this case, desulphating is prevented from being performed in the step S7 of the
routine of FIG. 2, so an increase in the fuel consumption which does not contribute
to promote SOx release is also prevented. The region D in FIG. 5B corresponds to
this state. Thus, if desulphating is interrupted due to the lowering of the vehicle
speed <i>V,</i> a desulphating flag <i>FLS1 can</i> be held at unity as shown in FIG. 5C.
Desulphating is then performed when the vehicle speed <i>V</i> reaches the predetermined
vehicle speed <i>VSP1 at</i> a point E in FIG. 5B. While the desulphating is being
interrupted, the SOx release rate <i>RSMILE</i> is set to zero in the step S6, so the
calculation precision of the SOx cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE</i> is not impaired
while desulphating is interrupted.</p>
    <p num="0072">Next, a second embodiment of this invention will be described referring
to FIGs. 6, 7.</p>
    <p num="0073">This embodiment relates to desulphating performed by the controller 6
in the step S10 of FIG. 2. In this embodiment, when the controller 6 performs
desulphating, the richness of the air-fuel ratio of the air-fuel mixture burnt by the
engine 1 is varied according to the SOx cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE</i> by performing
the subroutine shown in FIG. 6.</p>
    <p num="0074">Specifically, first in a step S101, the controller 6 calculates a rich
correction amount of an excess air factor by looking up a map having the
characteristics shown in FIG. 7 which is prestored in the memory of the controller
6, based on the SOx cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE<sub>-1</sub></i>. </p>
    <p num="0075">Here, the excess air factor is a value obtained by dividing the air-fuel
ratio by the stoichiometric air-fuel ratio, where unity denotes the stoichiometric
air-fuel ratio, a value larger than unity denotes a lean air-fuel ratio and a value
less than unity denotes a rich air-fuel ratio.</p>
    <p num="0076">The map shown in FIG. 7 has characteristics such that the excess air
factor approaches unity, the smaller the SOx cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE</i> during
desulphating becomes. In this map, the excess air factor during desulphating is
set to 0.99, and the excess air factor decreases as the SOx cumulative amount
<i>SOXMILE</i> increases. In other words, the richness of the air-fuel ratio increases.
The controller 6 determines a target excess air factor from this map, and calculates
a correction amount of the fuel injection amount corresponding to the difference
between the excess air factor for desulphating and the target excess air factor for
the state where desulphating is not performed.</p>
    <p num="0077">In a next step 102, the target fuel injection amount is corrected by the
correction amount.</p>
    <p num="0078">In a next step S103, the controller 6 outputs a signal corresponding to
the corrected target fuel injection amount to the fuel injector 3, and terminates
the routine.</p>
    <p num="0079">In this way, regarding the desulphating of the step S10, varying the
richness of the air-fuel of the air-fuel mixture which is burnt by the engine 1
according to the SOx cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE is</i> desirable from the viewpoint 
of suppressing increase of fuel consumption accompanying the desulphating process.</p>
    <p num="0080">When the SOx cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE</i> is near zero, as seen
from FIG. 3, the SOx release rate <i>RSMILE is</i> small, and <i>RSMILE</i> does not
increase even if the air-fuel ratio is enriched. In this embodiment, in this case, a
rich air-fuel ratio near the stoichiometric air-fuel ratio is applied, so ineffective
fuel consumption can be prevented.</p>
    <p num="0081">The contents of Tokugan 2001-174365, with a filing date of June 8,
2001 in Japan, are hereby incorporated by reference.</p>
    <p num="0082">Although the invention has been described above by reference to certain
embodiments of the invention, the invention is not limited to the embodiments
described above. Modifications and variations of the embodiments described above
will occur to those skilled in the art, in light of the above teachings.</p>
    <p num="0083">For example, as a variation of the air-fuel ratio control, instead of
setting a target air-fuel ratio according to the SOx cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE</i>,
a target air-fuel ratio can also be set according to the elapsed time from the start
of desulphating. In this case, the rich air-fuel ratio is made to approach the
stoichiometric air-fuel ratio as the elapsed time increases. Also, after desulphating
is interrupted due to a decrease of the vehicle speed,the desulphating may be
resumed in a state where the SOx cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE is</i> less than the
upper limiting value <i>SOXFUL</i>. In this case, to perform appropriate air-fuel ratio
control, the target air-fuel ratio when desulphating starts may be set according to 
the SOx cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE.</i> In the above description, the SOx cumulative
amount <i>SOXMILE</i> corresponds to the sulphur oxide poisoning amount, and the
decrease rate of SOx cumulative amount <i>SOXMILE,</i> i.e., Δ<i>V - RSMILE,</i> corresponds
to the decrease amount per unit time of the sulphur oxide poisoning amount.</p>
    <p num="0084">The embodiments of this invention in which an exclusive property or
privilege is claimed are defined as follows:</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>An exhaust gas purification device for a vehicle engine (1) comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a nitrogen oxide trapping catalyst (5A) which traps nitrogen oxides in exhaust
gas, the engine (1) comprising a mechanism (3, 4, 14) which removes sulphur
oxides which have poisoned the nitrogen oxide trapping catalyst (5A) from the
nitrogen oxide trapping catalyst (5A);</claim-text><claim-text>a sensor (20) which detects a running condition of the vehicle; and</claim-text><claim-text>a programmable controller (6) programmed to:
<claim-text><claim-text>calculate a sulphur oxide poisoning amount of the nitrogen oxide trapping
catalyst (5A) from the running condition of the vehicle (S13);</claim-text><claim-text>start operation of the mechanism (3, 4, 14) when the sulphur oxide
poisoning amount reaches a predetermined amount (S2);</claim-text><claim-text>set a decrease amount per unit time of the sulphur oxide poisoning
amount during operation of the mechanism (3, 4, 14) as a parameter based
on the sulphur oxide poisoning amount (S11);</claim-text><claim-text>calculate the sulphur oxide poisoning amount during operation of the
mechanism (3, 4, 14) based on an integral value of the decrease amount per
unit time (S13); and</claim-text><claim-text>after operation of the mechanism (3, 4, 14) has started, stop operation of
the mechanism (3, 4, 14) when the sulphur oxide poisoning amount has
decreased to a predetermined desulphating completion equivalent value (S14,
S16).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The exhaust gas purification device as defined in Claim 1, wherein the controller
(6) is further programmed to set the decrease amount per unit time to a larger
value, the larger the sulphur oxide poisoning amount becomes (S11).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The exhaust gas purification device as defined in Claim 1 or Claim 2, wherein
the controller (6) is further programmed to set the decrease amount per unit time
to a smaller value as an elapsed time from start-up of the mechanism (3, 4, 14)
increases (S11).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The exhaust gas purification device as defined in any one of Claim 1 through
Claim 3, wherein the exhaust gas purification device further comprises a sensor
(20) which detects a temperature of the exhaust gas, and the controller (6) is
further programmed not to start operation of the mechanism (3, 4, 14) when the
temperature of the exhaust gas is less than a predetermined temperature (S5, S7).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The exhaust gas purification device as defined in Claim 4, wherein the controller
(6) is further programmed to stop operation of the mechanism (3, 4, 14), when the
temperature of the exhaust gas is less than the predetermined temperature after
the mechanism (3, 4, 14) has started.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The exhaust gas purification device as defined in Claim 4 or Claim 5, wherein
the temperature sensor comprises a sensor (20) which detects a running speed of
the vehicle.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>The exhaust gas purification device as defined in any one of Claim 4 through
Claim 6, wherein the controller (6) is further programmed to set, when the exhaust
gas temperature exceeds a second predetermined temperature higher than the
predetermined temperature while the mechanism (3, 4, 14) is operating, the decrease
amount per unit time of the sulphur oxide poisoning amount as a parameter
based on the sulphur oxide poisoning amount (S11), and the sulphur oxide
poisoning amount is calculated based on the integral value of the decrease amount
per unit time (S13).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The exhaust gas purification device as defined in any one of Claim 1 through
Claim 7, wherein the running condition detecting sensor comprises a sensor (20)
which detects a running speed of the vehicle, and the controller (6) is further
programmed to calculate the sulphur oxide poisoning amount based on the integral
value of the running speed (S12, S13).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>The exhaust gas purification device as defined in any one of Claim1 through
Claim 8, wherein the mechanism (3, 4, 14) comprises a fuel injector (3) which
injects fuel, a spark plug (4) which ignites the fuel and an exhaust gas recirculation
valve (14) which recirculates part of the exhaust gas of the engine (1) into an
intake air of the engine (1), and wherein the mechanism (3, 4, 14) removes sulphur
oxides from the nitrogen trapping catalyst (5A) by enriching an air-fuel ratio of the
intake air and the fuel by increasing the fuel injection amount of the fuel injector
(3), and by raising the exhaust gas temperature by delaying the ignition timing of
the spark plug (4) and closing the exhaust gas recirculation valve (14).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>The exhaust gas purification device as defined in Claim 9, wherein the controller
(6) is further programmed to vary a richness of the air-fuel ratio based on the
sulphur oxide poisoning amount during operation of the mechanism (3, 4, 14)
(S101, S102).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>The exhaust gas purification device as defined in Claim 10, wherein the
controller (6) is further programmed to decrease the richness of the air-fuel ratio
as the sulphur oxide poisoning amount decreases during operation of the mechanism
(3, 4, 14) (S101, S102).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>An exhaust gas purification method for a vehicle engine (1), the engine (1)
comprising a nitrogen oxide trapping catalyst (5A) which traps nitrogen oxides in
exhaust gas, means (3, 4, 14) for removing sulphur oxides which have poisoned
the nitrogen oxide trapping catalyst (5A) from the nitrogen oxide trapping catalyst
(5A), the method comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>detecting a running condition of the vehicle;</claim-text><claim-text>calculating a sulphur oxide poisoning amount of the nitrogen oxide trapping
catalyst (5A) from the running condition of the vehicle;</claim-text><claim-text>starting operation of the removing means (3, 4, 14) when the sulphur oxide
poisoning amount reaches a predetermined amount;</claim-text><claim-text>setting a decrease amount per unit time of the sulphur oxide poisoning
amount during operation of the removing means (3, 4, 14) as a parameter based
on the sulphur oxide poisoning amount;</claim-text><claim-text>calculating the sulphur oxide poisoning amount during operation of the
removing means based on an integral value of the decrease amount per unit time;
and</claim-text><claim-text>stopping, after operation of the removing mechanism (3, 4, 14) has started,
operation of the removing means (3, 4, 14) when the sulphur oxide poisoning
amount has decreased to a predetermined desulphating completion equivalent
value.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
