<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1249976-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1249976" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="18921720" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021016">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1249976-A2" status="new" fvid="23593311">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1249976</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021016</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02251479-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02251479</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020304</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001062606-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001062606</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010306</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04L   1/00        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04L   1/00        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04L   1/16        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04L   1/18        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04L  12/56        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04L  12/56        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04L  12/66        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04L  12/66        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04W  28/02        20090101C I20090105RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04W  28/04        20090101A N20090105RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04W  28/06        20090101A I20090105RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04W  28/14        20090101A N20090105RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04W  72/00        20090101C N20090105RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04W  72/12        20090101A N20090105RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H04L  12/56B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H04L  12/56D5R</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H04W  28/06</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">T04L1:00U</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">T04L1:18C</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">T04L12:56T15A</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">T04L12:56T15B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">T04L12:56T15C2</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">T04L12:56T4</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">T04W28:04</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">T04W28:14</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">T04W72:12</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Paketübertragung Verfahren und Vorrichtung</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Packet transmission method and system</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé et dispositif de transmission de paquets</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NTT DOCOMO INC</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NTT DOCOMO, INC.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>NTT DoCoMo, Inc.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>11-1, Nagatacho 2-chome, Chiyoda-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo 100-6150</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ETOH MINORU</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KAWAHARA TOSHIRO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YOSHIMURA TAKESHI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ETOH, MINORU</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KAWAHARA, TOSHIRO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YOSHIMURA, TAKESHI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>ETOH, MINORU</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>39-21 Noukendai-dori, Kanazawa-ku</street>
              <city>Yokohama-shi, Kanagawa 236-0053</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>KAWAHARA, TOSHIRO</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1955-1 Ninomiya</street>
              <city>Tsuyama-shi, Okayama 708-0013</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>YOSHIMURA, TAKESHI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>2-33-409 Mutsuura 1-chome, Kanazawa-ku</street>
              <city>Yokohama-shi, Kanagawa 236-0031</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Rees, Alexander Ellison</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Urquhart-Dykes &amp;amp; Lord, 30 Welbeck Street</street>
              <city>London W1G 8ER</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>IT</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A packet transmission method for
transmitting packets classified according to a
quality of service (QoS) requirement from a
transmitting node to a receiving node is provided.
In the transmitting node, the steps of selecting
sequentially a QoS class; dividing a queued packet
to be transmitted belonging to the selected class
into a plurality of predetermined data units, and
transmitting one of the obtained predetermined data
units; and applying a transmitter-side
retransmission control process to the data unit to
be transmitted when the selected class is a QoS
class specified for data type packets are provided.
In the receiving node, the steps of: receiving
sequentially the data units transmitted from the
transmitting node; assembling a plurality of
received data units to decompress the original
packet for each QoS class; and applying a receiver-side
retransmission control process to the received
data units to be assembled when the received data
unit belongs to one of the QoS classes specified for
the data type packets are provided.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="124" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="86"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <heading>1. Field of the Invention</heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention generally relates to
a packet transmission method and system, more
particularly to the packet transmission method and
system for dividing a normal transmission packet
into a plurality of data units each having a shorter
data length, and scheduling transmission order of
those data units.</p>
    <heading>2. Description of the Related Art</heading>
    <p num="0002">Today, on the Internet, services have been
provided that can support various quality of service
(QoS). QoS may be defined by allowable packet loss,
allowable delay time, and the like.</p>
    <p num="0003">For example, between transmission of E-mail
and transmission of audio or video streaming,
there is a big difference in the required QoS. In
data type transmission such as for E-mail or Web
pages, it may be more important to ensure an arrival
of all the information (reliability or low bit
error) than an arrival with no or minimal delay.
That is, the data type transmission may allow some
delay if necessary for the reliability. While, in
real-time type transmission such as for audio or
video streaming, minimal delay is more important
because the real-time type data can be practically
unusable if the delay is too large.</p>
    <p num="0004">Some architectures offer different QoS
such as Intserv (Integrated Service) and Diffserv
(Differentiated Service). The Intserv guarantees
throughput for every QoS class, which is a so-called 
bandwidth-guaranteed type service, and utilizes RSVP
(Resource Reservation Protocol). The Diffserv sets
up a priority for every packet, based on user (IP
address) or contents of transmitted information.</p>
    <p num="0005">A conventional packet transmission method
and system is described below with reference to
FIG.1. FIG.1 schematically shows the configuration
of the conventional packet transmitting apparatus.</p>
    <p num="0006">In Fig.1, a classifying part 101 processes
packets (IP packets) to be transmitted to classify
them on the basis of QoS requirement. It is assumed
as an example that roughly there are some service
classes classified as real-time type and some
service classes classified as data type.</p>
    <p num="0007">Alternatively, for classifying, a
different service class is assigned to each flow if
this node is an RSVP router, while service classes
are allocated based on DSCP (Diffserv Codepoint) in
IP header if the node is a Diffserv router.</p>
    <p num="0008">Each classified transmission packet is
managed in an IP datagram queue, using various
buffer management techniques for each queue. As an
example, some packets are dropped according to a
predetermined discard policy such as RED or RIO.
The IP datagram queues are provided for each service
class in an IP queue 102.</p>
    <p num="0009">A transmission order for the packets to be
transmitted buffered in each queue is scheduled by a
scheduling part 103 according to a scheduling
technique such as PQ (Priority Queuing), WFQ
(Weighted Fair Queuing), or CBQ (Class-based
Queuing). The scheduling may be based on allocated
bands in case of the above-mentioned Intserv, while
it may be based on the priority of each queue in
case of the above Diffserv. Anyway, a front packet
in each queue is pulled out according to one of the
above techniques, and is transferred into a data 
link layer (the second layer).</p>
    <p num="0010">The packets to be transmitted transferred
into the data link layer are transmitted by a data
link control part 104.</p>
    <p num="0011">As described above, the conventional
packet transmitting apparatus performs the QoS
control by scheduling the packets to be transmitted
in the IP layer on the basis of the QoS class.</p>
    <p num="0012">However, the above conventional QoS
control assumes the use of wired transmission where
fine connections are maintained, and performs the
same process to each QoS class in the data link
layer (the second layer).</p>
    <p num="0013">If such QoS control method is applied to
radio transmission where packet losses may likely
occur in radio paths, a larger delay may adversely
occur in the real-time type packets requiring
minimal delay. It is described as below.</p>
    <p num="0014">With reference to FIG.2, the configuration
of a typical mobile communication system is now
described. FIG.2 shows schematically the whole
configuration of the typical mobile communication
system.</p>
    <p num="0015">In FIG.2, a plurality of radio network
controllers (RNC) 202 are connected to a core
network (CN) 201, and each radio network controller
202 controls a plurality of base stations (BS) 203.
Each radio base station 203 manages a plurality of
cells 204. The number of each kind of stations
shown is only an example and may include others.</p>
    <p num="0016">In the mobile communication system, the
data link control is usually performed in the RNC
202.</p>
    <p num="0017">In the mobile communication system having
such configuration, when the packet loss occurs, the
same packet is usually retransmitted in the radio
path in order to maintain the quality of 
transmission. With a typical control, when one
packet is lost in the radio path, a receiver-side
awaits the retransmission of the lost packet even if
the subsequent packet is successfully transmitted.</p>
    <p num="0018">As mentioned above, since reliability (low
bit error) is important in the transmission of the
data type packets, a process required for the
retransmission control is applied to each of the
packets to be transmitted in the data link control.</p>
    <p num="0019">However, applying the data link control
including the retransmission control uniformly to
all the packets belonging to all QoS classes,
consequently the retransmission control is applied
to the real-time type packets.</p>
    <p num="0020">In the radio transmission, particularly
the retransmission control is frequently performed.
Therefore, applying the above conventional QoS
control to the radio transmission, the transmission
delay may likely occur in the transmission of the
real-time type packets where minimal delay may be
more important than the reliability.</p>
    <p num="0021">Also, transmission rate in the radio
transmission is slower than one in the wired
transmission, and hence longer packet transmission
time is required in the former than in the latter.
For example, when a packet having 1,500 bytes is
transmitted at 128 kilobit per second (kbps), it
takes approximately 100 milliseconds (ms). In audio
or voice communication, 100 ms delay is quite large.</p>
    <p num="0022">Therefore, when a real-time type packet is
to be transmitted during the transmission of the
data type packet, according to the above example,
even if the scheduling process is performed taking
account of QoS (i.e. the real-time type packet shall
be given higher priority for transmission), this
real-time type packet waits to be transmitted at
most for 100 ms. </p>
    <p num="0023">Thus, in the conventional data link
control apparatus, the QoS control is exclusively
performed in the IP layer (the third layer), and the
QoS is not adequately reflected in the process of
the data link layer (the second layer).</p>
    <p num="0024">Therefore, the conventional packet
transmitting apparatus has a problem that the
transmission delay is likely to occur in the real-time
type packets when it is used for the radio
transmission.</p>
    <p num="0025">Japanese laid-open patent application No.
2000-224261 discloses a data link control method in
which a plurality of QoS planes are generated in the
data link layer on the basis of the QoS information
of the IP layer.</p>
    <p num="0026">In this method, in fact, the data link
control varies according to the QoS. However,
although this method varies its retransmission
method on the basis of the QoS requirement, the
above-mentioned problem that the delay may occur in
the real-time type packets due to the occurrence of
the retransmission packet waiting time remains,
because this method does not include a mode that
does not perform the retransmission method.</p>
    <p num="0027">Also, in this method, although a frame
length to divide into is varied in the data link
layer according to conditions of the radio
transmission path, a frame by frame scheduling is
not performed. Therefore, this method does not
solve the problem that delay may occur in the real-time
type packets because of the transmission
waiting time until completion of transmission of the
data type packets.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0028">The present invention is directed toward
solving these problems, and hence its object is to 
provide the packet transmission method and system
that performs the data link control taking into
account the QoS in order to achieve minimal delay of
the real-time type packets in the radio transmission,
while maintaining the reliability of the data type
packets.</p>
    <p num="0029">According to one aspect of the present
invention, a packet transmission system transmits
packets classified according to QoS requirement from
a transmitting node to a receiving node. The
transmitting node includes: a dividing part provided
for each QoS class for dividing a packet to be
transmitted into a plurality of predetermined data
units in each QoS class; a transmitter-side
retransmission control part for applying a
transmitter-side retransmission control process in
each QoS class to the data unit that belongs to one
of QoS classes specified for data type packets and
is one of the data units obtained from the dividing
part; and a scheduling part for selecting a data
unit to be transmitted from a set of data units
including a data unit that belongs to one of QoS
classes not specified for data type packets and is
obtained from the dividing part, and a data unit
that belongs to one of the QoS classes specified for
data type packets and is obtained from the
transmitter-side retransmission control part, and
transmitting the selected data unit. The receiving
node includes: a receiver-side retransmission
control part for applying a receiver-side
retransmission control process in each QoS class to
the data unit that belongs to one of the QoS classes
specified for data type packets and is one of the
received data units; an assembling part for
assembling in each QoS class the data units that
belong to one of the QoS classes not specified for
data type packets and are some of the received data 
units, and the data units that belong to one of the
QoS classes specified for data type packets and are
obtained from the receiver-side retransmission
control part to decompress the original packet.</p>
    <p num="0030">According to another aspect of the present
invention, a packet transmission system transmits
packets classified according to QoS requirement from
a transmitting node to a receiving node. The
transmitting node includes: a first pre-scheduling
part for selecting classes having high priority for
transmission from QoS classes specified for data
type packets; a second pre-scheduling part for
selecting classes having high priority for
transmission from QoS classes not specified for data
type packets; a first dividing part for dividing a
queued packet to be transmitted belonging to the QoS
class selected by the first pre-scheduling part into
a plurality of predetermined data units; a second
dividing part for dividing a queued packet to be
transmitted belonging to the QoS class selected by
the second pre-scheduling part into a plurality of
the predetermined data units; a transmitter-side
retransmission control part for applying a
transmitter-side retransmission control process to
the packet to be transmitted to be divided by the
first dividing part; and a scheduling part for
selecting either one of the QoS classes specified
for data type packets or one of the QoS classes not
specified for data type packets to be transmitted,
transmitting the data unit obtained from the
transmitter-side retransmission control part when
the QoS class specified for data type packets is
selected, and transmitting the data unit obtained
from the second dividing part when the QoS class not
specified for data type packets is selected. The
receiving node includes: a receiver-side
retransmission control part for applying a receiver-side 
retransmission control process in each QoS
class to the data unit that belongs to one of the
QoS classes specified for data type packets and is
one of the received data units; and an assembling
part for assembling the data units that belong to
one of the QoS classes not specified for data type
packets and are some of the received data units, and
the data units that belong to one of the QoS classes
specified for data type packets and are obtained
from the receiver-side retransmission control part
in each QoS class to decompress the original packet.</p>
    <p num="0031">According to a further aspect of the
present invention, a packet transmission system
transmits packets classified according to QoS
requirement from a transmitting node to a receiving
node. The transmitting node includes: a first
scheduling part for determining transmission order
for packets to be transmitted; a dividing part
provided for each QoS class for dividing the packet
to be transmitted of which transmission order is
determined by the first scheduling part into a
plurality of predetermined data units in each QoS
class; a transmitter-side retransmission control
part for applying a transmitter-side retransmission
control process in each QoS class to the data unit
that belongs to one of QoS classes specified for
data type packets and is one of the data units
obtained from the dividing part; and a scheduling
part for selecting a data unit to be transmitted
from a set of data units including a data unit that
belongs to one of QoS classes not specified for data
type packets and is obtained from the dividing part,
and a data unit that belongs to one of the QoS
classes specified for data type packets and is
obtained from the transmitter-side retransmission
control part, and transmitting the selected data
unit. The receiving node includes: a receiver-side 
retransmission control part for applying a receiver-side
retransmission control process in each QoS
class to the data unit that belongs to one of the
QoS classes specified for data type packets and is
one of the received data units; an assembling part
for assembling in each QoS class the data units that
belong to one of the QoS classes not specified for
data type packets and are some of the received data
units, and the data units that belong to one of the
QoS classes specified for data type packets and are
obtained from the receiver-side retransmission
control part to decompress the original packet.</p>
    <p num="0032">In this context, the QoS class specified
for data packets may be a QoS used for transmission
of information such as E-mails or Web pages, that is,
a QoS used for transmission that is required to be
reliable or to have low bit error and can allow some
delay. Also in this context, the QoS class not
specified for data packets may be a QoS class
specified for real-time packets such as audio or
video streaming, that is, a QoS used for
transmission that is strongly required to be
minimally delayed because it may be unusable when
the delay is large.</p>
    <p num="0033">Further in this context, to transmit a
data unit may mean to transmit a data unit being at
the front of the queue.</p>
    <p num="0034">It may be possible to add a header
compression process to one of the above aspects to
reduce the amount of the transmitted information.</p>
    <p num="0035">The present invention also includes a
packet transmitting/receiving apparatus that may be
a communication node, a packet transmitting
apparatus that may be provided in the communication
node, and a packet receiving apparatus. The present
invention further includes a packet transmission
method used in the above systems and apparatuses. </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0036">These and other aspects, and other objects,
features and advantages of the present invention
will become more apparent from the following
detailed description when read in conjunction with
the accompanying drawings, in which:
<sl><li>FIG.1 is the schematic diagram showing the
configuration of the conventional packet
transmitting apparatus;</li><li>FIG.2 is the schematic diagram showing the
whole configuration of the typical mobile
communication system;</li><li>FIG.3 is the schematic diagram showing the
configuration of the packet transmitting apparatus
according to the first embodiment of the present
invention;</li><li>FIG.4 is the schematic diagram showing the
configuration of the packet receiving apparatus
according to the first embodiment of the present
invention;</li><li>FIG.5 is the schematic diagram showing the
configuration of the packet transmitting/receiving
apparatus according to the first embodiment of the
present invention;</li><li>FIG.6 is a process flow chart of the IP
packet to be transmitted in the packet transmitting
apparatus according to the first embodiment of the
present invention;</li><li>FIG.7 is a process flow chart of the data
unit transmission in the packet transmitting
apparatus according to the first embodiment of the
present invention;</li><li>FIG.8 is a process flow chart of the data
unit reception in the packet receiving apparatus
according to the first embodiment of the present
invention; </li><li>FIG.9 is a process flow chart of reception
of a retransmission request control signal in the
packet transmitting apparatus according to the first
embodiment of the present invention;</li><li>FIG.10 is a schematic diagram showing an
example in which the IMT-2000 standard is applied to
the packet transmitting apparatus according to the
first embodiment of the present invention;</li><li>FIG.11 is the schematic diagram showing
the configuration of the packet transmitting
apparatus according to the second embodiment of the
present invention;</li><li>FIG.12 is a process flow chart of the data
unit transmission in the packet transmitting
apparatus according to the second embodiment of the
present invention;</li><li>FIG.13 is the schematic diagram showing
the configuration of the packet transmitting
apparatus according to the third embodiment of the
present invention;</li><li>FIG.14 is the schematic diagram showing
the configuration of the packet receiving apparatus
according to the third embodiment of the present
invention;</li><li>FIG.15 is a process flow chart of the data
unit transmission in the packet transmitting
apparatus according to the third embodiment of the
present invention;</li><li>FIG.16 is a process flow chart of the data
unit reception in the packet receiving apparatus
according to the third embodiment of the present
invention;</li><li>FIG.17 is the schematic diagram showing
the configuration of the packet transmitting
apparatus according to the fourth embodiment of the
present invention.</li></sl></p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0037">As below, the embodiments of the present
invention are described with reference to the
accompanying figures.</p>
    <p num="0038">First, the packet transmitting system
according to the first embodiment of the present
invention is described with reference to FIGs.3-5.
FIG.3 shows the configuration of the packet
transmitting apparatus according to this embodiment,
FIG.4 shows the configuration of the packet
receiving apparatus according to this embodiment,
and FIG.5 shows the configuration of the packet
transmitting/receiving apparatus according to this
embodiment.</p>
    <p num="0039">As shown in FIG.3, the packet transmitting
apparatus according to this embodiment includes a
classifying part 301, an IP queue 302, a data link
control part 303, and a scheduling part 306. The
data link control part 303 includes dividing parts
304 and retransmission control parts 305.</p>
    <p num="0040">The classifying part 301 classifies the IP
packets input from an upper layer into different IP
datagram queues on the basis of the QoS requirement
obtained from, for example, IP header information of
the packets.</p>
    <p num="0041">The IP queue 302 includes a plurality of
IP datagram queues, and stores the packets to be
transmitted for each QoS class. The IP queue 302
also determines whether the IP packet should be
discarded on the basis of the number of queued
packets, total length of the queued packets, and the
IP header information of the input packet, according
to the predetermined arbitrary discard policy.</p>
    <p num="0042">The dividing part 304 divides each of the
packets to be transmitted into a plurality of
predetermined data units each having shorter data
length than ones of the typical IP packets. The 
data unit may be, for example, a PDU (Protocol Data
Unit) having a fixed length.</p>
    <p num="0043">The dividing part 304 then writes
specification of the dividing process such as the
number to divide into, a flag indicating front or
tail of the packet, or information about the packet
length, into the header of each data unit. The
dividing part 304 also writes a sequence number and
identification for process line that indicates which
dividing part generates this data unit (or
identification for QoS class) into the header of
each data unit.</p>
    <p num="0044">The dividing part 304 also includes
buffers each storing temporarily the data units
generated by dividing one or more packets. The
dividing part 304 can store any number of the data
units, and the dividing part 304 may buffer as many
as possible of the data units in order to make it
smooth for the subsequent packet to be transmitted
to be input into the IP queue.</p>
    <p num="0045">The retransmission control part 305
applies a process required for retransmission
control to the data unit to be transmitted, and
transmits a packet indicated by an opposing
communicating station when the opposing
communicating station requires packet retransmission.
This is detailed later.</p>
    <p num="0046">The scheduling part 306 selects a QoS
class having top priority for transmission at the
moment on the basis of an allocated band, the
priority of the QoS class, and the like, and
transmits a data unit being at the front of the
selected class. This selection of the data unit to
be transmitted is performed each time, transmitting
one data unit. The scheduling part 306 also
transmits a retransmission request to be transmitted
to the opposing communicating station. This is 
detailed later.</p>
    <p num="0047">On the other hand, as shown in FIG.4, the
packet receiving apparatus according to this
embodiment includes a classifying part 401 and a
data link control part 402. The data link control
part 402 includes retransmission control parts 403
and assembling parts 404.</p>
    <p num="0048">The classifying part 401 classifies the
data units received from the radio path to the
assembling part 404 or the retransmission control
part 403 appropriate for that data unit according to
the identification written on the data unit.</p>
    <p num="0049">The retransmission control part 403
performs the process required for retransmission by,
for example, reading out the sequence numbers in the
header information of the received data units in
turn. If loss is detected, the retransmission
control part 403 requests for retransmission of the
lost data unit to the opposing communicating station.
This is detailed later.</p>
    <p num="0050">The assembling part 404 includes a buffer
storing temporarily the received data units, and
assembles a plurality of the data units into the
original packet based on their header information.
Although the shown assembling part is provided in
each process line, the above assembling parts may be
integrated into one element if the element can
identify in which process line for the data unit or
the assembled IP packet is processed (or which QoS
class the data unit or the assembled IP packet
belongs to).</p>
    <p num="0051">The retransmission request process is now
detailed with reference to FIG.5. In a packet
transmitting/receiving apparatus 500, the
classifying part 401 picks up a retransmission
request signal among signals received from the
opposing communicating station, and outputs the 
picked up retransmission request signal to the
retransmission control part 305 in the data link
control part 303 as shown in FIG.3.</p>
    <p num="0052">Also as shown in FIG.4, when the
retransmission control part 403 in the data link
control part 402 detects a packet loss, the
retransmission control part 403 generates a control
signal requesting retransmission of the lost packet,
and inputs the generated control signal into the
scheduling part 306. The scheduling part 306
performs scheduling the input control signal with
other data to be transmitted, and transmits the
whole scheduled data to the opposing communicating
station.</p>
    <p num="0053">Generally, the packet
transmitting/receiving apparatuses according to this
embodiment communicating with each other exchange
the retransmission request control signals.</p>
    <p num="0054">The operation of the packet transmitting
system according to this embodiment is then
described with reference to FIGs.6-9 and FIG.4.
FIG.6 shows the process flow of the IP packet to be
transmitted in the packet transmitting apparatus
according to this embodiment, FIG.7 shows the
process flow of the data unit transmission in the
packet transmitting apparatus according to this
embodiment, FIG.8 shows the process flow of the data
unit reception in the packet receiving apparatus
according to this embodiment, and FIG.9 shows the
process flow of the reception of the retransmission
request control signal in the packet transmitting
apparatus according to this embodiment.</p>
    <p num="0055">First, the process for the IP packet to be
transmitted in the packet transmitting apparatus is
described with reference to FIG.6. The packet to be
transmitted is input from an upper layer to the data
link control apparatus 300 (S601), and is classified 
and classified by the classifying part 301 according
to the QoS requirement from, for example, the IP
header information (S602) into each queue in the IP
queue 302.</p>
    <p num="0056">For the IP packet distributed into each
queue it is determined whether the IP packet is
discarded based on the number of packets stored in a
queue, total packet length, the IP header
information in the input packet and the like,
according to the predetermined arbitrary discard
policy.</p>
    <p num="0057">The process of the data unit transmission
in the packet transmitting apparatus is now
described with reference to FIG.7. The scheduling
part 306 selects a QoS class having the top priority
for transmission at the moment on the basis of the
allocated band, the priority of each QoS class, and
the like (S701). The selected class is one of the
classes queuing the IP packet or the data unit to be
transmitted.</p>
    <p num="0058">The scheduling part 306 determines whether
there is a data unit to be transmitted in the
dividing part 304 in the process line for the
selected class (in case of a real-time type), or in
the buffer of the retransmission control part for
the selected class (in case of a data type) (S702).
If there is the data unit to be transmitted
belonging to the selected class ('Yes' at S702), the
process proceeds to S706, and that data unit is
transmitted. Otherwise, i.e. if there is no data
unit to be transmitted belonging to the selected
class ('No' at S702), the IP packet belonging to the
selected class is pulled out from the IP queue 302
(S703). The pulled out IP packet is divided into a
plurality of data units by the dividing part 304
(S704). If the IP packet is a kind of data type
packet, the process required for retransmission 
control is applied to the data unit divided by the
dividing process at S704 by the retransmission
control part 305 (S705), and a front data unit of
the queue is transmitted (S706).</p>
    <p num="0059">After transmission of one data unit is
completed, it is determined whether the whole
transmission process is completed (S707). If it is
not completed ('No' at S707), the process goes back
to S501, and the scheduling part 306 selects a class
to be transmitted next. If the whole transmission
process is completed ('Yes' at S707), the
transmission of the data unit is finished.</p>
    <p num="0060">The process of the data unit reception in
the packet receiving apparatus is now described with
reference to FIG.8. The packet receiving apparatus
waits for reception of the data unit (S801 and 'No'
at S801), If the data unit is received ('Yes' at
S801), the classifying part 401 identifies a class
that the received data unit belongs to from the
identification in the received data unit, and
classifies the received data unit into the
corresponding process line (S802).</p>
    <p num="0061">If the received data unit is a kind of
data type ('Yes' at S803), the process required for
retransmission such as detection of lost packet is
applied to the data unit by the retransmission
control part 403. If necessary, the retransmission
request control signal is generated and transmitted
to the opposing communicating station.</p>
    <p num="0062">The data type data unit processed for
retransmission and the real-time type data unit are
respectively assembled by the respective assembling
part 404 based on the header information in the
original IP packet.</p>
    <p num="0063">The assembled IP packet is in turn
transferred to the upper layer via, for example, a
bus. Since transfer rate at the data link control 
part 202 is normally slower than one at the bus, it
is considered that no packet collision occurs.</p>
    <p num="0064">Then, if the whole reception process is
completed ('Yes' at S806), the process is finished.
If the reception process continues ('No' at S806),
the process goes back to S801 to wait for the next
reception of the data unit.</p>
    <p num="0065">The process of the reception of the
retransmission request control signal in the packet
transmitting apparatus is now described with
reference to FIG.9. The packet transmitting
apparatus waits for the reception of the
retransmission request control signal (S901 and 'No'
at S901).</p>
    <p num="0066">If the retransmission request control
signal is received ('Yes' at S901), as shown in
FIGs.3-5, the retransmission request control signal
is extracted by the classifying part 401 and is
output into the retransmission control part 305 of
the appropriate process line for the received
retransmission request control signal.</p>
    <p num="0067">The retransmission control part 305 that
receives the retransmission request retransmits the
data unit indicated by the retransmission request
(S903). Then, if the whole transmission process is
completed ('Yes' at S904), the process is finished.
If the whole transmission process continues ('No' at
S904), the process goes back to S901 to wait for the
next reception of the retransmission request control
signal.</p>
    <p num="0068">It is noted that the processes shown in
FIGs.6-9 can be carried out in parallel in order to
allow parallel occurrence of events, and are not to
be carried out sequentially.</p>
    <p num="0069">Thus, according to this embodiment, the
scheduling process is performed at the data link
layer, while the conventional scheduling process is 
performed at the IP layer that is an upper layer
compared to the data link layer. Also, in the data
link control process, by dividing each transmission
packet into a plurality of shorter data units, and
by scheduling the data units, when the real-time
type packet comes to be transmitted during
transmission of the data type packet, since the
length of one unit of transmitted data (that is the
above predetermined data unit) is shorter than one
of the conventional transmitted packet, the waiting
time for a real-time type packet to be transmitted
can be reduced.</p>
    <p num="0070">In other words, even during transmission
of the data type IP packet that is relatively large
(of which data length is relatively long), the
apparatus can start to transmit the real-time type
packet that is subject to relatively stringent delay
constraints.</p>
    <p num="0071">Further, according to this embodiment, by
reflecting the QoS requirement to the data link
control process, by not applying the retransmission
control process to the real-time type packet that
practically does not require the retransmission
process, and by applying the retransmission control
process only to the data type packet that requires
the retransmission control function, the data
processing required in the data link control process
can be reduced.</p>
    <p num="0072">An example is now shown in FIG.10 that the
IMT-2000 (W-CDMA) standard is applied to the packet
transmitting apparatus according to the first
embodiment of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0073">As shown, in the data link control part
303, a processing part 1001 processes the real-time
type packet, and a processing part 1002 processes
the data type packet, where the processing part 1001
achieves RLC UM (Radio Link Control Unacknowledged 
Mode) that is a transmission control function
defined by 3GPP (3rd Generation Partnership Project)
and has only a dividing and assembling function, and
where the processing part 1002 achieves RLC AM
(Radio Link Control Acknowledged Mode) that is also
a transmission control function defined by 3GPP and
has a dividing and assembling function and a
retransmission control function. By employing such
configuration, the configuration according to this
embodiment is implemented in compliance with the
IMT-2000 standard.</p>
    <p num="0074">The packet transmission method and system
according to the second embodiment of the present
invention is now described with reference to
FIGs.11-12. FIG.11 shows the configuration of the
packet transmitting apparatus according to this
embodiment, and FIG.12 shows the process of the data
unit transmission in the packet transmitting
apparatus according to this embodiment. The same
elements as ones in the packet transmitting
apparatus according to the first embodiment shown in
FIG.1 are indicated with the consistent reference
numbers, and are not further described in detail.</p>
    <p num="0075">First, the configuration of the packet
transmitting apparatus according to this embodiment
is described with reference to FIG.11. In FIG.11,
two pre-scheduling parts 1101 are provided before
the data link control part 303, where one of the two
performs the preliminary scheduling process to each
packet belonging to one of the real-time type QoS
classes based on the QoS requirement, and the other
performs the preliminary scheduling process to each
packet belonging to one of the data type QoS classes
based on the QoS requirement.</p>
    <p num="0076">The process of the data unit transmission
in the packet transmission apparatus according to
this embodiment is then described with reference to 
FIG.12. The scheduling part 306 selects which type
has the top priority for transmission at the moment
on the basis of the allocated band, the priority of
each QoS class, and the like (S1001).</p>
    <p num="0077">The scheduling part 306 determines whether
there is a data unit to be transmitted for the
selected type, with making reference to the buffer
of the dividing part 304 when the real-time type is
selected and to the buffer of the retransmission
control part 305 when the data type is selected
(S1202). If there is a data unit to be transmitted
in the selected type ('Yes' at S1202), the process
proceeds to S1207 and transmits the data unit. If
there is no data unit to be transmitted in the
selected type ('No' at S1202), the pre-scheduling
part 1101 specified for the selected type selects a
class having the top priority for transmission at
the moment in the selected type on the basis of the
allocated band, the priority of each QoS class, and
the like (S1203), and pulls out an IP packet
belonging to the selected class from the IP queue
302 (S1204). The pulled out IP packet is divided
into a plurality of data units by the dividing part
304 (S1205). If the pulled out IP packet is a kind
of data type packet, the process required for
retransmission control is applied to the data units
divided by the dividing process at S1205 by the
retransmission control part 305 (S1206), and a front
data unit of the queue is transmitted (S1207).</p>
    <p num="0078">After transmission of one data unit is
completed, it is determined whether the whole
transmission process is completed (S1208). If it is
not completed ('No' at S1208), the process goes back
to S1201, and the scheduling part 306 selects a type
to be transmitted next. If the whole transmission
process is completed ('Yes' at S1208), the
transmission of the data unit is finished. </p>
    <p num="0079">Thus, according to this embodiment, the
preliminary scheduling is performed respectively
among the data type classes and among the real-time
type classes to the packets to be transmitted
classified into a plurality of queues based on the
QoS requirement before being input into the data
link control part 303. Therefore, since only one
input flow specified for the real-time type packet
and only one input flow specified for the data type
packet are provided for the data link control part
303, as shown, only one process line specified for
the real-time type packet and only one process line
specified for the data type packet are necessary to
be provided in the data link control part 303,
thereby both the configuration of the data link
control part 303 and the data processing required in
the data link control part 303 are reduced.</p>
    <p num="0080">In the case that the dividing parts are
provided in each QoS class, the remainder after the
dividing into the above predetermined data units
each having a fixed length might need to be padded.
If there is a subsequent packet in the QoS class, an
empty space of the predetermined data unit holding
the remainder can be filled with a part of the
subsequent packet, however, if there is no
subsequent packet in the QoS class, the empty space
may have to be filled with 0 bits (so-called
padding) to form one complete data unit. In this
embodiment, since only one dividing part has to be
provided for data type and only one dividing part
has to be provided for real-time type, the case that
such padding happens is significantly reduced.</p>
    <p num="0081">Although according to this embodiment the
number of the scheduling parts increases, the data
processing does not increase because each scheduling
part merely outputs the input data selectively based
on the predetermined condition. Therefore, although 
the number of the scheduling parts increases, since
too large data processing power is not required and
the configuration of the data link control part is
simplified, the total data processing is eventually
reduced.</p>
    <p num="0082">The packet transmission method and system
according to the third embodiment of the present
invention is now described with reference to
FIGs.13-16.</p>
    <p num="0083">A header in the packet transmission has
high compressibility, because the information
included in the header may hold the same contents in
some cases, and the subsequent value may be easily
predicted. In the prior art, it is proposed to
compress the header of each packet in the packet
transmission in order to reduce an amount of
transmitted information. This embodiment applies
the header compressing process to the packet
transmission system according to the present
invention.</p>
    <p num="0084">FIG.13 shows the configuration of the
packet transmitting apparatus according to this
embodiment, FIG.14 shows the configuration of the
packet receiving apparatus according to this
embodiment, FIG.15 shows the process of the data
unit transmission in the packet transmitting
apparatus according to this embodiment, and FIG.16
shows the process of the data unit reception in the
packet receiving apparatus according to this
embodiment. The same elements as ones in the packet
transmitting apparatus and the receiving apparatus
according to the first embodiment shown in FIGs.3-4
are indicated with the consistent reference numbers,
and are not further described in detail.</p>
    <p num="0085">First, the configuration of the packet
transmitting apparatus according to this embodiment
is described with reference to FIG.13. In FIG.13, 
each of header compressing parts 1301 performs the
header compressing process to each of the IP packets
input into the data link control part 303 before
being divided into a plurality of the data units by
the dividing part 304.</p>
    <p num="0086">The header compression parts 1301 may
employ arbitrary header compressing algorithm as the
header compression process, such as RFC1144, RFC2507,
and RFC2508 of IETF (Internet Engineering Task
force), or RFC3095.</p>
    <p num="0087">The headers to be compressed by the above
header compression process may be IP header, TCP/IP
header, UDP/IP header, or RTP/UDP/IP header.</p>
    <p num="0088">In this embodiment, the dividing part 304
divides a header-compressed packet that is subject
to the header compressing process into a plurality
of the data units.</p>
    <p num="0089">The configuration of the packet receiving
apparatus according to this embodiment is then
described with reference to FIG.14. In FIG.14, each
of header decompression parts 1401 applies the
process to decompress the compressed header to the
header-compressed packets each assembled by the
assembling parts 404 in order to reproduce the
original IP packet. The decompressing process
corresponds to the compressing algorithm in the
transmitter-side.</p>
    <p num="0090">The header-decompressed IP packet is
transferred to the upper layer via, for example, a
bus.</p>
    <p num="0091">The process of the data unit transmission
in the packet transmitting apparatus according to
this embodiment is then described with reference to
FIG.15. The same processes as ones in the operation
according to the first embodiment shown in FIG.7 are
not further described in detail.</p>
    <p num="0092">As shown in FIG.15, after the IP packet is 
obtained at S1503, the header compressing process is
applied to the obtained IP packet by the header
compressing part 1301 (S1504), and the dividing
process is applied by the dividing part 304 (S1505).</p>
    <p num="0093">The process of the data unit reception in
the packet receiving apparatus according to this
embodiment is then described with reference to
FIG.16. The same processes as ones in the operation
according to the first embodiment shown in FIG.8 are
not further described in detail.</p>
    <p num="0094">As shown in FIG.16, after the header-compressed
packet is assembled at S1605, the header
decompressing process is applied to the assembled
header-compressed packet by the header decompression
part 1401 (S1606), and the decompressed IP packet is
transferred to the upper layer.</p>
    <p num="0095">Thus, according to this embodiment, not
only can the delays in the real-time type packets be
reduced as well as in the previous embodiments, but
also the amount of the transmitted information can
be reduced by employing the header compressing
process.</p>
    <p num="0096">Although the shown header compressing part
is provided in each process lines, the above header
compressing parts may be integrated into one element
if the element can identify in which process line
for the data unit or the IP packet are processed (or
to which QoS class the data unit or the IP packet
belongs). Similarly, although the shown header
decompression part is provided in each process line,
the above header decompression parts may be
integrated into one element if the element can
identify in which process line for the data unit or
the IP packet are processed (or to which QoS class
the data unit or the IP packet belongs).</p>
    <p num="0097">The compressing algorithm used in this
embodiment may be fixed uniquely to each apparatus 
at the design phase, or may be designed to support a
plurality of algorithms and be set up by negotiating
between nodes before the start of communication.</p>
    <p num="0098">The packet transmission method and system
according to the fourth embodiment of the present
invention is now described with reference to FIG.17.
FIG.17 shows the configuration of the packet
transmitting apparatus according to this embodiment.</p>
    <p num="0099">In FIG.17, the pre-scheduling part 1701
processes each of the packets to be transmitted
packet by packet on the basis of the QoS requirement,
as with the conventional scheduling part such as the
scheduling part 103 shown in FIG.1.</p>
    <p num="0100">The classifying part 1702 classifies the
IP packets by outputting each of the pre-scheduled
IP packets to different dividing parts 304 on the
basis of the QoS requirement obtained from, for
example, the IP header information of the IP packets,
as with the classifying part 301 according to the
first embodiment of the present invention (see
FIG.3).</p>
    <p num="0101">Now, along the process flow, a section
from the classifying part 301 to the pre-scheduling
part 1701 is referred to as a first half section,
and a section from the classifying part 1702 to the
scheduling part 306 is referred to as a second half
section. It is clear from the figure that the first
half section of the packet transmitting apparatus
according to this embodiment has the same
configuration as one of the conventional packet
transmitting apparatuses in FIG.1.</p>
    <p num="0102">Thus, according to this embodiment, not
only the subsequently same process as one in the
first embodiment of the present invention is
achieved, but also this configuration is achieved by
adding the classifying part 1702, the data link
control part 303, and the scheduling part 306 to the 
conventional packet transmitting apparatus, thereby
the packet transmitting apparatus can be easily
manufactured and also modified.</p>
    <p num="0103">Although the embodiments of the present
invention are described as above, the number of the
queues and the classes based on the QoS requirement
shown in the figures are only illustrative and are
not to be construed as limiting the scope of the
present invention.</p>
    <p num="0104">Also, in any of the above embodiments, it
may be possible that only the data type packets are
divided into the above-mentioned predetermined data
units. In other words, it may be possible that the
real-time type packets are not divided. This is
because the waiting time to be transmitted for the
real-time type packet is reduced and the delay is
avoided when the length of the data type packets is
not so long, and because the data type packets
relatively allow some delay.</p>
    <p num="0105">Similarly, it may be possible that only
the data type packets of which data length is beyond
the predetermined threshold are divided. It may be
also possible that the data type packet and the
real-time type packet are divided into respective
unit packets having a different data length.</p>
    <p num="0106">However, it is preferable to divide all
the packets into the unit packets each having the
same length in order to realize uniform processing.</p>
    <p num="0107">Further, although it is mainly described
in the above description that the packet
transmitting apparatus and the packet receiving
apparatus, or the packet transmitting/receiving
apparatuses according to the present invention are
provided within the nodes in the mobile
communication system, the present invention is not
limited to such aspects and may be applied to mobile
stations that are in use for radio communication and 
transmits and receives the real-time type packets
and the data type packets, because it is possible
that the radio communication terminal simultaneously
transmits or receives the real-time type packets
such as video streaming and the data type packets
such as E-mail. In this respect, the present
invention may also be applied to nodes located in a
wired network for use in wired packet transmission.</p>
    <p num="0108">Further, although the above third
embodiment is described and shown as an aspect that
the header compressing/decompressing process is
added to the aspect according to the first
embodiment, the header compressing/decompressing
process according to the present invention may be
added to the aspect according to the above second or
fourth embodiment.</p>
    <p num="0109">Thus, it is clear from the above
description that according to the present invention,
the waiting time for real-time type packets to be
transmitted can be reduced when the real-time type
packet comes to be transmitted during transmission
of the data type packet. In other words, even
during transmission of the data type packet, the
real-time type packet can be transmitted. Also, the
data processing required in the data link control
process can be reduced.</p>
    <p num="0110">The present invention is not limited to
the specifically disclosed embodiments, and
variations and modifications may be made without
departing from the scope of the invention.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A packet transmission method for
transmitting packets classified according to a
quality of service (QoS) requirement from a
transmitting node to a receiving node, the packet
transmission method characterized by the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>in the transmitting node,</claim-text><claim-text>selecting sequentially a QoS class;</claim-text><claim-text>dividing a queued packet to be transmitted
belonging to the selected class into a plurality of
predetermined data units, and transmitting one of
the predetermined data units; and</claim-text><claim-text>applying a transmitter-side retransmission
control process to the data unit to be transmitted
when the selected class is a QoS class specified for
data type packets;</claim-text><claim-text>in the receiving node,</claim-text><claim-text>receiving sequentially the data unit
transmitted from the transmitting node;</claim-text><claim-text>applying a receiver-side retransmission
control process to the received data unit to be
assembled when the received data unit belongs to one
of the QoS classes specified for the data type
packets; and</claim-text><claim-text>assembling a plurality of received data
units to decompress the original packet in each QoS
class.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The packet transmission method as
claimed in claim 1, characterized in that:
<claim-text><claim-text>the queued packet to be transmitted is
divided into a plurality of the data units only when
there is no data unit which is not yet transmitted
and belongs to the same QoS class as the queued
packet to be transmitted.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The packet transmission method as
claimed in claim 1, characterized in that:
<claim-text><claim-text>the queued packet to be transmitted is
divided into a plurality of the data units and
stored; and</claim-text><claim-text>one of the data units belonging to the
selected class from the stored data units is
transmitted.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The packet transmission method as
claimed in claim 1, characterized in that:
<claim-text><claim-text>the transmitting node applies a header
compression process to the queued packet to be
transmitted in a predetermined manner, and divides
the header-compressed packet into a plurality of the
predetermined data units; and</claim-text><claim-text>the receiving node applies to the
assembled packet a header decompression process
corresponding to the header compression process.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The packet transmission method as
claimed in claim 2, characterized in that:
<claim-text><claim-text>the transmitting node applies a header
compression process to the queued packet to be
transmitted in a predetermined manner, and divides
the header-compressed packet into a plurality of the
predetermined data units; and</claim-text><claim-text>the receiving node applies to the
assembled packet a header decompression process
corresponding to the header compression process.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The packet transmission method as
claimed in claim 3, characterized in that:
<claim-text><claim-text>the transmitting node applies a header
compression process to the queued packet to be
transmitted in a predetermined manner, and divides
the header-compressed packet into a plurality of the
predetermined data units; and</claim-text><claim-text>the receiving node applies to the
assembled packet a header decompression process
corresponding to the header compression process.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A packet transmission system for
transmitting packets classified according to a QoS
requirement from a transmitting node to a receiving
node, characterized in that,
   the transmitting node comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a dividing part provided for each of QoS
classes for dividing a packet to be transmitted into
a plurality of predetermined data units in each of
QoS classes;</claim-text><claim-text>a transmitter-side retransmission control
part for applying a transmitter-side retransmission
control process in each QoS class to the data unit
that belongs to one of QoS classes specified for
data type packets and is one of the data units
obtained from the dividing part; and</claim-text><claim-text>a scheduling part for selecting a data
unit to be transmitted from a set of data units
including a data unit that belongs to one of QoS
classes not specified for data type packets and is
obtained from the dividing part, and a data unit
that belongs to one of the QoS classes specified for
data type packets and is obtained from the
transmitter-side retransmission control part, and
transmitting the selected data unit, and</claim-text><claim-text>the receiving node comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a receiver-side retransmission control
part for applying a receiver-side retransmission
control process in each QoS class to the data unit
that belongs to one of the QoS classes specified for
data type packets and is one of the received data
units;</claim-text><claim-text>an assembling part for assembling in each
QoS class the data units that belong to one of the
QoS classes not specified for data type packets and
are some of the received data units, and the data
units that belong to one of the QoS classes
specified for data type packets and are obtained
from the receiver-side retransmission control part
to decompress the original packet.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The packet transmission system as
claimed in claim 7, characterized in that:
<claim-text><claim-text>the transmitting node further comprises a
header compressing part for applying a header
compression process in a predetermined manner to the
packet to be transmitted;</claim-text><claim-text>the receiving node further comprises a
header decompression part;</claim-text><claim-text>the dividing part divides a header-compressed
packet obtained from the header
compressing part into a plurality of the
predetermined data units;</claim-text><claim-text>the assembling part applies the assembling
process to the plurality of the predetermined data
units to decompress the header-compressed packet;
and</claim-text><claim-text>the header decompression part applies a
header decompression process corresponding to the
header compression process in the header compressing
part to the header-compressed packet obtained from
the assembling part to decompress the original
packet.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>A packet transmission system for
transmitting packets classified according to a QoS
requirement from a transmitting node to a receiving
node, characterized in that,
   the transmitting node comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a first pre-scheduling part for selecting
classes having high priority for transmission from
QoS classes specified for data type packets;</claim-text><claim-text>a second pre-scheduling part for selecting
classes having high priority for transmission from
QoS classes not specified for data type packets;</claim-text><claim-text>a first dividing part for dividing a
queued packet to be transmitted belonging to the QoS
class selected by the first pre-scheduling part into
a plurality of predetermined data units;</claim-text><claim-text>a second dividing part for dividing a
queued packet to be transmitted belonging to the QoS
class selected by the second pre-scheduling part
into a plurality of the predetermined data units;</claim-text><claim-text>a transmitter-side retransmission control
part for applying a transmitter-side retransmission
control process to the packet to be transmitted to
be divided by the first dividing part; and</claim-text><claim-text>a scheduling part for selecting either one
of the QoS classes specified for data type packets
or one of the QoS classes not specified for data
type packets to be transmitted, transmitting the
data unit obtained from the transmitter-side
retransmission control part when the QoS class
specified for data type packets is selected, and
transmitting the data unit obtained from the second
dividing part when the QoS class not specified for
data type packets is selected, and</claim-text><claim-text>the receiving node comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a receiver-side retransmission control
part for applying a receiver-side retransmission
control process in each QoS class to the data unit
that belongs to one of the QoS classes specified for
data type packets and is one of the received data
units; and</claim-text><claim-text>an assembling part for assembling the data
units that belong to one of the QoS classes not
specified for data type packets and are some of the
received data units, and the data units that belong
to one of the QoS classes specified for data type
packets and are obtained from the receiver-side
retransmission control part in each QoS class to
decompress the original packet.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>The packet transmission system as
claimed in claim 9, characterized in that:
<claim-text><claim-text>the transmitting node further comprises a
header compressing part for applying a header
compression process in a predetermined manner to the
packet to be transmitted;</claim-text><claim-text>the receiving node further comprises a
header decompression part;</claim-text><claim-text>the dividing part divides a header-compressed
packet obtained from the header
compressing part into a plurality of the
predetermined data units;</claim-text><claim-text>the assembling part applies the assembling
process to the plurality of the predetermined data
units to decompress the header-compressed packet;
and</claim-text><claim-text>the header decompression part applies a
header decompression process corresponding to the
header compression process in the header compressing
part to the header-compressed packet obtained from
the assembling part to decompress the original
packet.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>A packet transmission system for
transmitting packets classified according to a QoS
requirement from a transmitting node to a receiving
node, characterized in that,
   the transmitting node comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a first scheduling part for determining
transmission order for packets to be transmitted;</claim-text><claim-text>a dividing part provided for each QoS
class for dividing the packet to be transmitted of
which transmission order is determined by the first
scheduling part into a plurality of predetermined
data units in each QoS class;</claim-text><claim-text>a transmitter-side retransmission control
part for applying a transmitter-side retransmission
control process in each QoS class to the data unit
that belongs to one of QoS classes specified for
data type packets and is one of the data units
obtained from the dividing part; and</claim-text><claim-text>a scheduling part for selecting a data
unit to be transmitted from a set of data units
including a data unit that belongs to one of QoS
classes not specified for data type packets and is
obtained from the dividing part, and a data unit
that belongs to one of the QoS classes specified for
data type packets and is obtained from the
transmitter-side retransmission control part, and
transmitting the selected data unit, and</claim-text><claim-text>the receiving node comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a receiver-side retransmission control
part for applying a receiver-side retransmission
control process in each QoS class to the data unit
that belongs to one of the QoS classes specified for
data type packets and is one of the received data
units;</claim-text><claim-text>an assembling part for assembling in each
QoS class the data units that belong to one of the
QoS classes not specified for data type packets and
are some of the received data units, and the data
units that belong to one of the QoS classes
specified for data type packets and are obtained
from the receiver-side retransmission control part
to decompress the original packet.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>The packet transmission system as
claimed in claim 11, characterized in that:
<claim-text><claim-text>the transmitting node further comprises a
header compressing part for applying a header
compression process in a predetermined manner to the
packet to be transmitted;</claim-text><claim-text>the receiving node further comprises a
header decompression part;</claim-text><claim-text>the dividing part divides a header-compressed
packet obtained from the header
compressing part into a plurality of the
predetermined data units;</claim-text><claim-text>the assembling part applies the assembling
process to the plurality of the predetermined data
units to decompress the header-compressed packet;
and</claim-text><claim-text>the header decompression part applies a
header decompression process corresponding to the
header compression process in the header compressing
part to the header-compressed packet obtained from
the assembling part to decompress the original
packet.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>A packet transmitting/receiving
apparatus comprising a transmitting part and a
receiving part for transmitting and receiving
packets classified according to a QoS requirement
respectively, characterized in that,
   the transmitting part comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a dividing part provided for each QoS
class for dividing a packet to be transmitted into a
plurality of predetermined data units in each QoS
class;</claim-text><claim-text>a transmitter-side retransmission control
part for applying a transmitter-side retransmission
control process in each QoS class to the data unit
that belongs to one of QoS classes specified for
data type packets and is one of the data units
obtained from the dividing part; and</claim-text><claim-text>a scheduling part for selecting a data
unit to be transmitted from a set of data units
including a data unit that belongs to one of QoS
classes not specified for data type packets and is
obtained from the dividing part, and a data unit
that belongs to one of the QoS classes specified for
data type packets and is obtained from the
transmitter-side retransmission control part, and
transmitting the selected data unit,</claim-text><claim-text>the receiving part comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a receiver-side retransmission control
part for applying a receiver-side retransmission
control process in each QoS class to the data unit
that belongs to one of the QoS classes specified for
data type packets and is one of the received data
units;</claim-text><claim-text>an assembling part for assembling in each
of QoS classes the data units that belong to one of
the QoS classes not specified for data type packets
and are some of the received data units, and the
data units that belong to one of the QoS classes
specified for data type packets and are obtained
from the receiver-side retransmission control part
to decompress the original packet,</claim-text><claim-text>the receiver-side retransmission control
part generates a retransmission request control
signal to indicate a data unit requested to be
retransmitted to another packet
transmitting/receiving apparatus communicating with
the packet transmitting/receiving apparatus,</claim-text><claim-text>the scheduling part performs a scheduling
process on the retransmission request control
signals with the data unit to be transmitted,</claim-text><claim-text>the transmitting part further comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a classifying part for classifying and
outputting the retransmission request control
signals transmitted from the opposing packet
transmitting/receiving apparatus into the
transmitter-side retransmission control part, and</claim-text><claim-text>the transmitter-side retransmission
control part outputs to the scheduling part the data
unit indicated by the retransmission request control
signal transmitted from the opposing packet
transmitting/receiving apparatus upon the
retransmission request control signal being input.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>The packet transmitting/receiving
apparatus as claimed in claim 13, characterized in
that:
<claim-text><claim-text>the transmitting part further comprises a
header compressing part for applying a header
compression process in a predetermined manner to the
packet to be transmitted;</claim-text><claim-text>the receiving part further comprises a
header decompression part;</claim-text><claim-text>the dividing part divides a header-compressed
packet obtained from the header
compressing part into a plurality of the
predetermined data units;</claim-text><claim-text>the assembling part applies the assembling
process to the plurality of the predetermined data
units to decompress the header-compressed packet;
and</claim-text><claim-text>the header decompression part applies a
header decompression process corresponding to the
header compression process in the header compressing
part to the header-compressed packet obtained from
the assembling part to decompress the original
packet.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>A packet transmitting/receiving
apparatus comprising a transmitting part and a
receiving part for transmitting and receiving
packets classified according to a QoS requirement
respectively, characterized in that,
   the transmitting part comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a first pre-scheduling part for selecting
classes having high priority for transmission from
QoS classes specified for data type packets;</claim-text><claim-text>a second pre-scheduling part for selecting
classes having high priority for transmission from
QoS classes not specified for data type packets;</claim-text><claim-text>a first dividing part for dividing a
queued packet to be transmitted belonging to the QoS
class selected by the first pre-scheduling part into
a plurality of predetermined data units;</claim-text><claim-text>a second dividing part for dividing a
queued packet to be transmitted belonging to the QoS
class selected by the second pre-scheduling part
into a plurality of the predetermined data units;</claim-text><claim-text>a transmitter-side retransmission control
part for applying a transmitter-side retransmission
control process to the packet to be transmitted to
be divided by the first dividing part; and</claim-text><claim-text>a scheduling part for selecting either one
of the QoS classes specified for data type packets
or one of the QoS classes not specified for data
type packets to be transmitted, transmitting the
data unit obtained from the transmitter-side
retransmission control part when the QoS class
specified for data type packets is selected, and
transmitting the data unit obtained from the second
dividing part when the QoS class not specified for
data type packets is selected, and</claim-text><claim-text>the receiving node comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a receiver-side retransmission control
part for applying a receiver-side retransmission
control process in each QoS class to the data unit
that belongs to one of the QoS classes specified for
data type packets and is one of the received data
units;</claim-text><claim-text>an assembling part for assembling in each
QoS class the data units that belong to one of the
QoS class not specified for data type packets and
are some of the received data units, and the data
units that belong to one of the QoS classes
specified for data type packets and are obtained
from the receiver-side retransmission control part
to decompress the original packet,</claim-text><claim-text>the receiver-side retransmission control
part generates a retransmission request control
signal to indicate a data unit requested to be
retransmitted to another packet
transmitting/receiving apparatus communicating with
the packet transmitting/receiving apparatus,</claim-text><claim-text>the scheduling part performs a scheduling
process on the retransmission request control
signals with the data unit to be transmitted,</claim-text><claim-text>the transmitting part further comprises
the classifying part for classifying and outputting
the retransmission request control signals
transmitted from the opposing packet
transmitting/receiving apparatus into the
transmitter-side retransmission control part, and</claim-text><claim-text>the transmitter-side retransmission
control part outputs to the scheduling part the data
unit indicated by the retransmission request control
signal transmitted from the opposing packet
transmitting/receiving apparatus upon the
retransmission request control signal being input.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>The packet transmitting/receiving
apparatus as claimed in claim 15, characterized in
that:
<claim-text><claim-text>the transmitting part further comprises a
header compressing part for applying a header
compression process in a predetermined manner to the
packet to be transmitted;</claim-text><claim-text>the receiving part further comprises a
header decompression part;</claim-text><claim-text>the dividing part divides a header-compressed
packet obtained from the header
compressing part into a plurality of the
predetermined data units;</claim-text><claim-text>the assembling part applies the assembling
process to the plurality of the predetermined data
units to decompress the header-compressed packet;
and</claim-text><claim-text>the header decompression part applies a
header decompression process corresponding to the
header compression process in the header compressing
part to the header-compressed packet obtained from
the assembling part to decompress the original
packet.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>A packet transmitting/receiving
apparatus comprising a transmitting part and a
receiving part for transmitting and receiving
packets classified according to a QoS requirement
respectively, characterized in that,
   the transmitting part comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a first scheduling part for determining
transmission order for packets to be transmitted;</claim-text><claim-text>a dividing part provided for each QoS
class for dividing the packets to be transmitted of
which transmission order is determined by the first
scheduling part into a plurality of predetermined
data units in each QoS class;</claim-text><claim-text>a transmitter-side retransmission control
part for applying a transmitter-side retransmission
control process in each QoS class to the data unit
that belongs to one of QoS classes specified for
data type packets and is one of the data units
obtained from the dividing part; and</claim-text><claim-text>a scheduling part for selecting a data
unit to be transmitted from a set of data units
including a data unit that belongs to one of QoS
classes not specified for data type packets and is
obtained from the dividing part, and a data unit
that belongs to one of the QoS classes specified for
data type packets and is obtained from the
transmitter-side retransmission control part,
according to the QoS requirement, and transmitting
the selected data unit,</claim-text><claim-text>the receiving part comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a receiver-side retransmission control
part for applying a receiver-side retransmission
control process in each QoS class to the data unit
that belongs to one of the QoS classes specified for
data type packets and is one of the received data
units;</claim-text><claim-text>an assembling part for assembling in each
QoS class the data units that belong to one of the
QoS classes not specified for data type packets and
are some of the received data units, and the data
units that belong to one of the QoS classes
specified for data type packets and are obtained
from the receiver-side retransmission control part
to decompress the original packet,</claim-text><claim-text>the receiver-side retransmission control
part generates a retransmission request control
signal to indicate a data unit requested to be
retransmitted to another packet
transmitting/receiving apparatus communicating with
the packet transmitting/receiving apparatus,</claim-text><claim-text>the scheduling part performs a scheduling
process on the retransmission request control
signals with the data unit to be transmitted,</claim-text><claim-text>the transmitting part further comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>the classifying part for classifying and
outputting the retransmission request control
signals transmitted from the opposing packet
transmitting/receiving apparatus into the
transmitter-side retransmission control part, and</claim-text><claim-text>the transmitter-side retransmission
control part outputs to the scheduling part the data
unit indicated by the retransmission request control
signal transmitted from the opposing packet
transmitting/receiving apparatus upon the
retransmission request control signal being input.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="18">
      <claim-text>The packet transmitting/receiving
apparatus as claimed in claim 17, characterized in
that:
<claim-text><claim-text>the transmitting part further comprises a
header compressing part for applying a header
compression process in a predetermined manner to the
packet to be transmitted;</claim-text><claim-text>the receiving part further comprises a
header decompression part;</claim-text><claim-text>the dividing part divides a header-compressed
packet obtained from the header
compressing part into a plurality of the
predetermined data units;</claim-text><claim-text>the assembling part applies the assembling
process to the plurality of the predetermined data
units to decompress the header-compressed packet;
and</claim-text><claim-text>the header decompression part applies a
header decompression process corresponding to the
header compression process in the header compressing
part to the header-compressed packet obtained from
the assembling part to decompress the original
packet.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="19">
      <claim-text>A packet transmitting apparatus for
transmitting packets classified according to a QoS
requirement, the packet transmitting apparatus
characterized by:
<claim-text><claim-text>a dividing part provided for each QoS
class for dividing a packet to be transmitted into a
plurality of predetermined data units in each QoS
class;</claim-text><claim-text>a transmitter-side retransmission control
part for applying a transmitter-side retransmission
control process in each QoS class to the data unit
that belongs to one of QoS classes specified for
data type packets and is one of the data units
obtained from the dividing part; and</claim-text><claim-text>a scheduling part for selecting a data
unit to be transmitted from a set of data units
including a data unit that belongs to one of QoS
classes not specified for data type packets and is
obtained from the dividing part, and a data unit
that belongs to one of the QoS classes specified for
data type packets and is obtained from the
transmitter-side retransmission control part, and
transmitting the selected data unit.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="20">
      <claim-text>The packet transmitting apparatus as
claimed in claim 19, characterized in that:
<claim-text><claim-text>the packet transmitting apparatus further
comprises a header compressing part for applying a
header compression process in a predetermined manner
to the packet to be transmitted; and</claim-text><claim-text>the dividing part divides a header-compressed
packet obtained from the header
compressing part into a plurality of the
predetermined data units.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="21">
      <claim-text>A packet transmitting apparatus for
transmitting packets classified according to a QoS
requirement, the packet transmitting apparatus
characterized by:
<claim-text><claim-text>a first pre-scheduling part for selecting
classes having high priority for transmission from
QoS classes specified for data type packets;</claim-text><claim-text>a second pre-scheduling part for selecting
classes having high priority for transmission from
QoS classes not specified for data type packets;</claim-text><claim-text>a first dividing part for dividing a
queued packet to be transmitted belonging to the QoS
class selected by the first pre-scheduling part into
a plurality of predetermined data units;</claim-text><claim-text>a second dividing part for dividing a
queued packet to be transmitted belonging to the QoS
class selected by the second pre-scheduling part
into a plurality of the predetermined data units;</claim-text><claim-text>a transmitter-side retransmission control
part for applying a transmitter-side retransmission
control process to the packet to be transmitted to
be divided by the first dividing part; and</claim-text><claim-text>a scheduling part for selecting either one
of the QoS classes specified for data type packets
or one of the QoS classes not specified for data
type packets to be transmitted, transmitting the
data unit obtained from the transmitter-side
retransmission control part when the QoS class
specified for data type packets is selected, and
transmitting the data unit obtained from the second
dividing part when the QoS class not specified for
data type packets is selected.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="22">
      <claim-text>The packet transmitting apparatus as
claimed in claim 21, characterized in that:
<claim-text><claim-text>the packet transmitting apparatus further
comprises a header compressing part for applying a
header compression process in a predetermined manner
to the packet to be transmitted;</claim-text><claim-text>the dividing part divides a header-compressed
packet obtained from the header
compressing part into a plurality of the
predetermined data units.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="23">
      <claim-text>A packet transmitting apparatus for
transmitting packets classified according to a QoS
requirement, the packet transmitting apparatus
characterized by:
<claim-text><claim-text>a first scheduling part for determining
transmission order for packets to be transmitted;</claim-text><claim-text>a dividing part provided for each QoS
class for dividing the packets to be transmitted of
which transmission order is determined by the first
scheduling part into a plurality of predetermined
data units in each QoS class;</claim-text><claim-text>a transmitter-side retransmission control
part for applying a transmitter-side retransmission
control process in each QoS class to the data unit
that belongs to one of QoS classes specified for
data type packets and is one of the data units
obtained from the dividing part; and</claim-text><claim-text>a scheduling part for selecting a data
unit to be transmitted from a set of data units
including a data unit that belongs to one of QoS
classes not specified for data type packets and is
obtained from the dividing part, and a data unit
that belongs to one of the QoS classes specified for
data type packets and is obtained from the
transmitter-side retransmission control part,
according to the QoS requirement, and transmitting
the selected data unit.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="24">
      <claim-text>The packet transmitting apparatus as
claimed in claim 23, characterized in that:
<claim-text><claim-text>the packet transmitting apparatus further
comprises a header compressing part for applying a
header compression process in a predetermined manner
to the packet to be transmitted;</claim-text><claim-text>the dividing part divides a header-compressed
packet obtained from the header
compressing part into a plurality of the
predetermined data units.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="25">
      <claim-text>A packet receiving apparatus for
receiving packets classified according to a QoS
requirement in the form of predetermined data units
into which the packets are divided, the packet
receiving apparatus characterized by:
<claim-text><claim-text>a receiver-side retransmission control
part for applying a receiver-side retransmission
control process in each QoS class to the data unit
that belongs to one of the QoS classes specified for
data type packets and is one of the received data
units;</claim-text><claim-text>an assembling part for assembling in each
QoS class the data units that belong to one of the
QoS classes not specified for data type packets and
are some of the received data units, and the data
units that belong to one of the QoS classes
specified for data type packets and are obtained
from the receiver-side retransmission control part
to decompress the original packet.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="26">
      <claim-text>A packet receiving apparatus for
receiving packets classified according to QoS
requirement in the form of predetermined data units
into which the packets are processed for header
compression and divided, the packet receiving
apparatus characterized by:
<claim-text><claim-text>a receiver-side retransmission control
part for applying a receiver-side retransmission
control process in each QoS class to the data unit
that belongs to one of the QoS classes specified for
data type packets and is one of the received data
units;</claim-text><claim-text>an assembling part for assembling in each
QoS class the data units that belong to one of the
QoS classes not specified for data type packets and
are some of the received data units, and the data
units that belong to one of the QoS classes
specified for data type packets and are obtained
from the receiver-side retransmission control part
to decompress the header-compressed packet; and</claim-text><claim-text>a header decompression part for applying a
header decompression process to the header-compressed
packet obtained from the assembling part
to decompress the original packet.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
