<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1239708-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1239708" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="26610588" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020911">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1239708-A2" status="new" fvid="23535268">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1239708</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20020911</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02251457-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02251457</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020301</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001059278-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001059278</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010302</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001392786-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001392786</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20011225</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H02M   7/48        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H02M   7/48        20070101ALI20061211RHJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H02M   7/538       20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H02M   7/538       20070101ALI20061211RHJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H05B  41/24        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H05B  41/24        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H05B  41/28        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H05B  41/288       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H05B  41/292       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H05B  41/288E2B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H05B  41/292L</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Beleuchtungsgerät für eine Entladungslampe hoher Intensität, und Leuchte zu diesem Zweck</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">High-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus and luminaire for using the same</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Appareil pour alimenter une lampe à décharge de forte intensité, et luminaire à cet usage</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TOSHIBA LIGHTING &amp; TECHNOLOGY</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TOSHIBA LIGHTING &amp; TECHNOLOGY CORPORATION</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>TOSHIBA LIGHTING &amp;amp; TECHNOLOGY CORPORATION</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>3-1, Higashishinagawa 4-Chome</street>
              <city>Shinagawa-ku, Tokyo</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KOZUKA HIDEO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MITA KAZUTOSHI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KOZUKA, HIDEO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MITA, KAZUTOSHI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Kozuka, Hideo, Toshiba Lighting &amp;amp; Technoloy Corp</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>4-3-1, Higashishinagawa</street>
              <city>Shinagawa-ku, Tokyo</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Mita, Kazutoshi, Toshiba Lighting &amp;amp; Technoloy Corp</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>4-3-1, Higashishinagawa</street>
              <city>Shinagawa-ku, Tokyo</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>O'Connell, David Christopher</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Haseltine Lake &amp;amp; Co., Imperial House, 15-19 Kingsway</street>
              <city>London WC2B 6UD</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>NL</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus, including
a main circuit (23), which contains an LC oscillation circuit (24), and to
which a high-intensity discharge lamp (8) is coupled, and an electronic
ballast (22) for starting up into a lighting state the high-intensity
discharge lamp via the main circuit which is coupled to its output
side, and it is operated at a resonance frequency of the LC
resonance circuit in the main circuit at a no-load time.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="143" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="102"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a high-intensity discharge
lamp lighting apparatus for stably lighting a high-intensity
discharge lamp and to a luminaire for using the same.</p>
    <p num="0002">Conventionally, such a discharge lamp lighting apparatus is
disclosed in the JP 62-241295.</p>
    <p num="0003">The discharge lamp lighting apparatus disclosed in the
JP62-241295 is provided with an LC resonance type electronic
ballast for preheating filaments in discharge lamps.</p>
    <p num="0004">The electronic ballast makes its frequency to continuously
lower in beginning with a frequency higher than an LC resonance
frequency. When the frequency becomes close to the LC resonance
frequency, the lamps having filaments are started up into a
lighting state. When the electronic ballast starts an oscillation at
such a high frequency, the filaments are preheated by a low
secondary voltage enough to avoid a start-up of the discharge lamp.
As the electronic ballast frequency gradually lowers and becomes
close to the LC resonance frequency, the secondary voltage is
boosted. When the secondary voltage reaches a predetermined
voltage, the discharge lamp is started up. After a discharge lamp
has lighted up, the electronic ballast frequency lowers below the
LC resonance frequency. Then the discharge lamp is maintained
in lighting state. </p>
    <p num="0005">However, the discharge lamp lighting apparatus disclosed in
the JP62-241295 has drawbacks of complicated operation and
control for varying the secondary voltage by continuously varying
the frequency. In a low pressure discharge lamp such as a
fluorescent lamp, the discharge lamp is started up into a lighting
state when the secondary voltage becomes a high voltage for a very
short period even shorter than a second. However, in a
high-intensity discharge lamp, especially using a neon (Ne) and an
argon (Ar), the secondary voltage must be maintained for a
relatively long period, i.e., one to two seconds for the glow-arc
transition. However, in the conventional discharge lamp, it was
unable to maintain the high voltage comparatively for a long time.
So that, it was difficult to start to light the high intensity
discharge lamp certainly.</p>
    <p num="0006">On the other hand, the electronic ballast needs a frequency of
20 kHz or more that is the upper limit of an audible frequency
range in order to prevent flickering. Moreover, it is common to
set the electronic ballast frequency to 100 kHz or less in order to
make measures against the flickering easy. However, in the band
of 20 kHz to 100 kHz, which is used relatively often for the
electronic ballast frequency, there exist dispersively several
frequency bands wherein the high intensity discharge lamp might
causes acoustic resonance. Thus, a frequency around the central
region of the stable operation window, that is a frequency band
free from acoustic resonance, among areas where the acoustic
resonance might occur on the high-intensity discharge lamp, is 
used for the electronic ballast resonance frequency.</p>
    <p num="0007">However, since the frequency band of this stable operation
window is very narrow, when the electronic ballast frequency is
being fixed, several frequency bands of acoustic resonance of the
high intensity discharge lamps overlap the fixed electronic ballast
frequency according to variations in products, so as to cause the
drawback of acoustic resonance, i.e., flickering. In such a case, it
is difficult to determine in which end of the fixed electronic ballast
frequency band the acoustic resonance occurs. That is, it is
difficult to determine whether the acoustic resonance occurs in the
upper end of a lower frequency band or in the lower end of a higher
frequency band. Therefore, it is difficult to deal with the acoustic
resonance.</p>
    <p num="0008">To solve such problems, it is considered to choose the
electronic ballast frequency in a sufficiently high frequency band
or in a sufficiently low frequency band which is free from acoustic
resonance.</p>
    <p num="0009">However, in such a high frequency, there is a drawback that
the switching loss of the electronic ballast becomes large.</p>
    <p num="0010">Further, for obtaining such a low frequency, the inductance of
an LC resonance circuit has to be made larger. As a result, there
is a drawback of upsizing a coil constituting the LC resonance
circuit.</p>
    <p num="0011">As described above, in the discharge lamp lighting apparatus
disclosed in the JP62-241295, the control of varying the secondary
voltage in the operation of continuously varying the electronic 
ballast frequency becomes complicated.</p>
    <p num="0012">Moreover, in the case of a high intensity discharge lamp, it is
required to maintain a high no-load voltage for 1 or 2 seconds for
causing the glow-arc transition. However, it is difficult to
continuously vary the frequency while fulfilling such conditions.
Thus it is also difficult to maintain the open circuit voltage for a
sufficient time.</p>
    <p num="0013">Furthermore, if it is tried to use the central frequency in a
stable operation window of a very narrow frequency band within
the frequency band of 20 kHz to 100 kHz that is used very often as
an electronic ballast oscillation frequency, an actual oscillation
frequency deviates from the stable operation window. Accordingly,
since it is unclear whether the oscillation frequency is higher or
lower than the stable operation window even when the lamp power
varies extensively, or the acoustic resonance occurs, it is difficult
to deal with these problems. When the electronic ballast
oscillation frequency rises to a high frequency enough for avoiding
acoustic resonance, there occurs a problem of increasing the
switching loss. On the contrary, however when the electronic
ballast oscillation frequency lowers to a low frequency enough for
avoiding acoustic resonance, there occurs another problem of
upsizing the apparatus.</p>
    <p num="0014">The present invention was made in view of these problems,
and it has an object to provide a high-intensity discharge lamp
lighting apparatus for stably lighting a high-intensity discharge
lamp and a luminaire for using the same. </p>
    <p num="0015">In order to achieve the object described above, the
high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus according to the
first embodiment of the present invention, comprising, a main
circuit which contains an LC resonance circuit, and which is
coupled to a high-intensity discharge lamp, an electronic ballast
which starts and lights the high-intensity discharge lamp via the
main circuit which is coupled to the output side of it, and which is
operated with a resonance frequency of the LC resonance circuit in
the main circuit in the no-load condition, and the electronic ballast,
which is operated at the resonance frequency of the LC resonance
circuit in the main circuit in the no-load condition, can increase a
secondary open voltage through the glow discharge condition and
maintain the high secondary voltage at the time of glow-arc
transition.</p>
    <p num="0016">The high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus
according to a second embodiment of the present invention, the LC
resonance circuit is provided with inductors in addition. The
inductors saturate at the start of the glow discharge of the
high-intensity discharge lamp, and fail to saturate during the glow
discharge and arc discharge operations. A high intensity
discharge lamp starts the glow discharge operation in a short time
by applied the high voltage since it requires the electrical
breakdown before lighting, and it applies less stress to a circuit
even under the condition that the inductors saturate. As it is
necessary to radiate thermions in a glow-arc transition, it is able
to avoid stresses being applied to the circuit if the circuit is 
maintained in a relatively high voltage for a period necessary for
the glow-arc transition by avoiding saturation of inductors.</p>
    <p num="0017">A high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus according
to a third embodiment of the present invention, wherein the
operating frequency of the electronic ballast at the start of the
glow discharge of the high-intensity discharge lamp matches the
resonance frequency of the LC resonance circuit in the no-load
condition under the state that the inductors saturate, and its
frequency during the glow discharge of the high-intensity
discharge lamp matches the no-load resonance frequency of the LC
resonance circuit under that state that the inductors fail to
saturate. So, it becomes easy to control the frequencies of the
high-intensity discharge lamp at the start of the glow discharge
time, during the glow discharge, and at the glow-arc transition
time. Accordingly, even in the high intensity discharge lamp
which requires a high voltage to maintain the glow discharge (a
high intensity discharge lamp in which Ne is filled), it is able to
maintain the glow discharge and improve the start-up performance.
Here, the no-load resonance frequency during a glow discharge
operation and at a glow-arc transition means an acoustic
resonance frequency of the whole including the high intensity
discharge lamp. Since the high-intensity discharge lamp during
the glow discharge operation and at the glow-arc transition time is
in a high impedance state, they are indicated as a no-load here.</p>
    <p num="0018">A high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus according
to a fourth aspect of the present invention further comprises, a 
glow discharge detector for detecting the glow discharge of the
high intensity discharge lamp, and an output reducer for reducing
an output voltage within the range where the glow discharge is
maintained at a frequency higher than the resonance frequency at
the no-load state of the LC resonance circuit under the condition
where the inductors are not saturate after detecting the glow
discharge in the glow discharge detector, wherein after the
detection of the glow discharge, the electronic ballast is effectively
operated at a lagging phase and a frequency higher than the
resonance frequency at the no-load state, while its output voltage
lowers. Accordingly, it is able to reduce the voltage inputted to
the high-intensity discharge lamp at the glow discharge time, and
suppress a blackening of the lamp by suppressing sputtering of
electrode materials in high-intensity discharge lamps.</p>
    <p num="0019">A high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus according
to a fifth aspect of the present invention, wherein the operating
frequency of the electronic ballast is set to be near the upper limit
or the lower limit of the frequency band where the acoustic
resonance occurs on the high-intensity discharge lamp. So, even
when the acoustic resonance occurs on the high-intensity discharge
lamp, it is easy to determine whether the lighting frequency is too
high or too low. Thus, by controlling the lighting frequency to be
shifted into either frequency band which is free from acoustic
resonance, so as to avoid the acoustic resonance.</p>
    <p num="0020">A high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus according
to a sixth aspect of the present invention, further comprising an 
acoustic resonance detector for detecting the acoustic resonance of
the high-intensity discharge lamp. When the acoustic resonance
is detected in the acoustic resonance detector, the operating
frequency of the electronic ballast shifts into either frequency band
which is free from acoustic resonance. As the acoustic resonance
is reduced if the electronic ballast frequency shifts into either
frequency band which is free from acoustic resonance, and is
opposite to the frequency band close to the ordinary set-up
frequency where the acoustic resonance might occur, the acoustic
resonance is avoided by shifting the frequency to the other end of
the frequency band which is free from acoustic resonance.</p>
    <p num="0021">A high intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus according
to a seventh aspect of the present invention comprises a timer
circuit in addition. When the glow discharge detector does not
detect the glow discharge of the discharge lamp within a specific
periods clocked with the timer circuit, the electronic ballast is
reset to the state at the start of operation. When the discharge
lamp fails the glow discharge, the operation is repeated from the
state at the start of operation.</p>
    <p num="0022">A luminaire according to an eighth aspect of the present
invention comprises a high-intensity discharge lamp lighting
apparatus of any embodiments described above, and a lighting
equipment main body whereon the high-intensity discharge lamp
to be lighted up in the high-intensity discharge lamp lighting
apparatus is mounted.</p>
    <p num="0023">Additional objects and advantages of the present invention 
will be apparent to persons skilled in the art from a study of the
following description and the accompanying drawings, which are
hereby incorporated in and constitute a part of this specification.</p>
    <p num="0024">A more complete appreciation of the present invention and
many of the attendant advantages thereof will be readily obtained
as the same becomes better understood by reference to the
following detailed description when considered in connection with
the accompanying drawings, wherein:
<sl><li>Fig. 1 is a circuit diagram showing the first embodiment of
the high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus according to
the present invention;</li><li>Fig. 2 is a sectional drawing showing the lighting system of
the eighth embodiment according to the present invention;</li><li>Fig. 3 is a graph showing the relation between the secondary
voltage and the frequency in the first embodiment of the
high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus according to the
present invention;</li><li>Figs. 4A to 4D are waveform diagrams showing the secondary
voltage, the drain current and the input voltage of the oscillation
driver IC in the first embodiment of the high-intensity discharge
lamp lighting apparatus according to the present invention;</li><li>Fig. 5 is a graph showing a current of the field-effect
transistor when the dead time lasts long in the first embodiment of
the high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus of the
present invention;</li><li>Fig. 6 is a graph showing a current of the field-effect 
transistor when the dead time lasts in short time in the first
embodiment of the high-intensity discharge lamp lighting
apparatus according to the present invention;</li><li>Fig. 7 is a circuit diagram showing the second embodiment of
the high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus according to
the present invention</li><li>Fig. 8 is a diagram explaining the relation between the stable
operation window and the frequency in the second embodiment of
the high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus according to
the present invention;</li><li>Fig. 9 is a circuit diagram showing the third embodiment of
the high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus according to
the present invention;</li><li>Fig. 10 is a waveform chart showing the no-load secondary
voltage in the third embodiment of the high-intensity discharge
lamp lighting apparatus according to the present invention;</li><li>Fig. 11 is waveform chart zoomed up showing the no-load
secondary voltage in the third embodiment of the high-intensity
discharge lamp lighting apparatus according to the present
invention;</li><li>Fig. 12 is a graph showing the relation between the input
power, the pulse width of the no-load secondary voltage and the
temperature rise in the third embodiment of the high-intensity
discharge lamp lighting apparatus according to the present
invention;</li><li>Fig. 13 is a circuit diagram showing the fourth embodiment of 
the high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus according to
the present invention;</li><li>Fig. 14 is a graph showing the relation between the secondary
voltage and the frequency in the fourth embodiment of
the present invention;</li><li>Fig. 15 is a waveform chart showing the change with time in
the voltage applied to the high-intensity discharge lamp in the
fourth embodiment of the high-intensity discharge lamp lighting
apparatus according to the present invention; and</li><li>Figs. 16A and 16B are graphs showing the relation of the
output voltage and the lamp voltage in the electronic ballast to the
current value applied to the high-intensity discharge lamp in the
fourth embodiment of the high-intensity discharge lamp lighting
apparatus according to the present invention.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0025">The present invention will be described in detail with
reference to the attached drawings, Figs. 1 through 16.</p>
    <p num="0026">Fig. 1 is a circuit diagram showing the first embodiment of
the high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus according to
the present invention. Fig. 2 is a sectional view of the luminaire
using therein the high-intensity discharge lamp lighting
apparatus.</p>
    <p num="0027">As shown in Fig. 2, the luminaire is provided with a
cylindrical main body 1. A screw base 2 is secured on the basic
end of the main body 1, and a light-projecting section 4 is fitted to
a cylindrical protector 3 defined at the tip end of the main body 1.
The light-projecting section 4 has a parabolic reflector 6 which is 
provided with a light projection opening 5. To the light projection
opening 5 a translucent cover 7 is attached. A high-intensity
discharge lamp (HID) 8 such as a ceramic metal halide lamp is
mounted in the parabolic reflector 6 around its focal point.</p>
    <p num="0028">A wiring board is settled inside the main body 1. The
high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus 11 for lighting
the high-intensity discharge lamp 8 is constructed on the wiring
board 10.</p>
    <p num="0029">The high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus 11 is
coupled to a commercial AC power source e via an input circuit
comprised of a resistor R1, an inductor L1, a constant-voltage
device Z1 and a capacitor C1, as shown in Fig. 1. The input
circuit is coupled to a double-voltage rectifier 21. The
double-voltage rectifier 21 is comprised of a series circuit of diodes
D1 and D2, and a series circuit of capacitors C2 and C3, and it is
coupled to an electronic ballast 22.</p>
    <p num="0030">The electronic ballast 22 is constructed in a half-bridge
configuration wherein two field-effect transistors Q1 and Q2
performing switching operation are coupled in series with each
other. To the field-effect transistor Q2 is coupled a main circuit
23 in parallel, in which a DC-blocking capacitor C4, two inductors
L2 and L3 in series which become a ballast chalk, and two
capacitors C5 and C6 in series which comprise an LC resonance
circuit 24 with the inductors L2 and L3 are coupled in series, and
it is coupled to the reference potential line RPL via a resistor R2.
The series circuit of two capacitors C5 and C6 of this main circuit 
23 is coupled over between the connecting ends 8A and 8B of the
high intensity discharge lamp 8. The LC resonance circuit 24
operates at a resonance frequency when the inductors L2 and L3
saturate, thus the high-intensity discharge lamp 8 produces an
electrical breakdown. So that, a high voltage necessary for
starting the glow discharge is obtained. Since a large resonance
current flows to the LC resonance circuit 24 at the start-up
operation of the glow discharge of the high-intensity discharge
lamp 8, the inductors L2 and L3 saturate due to the resonance
current. Here, since a current which flows to the high-intensity
discharge lamp 8 during the glow discharge, at the glow-arc
transition time, and during the arc discharge time, the inductors
L2 and L3 fail to saturate.</p>
    <p num="0031">Moreover, a snubber circuit 26 which serves as an auxiliary
power source for a oscillation driver IC 25 (Model UBA2021T
which is available from Philips Semiconductor Ltd.), as described
later, is coupled in parallel to the field-effect transistor Q2. The
snubber circuit 26 is constructed by a capacitor C7, a series circuit
of a diode D3 and a capacitor C8, and a diode D4 which is coupled
in parallel to the series circuit of the diode D3 and the capacitor
C8.</p>
    <p num="0032">Furthermore, pins P5 and P6 of the oscillation driver IC 25
are connected to the gates of the field-effect transistors Q1 and Q2.
A pin P1 of the oscillation driver IC 25 is coupled to a connection
node of the field-effect transistors Q1 and Q2. A pin P3 of the
oscillation driver IC 25 is coupled to a connection node of the 
field-effect transistor Q1 and Q2. Pins P12 and P13 of the
oscillation driver IC 25 are coupled to a pin P8 of the oscillation
driver IC 25. The pins P12 and P13 are connected to the pin P8
via capacitors C12 and C13. A pin P10 of the oscillation driver IC
25 is coupled to the pin P8 via resistors R3 and R4 in the order. A
negative electrode power-terminal pin P7 of the oscillation driver
IC 25 is coupled to the reference potential line RPL. Here, a
resistor R3, a variable resistor R4, and a capacitor C12 constitute
a time-constant circuit for determining an oscillation frequency of
the oscillation driver IC 25. Further, a positive electrode side of
the double-voltage rectifier 21 is connected to a positive electrode
power terminal pin P13 of the oscillation driver IC 25 via a
start-up resistor R5, and a negative electrode side of it is coupled
to a negative electrode power terminal pin P7 of the oscillation
driver IC 25 via the resistor R2.</p>
    <p num="0033">Furthermore, a lamp voltage detection circuit 27 is coupled
across connecting terminals 8A and 8B of the high-intensity
discharge lamp 8 via the resistor R2. The lamp voltage detection
circuit 27 is constructed by a resistor R6, a series circuit of
resistors R7 and R8, and a series circuit of a diode D5 and a
capacitor C14 which is coupled in parallel to the series circuit of
the resistors R7 and R8. Furthermore, a series circuit of a
resistor R11, a Zener diode ZD1 and a capacitor C15 is coupled to a
capacitor C14 of the lamp voltage detector 27. A connection node
of the Zener diode ZD1 and the capacitor C15 is coupled to the base
of a transistor Q3. A resistor R12 is coupled across the base and 
the emitter of the transistor Q3, and the collector of the transistor
Q3 is coupled to the pin P5 of the oscillation driver IC 25 and the
snubber circuit 26.</p>
    <p num="0034">Further, a series circuit of a capacitor C16 and a diode D6 is
coupled in parallel to the resistor R8. A diode D7 is coupled
between the connection node of the the capacitor C16 and the diode
D6 and a timer circuit 28. The timer circuit 28 is constructed by
a switching transistor Q4, capacitors C17, C18 and a diode D8.
The collector of the transistor Q4 is coupled to the diode D7, while
the emitter of the transistor Q4 is coupled to the reference
potential line RPL. The capacitor C17 is coupled across the
transistor Q4. The capacitor C18 and the diode D8 are connected
in series with each other, and then the series circuit is coupled
across the transistor Q4. Then the connection node of the
capacitor C18 and the diode D8 is coupled to the base of the
transistor Q4. On the other hand, a resistor R14 is coupled in
parallel with the timer circuit 28. A series circuit of a Zener
diode ZD2 and a resistor R15 is coupled across the
collector-emitter path of the transistor Q4.</p>
    <p num="0035">Moreover, a capacitor C19 is coupled in parallel to the
resistor R15. The gate of a thyristor Q5 is coupled to a connection
node of the Zener diode ZD2 and the capacitor C19. The anode of
the thyristor Q5 is coupled to the pin P5 of the oscillation driver
IC 25 through a diode D9. The cathode of the thyristor Q5 is
coupled to the reference potential line RPL. Furthermore, a
connection node of the diode D9 and the thyristor Q5 is coupled to 
the positive electrode of the double-voltage rectifier 21 via a
resistor R16.</p>
    <p num="0036">Now the operation of the first embodiment will be explained.</p>
    <p num="0037">First, a DC generated by rectifying and smoothing an AC
voltage of the commercial AC power source e in the double-voltage
rectifier circuit 21 is supplied to the electronic ballast 22. A small
current is supplied to the oscillation driver IC 25 via the start-up
resistor R5 from the electronic ballast 22. The oscillation driver
IC 25 makes the electronic ballast 22 oscillate by alternately
turning on and off the field-effect transistors Q1 and Q2.
Immediately after that the oscillation has started, the oscillation
driver IC 25 operates in a frequency which is twice or more of the
operation frequency of the high intensity discharge lamp 8 in
lighting state. Moreover, since the electronic ballast 22 oscillates
at the high frequency immediately after that the oscillation has
started the oscillation driver IC 25 is kept in operation by being
supplied a power from the snubber circuit 26. Here, since the
oscillation frequency rises higher only the time immediately after
that the electronic ballast 22 has started oscillation, a steady-state
current of power source is stably supplied to the oscillation driver
IC 25.</p>
    <p num="0038">After the start of the oscillation, the oscillation driver IC 25
gradually lowers the oscillation frequency until an advancing
phase is detected in the resistor R2 for detecting an advancing
phase oscillation. At that time, the operating frequency matches
with the resonance frequency at the time of the saturation of the 
inductors L2 and L3. At the time of starting the glow discharge
while the high intensity discharge lamp 8 is not discharging at all,
the inductors L2 and L3 saturate due to the resonance current.
Thus, the inductors L2 and L3 output high voltages. At that time,
a voltage for starting the glow discharge of the high-intensity
discharge lamp 8 is produced over the series circuit of the
capacitors C5 and C6.</p>
    <p num="0039">On the other hand, at the glow discharge and the glow-arc
transition time of the high-intensity discharge lamp 8, since a
small current of about 10 mA flows the circuit, the resonance
current lowers, and the inductors L2 and L3 fail to saturate. In
such a condition, when a lamp current is supplied for about two
seconds, the glow-arc transition is took place. So that, the
high-intensity discharge lamp 8 is started up into a lighting state.</p>
    <p num="0040">This is effective for a high-intensity discharge lamp, in which
a neon and an argon are filled e.g., and which requires a high
voltage to keep the glow discharge.</p>
    <p num="0041">When the high intensity discharge lamp 8 is in a normal
lighting state, the electronic ballast 22 operates at the frequency
of 20 kHz or more of unloaded main circuit 23 wherein the
inductors L2 and L3 fail to saturate, as shown in Fig. 3, that is, for
instance, a constant frequency almost equal to the resonance
frequency of 46 kHz. That is, the high-intensity discharge lamp is
regularly lighted at a frequency which is equivalent to a resonance
frequency having a resonance characteristic curve A1 at the
no-load state wherein the inductors L2 and L3 fail to saturate on a 
resonance characteristic curve A2 at the lighting time. Thus,
after the high intensity discharge lamp 8 transfers to an arc
discharge, it is able to oscillate the electronic ballast 22 at a
constant frequency which is free from acoustic resonance. As a
result, the high-intensity discharge lamp 8 can be lighted over all
the life periods.</p>
    <p num="0042">A resonance characteristic curve A0 during the inductors L2
and L3 saturate has a resonance point f01 that is higher than a
resonance characteristic curve A1 at the no-load state. Here, the
resonance point f01 differs according to the saturation levels of the
inductors L2 and L3.</p>
    <p num="0043">When the high intensity discharge lamp 8 is in a light-off
state, the voltage applied across the high-intensity discharge lamp
8 rises. Accordingly, the electric potential of the connection node
of the resistors R6 and R7 in the lamp voltage detection circuit 27
rises, and the electric potential of the capacitor C14 also rises.
When the electric potential of the capacitor 14 becomes a
predetermined value or more, the Zener diode ZD1 is turned on,
and a base current is applied to the transistor Q3. So that, the
transistor Q3 is turned On. Therefore, an output voltage Vc of
the snubber circuit which is coupled to the transistor Q3 lowers.
As a result, the oscillation driver IC 25 which uses the snubber
circuit 26 as an auxiliary power source is shut off. So that, the
electronic ballast 22 halts oscillation, as shown in Figs. 4A to 4D.
When the electronic ballast 22 halts oscillation, an electric
potential of the LC resonance circuit 24 lowers, and the electric 
potential of the connection node of the resistors R6 and R7 in the
lamp voltage detection circuit 27 also lowers. So that, a capacitor
C14 which is coupled to the connection node of the resistors R6 and
R7 via a diode D5 is discharged. Thus, when the electric potential
of the capacitor C14 is reduced lower than a predetermined value,
the Zener diode ZD1 is turned off, and the base current of the
transistor Q3 is interrupted. So that, the transistor Q3 is turned
off. Accordingly, the oscillation driver IC 25 is biased to the
operation state. At that time, a start-up current flows from a
start-up resistor R5 to the oscillation driver IC 25, thus, the
electronic ballast 22 starts oscillation. Then, the current is
supplied also from the snubber circuit 26, the electronic ballast 22
starts to operate at a normal frequency of 46 kHz after it operates
a frequency of 115 kHz which is 2.5 times as much as the operating
frequency at the lighting operation time. So that, the output of it
increases. Thus, as the charge and discharge of the capacitor C14
is repeated, the voltage is applied to the high-intensity discharge
lamp 8 intermittently, as shown in Figs. 4A to 4D. A peak to peak
value of the AC voltage supplied to the high-intensity discharge
lamp 8 is 20 kV or more at the restart-up operation, though it is 1
to 2 kV at the first start-up operation. So that, the high-intensity
discharge lamp 8 is maintained in the lighting-off state without
lighting on the lamp 8.</p>
    <p num="0044">For instance, in the late stage of the lamp life, the voltage
applied to the high-intensity discharge lamp 8 rises. The electric
potential at the connection node of the resistors R7 and R8 in the 
lamp voltage detection circuit 27 also rises. And then, the
potential of the capacitor C17 coupled to the connection node of the
resistors via the diode D5 and the resistor R11 rises. When the
electric potential of the capacitor C17 rises higher than a
predetermined value, the Zener diode ZD2 is turned on. Then a
trigger voltage is applied to the gate of a thyristor Q5. Thus, the
thyristor Q5 is turned on. As a result, a series circuit comprised
of the diode D9 and the thyristor Q5 is brought into conduction.
Thus, the voltage Vcc of the snubber circuit 26 lowers. The
current supplied to the oscillation driver IC 25 from the snubber
circuit 26 is halted. As a result, since the voltage Vcc of the
power input terminal pin P5 in the oscillation driver IC 25 lowers
below the oscillation sustaining voltage, the electronic ballast 22
halts oscillation. Since the thyristor Q5 is kept in conduction by a
current supplied from the resistor R16, the oscillation halting
makes the electronic ballast 22 suspend the oscillation driver IC
25 until the power source is reset. In other words, the electronic
ballast 22 is kept in a shut-off state.</p>
    <p num="0045">Moreover, when the inductors L2 and L3 saturate, the
inductances of those inductors 12 and L3 lower, while the
resonance frequency of the LC resonance circuit 24 rises. In this
case, the electronic ballast 22 oscillates in the state of advancing
phase. When the field-effect transistor Q2 is turned on by the
oscillation driver IC 25 under the advancing phase oscillation state
of the electronic ballast 22, an inverse voltage occurs across the
resistor R2 and then it is input to the oscillation driver IC 25. 
Therefore, when the inverse voltage of the resistor R2 is detected
by the voltage detecting terminal pin P9 of the oscillation driver
IC 25, it is determined that the electronic ballast 22 is in the
advancing phase oscillation state. When it is determined that the
electronic ballast 22 is in the advancing phase oscillation state,
the oscillation driver IC 25 makes the operation frequencies of the
transistors Q1 and Q2 rise in order to return the operation of the
electronic ballast 22 from the advancing phase state to the normal
operation. As a result, the oscillation frequency is controlled to
coincide with the resonance point.</p>
    <p num="0046">Furthermore, since the inductors L2 and L3 fail to saturate
while the high-intensity discharge lamp 8 is under the state of the
arc discharge operation, the electronic ballast 22 oscillates in the
advancing phase state. However, when a small current flows and
the so-called no-load secondary voltage is generated while the
high-intensity discharge lamp fails to start the glow discharge, and
it starts the glow discharge, the inductors L2 and L3 saturate.
The electronic ballast 22 then oscillates in the state of advancing
phase at the dead time when the field-effect transistors Q1 and Q2
are both turned off. Thus, there is a fear of flowing an advancing
phase current.</p>
    <p num="0047">So, the dead time when the field-effect transistors Q1 and Q2
are turned off for preventing a short circuit is set to 1 µ sec. in
ordinary time. While it is set to 0.1µ sec. at the occurrence of the
no-load secondary voltage.</p>
    <p num="0048">According to a simulation, when a dead time is 1 µ sec. as in 
the case of normal operations, the advancing phase oscillation
period lasts as it is. Then the advancing phase current Ix has
been generated for a relatively long time, as shown in Fig. 5.
When the dead time is set to 0.1 µ sec., which is 1/10 times the
normal operation time, the advancing phase oscillation period
decreases, and the duration of the advancing phase current Ix has
been generated also decreases, as shown in Fig. 6.</p>
    <p num="0049">So, in the first embodiment of the present invention, since
the oscillation driver IC 25 is able to be operated with an auxiliary
power of the snubber circuit 26 at the instant following the start of
operation of the electronic ballast 22, the start-up resistor R5 just
operates to feed a small current. That results in reducing the size
of the resistor R5.</p>
    <p num="0050">Since the high-intensity discharge lamp 8 does not have
thermal cathode, in addition, it does not need to emit a thermion
at the start of the glow discharge, it can start a glow discharge in a
short time. Here, even though the inductors L2 and L3 saturate,
it does not last so long time, so it is not a problem. On the other
hand, if a current of about 10 mA is supplied to the lamp when the
inductors L2 and L3 saturate, the stress to the circuit will become
large. Thus, the inductors L2 and L3 are adapted to avoid
saturations in the glow discharge operation and at the start of the
arc discharge. Furthermore, since the high-intensity discharge
lamp 8 requires a high start-up voltage when the lamp 8 is
restarted under a high temperature condition, the inductors L2
and L3 are miniaturized while ensuring its start-up performance 
by minimizing the saturation time which is required for starting
the glow discharge.</p>
    <p num="0051">Referring now to Fig. 7, the second embodiment of the
high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus 11 according to
the present invention will be explained hereinafter.</p>
    <p num="0052">Fig. 7 is a circuit diagram showing the second embodiment of
the high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus 11. As
shown in Fig. 7, the high-intensity discharge lamp lighting
apparatus 11 is coupled to a commercial AC power source e via an
input circuit comprised of a resistor R21, a fuse F1, a capacitor
C21, and an inductor L11. The input circuit is coupled to a
full-wave rectifier 31. The full-wave rectifier 31 is a diode bridge
circuit consisting of four diodes D11, D12, D13, and D14. A
smoothing capacitor C22 and an electronic ballast 32 are each
connected across the positive and negative output terminals of the
full-wave rectifier 31. In addition, the negative output terminal
of the full-wave rectifier 31 is also a reference potential line RPL.</p>
    <p num="0053">This electronic ballast 32 is constructed in a half-bridge
configuration wherein two field-effect transistors Q11 and Q12
performing switching operations are coupled in series with each
other. The gate of the field-effect transistor Q11, whose drain is
connected to the negative of the full-wave rectifier 31, is coupled to
a connection node of the inductor L11 of the input circuit and the
diode D11 of the full-wave rectifier 31 via a start-up resistor R22.
The source of the field-effect transistor Q12, whose source is again
connected to the positive side of the full-wave rectifier 31, that is 
the reference potential line RPL, is also coupled to the reference
potential line RPL via a start-up resistor R23 and a snubber
capacitor C23 connected in parallel.</p>
    <p num="0054">A connection node of the field-effect transistors Q11 and Q12
is coupled to one connecting terminal 8A of the high-intensity
discharge lamp 8 via a primary winding Tr1a of a transformer Tr1
and a DC-blocking capacitor C24 in order. Here, the primary
winding Tr1a performs as a ballast chalk function, too. The other
connecting terminal 8B of the high-intensity discharge lamp is
coupled to the reference potential line RPL. A resonance
capacitor C25 is connected across the connecting terminals 8A and
8B of the high-intensity discharge lamp 8. Further, Zener diodes
ZD11 and ZD12 are coupled in series with opposite polarities each
other between the gate and the source of the field-effect transistor
Q11. Also, Zener diodes ZD13 and ZD14 are coupled in series
with opposite polarities each other between the gate and the
source of the field-effect transistor Q12.</p>
    <p num="0055">In addition, between the gate and the source of the
field-effect transistor Q11, a series circuit of a capacitor C26, a
primary winding Tr2a of the transistor Tr2,, and a secondary
winding Tr1b of the transistor Tr1 is connected. Also, across the
gate ad the source of the field-effect transistor Q12, a series circuit
of a capacitor C27, a secondary winding Tr2b of the transistor Tr2,
and a secondary winding Tr1c of the transistor Tr1 is connected.</p>
    <p num="0056">Furthermore, a series circuit of resistors R24 and R25 for
detecting a lamp voltage is connected across the connecting 
terminals 8A and 8B of the high-intensity discharge lamp 8.
These resistor R24 and R25 constitute an acoustic resonance
detector 33. A connection node of the resistors R24 and R25 is
coupled to the reference potential line RPL via a series circuit of a
diode D14 and a Zener diode ZD16 with opposite polarities and a
parallel circuit of a resistor R26 and a capacitor C28 in order. A
connection node of the series circuit of the diode D14 and the Zener
diode ZD16 and the parallel circuit of the resistor R26 and the
capacitor C28 is coupled to the gate of a field-effect transistor Q14.
A source of the field-effect transistor Q14 is coupled to the
reference potential line RPL, and its drain is coupled to the
connection node of the Zener diodes ZD13 and ZD14 which are
coupled in series with the opposite polarities each other between
the source of the field-effect transistor Q12 and the reference
potential line RPL. Further, the source of the field-effect
transistor Q14 is coupled to a connection node of a resistor R27
and R28 of a series circuit which is comprised of the resistors R27,
R28, and R29 connected between the negative output terminal of
the rectifier 31 and the reference potential line RPL. Moreover, a
connection node of the resistors R28 and R29 is coupled to the
reference potential line RPL via a capacitor C29. In addition, the
connection node of the resistors R28 and R29 is also coupled to the
gate of a field-effect transistor Q15. A drain of the field-effect
transistor Q15 is coupled to the gate of the field-effect transistor
Q12 via a capacitor C30, and its source is coupled to the reference
potential line RPL. Further, the drain of the field-effect 
transistor Q15 is also coupled to the reference potential line RPL
via a resistor R30.</p>
    <p num="0057">Now, the operation of the second embodiment will be
explained hereinafter.</p>
    <p num="0058">First, the AC voltage of the commercial AC power source e is
rectified in the full wave rectifier 31, and smoothed in the
capacitor C22 so as to obtain the DC voltage, then the DC is
applied to the electronic ballast 32. Further, the AC voltage of
the commercial AC power source e flows into the series circuit
comprised of the start-up resistor R22, the Zener diode ZD11, the
Zener diode ZD12, and the start-up resistor R23, while the
field-effect transistor Q11 is turned on with the potential obtained
at the anode of the Zener diode ZD11. Then, the AC voltage
smoothed in the capacitor C22 turns on and off the field-effect
transistors Q11 and Q12 in the electronic ballast 32 by turns.
According to the switching operation, a high frequency alternating
current is generated. The high frequency alternating current is
supplied to the high intensity discharge lamp 8 for lighting the
lamp.</p>
    <p num="0059">The operating frequency of the electronic ballast 32 is chosen
within one frequency band of the stable operation windows A1, A2,
and A3 shown in Fig. 8 so that the acoustic resonance of the high
intensity discharge lamp 8 may not occur. For example, a
frequency fA2 near the lower limit of the stable operation window
A2 is chosen as an example. Here, other windows B1 through B5
shown in Fig. 8 are frequency bands where acoustic resonance 
might occur.</p>
    <p num="0060">That is, if the operating frequency of the electronic ballast 32
is fA2 in the stable operation window A2, an acoustic resonance
will not occur in the high intensity discharge lamp 8. If the
operating frequency of 20 kHz or less is chosen, there is a
drawback of upsizing the transformers Tr1 and Tr2 in order to
realize the operating frequency. On the contrary, if a frequency of
100 kHz or more is chosen, there is also a drawback of increasing
the switching loss of the field-effect transistors Q11 and Q12.
Therefore, by choosing an operating frequency from the range 20
kHz to 100 kHz such as the frequency fA2 in the stable operation
window A2, the acoustic resonance of the discharge lamp is avoided
without upsizing the transformers Tr1 and Tr2 and increasing the
switching losses of the field-effect transistors Q11 and Q12.</p>
    <p num="0061">On the other hand, although the operating frequency fA2 is
in the stable operation window A2, an acoustic resonance may still
occur. That is because, in most of the cases, the operating
frequency fA2 is close to a window B1 where the acoustic frequency
occurs, and the area of the window B1 is expanding even into the
frequency fA2 over the assumed range of an window B1 in fact.</p>
    <p num="0062">If the acoustic resonance occurs in the high intensity
discharge lamp 8, since an undulation occurs on a discharge path,
the discharge path becomes longer. So, the lamp voltage of the
high-intensity discharge lamp 8 rises. As a result, the voltage
across the series circuit comprised of the resistors R24 and R25 as
an acoustic resonance detector 33 rises. Then, the Zener diode ZD 
16 is turned on, and the electrical potential at the gate of the
field-effect transistor Q14 rises. So that, the field-effect
transistor Q14 is turned on. When the field-effect transistor Q14
is turned on, the capacitor C30 is separated from the electronic
ballast 32 in operation. Thus, the operating frequency of the
electronic ballast 32 rises. Thus, the operating frequency of the
electronic ballast 32 becomes higher than the upper limit of the
window B1 of an actual acoustic-resonance range, and the acoustic
resonance of the high-intensity discharge lamp 8 can be avoided.</p>
    <p num="0063">As described above, in the second embodiment of the present
invention, when the acoustic resonance in the high-intensity
discharge lamp occurs while the electronic ballast 32 operates at
its operating frequency which is close to the lower limit of the
stable operation window, the operating frequency becomes higher
than the upper limit of actual acoustic resonance area. It is able
to achieve the same effects even when the acoustic resonance
occurs in the high-intensity discharge lamp while the electronic
ballast 32 operates with its operating frequency which is close to
the upper limit of the stable operation window, the operating
frequency becomes lower than the lower limit of the actual acoustic
resonance area. For example, in the high-intensity discharge
lamp lighting apparatus shown in Fig. 7, the latter can be achieved
by that the field-effect transistor Q15 is turned off usually, but it
is turned on when the acoustic resonance occurs.</p>
    <p num="0064">Here, in the conventional high-intensity discharge lamp in
which a central frequency in the stable operation window area was 
chosen as the operating frequency of the electronic ballast, when
the actual area of the acoustic resonance window adjacent to the
operating frequency expands to overlap the operating frequency,
and the acoustic resonance occurred, it was difficult to find
whether the lower end or the upper end the expanded acoustic
resonance window of the operating frequency had been. Therefore,
in the conventional high-intensity discharge lamp, even if the
acoustic resonance occurred, the countermeasures for suppressing
the acoustic resonance could not be devised. However, on the
other hand, according to the circuit configuration (and the
modification), the operating frequency of the electronic ballast is
set to the frequency close to the lower limit (or to the frequency
close to the upper limit) of the stable operation window.
Therefore, when the actual area of the lower end of the acoustic
resonance window (or the upper end of the acoustic resonance
window) of the operating frequency overlaps the operating
frequency, and the acoustic resonance occurs in the high-intensity
discharge lamp 8, the lamp voltage rise of the high-intensity
discharge lamp 8 incident to the resonance is detected, then the
operating frequency appropriately shifts into an area where it does
not overlap the actual area of the acoustic resonance window.
That is, in the embodiment shown in Fig. 7, the operating
frequency shifts to the frequency higher than the area where the
lower end of the acoustic resonance window is expanded. On the
other hand, in its alternative arrangement, the operating
frequency shifts to a frequency below an expanded area of the 
upper acoustic resonance window. As a result, the acoustic
resonance of the high-intensity discharge lamp 8 can be avoided.</p>
    <p num="0065">Moreover, there is another conventional high-intensity
discharge lamp lighting apparatus wherein the electronic ballast
oscillation frequency rises or lowers to a frequency higher or lower
enough to avoid the acoustic resonance. However, in the case of
rising the frequency higher, there is a drawback of increasing the
switching loss in the electronic ballast. On the other hand, in the
case of lowering the frequency lower, there is also a drawback of
upsizing the high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus.
As compared with those conventional ones, the high-intensity
discharge lamp lighting apparatus, as shown in Fig. 7, it is able to
prevent the increasing of the switching loss or the upsizing of the
circuit by using the frequency from 20 kHz to 100 kHz.</p>
    <p num="0066">Here, such a high-intensity discharge lamp lighting
apparatus is effective especially to a ceramic high-intensity
discharge lamp wherein a luminescence tube is hardly deformed
during lighting.</p>
    <p num="0067">Next, referring not to Fig. 9, the third embodiment of the
high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus 11 according to
the present invention will be explained hereinafter.</p>
    <p num="0068">Fig. 9 is a circuit diagram showing the third embodiment of
the high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus 11. As
shown in Fig. 9, the high-intensity discharge lamp lighting
apparatus 11 is connected to an AC power source e via an input
circuit comprised of a fuse F2, an inductor L21, and capacitors C30 
and C31. The input circuit is coupled to a full-wave rectifier 41.
The full-wave rectifier 41 is constituted to a diode bridge circuit
comprised of diodes D21, D22, D23, and D24. One terminal of a
resistor R31 is coupled to a negative output terminal of the
full-wave rectifier 41. A smoothing capacitor C32 and an
electronic ballast 42 are each connected in parallel between the
other terminal of the resistor R31 and a positive output terminal of
the full-wave rectifier 41. In addition, the negative output
terminal of the full-wave rectifier 41 is also a reference potential
line RPL.</p>
    <p num="0069">The electronic ballast 42 is constructed in a forced
half-bridge configuration wherein two field-effect transistors Q21
and Q22 performing switching operations are coupled in series
with each other and driven by a driving circuit 45, as described
later. A capacitor C33 is coupled in parallel to the field-effect
transistor Q22 whose source terminal is coupled to the negative
output of the full-wave rectifier 31, i.e., the reference potential
line RPL.</p>
    <p num="0070">To the field-effect transistor Q22, a main circuit having an
LC resonance circuit is also coupled in parallel. In the main
circuit 43, a series circuit of an inductor L22 operating as a ballast
chalk and a DC-blocking capacitor C34 is coupled between a
connection node of the filed-effect transistors Q21 and Q22 and one
connecting terminal 8A of the high-intensity discharge lamp 8.
Moreover, a resonance point detection circuit 44 in which diodes
D25 and D26 are connected in reverse parallel is coupled between 
the source of the field-effect transistor Q22 and the other
connecting terminal 8B of the high-intensity discharge lamp.
Furthermore, a parallel circuit of capacitors C35 and C36 is
coupled across the both connecting terminals 8A and 8B of the
high-intensity discharge lamp 8.</p>
    <p num="0071">The driving circuit 45 for driving the field-effect transistors
Q21 and Q22 is provided with an oscillation driver IC 46 (Model
IR2153 which is available from International Rectifier Ltd.), and
the oscillation driver IC 46 drives the gates of the field-effect
transistors Q21 and Q22. That is, gate output terminal pins P7
and P6 of the oscillation circuit IC 46 are connected to each gate of
the field-effect transistors Q21 and Q22. Furthermore, a pin P6
of the oscillation driver IC 46 is coupled to a connection node of the
field-effect transistors Q21 and Q22, and a pin P8 is coupled to the
pin P6 via a capacitor C37. A power terminal pin P1 of the
oscillation driver IC 46 is coupled to the pin P8 via a diode D27.
The power is applied to the power terminal pin P1 from the
positive output of the full-wave rectifier 41 via a diode D28 and a
resistor R34 in order. A pin P3 of the oscillation driver IC 46 is
coupled to the other connecting terminal 8B of the high-intensity
discharge lamp 8 via a capacitor C38. A pin P2 of the oscillation
driver IC 46 is coupled to the pin P3 via a resistor R32 and a
variable resistor R33 in order. And a ground terminal pin P4 of
the oscillation driver IC 46 is coupled to the reference potential
line RPL.</p>
    <p num="0072">The electronic ballast 42 includes a series circuit of a diode 
D28, a resistor R34, and a capacitor C41 in order. In the series
circuit, the diode D28 is coupled to the other terminal of the
resistor R31, and the capacitor C41 is coupled to the reference
potential line RPL. The connection node of the resistor R34 and
the capacitor C41 is coupled to the connection node of the
oscillation driver IC 46. Moreover, a Zener diode ZD21, a
capacitor C42, and a field-effect transistor Q23 are coupled to the
capacitor C41 in parallel.</p>
    <p num="0073">Further, a lamp voltage detection circuit 47 is coupled to the
connecting terminal 8A of the high-intensity discharge lamp 8. In
the lamp voltage detection circuit 47, first, resistors R35 and R36
are coupled in series between the connection terminal 8a and the
reference potential line RPL. Next, between the connection node
of the resistors R35 and R36 and the reference potential line RPL,
a diode D28 and a capacitor C43 are coupled in series in order.
Then, a resistor R37 is coupled in parallel to the capacitor C43. A
connection node of the diode D28 and the resistor R37 is coupled to
the gate of the field-effect transistor Q23 of the electronic ballast
42 via a Zener diode ZD22.</p>
    <p num="0074">Furthermore, to the resonance point detection circuit 44 is
coupled a long time timer 48. In the long time timer 48, a
reverse-current blocking diode D31, a resistor R41 and a capacitor
C41 are coupled in series between the connection node of the
resistor R37 and the diode D28 and the reference potential line
RPL. And, a capacitor C45 is coupled in parallel to the capacitor
C41. In addition, a series circuit of a resistor R42 and a Zener 
diode ZD23 is coupled in parallel in order to the capacitor C44.
Furthermore, a series circuit of programmable unijunction
transistor Q24 and a resistor R43 in order is coupled in parallel to
the capacitor C44. To the resistor R42, a capacitor C46 is coupled
in parallel. A connection node of the resistor R42 and the Zener
diode ZD23 is coupled to the gate of the programmable unijunction
transistor Q24. A connection node of the programmable
unijunction transistor Q24 and the resistor R43 is connected to the
gate of the field-effect transistor Q23 of the electronic ballast 42.
Here, the time-constant circuit of the timer 48 is constructed by
the capacitors C44 and C45 and the resistor R41.</p>
    <p num="0075">On the other hand, a series circuit of resistors R44, R45, and
R46 in order is coupled between the connection node of the diode
D28 and the resistor R34 and the reference potential line RPL.
Finally, an anode of the programmable unijunction transistor Q24
is coupled to the connection node of the series circuit of the
resistors R45 and R46 via a diode D32.</p>
    <p num="0076">Now, the operation of the third embodiment of the present
invention will be explained hereinafter.</p>
    <p num="0077">First, the AC voltage of the commercial AC power source e is
rectified in the full wave rectifier 31, and smoothed in the
capacitor C22 so as to obtain the DC voltage, then the DC is
applied to the electronic ballast 42. In the electronic ballast 42,
the field-effect transistors Q21 and Q22 are turned on and off by
turns by the driving circuit 45. So that, the high frequency
current obtained by the switching operation is supplied to the 
high-intensity discharge lamp 8.</p>
    <p num="0078">The lamp voltage of the high-intensity discharge lamp 8 is
detected by divided in the resistors R35 and R36. The divided
voltage is rectified in the diode D28 and smoothed in the capacitor
C43. When the no-load secondary voltage is generated, the Zener
diode ZD22 is turned on, then the voltage applied to the gate of the
field-effect transistor Q23 in the electronic ballast 42 rises. So
that, the field-effect transistor Q23 is turned on. As a result, the
pin P1 of the oscillation driver IC46 is short-circuited to the
reference potential line RPL. And thus, the oscillation driver IC
45 is shut off. And also, the electronic ballast 42 is shut off. Due
to that the electronic ballast 42 is shut off, the capacitor C43 is
discharged so that the voltage detected by the lamp voltage
detection circuit 47 drops. And thus, the Zener diode ZD22 is
turned off. Therefore, the gate voltage of the field-effect
transistor Q23 in the electronic ballast 42 lowers, and the
field-effect transistor Q23 is turned off. Then, the oscillation
driver IC 46 starts operation again, and the high-frequency
current is supplied to the high-intensity discharge lamp 8 from the
electronic ballast 42. Thus, according to the intermittent
operation of the electronic ballast 42, an intermittent pulse, as
shown in Fig. 10 occurs on the no-load secondary voltage.</p>
    <p num="0079">Here, at the occurrence of the no-load secondary voltage the
inductor L22 saturates at the no-load secondary voltage generating
time, the field-effect transistors Q21 and Q22 produces heat more
than normal lighting time. However, the heat from the 
field-effect transistors Q21 and Q22 is controlled by the
intermittent operation of the electronic ballast 42 described above.
In order to control the heat moderately, it is necessary to decrease
the pulse duration, that is the pulse width, as shown in Fig. 10.
However, since the high-intensity discharge lamp 8 fails to start
up when the pulse width is too short, it is necessary to have
suitable pulse width. Here, the voltage across the capacitor C43
varies, as shown by a solid line Vc43 in Fig. 11. Further, the lamp
voltage of the high-intensity discharge lamp varies, as shown by
another solid line VL in Fig. 11.</p>
    <p num="0080">Since the inductor L22 saturates at the start-up of the
high-intensity discharge lamp 8, a large resonance current flows
into the capacitors C35 and C36, then the no-load secondary
voltage rises. So that, the high-intensity discharge lamp 8 lights
up.</p>
    <p num="0081">Moreover, a frequency which is close to the upper limit or the
lower limit of the stable operation window is used as a driving
frequency of the high-intensity discharge lamp 8 at the lighting
operation in order to prevent the acoustic resonance of the
high-intensity discharge lamp 8.</p>
    <p num="0082">On the other hand, the capacitors C44 and C45 in the timer
circuit 48 are charged every time before the high-intensity
discharge lamp 8 starts operation and during the no-load
secondary voltage is generated intermittently. So that ,the
voltage of the timer circuit 48 rises. When the voltage of the
timer circuit 48 gets to a predetermined value or more, for example, 
0.6 V or more of a Zener voltage of the Zener diode ZD23, the
programmable unijunction transistor Q24 is turned on, then the
gate voltage of the field-effect transistor Q23 in the electronic
ballast 42 rises. So that, the field-effect transistor Q23 is turned
on. As a result, the pin P1 of the oscillation driver IC46 is
short-circuited to the reference potential line RPL. And thus, the
oscillation driver IC 45 is shut off. And also, the electronic
ballast 42 is shut off. Here, the programmable unijunction
transistor Q24 remains on by a latching current which is supplied
through the series circuit of the resistors R44, R45, and R46.
Therefore, the oscillation driver IC 46 and the electronic ballast 42
are kept being shut-off.</p>
    <p num="0083">When the pulse width of the no-load secondary voltage varies
while the high-intensity discharge lamp 8 has an intermittent
operating frequency of 100 Hz, the temperature T of the field-effect
transistors Q21 and Q22 varies, as shown in Fig. 12. That is, the
greater the pulse width of the no-load secondary voltage is, the
higher the temperature T of the field-effect transistors Q21 and
Q22 will be. Therefore, while intermittent operating frequency of
the high-intensity discharge lamp 8 is 100 Hz, the pulse width of
the no-load secondary voltage is set to 3m a second or less, it is
able to prevent the temperature of the field-effect transistors Q21
and Q22 gets to the temperature rating or more.</p>
    <p num="0084">Furthermore, when the electronic ballast 42 operates in an
advancing phase state, an advancing phase current flows into the
high intensity discharge lamp 8. As a result, the lamp voltage of 
the high-intensity discharge lamp 8 rises. The voltage rise is
detected by the resonance point detection circuit 44. The voltage
detected by the resonance point detection circuit 44 is applied to
the resistors R32, R33 in the oscillation frequency determining
circuit coupled across the pins P2 and P3 of the oscillation driver
IC 46 via the capacitor C38. The oscillation driver IC 46 is
controlled to rise its oscillation frequency according to the detected
voltage. Therefore, the operating frequency of the electronic
ballast 42 rises, and the operation in the advancing phase
condition of the electronic ballast 42 is canceled.</p>
    <p num="0085">Further, when the acoustic resonance occurs in the
high-intensity discharge lamp, the operating frequency of the
electronic ballast 42 shifts to the frequency around the center of
the stable operation window. So that, the acoustic resonance is
avoided.</p>
    <p num="0086">According to the third embodiment of the present invention,
it is able to set the ratio of the operation time and the
non-operation time of the no-load secondary voltage easily by using
the Zener diode ZD22.</p>
    <p num="0087">Next, referring now to Fig. 13, the fourth embodiment of the
high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus 11 according to
the present invention will be explained hereinafter.</p>
    <p num="0088">The high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus 11
according to the fourth embodiment of the present invention is
principally the same as the high-intensity discharge lamp lighting
apparatus 11 of the first embodiment, as shown in Fig. 1. 
Therefore, in Fig. 13, the same elements as those of the first
embodiment are assigned with like reference numerals and their
descriptions will be omitted. The major differences from the first
embodiment are as follows. A resistor R51 is coupled to the
capacitor C7 in the snubber circuit 26 in series. A resistor R52 is
coupled to the resistor R5 in series. A capacitor C51 is coupled in
parallel to the series circuit of the resistor R3 and the variable
resistor R4, and an output reducing means 51 is coupled to the
connection node of the resistor R3 and the variable resistor R4.</p>
    <p num="0089">The output reducing means 51 is constituted as follows. It
has a series circuit of a diode D41 and a capacitor C53 are coupled
in order between the connection node of the resistors R6 and R7 in
the lamp voltage detection circuit 27 and the reference potential
line RPL. A series circuit of a resistor R53, a Zener diode ZD31 as
a glow discharge detector, and a capacitor C54 is coupled in order
to the connection node of the diode D41 and the capacitor C53 and
the reference potential line RPL. A resistor R54 is coupled in
parallel to the capacitor C54. A connection node of the Zener
diode ZD 31 and the capacitor C54 is coupled to the base of the
transistor Q31, and the resistor R54 is coupled between the base of
the transistor Q31 and the reference potential line RPL. An
emitter of the transistor Q31 is coupled across the reference
potential line RPL, and its collector is coupled to the connection
node of the resistors R3 and R4 via the resistor R55.</p>
    <p num="0090">Next, operations of the fourth embodiment of the present
invention will be explained hereinafter. </p>
    <p num="0091">Here, the basic operations are the same as that of the first
embodiment, as shown in Fig. 1, and the overlapping explanations
are omitted.</p>
    <p num="0092">First, referring not to Figs. 14 and 15, the operating
frequency of the electronic ballast of the fourth embodiment will be
explained hereinafter.</p>
    <p num="0093">When a power source e is turned on, and a rectified DC is
supplied from the double-voltage rectifier 21, the oscillation driver
IC 24 oscillates with a frequency f2, and a comparatively low
voltage applied from the electronic ballast 22 with a frequency
characteristic curve of B30 is applied to the high-intensity
discharge lamp 8. Then, the oscillation frequency of the
oscillation driver IC25 lowers until the advancing phase current is
detected in the resistor R2. When the operating frequency of the
electronic ballast 22 reaches around the resonance point f02 on the
frequency characteristic curve B30, the glow discharge occurs in
the high-intensity discharge lamp 8, then the inductors L2 and L3
of the LC resonance circuit 24 saturate. As a result, the
frequency characteristic curve B2 appears.</p>
    <p num="0094">At that time, the electronic ballast 22 operates with its
operating frequency of the no-load resonance frequency f01, and a
high pulse voltage occurs. Further, after the glow discharge
occurs, the high-intensity discharge lamp 8 operates with the
no-load resonance frequency f02 on the frequency characteristic
curve B3 in the fine discharge state, while the inductors L2 and L3
of the LC resonance circuit 24 fail to saturate. At this time, a 
voltage which is lower than the pulse voltage which is generated at
the start of the glow discharge time but higher than the voltage at
the start of operation is applied to the high intensity discharge
lamp 8.</p>
    <p num="0095">Accordingly, when the pulse voltage capable of causing the
glow discharge is generated in the high-intensity discharge lamp 8,
the lamp voltage of the high-intensity discharge lamp rises. Thus,
the voltage applied to the connection node of the resistors R6 and
R7 in the lamp voltage detection circuit 27 rises, and it is applied
to the output reducing means 51 via the diode D41. So that, the
Zener diode ZD as the glow discharge detector is turned on, and
the capacitor C54 is started to be charged. After the time
constant decided by the resistor R53 and the capacitor C54, the
transistor Q31 is turned on. Then, the resistor R55 in the output
reducing means 51 is coupled in parallel to the resistor R4 in the
oscillation driver IC 25. Thus, the oscillation frequency of the
oscillation driver IC25 rises, and the operating frequency of the
electronic ballast 22 rises. According to the operating frequency
rise, the voltage applied to the high-intensity discharge lamp 8
lowers to the extent in which the glow discharge is maintained.</p>
    <p num="0096">Here, even though the current flows in the high-intensity
discharge lamp 8 at the glow discharge time, the current is very
little, so it can be dealt with almost like the no-load state.
However, it is different in that the inductors L2 and L3 saturates
before starting the glow discharge, but they fail to saturate during
the glow discharge operation. Further, when the glow discharge 
changes to the arc discharge of the high-intensity discharge lamp 8,
the Zener diode ZD31 as a glow discharge detector is turned off.
Thus, the transistor Q31 is turned off, and the resistor R55 is
released its parallel connection to the resistor R4 in the oscillation
driver IC25. So that, the oscillation frequency of the oscillation
driver IC25, that is the operating frequency of the electronic
ballast 22, lowers to the frequency f1. Accordingly, the voltage
applied to the high-intensity discharge lamp 8 lowers below the
voltage at the start of operation before starting the glow discharge.</p>
    <p num="0097">In addition, when the glow discharge is not detected, the
oscillation driver IC 25 is reset in the lamp voltage detector 27.
Therefore, at this time, the glow discharge is tried again by
starting the electronic ballast 22 to operate with the same
condition at the time that the power has been turned on.</p>
    <p num="0098">Referring to Figs. 16A and 16B, the operations of the fourth
embodiment will be comparatively explained in a discharge lamp
in which an argon gas (Ar) is filled and a discharge lamp in which
a neon-argon mixed gas (Ne-Ar) is filled. In the high-intensity
discharge lamp in which an argon gas (Ar) is filled, the voltage to
the current at the glow discharge operation time is reduced, as
shown by a solid line D1 in Fig. 16A. That is, in the
high-intensity discharge lamp in which an argon (Ar) is filled, it is
able to operate the glow discharge and the glow-arc transition with
a lower power, since it is operated with comparatively low lamp
current and lamp voltage at the glow discharge operation time, as
shown by a dotted line. Therefore, the sputtering of electrode 
materials in the high intensity discharge lamp 8 can be suppressed.</p>
    <p num="0099">On the other hand, in the high-intensity discharge lamp in
which a neon-argon mixed gas (Ne-Ar) is filled, the voltage to the
current is high, as shown by a pint P2 in Fig. 16B. Accordingly, if
the output is excessively reduced, the glow discharge is not
maintained.

In such a high-intensity discharge lamp in which a neon-argon
mixed gas (Ne-Ar) is filled, it requires an output curve, as shown
in a broken line D2. Therefore, in the high-intensity discharge
lamp in which a neon-argon mixed gas (Ne-Ar) is filled, it does not
need the output reducing means. So that, the high-intensity
discharge lamp lighting apparatus of the first embodiment, as
shown in Fig. 1 is suitable such a high-intensity discharge lamp.
Here, since a neon-argon mixed gas is used for the high-intensity
discharge lamp, it has less sputtering caused by a lamp current at
the glow discharge operation.</p>
    <p num="0100">According to the first embodiment of the high-intensity
discharge lamp lighting apparatus, the electronic ballast is able to
be operated with the resonance frequency of the LC resonance
circuit in the main circuit at a no-load state. It is also able to
increase the secondary open voltage through the glow discharge
operation. Thus it is able to keep the high secondary voltage at
the time of glow-arc transition.</p>
    <p num="0101">According to the second embodiment of the high-intensity
discharge lamp lighting apparatus, a high-intensity discharge
lamp starts the glow discharge operation in short time by being 
applied a high voltage for causing the electrical breakdown before
lighting. Thus it has less stress to the circuit even when the
inductors saturate. On the other hand, for avoiding saturation of
inductors at the start of arc discharge, it is able to prevent to
stress to the circuit even when a comparatively high voltage is
kept during the time required for the glow-arc transition.</p>
    <p num="0102">According to the third embodiment of the high-intensity
discharge lamp lighting apparatus, the frequency of the
high-intensity discharge lamp at the start of glow discharge, the
frequency in the glow discharge operation, and the frequency at
the glow-arc transition time coincide with the no-load resonance
frequency of the LC resonance circuit. Thus, these frequencies
are easily controlled</p>
    <p num="0103">According to the fourth embodiment of the high-intensity
discharge lamp lighting apparatus, the electronic ballast is
effectively operated in a lagging phase at the frequency which is
higher than the resonance frequency at the no-load state, while its
output voltage lowers.</p>
    <p num="0104">According to the fifth embodiment of the high-intensity
discharge lamp, the operating frequency shifts to the frequency
band which is free from the acoustic resonance when the acoustic
resonance occurs. Thus, it is easy to avoid the acoustic resonance.</p>
    <p num="0105">According to the sixth embodiment of the high-intensity
discharge lamp lighting apparatus, the operating frequency shifts
into either frequency band which is free from acoustic resonance
when an acoustic resonance occurs. Thus, it is easy to avoid the 
acoustic resonance.</p>
    <p num="0106">According to the seventh embodiment of the high-intensity
discharge lamp lighting apparatus, when it does not start the glow
discharge the lighting operation is reset. So that, it is able to
repeat the operation for lighting the discharge lamp from the
beginning.</p>
    <p num="0107">According to the eighth embodiment, the luminaire is
provided with a lighting equipment main body whereon the
high intensity discharge lamp lighted up in the high-intensity
discharge lamp lighting apparatus of either the first or the seventh
embodiment is mounted. Thus, the luminaire is able to have the
effects obtained in the first through the seventh embodiments of
the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0108">While there have been illustrated and described what are at
present considered to be preferred embodiments of the present
invention, it will be understood by those skilled in the art that
various changes and modifications may be made, and equivalents
may be substituted for elements thereof without departing from
the true scope of the present invention. In addition, many
modifications may be made to adapt a particular situation or
material to the teaching of the present invention without
departing from the central scope thereof. Therefore, it is intended
that the present invention not be limited to the particular
embodiment disclosed as the best mode contemplated for carrying
out the present invention, but that the present invention includes
all embodiments falling within the scope of the appended claims. </p>
    <p num="0109">The foregoing description and the drawings are regarded by
the applicant as including a variety of individually inventive
concepts, some of which may lie partially or wholly outside the
scope of some or all of the following claims. The fact that the
applicant has chosen at the time of filing of the present application
to restrict the claimed scope of protection in accordance with the
following claims is not to be taken as a disclaimer or alternative
inventive concepts that are included in the contents of the
application and could be defined by claims differing in scope from
the following claims, which different claims may be adopted
subsequently during prosecution, for example, for the purposes of a
divisional application.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus,
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a main circuit, which contains an LC oscillation circuit, and
to which a high-intensity discharge lamp is coupled; and</claim-text><claim-text>an electronic ballast for starting up into a lighting state the
high-intensity discharge lamp via the main circuit which is
coupled to its output side, and it is operated at a resonance
frequency of the LC resonance circuit in the main circuit at a
no-load time.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus as
claimed in claim 1,
   wherein the LC resonance circuit is provided with inductors,
and the inductors saturate at start-up operation of a glow
discharge of the high-intensity discharge lamp, but fail to saturate
during the glow discharge and the arc discharge.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus as
claimed in claim 2,
   wherein the frequency of the electronic ballast at the start of
the glow discharge of the high-intensity discharge lamp coincides
with the resonance frequency of the LC resonance circuit in the
no-load condition under the state that the inductors saturate, and
its frequency during glow discharge of the high-intensity discharge
lamp coincides with the a no-load resonance frequency of the LC
resonance circuit under the state that the inductors fail to
saturate.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus as
claimed in claim 2, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a glow discharge detector for detecting the glow discharge of
the high-intensity discharge lamp; and</claim-text><claim-text>an output reducing means for reducing an output voltage into
a range where the glow discharge is maintained at the operating
frequency of the electronic ballast which is higher than the
resonance frequency of the LC resonance circuit in the no-load
condition when the inductors fail to saturate after the glow
discharge is detected by the glow discharge detector.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus as
claimed in any one of claim 1 to claim 4,
   wherein the electronic ballast is operated to light the
high-intensity discharge lamp at a frequency which is close to
either end of a frequency band which is free from acoustic
resonance of the high-intensity discharge lamp.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus as
claimed in claim 5, further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>an acoustic resonance detector for detecting an acoustic
resonance of the high-intensity discharge lamp,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein, when the acoustic resonance is detected by the
acoustic resonance detector, the operating frequency of the
electronic ballast shifts to either frequency band which is free from
acoustic resonance.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus as
claimed in any one of claim 1 to claim 6, comprising
   a timer,
   wherein the electronic ballast is reset to the state at the start
of operation when the glow discharge detector fails to detect the
glow discharge in a predetermined time given by the timer.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A luminaire, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus as
claimed in any one of claim 1 to claim 7; and</claim-text><claim-text>a main body in which the high-intensity discharge lamp to be
lighted up by the high-intensity discharge lamp lighting apparatus
is mounted.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
