<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1262288-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1262288" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="25358072" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021204">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1262288-A2" status="new" fvid="23608064">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1262288</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021204</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02100550-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02100550</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020523</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="US-87176601-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>87176601</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010601</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B26D   1/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B26D   1/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B26D   3/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B26D   3/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B26D   7/08        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B26D   7/08        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B26D   1/00D</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B26D   3/02</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B26D   7/08C</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zum Schneiden von elastomerischen Materialien</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Method for cutting elastomeric materials</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé pour découper des matériaux elastomères</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GOODYEAR TIRE &amp; RUBBER</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>THE GOODYEAR TIRE &amp; RUBBER COMPANY</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>THE GOODYEAR TIRE &amp;amp; RUBBER COMPANY</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1144 East Market Street</street>
              <city>Akron, Ohio 44316-0001</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>DOWNING DANIEL RAY</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>DOWNING, DANIEL RAY</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>DOWNING, DANIEL RAY</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>13470 Inverness Avenue</street>
              <city>Uniontown, OH 44685</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Leitz, Paul</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Goodyear Technical Center, Patent Department, Avenue Gordon Smith</street>
              <city>7750 Colmar-Berg</city>
              <country>LU</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A method and an apparatus for cutting segments (10) to desired lengths from a
strip (1) of elastomeric tire components having at least one cord reinforced
component includes the step of impacting one cord (22) as the cut is being
made and lifting the cord (22) to avoid cutting cords (22) while directing the
cutting path (3) along the lifted cord (22). The article resulting from the method
has a plurality of cords (22) adjacent a flat cut splicing surface (8) suitable for
lap splicing.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="84"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Technical Field</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0001">This invention relates to a method and apparatus for cutting elastomeric
materials at low skive angles, in particular cutting layered composites of
elastomeric materials including layers containing reinforcing materials.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Background of the Invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0002">Various methods and apparatus have been used for the cutting of sheets
of elastomeric material. Such elastomeric material might consist of single
sheets of the homogeneous material, or multiple layered sheets of materials
having properties that are different from one another. In the case of multiple
layered sheets of elastomeric material that, for various reasons, need to be cut,
one or more of the layers might contain reinforcing cords or fibers made of
metal or fabric. Such reinforcing cords or fibers might be simply aligned in such
a way as to be parallel to one another. Furthermore, the elastomeric materials
that are to be cut may or may not be cured or vulcanized at the time of cutting.</p>
    <p num="0003">Prior art cutting methods and apparatus include cutting wheels,
ultrasonic cutters, guillotine knives, wire cutters and vibrating scroll cutters
whose active cutting principle is a saw blade or a blade or a tensioned wire.</p>
    <p num="0004">While such prior art cutting methods are effective to varying degrees,
each has disadvantages. For example, the guillotine knife is somewhat
effective in cutting composite elastomeric materials, but it has the disadvantage
of having a tendency to deform the cut surfaces of the elastomeric material as
the knife penetrates the material. Such deformation of the cut edge increases
the difficulty of subsequent splicing the ends of the elastomeric material.
Moreover, the guillotine knife produces a continually degraded cut surface as
the blade becomes dull and as small pieces of elastomer began to build up on
the blade. Yet another disadvantage was the inability of the blade to cut at an
angle less than 30 degrees relative to the plane of the material being cut. The
guillotine blade also tends to generate heat during the cutting process such that,
as numerous cuts are made, the temperature of the knife becomes sufficiently
elevated in some cases to induce precuring of unvulcanized elastomer in the
region of the cut, which then inhibits subsequent proper splicing along the cut
edges</p>
    <p num="0005">Another prior art cutting system and method, disclosed in US-A-5,638,732,
employs a cutting wire. This system could not, however, be used to 
cut preassembled elastomeric composite sheets containing reinforcing cords
because the reinforcing cords themselves, though aligned more or less parallel
to the direction of the cut, get severed. This deficiency is actually inherent to
nearly every prior art cutting technology including ultrasonic knives, that cut
composite elastomeric preassemblies at relatively low skive angles. That is to
say, nearly all prior art cutting methods tended to cut the parallel-aligned cords
that are used to reinforce one or more layers of reinforced ply. The cut is ideally
intended to be made between the parallel-aligned reinforcing cords. One prior
art exception is the scroll cutter, which can cut at low skive angles without also
risking cutting the reinforcing cords.</p>
    <p num="0006">The scroll cutter cannot, however, initiate its cut at a low skive angle
through a cord reinforced sheet of preassembled composite elastomeric sheets,
because of its geometry, which includes a wire held at each end by a fixture.
The scroll cutter must start its cut from the side of the preassembly, such that
the cutting has difficulty entering the ply without splitting the reinforcing cords.
Even at a 90-degree skive angle, the reliability of not splitting cords is in
question. At low skive angles it becomes exponentially difficult to enter the ply
without splitting a ply cord. Sometimes the reinforced ply end will be buried
under the other layers, such as, in the case of tire manufacturing, the sidewall
layer or other layers such as the extreme edge of the preassembly within the
context of envelope construction. This adds another dimension of difficulty for
the wire scroll cutter to cut reliably a preassembly with reinforced layers, such
as specifically, the ply of tires.</p>
    <p num="0007">Ultrasonic cutting systems as disclosed in US-A- 5,265,508, can cut
stock material at low skive angles. However, they require that the material be
secured to an anvil during cutting. Another system, disclosed in US-A-4,922,774,
employs an ultrasonic cutting device, which vibrates a knife that
moves across an elastomeric strip. However, this system is limited to cutting
angles of between 10 and 90 degrees, and it does not provide for cutting
between parallel disposed, reinforcement cords within the strip, which is to say,
the cords can get cut.</p>
    <p num="0008">Various method have been attempted to cut through cord-reinforced
composites employing ultrasonic knives. In WO-A- 00/23261, a pair of
ultrasonic blades are employed wherein after the article to be cut is pierced in a
central region the two blades cut in opposite directions toward each lateral edge
of the composite.</p>
    <p num="0009">In WO-A-01/51810 an ultrasonic skive cuts above the cord reinforced 
member as a cutting knife follows making a second cut through the ply and
between parallel cords thus forming an abutment surface for subsequent tire
splicing of the cut to length segment. Each of these concepts requires multiple
cutting mechanisms and are arguable complex to build and maintain the
equipment.</p>
    <p num="0010">A significant problem with the prior art cutting systems and methods is
the inability to cut at angles less than 30 degrees relative to the plane of the
elastomeric layers being cut without deformation or precuring the material. This
can be a problem in, for example, automated tire building operations wherein
the cutting has to be done precisely and quickly and where the cutter can also
provide improvements to the cut surface which is subsequently to be spliced.</p>
    <p num="0011">An ideal cutting method and apparatus should be able to make cuts at
low angles relative to the plane of the elastomeric sheet being cut, and it should
be able to do so without cutting the parallel-aligned reinforcing cords between
which the cutter is ideally to move. It should also be able to make these low
angle cuts rapidly and reliably.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Summary of the Invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0012">A method of cutting segments to desired lengths from the strip of
elastomeric material as disclosed. The segments have a width W, elastomeric
strips being formed of a plurality of tire components, at least one of the tire
components being a cord reinforced component. The cords of the reinforced
tire component are substantially parallel oriented in the direction of a cutting
path formed across the width W.</p>
    <p num="0013">The method has the step of moving an ultrasonic knife into cutting
engagement of the elastomeric strip while supporting the strip along the cutting
path. Cutting the segment at a skive angle α. Impacting a cord of the cord
reinforced component while cutting thereby lifting said cord over the ultrasonic
knife as the segment is being cut. The impacted cord is at a cut end adjacent to
the cutting path. The method further has the step of orienting a cutting edge on
the ultrasonic knife inclined at an acute angle  relative to the strip-cutting path.
In one embodiment of the invention, the method further has the step of movably
restraining the strip ahead of the cutting.</p>
    <p num="0014">The step of supporting the strip may further include supporting the strip
at an angle <sub>1</sub> less than the skive angle α on one side of the cutting path and at
an angle <sub>2</sub> greater than the skive angle on the opposite side of the cutting path.
This causes the location of the impacted cord to occur approximately at the 
location wherein the supporting angle changes from <sub>1</sub> to <sub>2</sub>.</p>
    <p num="0015">In another embodiment the step of positioning the cutting edge of the
ultrasonic knife includes the step of setting a gap distance (d) above the support
approximately slightly less than or equal to the thickness of the cord reinforced
component, along the region wherein the support is oriented at the angle <sub>1</sub>.
The method further includes forming one cut end of the segment wherein a
plurality of cords is beneath and adjacent to a flat cut surface.</p>
    <p num="0016">A segment formed by the method described above results in a first cut
end having a cut splicing surface extending outward from the cord reinforced
component and a second cut end having a plurality of cords beneath and
adjacent to a flat cut surface. The segment, when the first cut end and the
second cut end are joined, forms a lap splice having one or more overlapping
cords.</p>
    <p num="0017">An apparatus for cutting segments from a strip of multi-layered
elastomeric material containing reinforcing cords, the cords being substantially
parallel and more or less oriented in the direction of the cut path, is described
by the following features. A cutting element for cutting the strip to form cut ends
has a cutting edge oriented to cut along a line 3, the line 3 being tangent to one
or more cords and inclined at a desired skive angle α, and a means for
supporting the strip along the cutting path, the means for supporting the strip
having a first surface oriented at an angle <sub>1</sub> less than the skive angle α, and a
second surface oriented at an angle <sub>2</sub> greater than or equal to the skive angle
α, and a means for restraining the strip against the means for supporting, the
means for restraining the strip preferably lying ahead of the cutting element, and
being moveable. The apparatus further has a means for moving both the
cutting element and the means for restraining during the cutting of the strip. In
one embodiment, the apparatus has the cutting element having a cutting edge
inclined at an acute angle β relative to the width of the strip. The cutting edge
when oriented as described initiates cutting on the surface furthest away from
the means for supporting the strip. The skive angle α is normally set about 10°
or less forming a cut path adjacent to one or more cords of the strip being cut.
While the means of supporting the strip has two surfaces inclined at angles <sub>1</sub>,
and <sub>2</sub> respectively, <sub>1</sub> is preferably set at about 2° less than the skive angle α,
the angle <sub>2</sub> is about 2° more than the skive angle α. In one embodiment the
skive angle α is set to about 8°.</p>
    <p num="0018">In a preferred embodiment the cutting element is an ultrasonic knife. The
cutting element has a planer surface adjacent to the supporting means. The 
cutting element has a wedge shape increasing in thickness away from the
cutting edge.</p>
    <p num="0019">In a preferred embodiment the means for supporting the strip includes
the vacuum-means for adhering the strip to the means for supporting during the
cutting procedure.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Definitions</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0020">"Aspect Ratio" means the ratio of a tire's section height to its section
width.</p>
    <p num="0021">"Axial" and "axially" means the lines or directions that are parallel to the
axis of rotation of the tire.</p>
    <p num="0022">"Bead" or "Bead Core" means generally that part of the tire comprising an
annular tensile member, the radially inner beads are associated with holding the
tire to the rim being wrapped by ply cords and shaped, with or without other
reinforcement elements such as flippers, chippers, apexes or fillers, toe guards
and chafers.</p>
    <p num="0023">"Belt Structure" or "Reinforcing Belts" means at least two annular layers
or plies of parallel cords, woven or unwoven, underlying the tread, unanchored
to the bead, and having both left and right cord angles in the range from 17° to
27° with respect to the equatorial plane of the tire.</p>
    <p num="0024">"Bias Ply Tire" means that the reinforcing cords in the carcass ply extend
diagonally across the tire from bead-to-bead at 25-65° angle with respect to the
equatorial plane of the tire, the ply cords running at opposite angles in alternate
layers</p>
    <p num="0025">"Breakers" or "Tire Breakers" means the same as belt or belt structure or
reinforcement belts.</p>
    <p num="0026">"Carcass" means a laminate of tire ply material and other tire
components cut to length suitable for splicing, or already spliced, into a
cylindrical or toroidal shape. Additional components may be added to the
carcass prior to its being vulcanized to create the molded tire.</p>
    <p num="0027">"Circumferential" means lines or directions extending along the perimeter
of the surface of the annular tread perpendicular to the axial direction; it can
also refer to the direction of the sets of adjacent circular curves whose radii
define the axial curvature of the tread as viewed in cross section.</p>
    <p num="0028">"Cord" means one of the reinforcement strands, including fibers, which
are used to reinforce the plies.</p>
    <p num="0029">"Inner Liner" means the layer or layers of elastomer or other material that 
form the inside surface of a tubeless tire and that contain the inflating fluid
within the tire.</p>
    <p num="0030">"Inserts" means the crescent ― or wedge-shaped reinforcement typically
used to reinforce the sidewalls of runflat-type tires; it also refers to the
elastomeric non-crescent shaped insert that underlies the tread.</p>
    <p num="0031">"Ply" means a cord-reinforced layer of elastomer-coated, radially
deployed or otherwise parallel cords.</p>
    <p num="0032">"Radial" and "radially" mean directions radially toward or away from the
axis of rotation of the tire.</p>
    <p num="0033">"Radial Ply Structure" means the one or more carcass plies or which at
least one ply has reinforcing cords oriented at an angle of between 65° and 90°
with respect to the equatorial plane of the tire.</p>
    <p num="0034">"Radial Ply Tire" means a belted or circumferentially-restricted pneumatic
tire in which the ply cords which extend from bead to bead are laid at cord
angles between 65° and 90° with respect to the equatorial plane of the tire.</p>
    <p num="0035">"Sidewall" means a portion of a tire between the tread and the bead.</p>
    <p num="0036">"Skive" or "skive angle" refers to the cutting angle of a knife with respect
to the material being cut; the skive angle is measured with respect to the plane
of the flat material being cut.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Brief Description of the Drawing</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0037">The structure, operation, and advantage of the invention will become
further apparent upon consideration of the following description taken in
conjunction with the accompanying drawings wherein:
<sl><li>Figure 1 is a schematic view of a multi-component strip of elastomeric
material, showing a path where the ends of a segment are to be formed;</li><li>Figure 2 and 3 are detailed views of one type of multi-component strip of
elastomeric material shown in Figure 1;</li><li>Figure 4A is a detailed view of a multi-component cord reinforced
elastomeric strip wherein the cords are in a parallel layer oriented at a bias
angle relative to the length of the strip;</li><li>Figure 4B is a detailed view of a multi-component cord reinforced
elastomeric strip wherein the cords are in a parallel layer oriented at an angle
normal to the length of the strip;</li><li>Figure 5A is an edge view of an elastomeric strip showing the forming of
the low skive angle surface;</li><li>Figure 5B is an edge view of the preferred method of after impacting a 
cord and then forming the rest of the low angle skive surface on an elastomeric
strip.</li><li>Figure 5C is another edge view of the preferred method of forming the
ends on the elastomeric strip of Figure 5B showing the strip separating at the
cut ends;</li><li>Figure 6A is a perspective view showing the segment being formed
cylindrically about a tire-building drum;</li><li>Figure 6B is a perspective view of the cylindrically formed segment of
Figure 6A;</li><li>Figure 7 is a perspective view of a first cutting element for forming the
low skive angle surface, the preferred first cutting element being an ultrasonic
knife;</li><li>Figure 8A is an edge view of the segment first end;</li><li>Figure 8B the second end;</li><li>Figure 8C the cut-to-length segment;</li><li>Figure 9 is a perspective view of the preferred apparatus for forming the
segment; and</li><li>Figures 10A and 10B show respectively a cross-section of the cut ends
and a joined lap splice.</li></sl></p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Detailed Description of the Invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0038">With reference to Figure 1, a strip of elastomeric material is illustrated in
oblique view. The strip 1 has a transverse width W and an indefinite length
designated by the L direction. The strip 1 is transported upon a conveyor
means (not shown) in the direction D. The strip 1 comprises one or more
elastomeric components. The dotted line 3 shows the location or path of a
lateral cut that is to be made across the width of the strip 1 of elastomeric
material.</p>
    <p num="0039">The path 3 that extends across the width W of the strip 1 can be
perpendicular to the length L of the strip or obliquely traversing across the width
W. If the strip 1 has one or more layers of the parallel cords 22 that are
similarly oriented, then it is preferred that the path 3 is similarly oriented relative
to the cord 22 path.</p>
    <p num="0040">In the various figures shown, the elastomeric strips 1 are various
components used in the manufacture of tires. Figures 2 and 3, for example, is a
detailed view of a multi-component strip 1 of elastomeric material, the strip 1as
shown has ply 20 having a width Wp less than the strip width W, inserts 30, 
shoulder gum strips 40, a liner 50, a pair of chaffer strips 60, and a pair of
sidewall components 70. In Figured 4A and 4B, multi-component strips are
shown. In Figure 4A, the combination of tire components of Figure 2 are
combined with a bias ply 20 reinforced by cords 22 that are parallel and
similarly oriented at an oblique angle relative to the length of the ply 20,
generally in an angular orientation of 30° to 65°. In Figure 4B, the combination
tire components of Figures 2 and 3 is combined with a ply 20 having parallel
and similarly oriented cords 22 that are inclined at an angle in the range of 65°
to 90° relative to the length of the strip 1. In Figures 4A and 4B, the cords of the
multi-component strip 1 are substantially shorter in length than the path 3
across the strip. In such a case, the ends of the cords 22 are not exposed
making it very difficult to form a splice end without cutting or damaging a cord
22. The method of the present invention is not limited to the creation of splice
surfaces for tire components and is readily applicable to any elastomeric strip
having tacky surface adhesion properties.</p>
    <p num="0041">In practicing the invention, it is understood that the forming of the ends
12, 14 of a segment 10 taken from a strip 1 of elastomeric material is
accomplished in a similar way regardless of the component types. This is true if
the strip 1 is reinforced with parallel cords 22 perpendicular to the strip length or
reinforced with bias angled cords 22.</p>
    <p num="0042">In practicing the invention, as shown in Figures 5A through 5C, a strip 1
of elastomeric material is shown on an edge view. As shown in Figure 5A, the
preferred method has the strip 1 supported on a second side 4 and a cutting
element 120 passes through the strip 1 along a path that transverses across the
entire width of the strip 1. The cutting element 120 is positioned to cut at a very
low skive angle α of less than 30° relative to the first side 2 of the strip 1,
preferably the skive angle α is 10° or less.</p>
    <p num="0043">As shown, the cutting element 120 is an ultrasonic blade. The ultrasonic
blade initiates cutting to one side of the elastomeric strip 1 while the strip is
supported on a supporting means 110. The supporting means 110 is preferably
an anvil that has an outer surface adjacent to the cord reinforced tire
component. This outer surface preferably has a first surface 111 inclined at an
angle of <sub>1</sub>, <sub>1</sub> being less than the skive angle α. A second surface 112 is
provided wherein the second surface 112 is inclined at an angle <sub>2</sub>, <sub>2</sub> being at
an angle equal to or greater than the skive angle α. As illustrated, the cord
reinforced tire component 20 is adjacent to the surfaces 111, 112. As can be
seen, the ultrasonic blade 120 is positioned at a slight distance d spaced above 
the anvil 110. That distance creates a gap d of approximately 0.0030 inch (0.07
mm). This gap d is sufficient to allow the cord reinforced tire component 20 to
pass under the ultrasonic blade 120 during the cutting procedure.</p>
    <p num="0044">With reference to Figure 5B, as the ultrasonic blades 120 transverses
through the strip 1 being cut, the blade 120 will make initial contact with non
cord reinforced components prior to meeting with the cord-reinforced
component 20. The blade 120 will impact a cord 22, which results in the cord
22 being lifted off of the anvil 110 slightly and thus rides over the blade 120. On
the opposite side of the cut, the cords 22 are pressed under the ultrasonic blade
120 and occupy the gap d that was provided between the anvil 110 and the
blade 120 for this cutting procedure. As illustrated, three or more cords 22 are
shown adjacent to the flat surface 122 of the cutting blade 120. The ability of
the cords 22 to be lifted over the blade 120 permits the ultrasonic knife blade
120 to pass through the cords 22 without cutting any of the cords 22. This is
true because of the separation of the cut ends 12, 14 is created by the sharp
cutting edge 121 of the blade 120. By combining the rate of speed at which the
blade 120 is moving and the fact that the cords 22 are a more resistant material
than the elastomeric rubber, it is possible to easily cut through the rubber
without damaging the cords 22. As illustrated in Figure 5C, once the blade 120
is interposed between two adjacent cords 22 the cut surface 6 riding over the
blade 120 is allowed to ride freely upward and is lifted slightly. This prevents
the cut surface 6 of end 14 from reattaching itself to the other cut end 12 of the
elastomeric strip 1.</p>
    <p num="0045">All the cutting is shown with the components lying in a horizontal
direction and being cut from the top. It should be noted that in normal cutting
and for simplicity of tire building it is sometimes desirable, even preferable to
invert these strips such that the entire figure could be inverted relative to the
ground and that the cutting is actually occurring from below the surface upward.
For purposes of this invention, however, it is sufficient to note that these
materials can be cut from either direction as shown or in an inverted position
cutting from the underside.</p>
    <p num="0046">As illustrated in the Figure 5C, the ultrasonic blade 120 itself provides a
key feature in enabling the strip to be cut in such a fashion that one end 14 of
the cut segment 10 lifts and rides over the blade 120 as the blade 120 traverses
through the strip while the other cut end 12 is actually held down by the blade
120 as the blade is making the cut. As illustrated, one cord 22 is generally
snagged or raised off the anvil 110 slightly as the cutting blade 120 enters the 
ply edge. This snagged cord 22 often times can be slightly bent even pulled out
from the cut surface 56, 58. It has been determined in tire building that this cord
22 is of no consequence to the tire's structural integrity in that when the cord is
snagged or bent, that portion of the impacted cord 22 will lie on the turn-up side
of a bead and is not part of a structural component of the tire or the working
component of the tensioned ply because the bend portion of the impacted cord
lies at the radially outer portion of the ply turn up. It is important, however, that
the cord 22 that is snagged does not prevent good uniform splicing. It has been
found by having the cutting edge 121 of the cutting element 120 inclined at an
acute angle of approximately 60° or less relative to the width of the ply, the
cutting initials from the top surface to the anvil supported surface and can be
accomplished with minimal damage to the one impacted cord 22.</p>
    <p num="0047">It has been found that by transitioning the support 110 from an angle <sub>1</sub>
at one surface 111 to <sub>2</sub> at the other surface 112 and fixing the gap 2 at the
transition location 114, one can predict where the cord 22 impact with the blade
edge 121 will occur rather repeatedly. This is important in establishing a
precise length of the cut segment 10. As shown in the cross sectional view of
the segment 10, the cutting blade 120 has a flat surface 122 and the lower
portion 41 of the strip 1 adjacent to the support 111 at surface 112 is inclined at
an angle <sub>2</sub> is approximately equal to the lower inclination of the surface 122 of
the cutting blade 120 ensures that the elastomeric strip 1 is cut in such a
fashion that a flat surface 8 occurs directly above two or more preferably three
or more of the ply cords 22. This effectively filets the elastomeric material
directly above the ply cords, exposing these ply cords 22 to a flat cut surface 8.
This flat cut surface 8 greatly facilitates the ability to create an overlapping
splice joint 15 in tire building. This overlapping splice joint heretofore was
hindered by the elastomeric components being directly above the lapped ply
cords 22. By removing this material, in this unique cutting fashion it is possible
to create an overlap cord splice 15 that is stronger than other splices used in
radial tire building. It is well known that when the cord splices 15 are
overlapped, one can insure a stronger lap spliced joint. Heretofore, these lap
splice joints were avoided due to the fact that the multi-layered components
would create too much mass imbalance at the lap splice 15 due in part to the
amount of material directly above the cord 22. In attempts to reduce this
problem, the skive angle a was reduced to a very low angle of 10° or less.
Nevertheless, this resulted in still too much material at the lap splice joint
creating a slight mass imbalance. Therefore, it had been recommended in the 
past to create butt splices such that the cords 22 to not overlap. While this
prevented the problem of mass imbalance, it creates generally a more difficult
splice to repeatedly make in mass production. This is true because the
variation in length between the cut end 12, 14. If the segment 10 varies in
length by only a few thousandths of an inch, cord spacing can be affected.
Overlapping the splice cords prevents this from being an issue. The present
invention permits multi-layered components to be lap spliced with overlapping
cords without creating an undue mass imbalance. This is due to the fact that
the ply 20 as it is being cut is allowed to lift such that the elastomeric material
above the cutting element 120 is removed forming a flat cut surface 8 for
approximately a length of three or more cords 22 as shown in the illustrated
embodiment of Figure 5C. This permits lap splices 15 to be done effectively
and efficiently. What is unusual is that this can be accomplished without
additional cutting or additional steps. All cutting is done in one simple operation
of passing the ultrasonic blade 120 through the multi-layered component or strip
1.</p>
    <p num="0048">With reference to the supporting means 110, it is shown that the
supporting means is angled as previously discussed, the first outer surface 111
is inclined at a first angle <sub>1</sub> and the second outer surface 112 is inclined at a
second angle <sub>2</sub>. Internal of the supporting means 110 a plurality of holes 116
intersect the surfaces 111, 112 and are connected to a vacuum system. This
vacuum system helps keep the strip 1 secure to the support during the cutting
procedure and helps assist in this matter. To further assist and holding the
elastomeric strip 1 in place during the cutting procedure a retraining means 130
is provided just ahead of the cutting element 120. This restraining means 130
as illustrated, is a wheel 132 that rotates and is moveable along the same path
as the cutting means 120. This wheel 132 traverses directly in front of the
cutting path 3 but is at a sufficient distance to enable the strip 1 to lift and pass
over the cutting blade 120 as the blade is traversing.</p>
    <p num="0049">With reference to Figures 6A and 6B, the joining of the splice ends 12, 14
occurs when the cut-to-length segment 10 is cylindrically formed around a tire
building drum 5 as illustrated. As shown, the tire builder ideally brings the cut
surfaces 12, 14 together in a lapping splice relationship. This precisely sets the
circumferential length of the segment. The low angle skive surfaces 6, 8 are
then pressed together in a technique commonly referred to as stitching.</p>
    <p num="0050">The apparatus 100 has a means 120 for forming a low angle skive
surface across the width of the strip. The means preferably is a cutting element 
120. In the most preferred apparatus the cutting element 120 is an ultrasonic
knife. As shown in Figure 7, the knife 120 preferably has a somewhat wedge
like shape with a cutting edge 121 that is oriented at a fixed angle alpha relative
to the strip cut path 3 and is also canted at an angle β such that the cutting
edge 121 is inclined slightly at an acute angle relative to the width of the ply.
This dual angle setting of the cutting element 120 achieves a superior more
uniformed cut because the knife's cutting edge 124 is really the tip of a chisel
type-cutting tool. Unlike a conventional ultrasonic low amplitude high frequency
knife that cuts along a side of the blade, the chisel type blade has no node
along the cutting edge 121 because the cutting edge 121 is really the tip of the
blade tilted and canted slightly. This means that the excitation frequency is
traveling in the same distance all along the cutting edge 121. This fact enables
the rubber to be cut more uniformly than conventionally by standard ultrasonic
blade type cutters.</p>
    <p num="0051">A second feature of the preferred apparatus 100 is a means for moving
the means 120 for forming and the means 130 for restraining. The means 140
for moving preferably has a motor driven mechanism that slidedly traverses the
means 120 for forming and the means 130 for restraining across the width of
the strip 1. The means 120 ideally can be moved angularly relative to the strip
length to accommodate cutting along any bias angle.</p>
    <p num="0052">The means for moving 140 may also include a means 141 for orienting
the cutting element 120 at a range of angles to achieve the optimum skive
surface area. As shown in Figure 9, the prefer apparatus 100 may include a
conveyor means 150 to advance the strip 1 along the direction of the strip 1
length preferably the conveyor means 150 would be capable of advancing the
strip 1 to a predetermined distance to enable the strip 1 to be cut to form a
segment 10 having a fixed length L between the cut surfaces 12, 14 at a
location S1 and S2 as previously shown.</p>
    <p num="0053">Once cut, the segment 10, when spliced has the cut ends 12, 14 joined
and the strip 1 cylindrically forms a tire as previously discussed. The segment
10 as shown in Figures 8A, 8B and 8C can be thick, thin, flat, or irregularly
contoured, a single cord reinforced component 20 or a multi-component as
discussed. The angular orientation of the surfaces 6, 8 can be selected for
optimum lap joint splicing for the particular strip as shown in Figures 10A and
10B.</p>
    <p num="0054">While the strip may include some cured or partially cured components, it
is preferred that portions of this strip 1 be uncured or at least partially uncured. 
This permits the spliced surfaces 6, 8 to exhibit the tacky, self-sticking
properties to facilitate joint adhesion at the lap splice 15.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A method of cutting segments (10) to desired lengths from a strip (1) of
elastomeric material, the segments have a width W, the elastomeric strip being
formed of a plurality of tire components, at least one of the tire components
being a cord reinforced component, the cords (22) being substantially parallel
and oriented in the direction of a cutting path (3) formed across the width W of
the strip; the method comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>moving on ultrasonic knife (120) into cutting engagement of the elastomeric
strip while supporting the strip along the cutting path;</claim-text><claim-text>cutting the segment at a skive angle α; and</claim-text><claim-text>impacting a cord (22) of the cord reinforced component, lifting said cord over
the ultrasonic knife as the segment is being cut, the impacted cord being at a
cut end (8) adjacent the cutting path.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The method of claim 1 further comprising the step of orienting a cutting
edge (121) on the ultrasonic knife (12) inclined at an acute angle β relative to
the strip cutting path (3).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The method of claim 1 or 2 further comprising the steps of movably
restraining the strip (1) ahead of the cutting.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The method of claim 1, 2 or 3 wherein the steps of supporting the strip
includes supporting the strip at an angle 1, less than the skive angle α on one
side of the cutting path (3) and an angle 2 greater than the skive angle α on
the opposite side of the cutting path.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The method of any of claims 1- 4, wherein the location of the impacted
cord occurs approximately at the location wherein the supporting angle
changes from 1 to 2.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The method of any of claims 1-5 comprising the step of positioning the
cutting edge (121) of the ultrasonic knife (120) at a gap distance (d) above the
strip (1) slightly less than or slightly to the greater than the thickness of the
cord reinforced component.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>The method of any of claims 1- 6 wherein the step of cutting includes
cutting the segment (10) wherein a plurality of cords (22) are beneath and
adjacent a flat cut surface (8).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>An apparatus (100) for cutting segments (10) from a strip (1) of multi-layered
elastomeric material containing reinforcing cords (22), the cords being
substantially parallel and more or less oriented in the direction of a cutting path
(3), the apparatus characterized by:
<claim-text><claim-text>a) a cutting element (120) for cutting the strip to form cut ends (12, 14), the
cutting element having a cutting edge (121) oriented to cut along a line, the line
being tangent to one or more cords and inclined at a desired skive angle α;</claim-text><claim-text>b) a means (110) for supporting the strip (1) along the cutting path, the
means for supporting having a first surface (111) oriented at an angle 1 less
than the skive angle α and a second surface (112) oriented at an angle 2
greater than or equal to the skive angle α;</claim-text><claim-text>c) a means (130) for restraining the strip against the means (110) for
supporting, the means for restraining being located ahead of the cutting
element; and</claim-text><claim-text>d) a means (140) for moving the cutting element and the means for
restraining.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>The apparatus of claim 8 wherein the cutting element (120) has the
cutting edge (121) inclined at an acute angle β relative to the strip width, the
cutting edge oriented to initiate cutting on the surface furthest away from the
means (110) for supporting the strip (1).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>The apparatus of claim 8 or 9 wherein the skive angle α is 10° or less
adjacent the one or more cords (22).</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
