<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1243390-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1243390" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="25218749" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020925">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1243390-A2" status="new" fvid="23566474">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1243390</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20020925</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02100259-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02100259</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020315</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="US-81575401-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>81575401</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010323</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  33/02        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  33/02        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  33/38        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  33/38        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  35/02        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  35/02        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B29D  30/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B29D  30/06        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B29K 105/24        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B29L  30/00        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B29D  30/06B4</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verbundblatt für ein Reifenvulkanisierformwerkzeug</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Composite blade for a tire curing mould</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Lame composite pour un moule de vulcanisation de pneumatiques</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GOODYEAR TIRE &amp; RUBBER</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>THE GOODYEAR TIRE &amp; RUBBER COMPANY</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>THE GOODYEAR TIRE &amp;amp; RUBBER COMPANY</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1144 East Market Street</street>
              <city>Akron, Ohio 44316-0001</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>DOMANGE ANDRE</name>
            <address>
              <country>BE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>LOUIS PATRICK</name>
            <address>
              <country>BE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>DOMANGE, ANDRE</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>LOUIS, PATRICK</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Domange, André</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>19, Sainte-Marie / Semois</street>
              <city>6740 Etalle</city>
              <country>BE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>LOUIS, PATRICK</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>21, Benonchamps</street>
              <city>6600 Bastogne</city>
              <country>BE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Leitz, Paul</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Goodyear Technical Center, Patent Department, Avenue Gordon Smith</street>
              <city>7750 Colmar-Berg</city>
              <country>LU</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>Method of manufacturing a composite blade (300-312) having at least
two blade portions (101, 201), for a tire curing mold having the steps of
providing a first strip (100) of metallic material commonly used to form blades
for tire curing molds; stamping or punching out from the strip various shapes to
make main blade portions (101); providing a second strip (200) of metallic
material; stamping or punching out from the second strip (200) a further set of
blade portions (201) having a longitudinal and lateral dimensions which are
preferably at most equal to those of the first blade portions (101), assembling at
least one of the first and at least one of the second blade portions (201); and
affixing the different blade portions (101, 201) together.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="68" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="42"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Technical Field</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to blades for curing molds. More
particularly to composite type blades that have thicknesses which can easily be
tailored to the tire tread property requirements and a method of fabricating such
composite blades.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Background of the Invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0002">Blades for tire curing molds are well known in the art of tire manufacture.
Such blades are conventionally made from a running length or strip of a metallic
material such as steel, stainless steel or brass. The strip is generally 0.4 mm to
1 mm thick and has a length of 10 to 40 mm. Sometimes the strips are of solid
form; other times perforated strips are used to form the blades.</p>
    <p num="0003">US-A- 3,880,020, a method and apparatus for making blades, is
disclosed which enables small quantity lots of a multiplicity of different styles of
blades to be made rapidly and economically. The method and apparatus
permits blades to be blanked out from the stack of material by a plurality of
punch and die sets while the stock remains securely attached to an endless
loop carrier. If so desired, a plurality of sub-presses are used for forming bends
in the blade.</p>
    <p num="0004">In US-A- 3,581,535, a similar method and apparatus for making blades is
disclosed. The method and apparatus for making blades for use in tire molds
includes piercing, notching, bending or otherwise altering the shape of a free
end of strip material by successively positioning the free end and a plurality of
shape altering tools in operative engagement and cutting off the formed blade
from the free end. Bends, cuts, notches and holes are possible.</p>
    <p num="0005">WO-A1-99/21701 discloses a method of fabricating a composite blade
employing the steps of forming a blade blank and encapsulating at least one
end in a second material by placing the end in a die and molding an enlarged
cross-section of a second material around the end. Preferably, the second
material is a powdered metal.</p>
    <p num="0006">The blades create sipes in a tread during the vulcanization step of a
green tire in a curing mold. A sipe is a narrow groove or incision in the tread
and closes when located in the footprint, i.e., in the contact patch of the tire
tread with a flat surface at zero speed and under normal load and inflation
pressure. The sipes may extend circumferentially or laterally about the tread in 
a straight, curved or zig-zag manner and may be as deep as the block and rib
defining grooves. The sipes may pass through or cut one or both sides of the
ribs and blocks or be confined to their interior. It is also known to have the
sipes lying in planes which are not perpendicular to tangents to the surface of
the tread at their point of intersection. It is further known to use sipes having a
depth which varies along their length as well as sipes which have varying
thicknesses. However, the manufacturing of such blades is expensive and
lacks flexibility.</p>
    <p num="0007">It is an object of the present invention to provide a manufacturing
process for making a set of blades having different thicknesses.</p>
    <p num="0008">It is a further object of the present invention to provide a manufacturing
process for making blades having varying thicknesses along their length.</p>
    <p num="0009">It is a further object of the present invention to provide a manufacturing
process for making blades having varying thicknesses along their depth.</p>
    <p num="0010">It is a still further object of the present invention to provide a mold for
vulcanizing a tire as well as tire vulcanized in such mold.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Summary of the Invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0011">The invention provides a method of manufacturing a composite blade
having at least two blade portions for a tire curing mold comprising the steps of:
providing a first strip of metallic material commonly used to form blades for tire
curing molds; stamping or punching out from the strip various shapes to make
main blade portions; providing a second strip of metallic material; stamping or
punching out from the second strip a set of second blade portions having
longitudinal and lateral dimensions; assembling a main portion and at least one
of the second blade portions; and affixing the different blade portions together to
form the composite blade.</p>
    <p num="0012">Preferably, the blade portions are affixed by the step of welding or
soldering the blade portions together.</p>
    <p num="0013">The method further may have the steps of providing further strips of
metallic material; stamping or punching out from the further strips further sets of
blade portions having a longitudinal and lateral dimensions which are preferably
at most equal to those of the main blade portions; assembling a main and at
least one of the second blade portions together with at least one of the further
portions; and affixing the different blade portions together. A composite blade
obtained through the method is also disclosed.</p>
    <p num="0014">In one embodiment the second strip of metallic material has the same 
thickness as the first strip and the metal of the second strip of metallic material
has the same composition as the first strip. The composite blades may have
any number of slots or cuts to form various projections.</p>
    <p num="0015">A mold including the blade and a tire cured in the mold are also
disclosed.</p>
    <p num="0016">To acquaint persons skilled in the art, most closely related to the instant
invention, certain preferred embodiments are now described with reference to
the annexed drawings. These embodiments are illustrative and can be modified
in numerous ways within the scope of the invention defined in the claims.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Brief Description of the Figures</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0017">
      <sl>
        <li>Fig. 1 is a view of a first strip used to form the main portion of the
composite blade according to the invention;</li>
        <li>Figs. 2 to 4 show various main portions of differing shapes used in
assembling the composite blades according to the invention.</li>
        <li>Fig. 5 is a view of a second strip used to form second portions of the
composite blade according to the invention;</li>
        <li>Figs. 6 to 10 show various second blade portions of differing shapes
used in assembling the blades according to the invention;</li>
        <li>Figs. 11 to 17 are views of substantially flat composite blades obtained
by using the process according to the invention;</li>
        <li>Figs. 18 to 20 are side views of composite blades having varying depths
obtained by using the process according to the invention;</li>
        <li>Figs. 20 to 23 are top views on composite blades according to the
invention; and</li>
        <li>Figs. 24 to 25 are schematic sections across a block of rubbery tread
material.</li>
      </sl>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Detailed Description of the Invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0018">With reference to Fig. 1, a portion of a first strip 100 of metallic material
commonly used to form blades for tire curing molds is shown. The resultant
blades are stamped or punched out from the strip 100 and take various shapes
as shown in Figs. 2 to 4. The blades may have any number of slots 120 or cuts
121 to form the various projections 122. The blades may be wavy as shown in
Fig. 3 or have bends at their extremities (see Fig. 4). These features are well
known in the tire building art and such blades are used as main portion of the
composite blade according to the invention. </p>
    <p num="0019">According to the invention and with reference to Figs. 5 to 10, a second
strip 200 of metallic material commonly used to form blades for tire curing molds
is stamped or punched to form a second set of blade portions out from the strip
200 which may take various shapes as shown in Figs. 6 to 10. This second
strip 200 of metallic material may have the same thickness as the first strip 100,
a somewhat higher or smaller thickness. Usually the thickness of the first strip
100 ranges between 0.3 and 1 mm and the thickness of the second strip 200
between 0.3 and 0.8 mm. The metallic material of the second strip 200 may be
the same as the one of the first strip 100. Preferred metallic material is steel
because of its low cost. Further materials of interest are aluminum, nickel alloy,
and titanium. Combinations of carbon steel constituting the first strip 100 with
titanium or other metals containing steel alloys constituting the second strip 200
would allow a great flexibility in the choice of the blade portion thicknesses.</p>
    <p num="0020">The main blade portion 101 made out of the first strip 100 is usually at
least partly anchored in the mold by holes 21 (see Fig. 2). This anchoring must
be sufficient to insure that the composite blades do not pull out when the tread
is extracted from the tire curing mold. The blade portion 201 made out of the
second strip 200 is or is not anchored in the mold, depending on the design of
the blade.</p>
    <p num="0021">The second blade portions 201 made out of the second strip 200 may
take the shape of a rectangle (Fig. 6), parallelogram (Fig. 7), triangle (Fig. 9),
trapezoid (Fig. 10) and may basically have any geometrical shape which is
considered by a man skilled in the art to confer favorable properties to the tire
tread. They may be flat as shown in Figs. 6 and 7, or they may be given a
curved or wavy shape as shown in Fig. 8, depending on the fact that they will be
assembled to a corresponding flat, curved or wavy main portion obtained out of
the first strip 100. Alternatively the main portion 101 and the second portion
201 may be given at first a flat shape and after assembly stamped in order to
obtain the desired wavy, sinusoidal or crimped or similar shape.</p>
    <p num="0022">After assembly, the main and second blade portions 101, 201 are affixed
together. This may be done by gluing using a high temperature epoxy adhesive
or a high temperature cement. Another possibility is to subject the assembled
portions to a combined compression and heat treatment. A still further
possibility is to braze or solder the two portions. The presently preferred way is
to weld the different portions together along their lateral adjacent sides, or at
multiple points called "spot welding".</p>
    <p num="0023">The composite blades 300-312, according to the invention, may be 
fabricated at low cost in a great variety of shapes. Figs. 11 through 23 illustrate
a few of these exemplary shapes, featuring different depths, widths and lengths.
Fig. 11 shows a blade 300 providing a sipe having a greater width in its radially
middle portion, Fig. 12 shows a blade 301 having substantially a width double to
the one offered by single metallic strips 100 or 200. Figs. 13, 14 and 15 show
blades 302, 303, 304 providing sipes with laterally stepped off widths, allowing
to tailor the elastomeric block stiffness to the requirements; such sipes influence
locally transverse deformation of the blocks they are included in. Fig. 16 shows
a blade 305 providing a sipe having on part of its lateral length and on part of its
radially inner portion, a higher width. Fig. 17 shows a blade 306 producing a
sipe having on part of its length a higher width, which length decreases towards
the tread surface. Fig. 18 shows a blade 307 providing a sipe having on both
sides a higher width and a depth decreasing from both sides towards the
center. Fig. 19 shows a blade 308 providing a sipe having a first side a higher
width and a depth decreasing towards the second side. Fig. 20 shows a blade
309 providing a sipe having a lateral length decreasing radially towards the
tread bottom and a higher sipe width portion with a width and length remaining
constant.</p>
    <p num="0024">It must be appreciated that some of the composite blades obtained
through the method according to the invention result in rather complicated blade
layouts despite the fact that the manufacturing steps are simple.</p>
    <p num="0025">As more specifically illustrated in Figs. 21 and 22, the blades 310, 311
obtained according to the method of the invention may include the steps of
bending. The bending step may take place before or after assembly of the
different blade portions. The blades may further be crimped, notching or
perforated before or after assembly. In Fig. 23 a blade 312 is shown where only
part of the two metal sheets 101 and 201 overlap. The sheets 101 and 201 can
have the same height or different heights.</p>
    <p num="0026">With reference to Figs. 24 and 25, the possibility of making interlocking
sipes in the tread blocks is illustrated. For ease of representation, only one sipe
per block 241, 251 is shown and the block and grooves are not to scale. It is
understood that a block includes usually several sipes. In the instant case, the
further sipes may have the same section than the one shown in the drawing. In
Fig. 24 a block 241 is defined by laterally and circumferentially extending
grooves 242, wherefrom only one kind can be represented in this cross-section.
The block 241 includes sipe 245 which has in the case of the drawing
throughout its height, substantially uniform thickness. However, slightly above 
half-height, the sipe 245 shows a protrusion 243 on one side and a recess 247
on the other. Such sipe 245 is easily obtained according to the inventive
method by assembling to the radially outer part of a first side of a main portion
101 as shown in Fig. 2, a second blade portion 201 as shown in Fig. 6; a further
similar second blade portion 201, as shown in Fig. 6 is assembled to the radially
inner part of main portion 101.</p>
    <p num="0027">It can be easily seen that if there is block deformation as indicated by
arrow A, the protrusion 243 located on one side of the sipe, advances towards
recess 247 on the other side of the sipe, until it is in contact with such. Once in
contact, protrusion 243 opposes any further deformation of the block 245.
Opposite deformation does not result in such interlocking and the two adjacent
sipe sidewalls may slide along each other as far as allowed by the rigidity of the
rubbery material and the forces applied thereto. It appears that such sipe is
directional. It appears further that such interlocking stops when the tire is worn
down to the protrusion 243. At that time the stiffness of the block has increased
and a limiting of flexing is no more desired.</p>
    <p num="0028">With reference to Fig. 25, the possibility of making bi-directional
interlocking sipes 255 in the tread blocks 251 is illustrated. Also, in this case
only one sipe per block is shown for ease of representation. Furthermore, the
different elements are not to scale. In Fig. 25, a block 251 is defined by laterally
and circumferentially extending grooves 252. The block includes sipe 255
which has in the case of the drawing throughout its height, substantially uniform
thickness. However, slightly above half-height, the sipe shows a protrusion 254
on one side and a recess 253 on the other. Such sipe is easily obtained
according to the inventive method by assembling to a main portion 101 as
shown in Fig. 2, two blade portion as shown in Fig. 6, to one side, and more
specifically a first one 101 to its radially outer portion and a second one 201 to
its radially inner portion, leaving a free portion in the middle of the main portion
101, which free portion defines in the cured tire the protrusion 254. On the
middle portion of the other side of the main portion 101 a blade portion 201 as
shown in Fig. 6 is assembled, which blade portion defines the recess 253 in the
cured tire.</p>
    <p num="0029">It can be easily seen that if there is block deformation in a direction
indicated by arrow A or in the opposite direction, protruding rubbery material
254 will move towards recess 253 on the other side of the sipe, until it nests into
recess 253 opposing any further deformation on the block 251. The amount of
deformation required to have such interlocking depends on the width of the sipe 
and on the layout, mainly transverse dimensions, of the recess and the
protrusion. It appears that such sipe has no directional effect in a new tire.
Once the tire is about half worn down, the sipe will have substantially a cross-section
which can be compared to that shown in Fig. 24 and its behavior will be,
as explained in connection with Fig. 24.</p>
    <p num="0030">In case of the sipes shown in Figs. 24 and 25, the loss due to wear of the
non-directional interlocking (Fig. 24) or the change from non-directional to
directional of the interlocking (Fig. 25) may be controlled by giving the recess
247, 253 and similarly the protrusion 243, 254 a small inclination. This can
easily be implemented by assembling second blade portions 201, as shown in
Fig. 7 to the main portion 101 of the composite blade 300-312.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>Method of manufacturing a composite blade (300-312) having at least
two blade (101,201) portions for a tire curing mold comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>providing a first strip (100) of metallic material commonly used to
form blades for tire curing molds;</claim-text><claim-text>stamping or punching out from the strip various shapes to make
main blade portions (101);</claim-text><claim-text>providing a second strip (200) of metallic material;</claim-text><claim-text>stamping or punching out from the second strip (200) a set of
second blade portions (201) having longitudinal and lateral dimensions;</claim-text><claim-text>assembling a main portion and at least one of the second blade
portions (201); and</claim-text><claim-text>affixing the different blade portions (101,201) together to form the
composite blade.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The method according to claim 1 wherein the blade portions (101,201)
are affixed by the steps of welding or soldering the blade portions together.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The method according to claim 1 or 2 comprising the further step of
providing further strips of metallic material;
<claim-text><claim-text>stamping or punching out from the further strips sets of blade
portions having a longitudinal and lateral dimensions which are
preferably at most equal to those of the main blade portions;</claim-text><claim-text>assembling a main and at least one of the second blade portions
together with at least one of the further portions; and</claim-text><claim-text>affixing the different blade portions together.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A composite blade (300-312) obtained through the method of any of
claims 1 to 3.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The composite blade according to claim 4 wherein the second strip (200)
of metallic material has the same thickness as the first strip (100).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The composite blade according to claim 4 or 5 wherein the metal of the
second strip (200) of metallic material has the same compositions as the first
strip (100).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>The composite blade according to any of claims 4 to 6 wherein the
composite blades have any number of slots (120) or cuts (121) to form various
projections.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A mold including a blade according to any of claims 4 to 7.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>Tire cured in a mold according to claim 8.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
