<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1238790-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1238790" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="7676763" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020911">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1238790-A1" status="new" fvid="23537141">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1238790</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20020911</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02005455-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02005455</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020308</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="DE-10111229-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>DE</country>
          <doc-number>10111229</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010308</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A43B   7/14        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A43B   7/14        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A43B  13/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A43B  13/04        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A43B  13/12        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A43B  13/38        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A43B  13/40        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B29D  31/50        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B29D  31/518       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">A43B  13/12</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">A43B   7/14</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B29D  31/518B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K43B714:50M</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Mittelsohle mit Stützelemente</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Midsole with support element</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Semelle intermédiaire avec élément de support</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ADIDAS INTERNAT B V</name>
            <address>
              <country>NL</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ADIDAS INTERNATIONAL B.V.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>adidas International B.V.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Koningin Wilhelminaplein 30</street>
              <city>1062 KR Amsterdam</city>
              <country>NL</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KNOERR KLAUS</name>
            <address>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KNOERR, KLAUS</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>KNOERR, KLAUS</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Am Treibweg 25</street>
              <city>91315 Höchstadt</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Hess, Peter K., Dipl.-Phys.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Bardehle,Pagenberg,Dost,Altenburg,Geissler,Isenbruck Patent- und Rechtsanwälte Postfach 86 06 20</street>
              <city>81633 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>The present invention relates to a sole for shoes, in particular to a midsole with
support elements for athletic shoes wherein said midsole and said support
elements are made from the same polymer base having different mechanical
properties. Said midsole and said support elements are made of standard-EVA
according to a preferred embodiment. Within the scope of the method according
to the present invention, they are connected to each other by co-vulcanization
wherein no connecting means have to be added. Furthermore, the present
invention relates to a shoe comprising a sole according to the present invention.</p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <u style="single">1. Technical field</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a sole for shoes, in particular a midsole with a
support element for athletic shoes, wherein the midsole and the support element
are made of the same material. Furthermore, the present invention relates to a
method for the manufacture of this sole.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">2. Prior art</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0002">Known soles substantially have a three layered structure. They consist of an
outsole, a midsole and an inner sole. The outsole provides the shoe with an outer
profile so that it meets the requirements of good grip with the respective ground.
Furthermore, the outsole is made of a non-abrasive material to assure high wear
resistance and a long lifetime of the sole. The midsole is often made of a foamed
plastic as for example elastomers with different densities. Based on the ability of
the midsole materail to deform reversibly, it absorbs or dampens mechanical
impacts which are generated during the running motion and which are transmitted
to the body of the runner via the shoe. The damping of said mechanical impacts
induced in this way can be supported by the integration of damping elements of
different construction. Additionally, the midsole often serves for receiving
stability or support elements which are made of lightweight and stable plastics and
which support the foot during running. Based on their selectively adjustable
flexibility, a further function of this stability or support element is the support of
the running motion of the runner. An example of such a known support element is
described in DE-A-199 04 744 which is completely included by reference.</p>
    <p num="0003">The connection of the above referenced parts of a sole, the midsole and the
support element, can be realized with different methods known from the prior art. </p>
    <p num="0004">In this context, conventional methods comprise stitching, sewing and cementing.
In a sole construction of athletic shoes, the different layers are conventionally
connected by means of adhesive which has several disadvantages. Based on their
constitution, presently used adhesives are often volatile and harmful to the
environment because of the emission of certain gases. Additionally, the known
adhesives do not form a favorable bond for example between rubber and plastic
sole elements so that no durable connection is achieved and said elements become
detached from one another. It is a further disadvantage that the weight of the shoe
is increased by the use of adhesives. Additionally, the alignment of the sole
components to each other is an expensive process. In the case that the sole
components are not optimally aligned, the shoe is uncomfortable and does not
meet the expected requirements.</p>
    <p num="0005">According to the prior art, a rubber outsole and a foamed midsole are connected
together by using two different methods. According to the teaching of US-A-4
816 345, both elements are connected by heating while contacting each other
wherein this connection is not realized by a vulcanization process. Thermoplastic
polymers and rubber are connected by co-vulcanization according to US-A-4 921
762 wherein peroxidic vulcanization agents and vulcanization activators are added
to the rubber. Further methods are known for connecting together the outsole and
the midsole by vulcanization. In this context, it is yet important to note that the
respectively used plastic and rubber have to be supplemented by chemical
additives in the preliminary stage of the method in order to later achieve a good
connection. These additives are also indicated as bonding agents which are
expensive as basic material. Additionally, corresponding costly machines are
necessary to process the basic materials and the different additives. Based on the
number of necessary procedural steps only for mixing the materials, the whole
sole manufacture is expensive and time-consuming.</p>
    <p num="0006">It is therefore the problem of the present invention to provide a method for
connecting together sole elements which is less expensive and less time-consuming 
than conventional prior art methods. It is a further problem of the
present invention to provide a low-cost sole which comprises additional support
elements in the midsole region and to provide a shoe with such a sole.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">3. Summary of the invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0007">The present invention relates to a method for the manufacture of a sole element,
particularly for athletic shoes, comprising the following steps: manufacture of a
sole preform and a preform of a support element wherein said sole preform and
said preform of the support element are made from the same polymer base having
different mechanical properties and do not comprise any connecting means;
positioning of the sole preform and the preform of the support element in a mold;
and connecting together said sole preform with said preform of said support
element under the application of heat and pressure without adding connecting
means.</p>
    <p num="0008">For the manufacture of a sole element, the different preforms are made from the
same polymer-base. The manufacture of the preforms is performed by pre-vulcanization
wherein cross-linking agents contained in the material are not
completely vulcanized. As a result of the use of preforms with the same polymer
base and due to the remaining cross-linking agents, cross-linking and, thus, a
connection between the preforms is performed when heat and pressure are
applied. To this end, no connecting means have to be added during the whole
procedure so that both the materials used and the number of procedural steps are
reduced compared to conventional methods.</p>
    <p num="0009">Preferably according to the invention, the sole preform as well as the preform of
the support element are made of standard EVA.</p>
    <p num="0010">Furthermore, the present invention relates to a sole element, particularly for
athletic shoes, comprising a sole with at least one support element, wherein the
sole and the support element are made from the same polymer base having 
different mechanical properties and being connected to each other without
connecting means.</p>
    <p num="0011">The components of the sole element according to the invention are made from the
same polymer base. According to the invention, the single components are
connected to each other without using connecting means whereby a sole element
having the same functional properties as conventional sole elements can be
produced more cost effectively.</p>
    <p num="0012">In addition, the present invention relates to a shoe with a sole manufactured
according to the present invention.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">4. Detailed description of the invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0013">The present invention provides a method for the manufacture of sole elements
where, in particular, the low cost and reduction in the amount of materials used is
of primary importance.</p>
    <p num="0014">As already explained in the introductory part of the specification, the sole of
athletic shoes consist of an outsole, a midsole and an inner sole which are also
indicated as sole elements. The midsole is often supplemented by additional
support elements wherein the midsole is mostly made of damping plastics. Within
the scope of the present invention, the midsole is preferably made of standard-EVA
(ethylene vinyl acetate). The standard-EVA is made based on a vinyl-acetate(VA)-content
of 18-25 %. Further fillers as for example SiO<sub>2</sub> or TiO<sub>2</sub> as
well as cross-linking agents and processing promoters are added to said standard-EVA.
The cross-linking agents comprise for example peroxides. Additionally, co-agents
are added to the material-mixture hardening the material during
vulcanization. Such co-agents are for example acrylates or isocyanates.
Depending on whether the EVA is to be foamed later, blowing agents are also
added to the material mixture. </p>
    <p num="0015">Said support elements are made of plastics having high mechanical stability
compared to the properties of the midsole materials, as for example Pebax®, a
nylon-modification or TPU, a thermoplastic elastomer based on polyurethane. In
accordance with the invention, the support elements are also preferably made of
standard-EVA wherein different mechanical properties compared to the standard-EVA
of the midsole are achieved based on the degree of cross-linking of the
contained macromolecular substances. Although, the method according to the
present invention is explained on the basis of a midsole, it is also conceivable to
use the method for the manufacture of other sole elements and to thereby exploit
its advantages.</p>
    <p num="0016">Within the limits of the method according to the present invention, the midsole
and the support elements are preferably pre-manufactured as preforms. The
manufacture of the preforms also serves to pre-adjust the different mechanical
properties of the resulting midsole and the resulting support elements. The
manufacture of the preforms of the support element and the midsole is carried out
using standard-EVA material so that the midsole as well as the support elements
are made from the same polymer-bas. Thus, the support element and the midsole
are equal with respect to their polymer base but they do not correspond with
respect to their structure. The material-mixture is only supplemented by the
addition of blowing agents, peroxides and fillers. Di-comyl-peroxide is used for
example as a peroxide and silicic acid is for example used as a filler. The added
peroxides serve to cross-link the polymer-base. It follows therefrom that the
preforms of the midsole and the support element can differ in their mechanical
properties.</p>
    <p num="0017">Starting from the same polymer base (a standard-EVA), the preforms of the
midsole and the support element are manufactured according to different
production methods in order to achieve the different mechanical properties,
although both methods use pre-vulcanization. </p>
    <p num="0018">The midsole preferably consists of standard-EVA having vinyl acetate content of
18 to 27 % wherein additionally the above mentioned filler and peroxides are
added. Moreover, a blowing agent is supplemented so that the midsole preform
can be shaped later. The above composition is pre-vulcanized for adjustment of
the mechanical properties of the midsole preform and for the provision of the
shape. The pre-vulcanization is usually carried out at temperatures of 155-170 °C.
Compared to the conventional vulcanization, the difference is a shortened time-period.
As a result of the pre-vulcanization, a certain degree of cross-linking in the
standard-EVA is achieved and the mechanical properties of the midsole preform
are adjusted.</p>
    <p num="0019">The preform of the support element is also according to the invention preferably
made of standard-EVA having a vinyl acetate content of 18 to 25 %. It is, thus,
also made from the same polymer-base. Peroxides and fillers are added as
additives as already mentioned above. Additionally, co-agents are added to the
material-mixture hardening the material during vulcanization. Acrylates or
isocyanates are examples of such co-agents. In comparison to the material of the
midsole preform, no blowing agent is supplemented to the standard-EVA. In the
course of the pre-vulcanization process, the basic material is formed into preforms
of the support elements. Compared to the midsole preform, a higher degree of
cross-linking is attained to achieve certain mechanical properties. These
mechanical properties include a higher stiffness and hardness compared to the
midsole preform. For example, according to the invention it is preferred to obtain
a hardness of Shore A 80-95. By the addition of further additives, as for example
di- or trimodal acrylate, it is possible to produce the support elements having a
hardness in the range of Shore D. In this context, the hardness of Shore is
determined corresponding to the ISO-standard 868-1985 or the DIN-standard
53505.</p>
    <p num="0020">These mechanical properties correspond to the hardness values of Pebax® and
TPU which so far were used for the manufacture of known support elements. </p>
    <p num="0021">Since these materials are expensive and cannot be processed optimally in view of
their outer fashion and incorporation in the sole, it is a further advantage of this
invention that on the one hand further expenses are saved and on the other hand
better results in the processing are achieved by the use of standard-EVA as will be
described later. During the manufacture of the preforms of the support elements,
the same are pre-vulcanized and subsequently cut into pieces. The preform shape
can vary according to the function of the support element. For example elongated
structures or V-shaped structures are possible which support the flexibility of the
sole by their configuration. Furthermore, support elements having a comparably
greater volume can also be produced and positioned adjacent the medial or lateral
side of the sole to correctively support possible defects in the bone structure of the
foot.</p>
    <p num="0022">Based on the surface quality of the produced preforms of the support elements
made of standard-EVA, it is possible to fashion the same as desired and without
great expense by means of a silk screen printing procedure. In so doing, it is
possible to adapt the coloured surface design of these portions of the sole to the
upper and the whole sole of the resulting shoe. Thus, the application of aesthetic
designs to these preforms is preferably carried out according to the invention
preferably after the manufacture of the preform of the support element and by
means of silk screen printing. In contrast thereto, the films or foils used in the past
for fashioning the TPU-elements were applied with high technical efforts and they
were expensive to manufacture.</p>
    <p num="0023">After the preforms of the support element and the midsole have been produced
from the same polymer-base, they are arranged in a mold which determines the
resulting sole shape by its inner shape. In this process, the preforms of the support
elements are according to the invention preferably positioned on the lower side of
the mold and subsequently the midsole preform is arranged over the top. After
closing the mold, heat and pressure are applied to the contained preforms within
the mold. By this energy supply, a further shaping, a connecting between the 
midsole preform and the preform of the support element as well as a hardening of
the preform of the support element is provided. Generally, this process of
connecting is indicated as co-vulcanization in which a cross-linking between the
standard-EVA of the midsole and the support element is carried out. The co-vulcanization
is performed at temperatures of approximately 155-170°C. In this
context, it is important to note that the connection between the midsole and the
support elements results from the peroxides existing in the material. These
peroxides were not completely vulcanized during the step of pre-vulcanization for
the manufacture of the sole preform and the preform of the support element.
Therefore, the sole and the support element are connected without adding
connecting means. In this context, adhesives or generally the addition of reactive
functional groups to the polymer base are considered to be connecting means
enabling a connection between the support element and the sole. Connecting
means also comprise mechanical fastening means for providing a connection. In
contrast, peroxides are cross-linking agents; the vulcanization of the polymer-base
is not possible without them.</p>
    <p num="0024">After closing the mold, the above mentioned blowing agent contained in the
midsole preform is activated by the energy supply. The midsole preform is
foamed and thereby enlarges its volume whereby it is pressed in the
predetermined desired shape of the sole element and a midsole is formed. At the
same time, the midsole preform and the preform of the support element are
permanently connected to each other with low technical efforts by the energy
supply. Furthermore, the preform of the support element is hardened during this
process without substantially changing its shape and finally it forms a support
element. The substantial advantage of this process consists in the fact that a
permanent connection between the midsole and the support element is provided
without adding connecting means to the basic material of the midsole preform and
the preform of the support element. Additionally, no connecting means have to be
supplemented in the co-vulcanization process. For this reason, the material used is
less expensive and the whole manufacturing method requires less procedural 
steps. Thus, a midsole with support element is preferably produced according to
the invention completely from standard-EVA wherein the support element is only
connected to the midsole by the application of pressure and heat.</p>
    <p num="0025">After the manufacture of the midsole with support element according to the
invention, the outsole, the inner sole and the upper is connected by conventional
methods so that the shoe according to the invention is provided.</p>
    <p num="0026">The above described manufacturing process has substantial advantages with
respect to known methods. On the one hand, it is not necessary to connect the
support element with the midsole by means of adhesive. In this manner, a
previous shaping of the midsole having an exact fit to the support element is no
longer necessary. Furthermore, it is prevented that the midsole and the support
element are wrongly positioned with respect to each other during cementing them
together. Additionally, renouncing the use of adhesive leads to a reduced impact
on the environment which is of increasing importance today. The use of adhesive
also results in a loss of flexibility in the resulting sole due to the curing of the
adhesive. This disadvantage is overcome by the present invention. Additionally it
should be noted that the possibility of an exact fit of the support element to the
midsole naturally follows from the method according to the invention. Moreover,
several procedural steps are no longer necessary to position the support element
on the midsole and to apply the adhesive. Further, only one mold is necessary for
this process in which the midsole is at the same time shaped and connected to the
support element. The manufacture of the sole element and the whole shoe
according to the invention is, thus, less expensive and requires less time as a result
of the reduced number of procedural steps while, at the same time, it can be
executed more easily and is more environmentally friendly compared to known
methods. A further cost reduction is also achieved by the use of a standard-EVA
material for the support element since the materials traditionally used until now to
manufacture support elements are comparably more expensive as for example
TPU or Pebax®. </p>
    <p num="0027">Besides the advantages of the process, a substantial advantage also results with
respect to the comfort of the shoe according to the invention. As a result of using
standard-EVA for the manufacture of the preforms of the midsole and the support
element, the mechanical properties of the midsole and the support element can be
adjusted as desired. In contrast thereto, even the support elements made of
Pebax® or TPU were not variable in their mechanical properties and in addition
were stiff and inflexible. Especially with respect to children's shoes, this fact is of
great importance since a lower force is available to deform the sole due to the
lower weight of children. Thus, it is advantageous in this case to produce a sole
with a high degree of flexibility resulting from a suitable material adjustment.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A method for the manufacture of a sole element, particularly for athletic
shoes, comprising the following steps:
<claim-text><claim-text>a. manufacture of a sole preform and a preform of a support element wherein
said sole preform and said preform of the support element are made from
the same polymer base having different mechanical properties and do not
comprise any connecting means;</claim-text><claim-text>b. positioning of the sole preform and the preform of the support element in a
mold; and</claim-text><claim-text>c. connecting of said sole preform with said preform of said support element
under application of heat and pressure without adding connecting means.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>Method according to claim 1, wherein said sole preform and said preform of
the support element are made of standard-EVA.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>Method according to claim 2, wherein said preform of the support element
comprises a vinyl acetate content of 18 to 25% and peroxides.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>Method according to claim 2, wherein the sole preform comprises a vinyl
acetate content of 18 to 27%, fillers, peroxides and co-agents like acrylate and
isocyanate.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>Method according to claim 4, wherein the sole preform comprises a blowing
agent for foaming said sole preform in a mold.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A sole element, particularly for athletic shoes, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a. a sole with at least one support element, wherein</claim-text><claim-text>b. the sole and the support element are made from the same polymer base
having different mechanical properties and being connected to each other
without connecting means.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>Sole element according to claim 6, wherein the sole and the support element
are made of standard-EVA.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>Sole element according to claim 7, wherein said sole comprises a vinyl acetate
content of 18 to 27%, fillers, peroxides, and co-agents like acrylate and
isocyanate.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>Sole element according to claim 7, wherein the support element comprises a
vinyl acetate content of 18 to 25% and peroxides.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>Sole element according to claim 6, wherein said support element comprises a
hardness of Shore A 80 to 85.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>Sole element according to claim 6, wherein the support element comprises a
hardness of Shore D.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>A shoe, particularly an athletic shoe, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a. an outsole, an inner sole and an upper;</claim-text><claim-text>b. a midsole with at least one support element wherein said midsole and said
support element are made from the same polymer base having different
mechanical properties and being connected to each other without
connecting means.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>Shoe according to claim 12, wherein said midsole and said support element
are made of standard-EVA.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>Shoe according to claim 13, wherein said midsole comprises a vinyl acetate
content of 18 to 27%, fillers, co-agents like acrylate and isocyanate, and
peroxides.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>Shoe according to claim 13, wherein the support element comprise a vinyl
acetate content of 18 to 25% and peroxides.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>Shoe according to claim 15, wherein said support element comprises a
hardness of Shore A 80 to 95.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>Shoe according to claim 15, wherein said support element comprises a
hardness of Shore D.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
