<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1241235-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1241235" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="26611139" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020918">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1241235-A2" status="new" fvid="23570173">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1241235</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20020918</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02290626-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02290626</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020312</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001070198-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001070198</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010313</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001070199-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001070199</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010313</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C09D   5/44        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C09D   5/44        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C25D  13/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C25D  13/04        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C25D  13/20        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C25D  13/20        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D   5/44D4B4B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">C25D  13/04</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">C25D  13/20</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur kationischen Elektrotauchlackierungsbeschichtung und danach erhaltener beschichteter Gegenstand</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Method of cationic electrodeposition coating and coated article obtained thereby</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé d'électrodéposition cationique et article ainsi obtenu</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NIPPON PAINT CO LTD</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NIPPON PAINT CO., LTD.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Nippon Paint Co., Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1-2 Ohyodokita 2-chome, Kita-ku</street>
              <city>Osaka-shi, Osaka 531-8511</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KAWAKAMI ICHIRO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KAWANAMI TOSHITAKA</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SAKAMOTO HIROYUKI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TANAKA HIDENORI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KAWAKAMI, ICHIRO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KAWANAMI, TOSHITAKA</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SAKAMOTO, HIROYUKI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TANAKA, HIDENORI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>KAWAKAMI, ICHIRO</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>10-5-109, Kamihamuro 1-chome</street>
              <city>Takatsuki-shi, Osaka 569-1044</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>KAWANAMI, TOSHITAKA</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1-12-G608, Matsuodai 2-chome, Iganawacho</street>
              <city>Kawabe-gun, Hyogo 666-0261</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>SAKAMOTO, HIROYUKI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>11-501-608, Koyochonaka 5-chome, Higashinada-ku</street>
              <city>Kobe-shi, Hyogo 658-0032</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>TANAKA, HIDENORI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>16-19-402, Minamimukonoso 7-chome</street>
              <city>Amagasaki-shi, Hyogo 661-0033</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Hubert, Philippe</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Cabinet Beau de Loménie 158, rue de l'Université</street>
              <city>75340 Paris Cédex 07</city>
              <country>FR</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>NL</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>It is an object of the present invention to provide a
cationic electrocoating method capable of producing a
coating film with high filiform-rust resistance, corrosion
resistance, and rust prevention and a coated article
obtainable by the method.</p>
    <p>A cationic electrocoating method comprising
electrocoating a surface of an aluminum substrate with a
cationic electrodeposition coating composition,

   wherein said aluminum substrate is subjected to a
chemical conversion with a surface treating reagent not
containing a heavy metal, and

   wherein said cationic electrodeposition coating
composition contains a sulfonium- and propargyl-containing
resin composition.</p>
    <p>A cationic electrocoating method comprising
electrocoating a surface of an aluminum substrate with a
cationic electrodeposition coating composition,

   wherein said aluminum substrate is not subjected to a
chemical conversion with a surface treating reagent, and

   wherein said cationic electrodeposition coating
composition contains a sulfonium- and propargyl-containing
resin composition.</p>
    <p>A coated article obtainable by the above cationic
electrocoating method.</p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a cationic
electrocoating method and a coated article obtainable
thereby and more particularly to a cationic electrocoating
method of an aluminum substrate and a coated article
obtainable by the method.</p>
    <heading>BACKGROUND ART</heading>
    <p num="0002">Aluminum substrates, such as aluminum and aluminum
alloys, are lightweight, easy to process, and good in
corrosion resistance and rust prevention so that these are
processed into various shapes such as plate, foil, bar and
rod and used in a large variety of applications ranging
from comparatively small articles, such as home utensils
and sundry goods, to large articles, such as lumbers, sails,
automotive bodies and parts, and so forth.</p>
    <p num="0003">For capacitating additional corrosion resistance and
rust prevention to such an aluminum substrate, the
substrate is subjected to cationic electrocoating to form a
cationic electrodeposited coating film on its surface.
This cationic electrocoating method generally comprises
cleaning the aluminum substrate by degreasing in the first
place, then forming a chemical conversion coat on the
surface using a surface treating reagent, and thereafter
proceeding a cationic electrocoating to build up a
multilayer electrodeposited coating film on the chemical
conversion film. By forming a multilayer film composed of
a conversion film and an electrodeposited coating film on
the surface of an aluminum substrate in this manner,
excellent corrosion resistance and rust prevention can be 
obtained.</p>
    <p num="0004">However, the surface treating reagent is a material
containing a heavy metal, such as chromium ion, and the use
thereof is restricted of late because of the risk for
environmental pollution. Therefore, the method using a
chromium ion-free surface treating reagent and the method
comprising applying an electrocoating directly to the
degreased aluminum substrate surface omitting such a
surface treatment have been tried recently.</p>
    <p num="0005">However, the aluminum substrate obtained by cationic
electrocoating using a chromium ion-free surface treating
reagent is, in fact, excellent in corrosion resistance but
has the problem of poor filiform-rust resistance and,
therefore, the technology has not been commercially
applicable.</p>
    <p num="0006">Moreover, if electrodeposition coating is carried out
without prior surface treating, the poor adhesion between
the aluminum substrate and the electrodeposited coating
film results in the problem of poor filiform-rust
resistance and low corrosion resistance, so that the method
has not been commercially applicable.</p>
    <heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0007">It is an object of the present invention to provide a
cationic electrocoating method capable of producing a
coating film with high filiform-rust resistance, corrosion
resistance, and rust prevention and a coated article
obtainable by the method.</p>
    <p num="0008">The first aspect of the present invention relates to
a cationic electrocoating method comprising electrocoating
a surface of an aluminum substrate with a cationic
electrodeposition coating composition,

   wherein said aluminum substrate is subjected to a
chemical conversion with a surface treating reagent not
containing a heavy metal, and
 
   wherein said cationic electrodeposition coating
composition contains a sulfonium- and propargyl-containing
resin composition. Preferably, said heavy metal is chromium.</p>
    <p num="0009">The second aspect of the present invention relates to
a cationic electrocoating method comprising electrocoating
a surface of an aluminum substrate with a cationic
electrodeposition coating composition,

   wherein said aluminum substrate is not subjected to a
chemical conversion with a surface treating reagent, and

   wherein said cationic electrodeposition coating
composition contains a sulfonium- and propargyl-containing
resin composition.</p>
    <p num="0010">Preferably, the surface of the aluminum substrate is
degreased.</p>
    <p num="0011">It is preferred that the cationic electrodeposition
coating composition contains 5 to 400 mmol of the sulfonium
group and 10 to 495 mmol of the propargyl group per 100 g
solids of the resin composition and the total content of
the sulfonium and propargyl groups is not more than 500
mmol per 100 g solids. It is more preferred that the
cationic electrodeposition coating composition contains 5
to 250 mmol of the sulfonium group and 20 to 395 mmol of
the propargyl group per 100 g solids of the resin
composition and the total content of the sulfonium and
propargyl groups is not more than 400 mmol per 100 g solids.</p>
    <p num="0012">Furthermore, the resin composition preferably
comprises an epoxy resin as a skeleton. The epoxy resin is
more preferably a novolac cresol epoxy resin or a novolac
phenol epoxy resin and has a number average molecular
weight of 700 to 5000.</p>
    <p num="0013">The present invention also relates to a coated
article obtainable by the above cationic electrocoating
methods.</p>
    <heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0014">The cationic electrocoating method according to the
first aspect of the present invention is the cationic
electrocoating method comprising electrocoating a surface
of an aluminum substrate with a cationic electrodeposition
coating composition, wherein said aluminum substrate is
subjected to a chemical conversion with a surface treating
reagent not containing a heavy metal, and wherein said
cationic electrodeposition coating composition contains a
sulfonium- and propargyl-containing resin composition.</p>
    <p num="0015">The aluminum substrate for use in the cationic
electrocoating method according to the first aspect of the
present invention, is not particularly restricted, but
includes alloys for expanding and alloys for casting, for
example. The alloys for expanding and alloys for casting
can respectively be roughly divided into non-heat-treated
alloys and heat-treated alloys, and as said non-heat-treated
alloys, there can specifically be mentioned pure
aluminum, aluminum-manganese alloy, aluminum-silicon alloy,
aluminum-magnesium alloy, etc., and as said heat-treated
alloys, there can specifically be mentioned aluminum-copper
alloy, aluminum-magnesium-silicon alloy, and aluminum-zinc-magnesium
alloy, etc.</p>
    <p num="0016">For use in the cationic electrocoating method
according to the first aspect of the present invention, the
heavy metal which is not contained in said surface treating
reagent may specifically be chrominum and as a specific
example of the surface treating reagent containing chromium,
there can be mentioned a reagent comprising a chromium
chromate composed of a mixture of chromium ions such as
hexavalent chromium ion (Cr<sup>6+</sup>), available on reduction of
chromium trioxide, and trivalent chromium ion (Cr<sup>3+</sup>).</p>
    <p num="0017">The above surface treating reagent not containing the
heavy metal is not particularly restricted, but
specifically includes surface treating reagents of the
phosphate, oxide film, and so forth. As examples of the 
phosphate surface treating reagent, there can be mentioned
a zinc phosphate surface treating reagent and an iron
phosphate surface treating reagent. The method for forming
a conversion coat on a substrate using said zinc phosphate
surface treating reagent is not particularly restricted,
but may for example comprise dipping the substrate in said
treating reagent at 20 to 40°C. The concentration of the
zinc phosphate surface treating reagent and the immersion
time can be suitably selected according to the desired coat
weight. Moreover, for leveling the substrate surface, the
treatment with said zinc phosphate surface treating reagent
is preferably preceded by a pre-conversion treatment using
a surface conditioner to homogenize the substrate surface
in terms of electric resistance value.</p>
    <p num="0018">As the oxide film surface treating reagent mentioned
above, there can be mentioned a zirconium oxide surface
treating reagent, a titanium oxide surface treating reagent,
and a vanadium oxide surface treating reagent, among others.
Furthermore, the surface of the aluminum substrate may be
subjected to almite/boehmite treatment by such a technique
as anodic oxidation.</p>
    <p num="0019">The method of forming a conversion coat with said
oxide film surface treating reagent is almost the same as
the above method using said zinc phosphate surface treating
reagent. Furthermore, from the viewpoint of leveling the
substrate surface, the treatment with said oxide film
surface treating reagent is preferably preceded by an
etching operation for the substrate surface with an acid
solution.</p>
    <p num="0020">Said process for forming the conversion coat may be a
one-step process using only one kind of said surface
treating reagent or comprise two or more steps using two or
more kinds of said surface treating reagents.</p>
    <p num="0021">A cationic electrocoating method according to the
second aspect of the present invention is a cationic 
electrocoating method comprising electrocoating a surface
of an aluminum substrate with a cationic electrodeposition
coating composition, wherein said aluminum substrate is not
subjected to a chemical conversion with a surface treating
reagent, and wherein said cationic electrodeposition
coating composition contains a sulfonium- and propargyl-containing
resin composition.</p>
    <p num="0022">The aluminum substrate for use in the cationic
electrocoating method according to the second aspect of the
present invention is not particularly restricted, but
includes the same substrates as mentioned for the first
aspect of the invention, for instance.</p>
    <p num="0023">In the cationic electrocoating method according to
the second aspect of the present invention, the surface of
said aluminum substrate is not subjected to a chemical
conversion with a surface treating reagent.</p>
    <p num="0024">Moreover, in the cationic electrocoating method
according to the invention, the surface of said aluminum
substrate may be degreased or not degreased but is
preferably degreased from the viewpoint of washing the
substrate surface and leveling of the surface condition.
This degreasing can be made with an aqueous alkali solution,
for instance.</p>
    <p num="0025">Moreover, the surface of the aluminum substrate may
be etched to remove the aluminum oxide and other oxide
films intimately formed thereon.</p>
    <p num="0026">The cationic electrodeposition coating composition
for use in the cationic electrocoating method of the
invention contains a sulfonium- and propargyl-containing
resin composition. The component resins of such resin
composition may have both a sulfonium group and a propargyl
group per molecule but this is not absolutely necessary.
Thus, for example, the component resins may have only
sulfonium groups or only propargyl groups per molecule. In
the latter case, however, the whole resin composition 
should have both of these two kinds of curable functional
groups. Thus, said resin composition may comprise any of a
sulfonium- and propergyl-containing resin, a mixture of a
resin having only sulfonium groups and a resin having only
propargyl groups, and a mixture of all of said kinds of
resins. It is herein defined in the above sense that the
resin composition contained in the cationic
electrodeposition coating composition for use in the
invention has both sulfonium and propargyl groups.</p>
    <p num="0027">The sulfonium groups mentioned above are hydratable
functional groups of said resin composition. When an
electric voltage or current beyond a certain level is
applied for electrocoating, the sulfonium group is
electrically reduced on the electrode to lose its ionicity
and the resin is irreversibly rendered nonconductive. It
is probably for this reason that the cationic
electrodeposition coating composition for use in the
invention may exhibit a high degree of throwing power.</p>
    <p num="0028">Moreover, it is conjectured that, in this
electrocoating process, the electrode reaction is induced,
and the resulting hydroxide ion is captured by the
sulfonium group, whereby the electrolytically generated
base is formed in the electrodeposited coat.</p>
    <p num="0029">The sulfonium content of the resin composition in the
cationic electrodeposition coating composition according to
the invention is 5 to 400 mmol per 100 g solids of said
resin composition provided that the condition to be
described hereunder for the combined sulfonium and
propargyl content is satisfied. If the sulfonium content
is less than 5 mmol/100 g, neither sufficient throwing
power nor sufficient curability will be expressed and, in
addition, the hydratability and bath stability will also be
deteriorated. If the level of 400 mmol/100 g is exceeded,
the deposition of the coat on the substrate surface will be
deteriorated. As to the sulfonium content referred to 
above, a preferred content can be set according to the
resin skeleton to be used. For example, in the case of a
novolac phenol epoxy resin or a novolac cresol epoxy resin,
the sulfonium content is preferably 5 to 250 mmol, more
preferably 10 to 150 mmol, per 100 g solids of the resin
composition.</p>
    <p num="0030">It is also considered that the propargyl group which
shows low reactivity upon heating is comparatively low in
the electrodeposited coat can be transformed to an allene
bond which shows high reactivity upon heating.</p>
    <p num="0031">The propargyl groups of the resin composition in said
cationic electrodeposition coating composition are
transformed to allene bonds by the electrolytically
generated base in the electrocoating process, whereby the
reactivity is increased. In this manner, a curing system
is established in the cationic electrodeposition coating
composition of the invention. Moreover, though the reason
remains to be unknown, the concurrent existence of
propargyl and sulfonium groups results in a further
improvement in the throwing power of the cationic
electrodeposition coating composition.</p>
    <p num="0032">The propargyl content of the resin composition in
said cationic electrodeposition coating composition is 10
to 495 mmol per 100 g solids of said resin composition
provided that the condition to be described hereunder for
the combined sulfonium and propargyl content is satisfied.
If the propargyl content is less than 10 mmol/100 g,
neither sufficient throwing power nor sufficient curability
will be expressed. If the content exceeds 495 mmol/100 g,
when the resin is used as the cationic electrodeposition
coating, the hydration stability will be adversely affected.
As to the propargyl content referred to above, a preferred
content can be set according to the resin skeleton to be
used. For example, in the case of a novolac phenol epoxy
resin or a novolac cresol epoxy resin, the propargyl 
content is preferably 20 to 395 mmol per 100 g solids of
the resin composition.</p>
    <p num="0033">The resin to serve as the skeleton of the resin
composition in said cationic electrodeposition coating
composition is not particularly restricted, but an epoxy
resin can be used suitably. The preferred epoxy resin is
one having at least two epoxy groups per molecule and
includes such polyepoxy resins as epi-bis-epoxy resin and
as derived by chain extension with a diol, a dicarboxylic
acid, a diamine, or the like; epoxidized polybutadiene;
novolac phenol polyepoxy resin; novolac cresol polyepoxy
resin; polyglycidyl acrylate; polyglycidyl ethers of
aliphatic polyols or polyether polyols; polyglycidyl esters
of polybasic carboxylic acids; and so forth. Among these,
in view of the ease of polyfunctionalization for enhanced
curability, novolac phenol polyepoxy resin, novolac cresol
polyepoxy resin, and polyglycidyl acrylate are preferred.
Furthermore, a portion of said epoxy resin may be a
monoepoxy resin.</p>
    <p num="0034">The resin composition contained in said cationic
electrodeposition coating composition comprises a resin
having said epoxy resin as a skeleton and has a number
average molecular weight of 500 to 20000. If the number
average molecular weight is less than 500, the coating
efficiency in cationic electrocoating is decreased. On the
other hand, if it exceeds 20000, it will be impossible to
form a satisfactory coat on the substrate surface. It is
possible to select a preferred number average molecular
weight according to the resin skeleton. For example, in the
case of a novolac phenol epoxy resin or a novolac cresol
epoxy resin, the preferred number average molecular weight
is 700 to 5000.</p>
    <p num="0035">The total content of sulfonium and propargyl groups
in said resin composition is not more than 500 mmol per 100
g solids of the resin composition. If the total content 
exceeds 500 mmol, there may be cases in which the objective
resin cannot be practically obtained or the desired
performance characteristics are not obtained. As to said
total content of sulfonium and propargyl groups in the
resin composition, it is possible to select a preferred
content according to the resin skeleton to be used. For
example, in the case of a novolac phenol epoxy resin or a
novolac cresol epoxy resin, the total content is preferably
not more than 400 mmol/100 g.</p>
    <p num="0036">Some of the propargyl groups of the resin composition
in said cationic electrodeposition coating composition may
be converted to acetylides. The acetylide is an acetylene
bond-containing metal compound resembling a salt. When
some of the propargyl groups of said resin composition are
converted to acetylides, said propargyl content is
preferably 0.1 to 40 mmol per 100 g solids of the resin
composition. If it is less than 0.1 mmol, the effect of
conversion to acetylides will not be fully expressed. If
it exceeds 40 mmol, the conversion to acetylides will be
difficult. The content can be suitably selected from a
certain preferred range according to the metal species to
be used.</p>
    <p num="0037">When some of said propargyl groups are converted to
acetylides, the species of metal, which contained in the
propargyl groups converted to acetylides, is not
particularly restricted only provided that it is a metal
exhibiting catalyst activity. Thus, for example,
transition metals such as copper, silver and barium can be
mentioned. Among these, copper and silver are preferred
from the viewpoint of applicability to the environment and
copper is more preferred from the viewpoint of availability.
When the propargyl group is to be converted to an acetylide
with copper, the propargyl content to be converted to the
acetylide in said resin composition is more preferably 0.1
to 20 mmol per 100 g solids of the resin composition. </p>
    <p num="0038">Through this conversion of some of the propargyl
groups of the resin composition in said cationic
electrodeposition coating composition to acetylides, a
curing catalyst can be introduced into the resin. When
this is done, an organic transition metal complex, which is
generally not readily soluble or dispersible in organic
solvents and water, need not be added directly to the
coating. Thus, a transition metal can be easily introduced
after a conversion to acetylides and, therefore, any
transition metal compound which is difficult to be
dissolved can be used for the coating composition.
Furthermore, like the case in which a transition metal salt
of an organic acid is employed, the presence of such an
organic acid salt as an anion in the electrodeposition bath
can be avoided and, moreover, the metal ion is not removed
by ultrafiltration, with the result that both bath control
and design of a cationic electrodeponsition coating are
facilitated.</p>
    <p num="0039">In the resin composition for use in said cationic
electrodeposition coating composition, C-C double bonds may
optionally be contained. The above C-C double bond is so
highly reactive that a curability can further be improved.</p>
    <p num="0040">The C-C double bond content is preferably 10 to 485
mmol per 100 g solids of the resin composition provided
that the condition to be described hereunder for the
combined total propargyl and C-C double bond content is
satisfied. If the C-C double bond content is less than 10
mmol/100 g, no sufficient curability will be expressed. If
it exceeds 485 mmol/100 g, the hydration stability of a
cationic electrodeposition coating comprising the
composition will be adversely affected. As to the C-C
double bond content referred to above, a preferred content
can be set according to the resin skeleton to be used. For
example, in the case of a novolac phenol epoxy resin or a
novolac cresol epoxy resin, the preferred content is 20 to 
375 mmol per 100 g solids of the resin composition.</p>
    <p num="0041">In the case where the resin composition contains said
C-C double bond, the combined total propargyl and C-C
double bond content is preferably within the range of 80 to
450 mmol per 100 g solids of the resin composition. If the
total content is less than 80 mmol, curability may tend to
be insufficient. If it exceeds 450 mmol, the sulfonium
content will be too low to insure adequate throwing power.
As to the combined total propargyl and C-C double bond
content, a preferred content can be set according to the
resin skeleton to be used. For example, in the case of a
novolac phenol epoxy resin or a novolac cresol epoxy resin,
the more preferred range for said combined total content is
100 to 395 mmol.</p>
    <p num="0042">Furthermore, when the resin composition contains said
C-C double bonds, the combined total content of sulfonium
group, propargyl group, and C-C double bond is preferably
not more than 500 mmol per 100 g solids of the resin
composition. If this total content exceeds 500 mmol/100 g,
the resin may not be actually obtained or the objective
performance characteristics may not be obtained. As to the
combined total content of sulfonium group, propargyl group,
and C-C double bond, a preferred content can be set
according to the resin skeleton to be used. For example, in
the case of a novolac phenol epoxy resin or a novolac
cresol epoxy resin, it is more preferably not more than 400
mmol/100 g.</p>
    <p num="0043">The resin composition to be contained in said
cationic electrodeposition coating composition can be
suitably produced by, for example, the process which
comprises (i) a step of reacting an epoxy resin having at
least two epoxy groups per molecule with a compound having
both a functional group reactive with the epoxy group and a
propargyl group to give a propargyl-containing epoxy resin
composition and (ii) a step of reacting a sulfide/acid 
mixture with the residual epoxy group in the propargyl-containing
epoxy resin composition obtained in step (i) to
introduce a sulfonium group.</p>
    <p num="0044">The above-mentioned compound having both a functional
group reactive with the epoxy group and a propargyl group
(hereinafter referred to as "compound (A)") is a compound
having both a functional group reactive with the epoxy
group such as a hydroxyl group or a carboxyl group, and a
propargyl group for instance, and as specific examples,
propargyl alcohol and propargylic acid can be mentioned.
From the viewpoint of availability and simple reaction,
propargyl alcohol is preferred.</p>
    <p num="0045">When C-C double bonds are to be introduced, if
necessary, into the resin composition of said cationic
electrodeposition coating composition, a compound having
both a functional group reactive with the epoxy group and a
C-C double bond (hereinafter referred to as "compound (B)")
is used in conjunction with said compound (A) in the above
step (i). The compound (B) mentioned above may be a
compound having both a functional group reactive with the
epoxy group such as a hydroxyl group or a carboxyl group
and a C-C double bond for instance. Specifically, in the
case where the functional group reactive with the epoxy
group is a hydroxyl group, there can be mentioned such
compounds as 2-hydroxyethyl acrylate, 2-hydroxyethyl
methacrylate, hydroxypropyl acrylate, hydroxypropyl
methacrylate, hydroxybutyl acrylate, hydroxybutyl
methacrylate, allyl alchohol, and methacryl alcohol, among
others. In the case where the functional group reactive
with the epoxy group is a carboxyl group, there can be
mentioned acrylic acid, methacrylic acid, ethacrylic acid,
crotonic acid, maleic acid, phthalic acid, itaconic acid;
ethyl maleate, ethyl fumarate, ethyl itaconate, and half-esters
such as mono(meth)acryloyloxyethyl succinate,
mono(meth)acryloxyoxyethyl phthalate, etc.; synthetic 
unsaturated fatty acids such as oleic acid, linoleic acid,
ricinolic acid, etc.; and naturally-occurring unsaturated
fatty acids such as linseed oil, soybean oil and so on.</p>
    <p num="0046">In the above step (i), said epoxy resin having at
least two epoxy groups per molecule is reacted with said
compound (A) to give a propargyl-containing epoxy resin
composition or with said compound (A) and, if necessary,
compound (B) to give a propargyl- and C-C double bond-containing
epoxy resin composition. In the latter case, in
the step (i), said compound (A) and compound (B) may first
be mixed and then submitted to the reaction or said
compound (A) and compound (B) may be independently
submitted to the reaction. A functional group reactive
with the epoxy group in said compound (A) and a functional
group reactive with the epoxy group in said compound (B)
may be the same or different.</p>
    <p num="0047">The formulating ratio of said compound (A) and
compound (B) to be reacted in the above step (i) can be
selected so that the desired contents of functional groups,
said propargyl and C-C double bond content as an example,
may be introduced.</p>
    <p num="0048">The reaction conditions to be employed in the above
step (i) may usually be room temperature or 80 to 140°C and
several hours. If necessary, the known reaction-promoting
agents such as a catalyst and a solvent can be used. The
end-point of reaction can be confirmed by determining the
epoxy equivalent, and the introduced functional groups can
be identified by analysis of the nonvolatile fraction or
instrumental analysis of the resulting resin composition.
The reaction product obtainable in the above manner is
generally either a mixture of epoxy resins having one or a
plurality of propargyl groups or a mixture of epoxy resins
having one or a plurality of both propargyl groups and C-C
double bonds. In this sense, a propargyl-containing resin
composition or a propargyl- and C-C double bond-containing 
epoxy resin composition is obtained in the above step (i).</p>
    <p num="0049">In step (ii), the residual epoxy groups in the
propargyl-containing epoxy resin composition obtained in
step (i) are caused to react with a sulfide/acid mixture
for introduction of sulfonium groups. This introduction of
sulfonium groups can be effected by the method which
comprises causing the sulfide/acid mixture to react with
the epoxy group to effect introduction of the sulfide and
conversion thereof to the sulfonium group or the method
which comprises introducing a sulfide and then converting
the introduced sulfide to a sulfonium group with an acid,
an alkyl halide, such as methyl fluoride, methyl chloride
or methyl bromide, or the like reagent, if necessary,
followed by anion exchange. In view of the availability of
the reactant, the method using a sulfide/acid mixture is
preferred.</p>
    <p num="0050">The sulfide mentioned above is not particularly
restricted, but includes aliphatic sulfides, mixed
aliphatic-aromatic sulfides, aralkyl sulfides, and cyclic
sulfides. Specifically, there can be mentioned diethyl
sulfide, dipropyl sulfide, dibutyl sulfide, dihexyl sulfide,
diphenyl sulfide, ethyl phenyl sulfide, tetramethylene
sulfide, pentamethylene sulfide, thiodiethanol,
thiodipropanol, thiodibutanol, 1-(2-hydroxyethylthio)-2-propanol,
1-(2-hydroxyethylthio)-2-butanol, and 1-(2-hydroxyethylthio)-3-butoxy-1-propanol,
among others.</p>
    <p num="0051">The acid mentioned above is not particularly
restricted, but includes formic acid, acetic acied, lactic
acid, propionic acid, boric acid, butyric acid,
dimethylolpropionic acid, hydrochloric acid, sulfuric acid,
phosphoric acid, N-acetylglycine, N-acetyl-β-alanine, and
so forth.</p>
    <p num="0052">The preferred mixing ratio of the above sulfide and
the above acid in said sulfide/acid mixture is generally
about (sulfide/acid) = 100/60 to 100/100 on a molar basis. </p>
    <p num="0053">The reaction in said step (ii) can be carried out by
mixing the propargyl-containing epoxy resin composition
obtained in said step (i) and a calculated amount of, for
example, said sulfide/acid mixture required to insure said
sulfonium content with 5 to 10 molar equivalents of water
based on the sulfide used and stirring the mixture usually
at 50 to 90°C for several hours. The end-point of reaction
can be confirmed by a residual acid value as a guideline
being not more than 5. The introduction of sulfonium group
to the resulting resin composition can be confirmed by
potentiometric titration. The same procedure can be used
also in the case where the sulfide is first introduced and
then converted to the sulfonium group. In this connection,
by carrying out introduction of the sulfonium group after
introduction of the propargyl group, the decomposition of
the sulfonium group on heating can be prevented.</p>
    <p num="0054">In the case where some of the propargyl groups of the
resin composition in said cationic electrodeposition
coating composition are converted to acetylides, the
propargyl-containing epoxy resin composition obtained in
said step (i) is reacted with a metal compound to convert
some of the propargyl groups of said epoxy resin
composition to acetylides. The metal compound mentioned
above is preferably a transition metal compound capable of
forming an acetylide and, for example, includes complexes
or salts of transition metals such as copper, silver and
barium. Specifically, acetylacetonato-copper, copper
acetate, acetylacetonato-silver, silver acetate, silver
nitrate, acetylacetonato-barium, barium acetate, etc. can
be mentioned. Among these, compounds of copper or silver
are preferred from environmental points of view and
compounds of copper are more preferred from availability
points of view. For example, acetylacetonato-copper is
advantageous in terms of the ease of bath control.</p>
    <p num="0055">The conditions of said reaction for conversion of 
some of the propargyl groups to acetylides are usually 40
to 70°C and several hours. Progress of the reaction can be
confirmed from coloration of the product resin composition
and disappearance of the methine proton on the nuclear
magnetic resonance spectrum, for instance. By confirming
the point of time by which the desired proportion of the
propargyl groups of the resin composition has been
converted to acetylides, the reaction is then terminated.
The reaction product thus obtained is generally a mixture
of epoxy resins in which one or a plurality of propargyl
groups have been converted to acetylides. Using the epoxy
resin composition obtained in this manner in which some of
the propargyl groups have been converted to acetylides,
sulfonium groups can be introduced in said step (ii).</p>
    <p num="0056">The step for conversion of some of the propargyl
groups of the epoxy resin composition to acetylides and the
step (ii) described above can be equated in reaction
conditions and, therefore, the two steps can be carried out
concurrently. This mode of carrying out the two steps
concurrently is advantageous in that the production process
can be simplified.</p>
    <p num="0057">In this manner, a resin composition containing the
propargyl and sulfonium groups, if necessary, as well as C-C
double bond and/or acetylides derived from some of the
propargyl groups, can be produced while decomposition of
the sulfonium groups is prevented. Although an acetylide is
explosive in dry state, the production method according to
the invention is conducted in an aqueous medium and gives
the objective product as a water-soluble composition, thus
preventing the risk.</p>
    <p num="0058">The cationic electrodeposition coating composition of
the invention contains said resin composition. Since this
resin composition is curable by itself, the cationic
electrodeposition coating composition of the invention does
not necessarily require the use of a curing agent. However, 
a curing agent may be used for further improved curability.
As such curing agents, there can be mentioned compounds
having a plurality of groups of at least one kind selected
from propargyl and C-C double bond, for example those
compounds obtainable by the addition reaction between a
propargyl-containing compound, such as propargyl alcohol,
or a C-C double bond-containing compound, such as acrylic
acid, and a polyepoxide of e.g. novolac phenol,
pentaerythritol tetraglycidyl ether, or the like.</p>
    <p num="0059">The above cationic electrodeposition coating
composition does not necessarily require a curing catalyst.
However, when a further improvement in curability is
required depending on conditions of the curing reaction, a
routine transition metal compound and so on may be
optionally added, if necessary. Such compounds are not
particularly restricted, but those compounds which are
obtainable by using a transition metal, such as nickel,
cobalt, manganese, palladium or rhodium, in combination
with a ligand compound, such as cyclopentadiene or
acetylacetone, or a carboxylic acid, such as acetic acid,
or the like, can be mentioned. The formulating amount of
said curing catalyst is preferably 0.1 to 20 mmol per 100 g
solids of the cationic electrodeposition coating
composition.</p>
    <p num="0060">An amine can be incorporated in said cationic
electrodeposition coating composition. Incorporation of
the amine results in an increased conversion of sulfonium
to sulfide by electrolytic reduction in the
electrodeposition process. The amine mentioned above is
not particularly restricted, but includes amine compounds
such as primary through tertiary monofunctional and
polyfunctional aliphatic amines, alicyclic amines, and
aromatic amines, among others. The preferred, among these,
are water-soluble or water-dispersible amines, for example,
alkylamines containing 2 to 8 carbon atoms, such as 
monomethylamine, dimethylamine, trimethyamine,
triethylamine, propylamine, diisopropylamine, tributylamine,
etc.; monoethanolamine, dimethanolamine, methylethanolamine,
dimethylethanolamine, cyclohexylamine, morpholine, N-methylmorpholine,
pyridine, pyrazine, piperidine,
imidazoline, imidazole, and so forth. These may be used
each independently or in a combination of two or more
species. Because of the goodness in dispersion stability
in water, hydroxylamines such as monoethanolamine,
diethanolamine and dimethylethanolamine are preferred.</p>
    <p num="0061">The above amine may be directly incorporated in said
cationic electrodeposition coating composition. In the
conventional neutralized amine type cationic
electrodeposition coatings, addition of a free amine
deprives the resin of the neutralizing acid to considerably
deteriorate the stability of the electrodeposition bath but
such an inhibition on bath stability is not induced in the
present invention.</p>
    <p num="0062">The preferred formulating amount of said amine is 0.3
to 25 meq per 100 g solids of the cationic
electrodeposition coating composition. If it is less than
0.3 meq/100 g, there will be no sufficient contribution to
throwing power. Exceeding 25 meq/100 g will not be
rewarded with any additional effect but rather causes an
economic disadvantage. The more preferred formulating
amount is 1 to 15 meq/100 g.</p>
    <p num="0063">In the above cationic electrodeposition coating
composition, an aliphatic hydrocarbon-containing resin
composition may be incorporated. Incorporation of such an
aliphatic hydrocarbon-containing resin composition results
in an improved impact resistance of the coating film to be
obtained. The aliphatic hydrocarbon-containing resin
composition that can be used includes resin compositions
containing, based on 100 g solids of resin composition, 5
to 400 mmol of a sulfonium group, 80 to 135 mmol of a C<sub>8-24</sub> 
aliphatic hydrocarbon group optionally containing an
unsaturated double bond within the chain, and 10 to 315
mmol of at least one of a propargyl group and an
unsaturated double bond-terminated C<sub>3-7</sub> organic group, with
the combined total of the sulfonium group, C<sub>8-24</sub> aliphatic
hydrocarbon group optionally containing an unsaturated
double bond within the chain, unsaturated double bond-terminated
C<sub>3-7</sub> organic group and propargyl group being not
more than 500 mmol per 100 g solids of the resin
composition.</p>
    <p num="0064">In incorporating an aliphatic hydrocarbon-containing
resin composition in said cationic electrodeposition
coating composition, it is preferable to insure that, per
100 g solids of the cationic electrodeposition coating
composition, the amount of sulfonium group will be 5 to 400
mmol, that of the C<sub>8-24</sub> aliphatic hydrocarbon group
optionally containing an unsaturated double bond within the
chain will be 10 to 300 mmol, and that of the propargyl
group and unsaturated double bond-terminated C<sub>3-7</sub> organic
group combined will be 10 to 485 mmol, with the combined
total of the sulfonium group, C<sub>8-24</sub> aliphatic hydrocarbon
group optionally containing an unsaturated double bond
within the chain, the propargyl group, and the unsaturated
double bond-terminated C<sub>3-7</sub> organic group being not more
than 500 mmol per 100 g solids of the cationic
electrodeposition coating composition and the proportion of
said C<sub>8-24</sub> aliphatic hydrocarbon group optionally containing
an unsaturated double bond within the chain being 3 to 30
weight % of the resin solids in the cationic
electrodeposition coating composition.</p>
    <p num="0065">Referring to the above case in which an aliphatic
hydrocarbon-containing resin composition is formulated in
said cationic electrodeposition coating composition, if the
sulfonium content is less than 5 mmol/100 g, neither
sufficient throwing power nor sufficient curability will be 
obtained and, in addition, the hydratability and bath
stability will be adversely affected. If it exceeds 400
mmol/100 g, the deposition of the coating on the substrate
surface will be deteriorated. Furthermore, if the
proportion of the C<sub>8-24</sub> aliphatic hydrocarbon group
optionally containing an unsaturated double bond within the
chain is less than 80 mmol/100 g, no sufficient improvement
will be obtained in impact resistance. If it exceeds 350
mmol/100 g, the resin composition will not be easy to work
with. Furthermore, if the combined total amount of the
propargyl group and unsaturated double bond-terminated C<sub>3-7</sub>
organic group is less than 10 mmol/100 g, no sufficient
curability may be expected even when the composition is
used in combination with other resin or a curing agent. If
it exceeds 315 mmol/100 g, the impact resistance will not
be sufficiently enhanced. The combined total amount of the
sulfonium, C<sub>8-24</sub> aliphatic hydrocarbon group optionally
containing an unsaturated double bond within the chain,
propargyl, and unsaturated double bond-terminated C<sub>3-7</sub>
organic group is not more than 500 mmol per 100 g solids of
the resin composition. If the level of 500 mmol is
exceeded, the objective resin may not be actually obtained
or the desired performance characteristics may not be
expressed.</p>
    <p num="0066">If necessary, said cationic electrodeposition coating
composition may contain other ingredients which are
generally formulated in the conventional cationic
electrodeposition coatings. Said other ingredients are not
particularly restricted, but include the color pigment,
pigment dispersant resin, surfactant, antioxidant, UV
absorber, and like other coating additives.</p>
    <p num="0067">The color pigment mentioned above is not particularly
restricted, but includes color pigments such as titanium
dioxide, carbon black, red iron oxide, etc; and such
extender pigments as kaolin, clay, talc, etc., all of which 
are commonly formulated in cationic electrodeposition
coatings. When such a color pigment is formulated in the
cationic electrodeposition coating composition of the
invention, the combined total formulating amount of the
above color pigment and said rust inhibitor is preferably
not more than 50 weight % based on the solids of the
cationic electrodeposition coating composition. Regarding
the method of mixing said color pigment with said resin
composition, the method comprising dispersing said rust
inhibitor into a pigment dispersing resin in advance to
prepare a dispersion paste and mixing the paste with said
resin composition can be mentioned as an example.</p>
    <p num="0068">The cationic electrodeposition coating composition
can be obtained by mixing said resin composition with said
respective ingredients where necessary and dissolving or
dispersing the mixture in water. For cationic
electrocoating, the composition is preferably prepared as a
bath containing 10 to 30% of nonvolatile matter. It is
also preferably prepared so that the content of propargyl
groups, C-C double bond, and sulfonium groups in the
cationic electrodeposition coating composition will not
deviate from the above-defined ranges of the resin
composition.</p>
    <p num="0069">The curing temperature of said cationic
electrodeposition coating composition is preferably
controlled at 130 to 220°C. When the curing temperature is
lower than 130°C, the smoothness of the multilayer coating
film obtained by further coating on the coating film formed
from the cationic electrodeposition coating composition of
the invention tends to be deteriorated. If the curing
temperature is higher than 220°C, the poor curability of
said multilayer coating film results in deterioration of
coating film characteristics as well as the incidence of a
color difference in the multilayer coating film after
application of a top coating. </p>
    <p num="0070">The cationic electrocoating method of the present
invention comprises applying said cationic
electrodeposition coating composition to the surface of the
aluminum substrate described hereinbefore.</p>
    <p num="0071">The above application can be carried out by, for
example, the process in which said aluminum substrate as
the cathode is immersed in said cationic electrodeposition
coating composition and an electric voltage of, generally,
50 to 450 V is applied between the cathode and an anode.
If the application voltage is less than 50 V, the
electrodeposition will be insufficient. If it exceeds 450
V, the power consumption will be uneconomically too large.
By using said cationic electrodeposition coating
composition and applying an electric voltage at a level
within the above-mentioned range, a homogeneous coat can be
produced all over the substrate surface without a sharp
buildup in coat thickness in the course of
electrodeposition. The preferred bath temperature of said
cationic electrodeposition coating composition at voltage
application is usually 10 to 45°C. On the other hand, the
duration of voltage application may generally be 2 to 4
minutes, although it depends on other conditions of
electrodeposition.</p>
    <p num="0072">In the above electrodeposition process, the electric
resistance per unit volume of the above coat can be
increased by applying a voltage between said aluminum
substrate as the cathode and an anode and further applying
a voltage to thus-deposited coat.</p>
    <p num="0073">After completion of electrodeposition processs, the
resulting electrodeposited coat is baked, either as it is
or after cleaning with water, at a temperature of 120 to
260°C, preferably 160 to 220°C, for 10 to 30 minutes to
complete the coating procedure. There may also be employed
the two-coat, one-bake system in which thus-obtained
electrodeposited coat is not cured but an intermediate 
uncured coating film is formed directly thereon using an
intermediate coating to be described hereunder by so-called
wet-on-wet technique and the uncured coating films are
baked together in one step to give a multilayer coating
film.</p>
    <p num="0074">In the cationic electrocoating method according to
the invention, the film thickness of the electrodeposited
coating film after curing is preferably 10 to 25 µm. If it
is less than 10 µm, corrosion resistance and rust
prevention tend to be insufficient. The use of a film
thickness in excess of 25 µm will result in a waste of the
coating material and, hence, be uneconomical.</p>
    <p num="0075">The coated article according to the invention is the
article obtainable by the above cationic electrocoating
methods.</p>
    <p num="0076">If necessary, an intermediate coating film and/or a
top coating film may be further formed on the surface of
the coated article of the invention depending on
requirements. The above intermediate coating film can be
formed by applying an intermediate coating and the above
top coating film can be formed by applying a top coating.</p>
    <p num="0077">In the case where the coated article is an automotive
shell plate, for instance, said intermediate coating film
preferably has such performance characteristics as good
adhesion, smoothness, image clarity, overbake resistance,
and weather resistance, and the like. As an intermediate
coating for forming such an intermediate coating film, a
thermosetting coating agent comprising a binder and a
curing agent is generally employed. The binder mentioned
above includes acrylic resins, polyester resins, alkyd
resins, and epoxy resins. The above curing agent can be
selected from a broad range of substances according to the
curable functional groups of the above binder, and includes
amino resins, blocked isocyanates, aliphatic polycarboxylic
acids and anhydrides thereof, and epoxy resins, and the 
like. The intermediate coating may be provided in various
forms, such as a solvent-borne coating, a water-borne
coating, an aqueous dispersion, a powder coating, and so
forth.</p>
    <p num="0078">The top coating preferably is satisfactory in
finished appearance (image clarity, smoothness, gloss,
etc.), weather resistance (gloss retention, color retention,
chalking resistance, etc.), chemical resistance, water
resistance, moisture resistance, and curability. As such
top coatings, there can be mentioned solid color coatings
for use as one-coat solid coatings, base coatings which can
be applied by the two-coat, one-bake coating technique, and
clear coatings. These top coatings are preferably
thermosetting coatings comprising a binder and a curing
agent. As the binder and curing agent for the top coating,
the substances mentioned for said intermediate coatings can
be used. Said solid color coatings may contain the well-known
inorganic or organic color pigment, such as carbon
black, phthalocyanine blue, titanium dioxide, and so forth.
The base coatings may contain the well-known luster
material, such as aluminum flakes, mica flakes, or the like,
in addition to said inorganic or organic color pigment. On
the other hand, said clear coatings usually do not contain
a pigment but may be supplemented with said color pigment
and/or luster material to the extent not detracting from
clarity. Such top coatings may be any of water-borne,
solvent-borne and powder coatings but are preferably
formulated as water-borne or powder coatings for protection
of the environment. In the case of a water-borne system,
the carboxyl group of the binder is neutralized with an
amine to make the binder water-soluble and in the case of a
powder coating, the glass transition temperature is set
higher than room temperature. In this manner, the
respective application forms can be established.</p>
    <p num="0079">Said intermediate coating and top coating may contain 
such additives as extender pigments, curing catalists,
leveling agents, UV absorbers, and light stabilizers.</p>
    <p num="0080">According to the application forms of said
intermediate coating or said top coating, the coating
techniques known to those skilled in the art can be
employed. For example, spray coating, brush coating, dip
coating, electrostatic coating, etc. can be mentioned.
Particularly in the coating stage in an automotive body
production line, the electrostatic coating method is
preferably employed. With regard to the film thickness for
the intermediate coating or the top coating and the
conditions of heating after coating, too, the amounts and
conditions suited to the respective coating species can be
employed.</p>
    <p num="0081">By superimposing the intermediate coating film and
top coating film on the electrodeposited coating film
obtained by the cationic electrocoating method of the
invention, a multilayer coating film can be obtained.</p>
    <p num="0082">The cationic electrocoating method according to the
present invention is a cationic electrocoating method
comprising electrocoating a surface of an aluminum
substrate with a cationic electrodeposition coating
composition containing a sulfonium- and proparygyl-containing
resin composition, and the resulting
electrodeposited coating film shows excellent corrosion
resistance. This is probably because, in the course of
electrocoating, the sulfur atom contained in the coating
component forms a sulfur-aluminum covalent bond with the
aluminum atom on the substrate surface.</p>
    <p num="0083">A further possible reason is that, compared with the
conventional cationic electrodeposition coating, the
cationic electrodeposition coating composition containing
said suflonium- and propargyl-containing resin composition
provides a coating film which, by itself, is superior in 
rust resistance and corrosion resistance.</p>
    <p num="0084">The cationic electrocoating method according to the
first aspect of the present invention does not require a
treatment of heavy metal-containing effluents, thus being
free from risks for environmental pollutions and economical.</p>
    <p num="0085">The cationic electrocoating method according to the
second aspect of the invention does not require a surface
treatment of aluminum substrates, thus contributing to
improved productivity through process curtailment and
energy savings.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>EXAMPLES</b>
    </heading>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Production Example 1 Preparation of a sulfonium- and
propargyl-containing epoxy resin composition</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0086">A separable flask equipped with a stirrer,
thermometer, nitrogen inlet pipe and reflux condenser was
charged with 100.0 weight parts of Epototo YDCN-701 (epoxy
equivalent: 200.4; cresol novolak epoxy resin, product of
Toto Chemical), 23.6 weight parts of propargyl alcohol, and
0.3 weight part of dimethylbenzylamine and the temperature
was raised to 105°C. The reaction was carried out for 3
hours to give a propargyl-containing resin composition with
an epoxy equivalent of 1580. To this resin composition was
added 2.5 weight parts of acetylacetonato-copper, and the
reaction was carried out at 90°C for 1.5 hours. It was
confirmed that some of the terminal hydrogen atoms of the
added propargyl groups was disappeared by proton (<sup>1</sup>H) NMR
spectrometry (propargyl converted to acetylide: 14 mmol/100
g resin solids). The flask was then charged with 10.6
weight parts of 1-(2-hydroxyethylthio)-2,3-propanediol, 4.7
weight parts of glacial acetic acid, and 7.0 weight parts
of deionized water and the reaction was carried out at a
constant temperature of 75°C for 6 hours. After the
residual acid value was confirmed to be not more than 5, 
43.8 weight parts of deionized water was further added,
whereby the objective resin composition solution was
obtained. The concentration of solids in this mixture was
70.0 weight % and the sulfonium content was 28.0 mmol/100 g
solids of the resin. The number average molecular weight
(GPC, polystyrene equivalent) was 2443. This resin
composition was further diluted with deionized water to
finally give an aqueous solution of 15 weight % solids. In
this manner, a cationic electrodeposition coating
composition was obtained.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Example 1</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0087">The lower half of an aluminum-magnesium alloy (5052)
plate (75 x 150 x 0.8 mm) was ground with an air sander
(manufactured by URYU Co., Type UP-25DB) at a max. speed of
9000 rpm, a pad. size of 125 mm, and a max. pressure of 6
kg/cm<sup>2</sup> and further ground evenly with sandpaper (product of
Sankyo Rikagaku; high-pitch paper, grit 80, HAND type, size
125 mm). The ground part was cleaned with water to remove
grindings and dried. Then, the plate was immersion-degreased
with a degreasing agent (a 2 weight % aqueous
solution of Surf Cleaner 53, product of Nippon Paint Co.)
at 50°C for 160 seconds and, then, dipped in a surface
conditioner (a 0.1 weight % aqueous solution of Surf Fine
5N-8 Architect, product of Nippon Paint Co.) at 25°C for 45
seconds. Thereafter, the plate was subjected to a chemical
conversion with a zinc phosphate surface treating reagent
(a 2 weight % aqueous solution of Surf Dyne SD5600, product
of Nippon Paint Co.) at 45°C until a coating weight of 2.0
mg/m<sup>2</sup> had been attained to provide a substrate.</p>
    <p num="0088">The cationic electrodeposition coating composition
obtained in Production Example 1 was transferred to a
stainless steel vessel, which was to serve as the anode, to
prepare an electrodeposition bath and the ground lower half
of the substrate was immersed in the bath to serve as the 
cathode. Electrodeposition coating was carried out until a
dry film thickness of 15 µm had been attained. After this
electrocoating, the substrate was withdrawn from the
electrodeposition bath in the stainless steel vessel,
cleaned with water, and heated in a drying oven at a
controlled temperature of 180°C for 30 minutes to provide a
test plate 1 carrying a cationic electrodeposited coating
film on the surface of the lower half of the substrate.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Example 2</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0089">Except that, instead of dipping in the surface
conditioner, the substrate was dipped in an acid cleaner (a
3 weight % aqueous solution of Surf Cleaner 355A, product
of Nippon Paint Co.) at 45°C for 120 seconds and that,
instead of dipping in the zinc phosphate surface treating
bath, the substrate was dipped in a zirconic acid surface
treating bath (a 2 weight % aqueous solution of Alsurf
301N-1, product of Nippon Paint Co.) at 45°C for 60 seconds
to a coat weight of 20 to 50 mg/m<sup>2</sup>, the procedure of
Example 1 was otherwise repeated to provide a test plate 2
carrying a cationic electrodeposited coating film on the
surface of the lower half of the substrate.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Comparative Example 1</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0090">Except that, instead of the cationic
electrodeposition coating composition obtained in
Production Example 1, Power Top U-30 (a blocked isocyanate
curable epoxy resin cationic electrodeposition coating,
product of Nippon Paint Co.) was used, the procedure of
Example 1 was otherwise repeated to provide a test plate 3
carrying a cationic electrodeposited coating film on the
surface of the lower half of the substrate.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Comparative Example 2</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0091">Except that, instead of the cationic 
electrodeposition coating composition obtained in
Production Example 1, Power Top U-30 (a blocked isocyanate
curable epoxy resin cationic electrodeposition coating,
product of Nippon Paint Co.) was used, the procedure of
Example 2 was otherwise repeated to provide a test plate 4
carrying a cationic electrodeposited coating film on the
surface of the lower half of the substrate.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Comparative Example 3</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0092">The substrate obtained in Example 1 was further
subjected to a chemical conversion by dipping in an aftertreatment
agent bath (a 0.5 weight % aqueous solution of
Surf Lite 80MZ, product of Nippon Paint Co.) at 25°C for 30
seconds. Then, except that Power Top U-30 (a blocked
isocyanate curable epoxy resin cationic electrodeposition
coating, product of Nippon Paint Co.) was used instead of
the cationic electrodeposition coating composition obtained
in Production Example 1, the procedure of Example 1 was
otherwise repeated to provide a test plate 5 carrying a
cationic electrodeposited coating film on the surface of
the lower half of the substrate.</p>
    <heading>&lt;Evaluation tests&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0093">The test plates 1 through 5 obtained in Examples 1
and 2 and Comparative Examples 1 to 3, respectively, were
evaluated for the following parameters. The results are
shown in Table 1.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Filiform-rust resistance</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0094">Using an NT cutter, each test plate was scored in a
cross of two 10 cm-long cuts. The scored plate was dipped
in 0.5 mol/1 hydrochloric acid solution for 10 seconds and,
then, transferred to an incubator controlled at 40°C and 70
to 75% R.H., in which it was allowed to sit for 240 hours.
Using the above procedure as one cycle, a total of 5 cycles 
were carried out. The length of the filiform rust which
had developed on the surface was measured and the coated
film appearance of the test plate was evaluated. The
following evaluation criteria were used.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="2"><dt>O:</dt><dd>The length of filiform rust per 10 cm of crosscut (L):
≤15 mm; no abnormality of appearance.</dd><dt>Δ:</dt><dd>The length of filiform rust per 10 cm of crosscut (L):
15 mm ≤ L &lt; 18 mm; no abnormality of appearance.</dd><dt>X:</dt><dd>The length of filiform rust per 10 cm of crosscut (L) :
&gt;18 mm or an abnormal appearance.</dd></dl></p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Environment-applicability</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0095">The test plate was evaluated for possible contamination
with heavy metals.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="3"><dt>O :</dt><dd>Neither chromium nor lead is detected.</dd><dt>X:</dt><dd>Chromium or lead is detected.</dd></dl><tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2">Example 2</entry><entry nameend="6" align="center" namest="4">Comparative Example 3</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Filiform-rust resistance</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">×</entry><entry align="center">Δ</entry><entry align="center">○</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Environment-applicability</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">×</entry><entry align="center">×</entry><entry align="center">×</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0096">It is apparent from Table 1 that, by using the
cationic electrocoating method according to the first
aspect of the present invention, a coated aluminum article
with excellent filiform-rust resistance and corrosion
resistance can be obtained without use of a heavy metal-containing
surface treating reagent.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Example 3</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0097">The lower half of an aluminum-magnesium alloy (5052)
plate (75 x 150 x 0.8 mm) was ground with an air sander 
(manufactured by URYU Co., Type UP-25DB) at a max. speed of
9000 rpm, a pad. size of 125 mm, and a max. pressure of 6
kg/cm<sup>2</sup> and further ground evenly with sandpaper (product of
Sankyo Rikagaku; high-pitch paper, grit 80, HAND type, size
125 mm). The ground part was cleaned with water to remove
grindings and dried to provide a substrate.</p>
    <p num="0098">The cationic electrodeposition coating composition
obtained in Production Example 1 was transferred to a
stainless steel vessel, which was to serve as the anode, to
prepare an electrodeposition bath and the ground lower half
of the substrate was immersed in the bath to serve as the
cathode. Electrodeposition coating was carried out until a
dry film thickness of 15 µm had been attained. After this
electrocoating, the substrate was withdrawn from the
electrodeposition bath in the stainless steel vessel,
cleaned with water, and heated in a drying oven at a
controlled temperature of 180°C for 30 minutes to provide a
test plate 6 carrying a cationic electrodeposited coating
film on the surface of the lower half of the substrate.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Example 4</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0099">Except that a substrate was used as prepared by further
degreasing the substrate by dipping in a degreasing bath (a
2 weight % aqueous solution of Surf Cleaner 53, product of
Nippon Paint Co.) at 50°C for 120-180 seconds, instead of
same substrate as used in Example 3, the procedure of
Example 3 was otherwise repeated to provide a test plate 7
carrying a cationic electrodeposited coating film on the
surface of the lower half of the substrate.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Comparative Example 4</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0100">Except that Power Top U-30 (a blocked isocyanate
curable epoxy resin cationic electrodeposition coating,
product of Nippon Paint Co.) was used instead of the
cationic electrodeposition coating composition obtained in 
Production Example 1, the procedure of Example 3 was
otherwise repeated to provide a test plate 8 carrying a
cationic electrodeposited coating film on the surface of
the lower half of the substrate.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Comparative Example 5</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0101">Except that Power Top U-30 (a blocked isocyanate
curable epoxy resin cationic electrodeposition coating,
product of Nippon Paint Co.) was used instead of the
cationic electrodeposition coating composition obtained in
Production Example 1, the procedure of Example 4 was
otherwise repeated to provide a test plate 9 carrying a
cationic electrodeposited coating film on the surface of
the lower half of the substrate.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Comparative Example 6</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0102">Except that a chromated substrate was used as
prepared by degreasing the substrate by dipping in a
degreasing bath (a 2 weight % aqueous solution of Surf
Cleaner 53, product of Nippon Paint Co.) prewarmed to 50°C
for 160 seconds and further subjecting it to a surface
treatment by dipping in a surface treating bath (a 2
weight % aqueous solution of Al Surface 1200, product of
Nippon Paint Co.) prewarmed to 35°C until a coat weight
(total chromium amount) of 200 mg/m<sup>2</sup> had been attained,
instead of same substrate as used in Comparative Example 3,
the procedure of Comparative Example 3 was otherwise
repeated to provide test plate 10 carrying a cationic
electrodeposited coating film on the surface of the lower
half of the substrate.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Evaluation Tests</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0103">The test plates 6 through 10 obtained in Examples 3 and
4 and comparative Examples 4-6, respectively, were
evaluated for filiform-rust resistance and environment-applicability 
as above and, in addition, for the following
parameters. The evaluation results are shown in Table 2.</p>
    <heading>&lt;Corrosion Resistance&gt;</heading>
    <p num="0104">Using an NT cutter, the test plate was scored in a
cross of two 10 cm-long cuts. Then, in accordance with
JIS-Z-2371, a salt spray test (a 5 weight % aqueous
solution of sodium chloride, 35°C × 1500 hrs) was
performed. The test plate withdrawn was evaluated for
rusted surface peeling. The following evaluation criteria
were used.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="3"><dt>O :</dt><dd>The maximum width of rusted surface peeling on one side
(W) : ≤1.5 mm.</dd><dt>Δ:</dt><dd>The maximum width of rusted surface peeling on one side
(W): 2.0 mm ≥ W &gt; 1.5 mm</dd><dt>X:</dt><dd>The maximum width of rusted surface peeling on one side
(W) : &gt; 2.0 mm</dd></dl><tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2">Example</entry><entry nameend="6" align="center" namest="4">Comparative Example</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Filiform-rust resistance</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">×</entry><entry align="center">×</entry><entry align="center">○</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Corrosion resistance</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">×</entry><entry align="center">Δ</entry><entry align="center">○</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Environment-applicability</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">×</entry><entry align="center">×</entry><entry align="center">×</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0105">It is apparent from Table 2 that, by using the
cationic electrocoating method according to the second
aspect of the present invention, a coated aluminum article
with excellent filiform-rust resistance and corrosion
resistance can be obtained without use of a harmful metal-containing
surface treating reagent.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A cationic electrocoating method comprising
electrocoating a surface of an aluminum substrate with a
cationic electrodeposition coating composition,
   wherein said aluminum substrate is subjected to a
chemical conversion with a surface treating reagent not
containing a heavy metal, and
   wherein said cationic electrodeposition coating
composition contains a sulfonium- and propargyl-containing
resin composition.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The cationic electrocoating method according to
Claim 1,
   wherein said heavy metal is chromium.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The cationic electrocoating method according to
Claim 1 or 2,
   wherein the surface of said aluminum substrate is
degreased.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The cationic electrocoating method according to
any of Claims 1 to 3,
   wherein said cationic electrodeposition coating
composition contains 5 to 400 mmol of the sulfonium group
and 10 to 495 mmol of the propargyl group per 100 g solids
of said resin composition and the total content of the
sulfonium and propargyl groups is not more than 500 mmol
per 100 g solids.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The cationic electrocoating method according to
any of Claims 1 to 3,
   wherein said cationic electrodeposition coating
composition contains 5 to 250 mmol of the sulfonium group
and 20 to 395 mmol of the propargyl group per 100 g solids
of said resin composition and the total content of the
sulfonium and propargyl groups is not more than 400 mmol
per 100 g solids.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The cationic electrocoating method according to
any of Claims 1 to 5,
   wherein some of the propargyl groups of the resin
composition in said cationic electrodeposition coating
composition are in the form of acetylides.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>The cationic electrocoating method according to
any of Claims 1 to 6,
   wherein said resin composition comprises an epoxy
resin as a skeleton.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The cationic electrocoating method according to
Claim 7,
   wherein said epoxy resin is a novolac cresol epoxy
resin or a novolac phenol epoxy resin and
   has a number average molecular weight of 700 to 5000.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>A coated article obtainable by the cationic
electrocoating method according to any of Claims 1 to 8.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>A cationic electrocoating method comprising
electrocoating a surface of an aluminum substrate with a
cationic electrodeposition coating composition,
   wherein said aluminum substrate is not subjected to a
chemical conversion with a surface treating reagent, and
   wherein said cationic electrodeposition coating
composition contains a sulfonium- and propargyl-containing
resin composition.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>The cationic electrocoating method according to
Claim 10,
   wherein the surface of said aluminum substrate is
degreased.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>The cationic electrocoating method according to
Claim 10 or 11,
   wherein said cationic electrodeposition coating
composition contains 5 to 400 mmol of the sulfonium group
and 10 to 495 mmol of the propargyl group per 100 g solids
of said resin composition and the total content of the
sulfonium and propargyl groups is not more than 500 mmol
per 100 g solids.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>The cationic electrocoating method according to
Claim 10 or 11,
   wherein said cationic electrodeposition coating
composition contains 5 to 250 mmol of the sulfonium group
and 20 to 395 mmol of the propargyl group per 100 g solids
of said resin composition and the total content of the
sulfonium and propargyl groups is not more than 400 mmol
per 100 g solids.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>The cationic electrocoating method according to
any of Claims 10 to 13,
   wherein said resin composition comprises an epoxy
resin as a skeleton.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>The cationic electrocoating method according to
Claim 14,
   wherein said epoxy resin is a novolac cresol epoxy
resin or a novolac phenol epoxy resin and
   has a number average molecular weight of 700 to 5000.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>A coated article obtainable by the cationic
electrocoating method according to any of Claims 10 to 15.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
