<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1236886-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1236886" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="18899742" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020904">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1236886-A2" status="new" fvid="23540305">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1236886</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20020904</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02003318-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02003318</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020213</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001036474-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001036474</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010214</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F02M  47/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F02M  47/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F02M  51/06        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F02M  51/06        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F02M  55/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F02M  55/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F02M  61/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F02M  61/10        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F02M  61/16        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F16J  15/08        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F16J  15/08        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F02M  47/02D</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F02M  55/00D2</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F02M  61/10</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F02M  61/16</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Vorrichtung zur Flächenpressungserhöhung bei fluidführenden Rohrleitungen</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Arrangement for increasing the sealing surface pressure of fluid conducting system</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Dispositif pour augmenter la pression de contact entre des conduites pour fluide</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>DENSO CORP</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>DENSO CORPORATION</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Denso Corporation</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1-1, Showa-cho</street>
              <city>Kariya-city, Aichi-pref., 448-8661</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ITOU TAKEHIRO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ITOU, TAKEHIRO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>ITOU, TAKEHIRO</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>c/o DENSO CORPORATION, 1-1 Showa-cho</street>
              <city>Kariya-city, Aichi-pref., 448-8661</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Leson, Thomas Johannes Alois</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Patentanwälte Tiedtke-Bühling-Kinne &amp;amp; Partner, Bavariaring 4</street>
              <city>80336 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>IT</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>Reduced thickness portions (35) in a form of a recess are
formed in a contact surface in a lower end of a tip packing (4),
which contacts with an upper end of a nozzle body (2).
Furthermore, reduced thickness portions (36, 37) in a form of
a recess are formed in a contact surface in an upper end of the
tip packing (4), which contacts with a nozzle holder (3). With
this arrangement, a sealing surface pressure around a connection
between corresponding fuel passages (13-15) is increased with
use of a reduced axial fastening force by reducing the sealing
surface area in each contact surface. Furthermore, one (37) of
the reduced thickness portions (35-37) formed in the contact
surface in the upper end of the tip packing (4) is used as a
leakage recovery passage.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="66" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="141"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a sealing surface pressure
increasing arrangement of a fluid conducting system, which is
capable of increasing a sealing surface pressure around a
connection between fluid passages in the fluid conducting system.
More particularly, the present invention relates to a sealing
surface pressure increasing arrangement of a fuel injection
nozzle of an internal combustion engine.</p>
    <p num="0002">One previously proposed fuel injection nozzle 100 of an
internal combustion engine is provided in each cylinder of the
internal combustion engine. With reference to FIGS. 3 to 4C,
the fuel injection nozzle 100 has a retaining nut 104. The
retaining nut 104 makes tight sealing contact of a contact
surface between a nozzle body 101 and a tip packing 103 and also
makes tight sealing contact of a contact surface between the tip
packing 103 and a nozzle holder 102 by applying a predetermined
axial fastening force to these contact surfaces. In the fuel
injection nozzle 100, there is no particular structure for
achieving the tight contact in these contact surfaces, and the
tight sealing contact is achieved only by applying the
predetermined axial fastening force to the contact surfaces from
the retaining nut 104.</p>
    <p num="0003">The tip packing 103 includes pin holes 111, 112 and a fuel
relay passage 108. The pin holes 111, 112 receive corresponding 
positioning pins for positioning between the nozzle body 101 and
the nozzle holder 102. The fuel relay passage 108 communicates
a pressure chamber 105 and a fuel feed passage 106 of the nozzle
body 101 to a fuel supply passage 107 of the nozzle holder 102.</p>
    <p num="0004">The nozzle holder 102 has a leakage recovery passage 109.
The leakage recovery passage 109 recovers fuel leaked through
the contact surface of the nozzle holder 102 and through the
contact surface of the tip packing 103 and conducts the leaked
fuel to a low-pressure pipeline system. One end of the leakage
recovery passage 109, which is located adjacent to the contact
surface of the nozzle holder 102, is communicated with another
leakage recovery passage 110. This leakage recovery passage 110
communicates an axial bore 115 of the tip packing 103 and an axial
bore 116 of the nozzle holder 102 to the leakage recovery passage
109.</p>
    <p num="0005">In recent years, fuel injection pressure of a fuel
injection nozzle of a diesel engine has been progressively
increased. Thus, there is a demand for increasing a sealing
surface pressure between the contact surfaces of the components
by increasing the axial fastening force of the retaining nut.
However, when the contact surface of the nozzle body and the
contact surface of the nozzle holder are fastened together via
the tip packing by fastening or tightening the retaining nut,
a frictional force generated between a shoulder of the nozzle
body and an inner seat surface of the retaining nut upon
application of the axial fastening force induces twist of the
nozzle body. The twist of the nozzle body, in turn, causes a 
reduction of a roundness of a sliding portion of a nozzle needle
and can finally prevents smooth sliding movement of the nozzle
needle.</p>
    <p num="0006">Thus, the increase of the sealing surface pressure achieved
by increasing the axial fastening force of the retaining nut
poses various disadvantages in terms of deformation and strength
of the components, such as the nozzle body. Furthermore, the
arrangement that increases the sealing surface pressure of the
components by increasing the axial fastening force of the
retaining nut poses a disadvantage in terms of manufacturing
costs.</p>
    <p num="0007">Thus, it is an objective of the present invention to provide
a sealing surface pressure increasing arrangement of a fluid
conducting system capable of increasing a sealing surface
pressure around a connection between fluid passages without
substantially increasing an axial fastening force applied to the
connection.</p>
    <p num="0008">To achieve the objective of the present invention, there
is provided a sealing surface pressure increasing arrangement
of a fluid conducting system. The arrangement includes a first
fluid conducting component, a second fluid conducting component
and a third fluid conducting component. The first fluid
conducting component has a first fluid passage therein. The
second fluid conducting component has a second fluid passage
therein. The third fluid conducting component is clamped between
the first fluid conducting component and the second fluid
conducting component and has a third fluid passage for 
communicating between the first fluid passage and the second
fluid passage. At least one reduced thickness portion in a form
of a recess is provided in at least one of a first contact surface
between the first fluid conducting component and the third fluid
conducting component and a second contact surface between the
second fluid conducting component and the third fluid conducting
component, so that a sealing surface area of the at least one
of the first and second contact surfaces is reduced to increase
a sealing surface pressure in the at least one of the first and
second contact surfaces around at least one of the fluid
passages.</p>
    <p num="0009">The invention, together with additional objectives,
features and advantages thereof, will be best understood from
the following description, the appended claims and the
accompanying drawings in which:
<sl><li>FIG. 1 is a cross-sectional view showing a main feature of
a fuel injection nozzle of an internal combustion engine
according to one embodiment of the present invention;</li><li>FIG. 2A is a top plan view of a tip packing of the fuel
injection nozzle according to the embodiment, showing an upper
end surface of the tip packing;</li><li>FIG. 2B is a cross-sectional view along line IIB-IIB in FIG.
2A;</li><li>FIG. 2C is a bottom plan view of the tip packing according
to the embodiment, showing a lower end surface of the tip packing;</li><li>FIG. 3 is a cross-sectional view of a previously proposed
fuel injection nozzle of an internal combustion engine; </li><li>FIG. 4A is a top plan view of a tip packing of the previously
proposed fuel injection nozzle, showing an upper end surface of
the tip packing;</li><li>FIG. 4B is a cross-sectional view along line IVB-IVB in FIG.
4A; and</li><li>FIG. 4C is a bottom plan view of the tip packing of the
previously proposed fuel injection nozzle, showing a lower end
surface of the tip packing.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0010">One embodiment of the present invention will be described
with reference to FIGS. 1 to 2C.</p>
    <p num="0011">A fuel injection nozzle 1 of an internal combustion engine
according to the present embodiment is the fuel injection nozzle
used in an injector of an accumulator fuel injection system
(common rail system), which acts as a fluid conducting system.
More particularly, the fuel injection nozzle is the
direct-injection type fuel injection valve provided in each
cylinder of a diesel engine (not shown). Highly pressurized fuel
is pumped from a high-pressure supply pump (not shown) and is
accumulated in a pressure accumulator chamber of a common rail
of the fuel injection system. The highly pressurized fuel
accumulated in the pressure accumulator chamber is directly
injected into a corresponding combustion chamber through the
fuel injection nozzle.</p>
    <p num="0012">The fuel injection nozzle 1 includes a nozzle body 2, a
nozzle holder 3, a tip packing 4 and a retaining nut 5. The nozzle
body 2 receives a nozzle needle (not shown). The nozzle holder 
3 receives an urging means, such as a spring, for urging the
nozzle needle toward a valve closing side (downside in FIG. 1).
The tip packing 4 is arranged between the nozzle body 2 and the
nozzle holder 3. The retaining nut 5 connects or fastens the
nozzle body 2 and the nozzle holder 3 together via the tip packing
4 with a predetermined axial fastening force.</p>
    <p num="0013">The nozzle body 2 corresponds to a first fluid conducting
component of the present invention, which has one or more fuel
injection holes at its distal end (lower end in FIG. 1). The
highly pressurized fuel is injected from the nozzle body 2
through the one or more fuel injection holes. A slide bore 11
is formed in the nozzle body 2 for holding the nozzle needle in
a slidable manner. A pressure chamber 16, which has an enlarged
diameter, is provided in the middle of the slid bore 11. First
pin holes (not shown) are formed in an upper end surface (i.e.,
a contact surface that contacts with the tip packing 4) of the
nozzle body 2 in FIG. 1. Each first pin hole is communicated
with a corresponding first pin hole 12 (described later) and
receives a first knock-pin (not shown), which aids in positioning
between the nozzle body 2 and the tip packing 4 during assembly
and prevents relative rotation between the nozzle body 2 and the
tip packing 4.</p>
    <p num="0014">The nozzle body 2 further includes a fuel feed passage
(corresponding to a first fluid passage of the present invention)
15 that extends from the contact surface in the upper end of the
nozzle body 2 to the pressure chamber 16 in FIG. 1. The fuel
feed passage 15 is communicated with a fuel supply passage 13 
(described later) of the nozzle holder 3 and also with a fuel
relay passage 14 (described later) of the tip packing 4 and thus
constitutes a fuel passage for supplying the highly pressurized
fuel from the pressure accumulator chamber of the common rail
to the pressure chamber 16.</p>
    <p num="0015">The nozzle holder 3 corresponds to a second fluid
conducting component of the present invention. The nozzle holder
3 is a tubular body that includes a spring chamber 21 therein.
The spring chamber 21 receives the urging means (not shown), such
as the spring, and a pressure pin or hydraulic piston (not shown)
connected to the nozzle needle. A lower part of the spring
chamber 21, which is located below a step 23, has a larger
diameter than an upper part of the spring chamber 21, which is
located above the step 23 in FIG 1.</p>
    <p num="0016">A hydraulic pressure control chamber (not shown) is
provided at one end (top side in FIG. 1) of the hydraulic piston.
An electromagnetic actuator, such as an electromagnetic valve,
supplies and drains hydraulic pressure or oil pressure relative
to the hydraulic pressure control chamber. When the hydraulic
pressure is drained from the hydraulic pressure control chamber,
the nozzle needle and the hydraulic piston are urged against the
urging force of the urging means, such as the spring, and thus
are axially moved (lifted). That is, the nozzle needle is placed
in a valve opening position. On the other hand, when the
hydraulic pressure is supplied to the hydraulic pressure control
chamber, the nozzle needle and the hydraulic piston are urged
by the urging force of the urging means, such as the spring, and 
thus are axially moved to place the nozzle needle in a valve
closing position.</p>
    <p num="0017">Second pin holes (not shown) are formed in a lower end
surface (i.e., a contact surface that contacts with the tip
packing 4) of the nozzle holder 3 in FIG. 1. Each second pin
hole is communicated with a second pin hole 22 (described later)
of the tip packing 4 and receives a second knock-pin (not shown),
which aids in positioning between the nozzle holder 3 and the
tip packing 4 during assembly and prevents relative rotation
between the nozzle holder 3 and the tip packing 4. Furthermore,
the nozzle holder 3 has a joint portion (not shown). The joint
portion of the nozzle holder 3 connects the nozzle holder 3 to
a high-pressure pipeline, which, in turn, is connected to a
branch pipe of the common rail. Thus, the highly pressurized
fuel supplied from the common rail is provided to the joint
portion of the nozzle holder 3.</p>
    <p num="0018">The fuel supply passage (corresponding to a second fluid
passage of the present invention) 13 is arranged in the joint
portion of the nozzle holder 3 and also around the spring chamber
21. The fuel supply passage 13 supplies the highly pressurized
fuel to the pressure chamber 16 of the nozzle body 2 via the fuel
relay passage 14 of the tip packing 4 and the fuel feed passage
15 of the nozzle body 2. The nozzle holder 3 also has a fuel
relief passage (leakage recovery passage) 24 for returning the
fuel from the spring chamber 21 to a low-pressure pipeline system,
such as a fuel tank. Furthermore, the nozzle holder 3 has a male
threaded portion 26, which is formed around a lower end side of 
the nozzle holder 3 and is engaged with a female threaded portion
25 (described later) of the retaining nut 5.</p>
    <p num="0019">The tip packing 4 corresponds to a third fluid conducting
component of the present invention. The tip packing 4 is an
annular body arranged between the contact surface in the upper
end of the nozzle body 2 and the contact surface in the lower
end of the nozzle holder 3 and has the fuel relay passage
(corresponding to a third fluid passage of the present invention)
14, which communicates between the fuel feed passage 15 of the
nozzle body 2 and the fuel supply passage 13 of the nozzle holder
3. A larger diameter bore 31 is formed in the tip packing 4.
An inner diameter of the larger diameter bore 31 is larger than
that of a smaller diameter bore 32 located below the larger
diameter bore 31 in FIG. 1.</p>
    <p num="0020">The center portion of a lower end surface of the tip packing
4 acts as a limiting surface. The limiting surface limits
movement of the nozzle needle when an amount of movement (i.e.,
amount of lift) of the nozzle needle at the time of valve opening
of the nozzle needle reaches its maximum amount. Furthermore,
the tip packing 4 includes the first and second pin holes 12,
22 around the smaller diameter bore 32 and the larger diameter
bore 31, respectively. Each first pin hole 12 is communicated
with the corresponding first pin hole of the nozzle body 2 and
receives the corresponding first knock-pin, which aids in
positioning between the nozzle body 2 and the tip packing 4 during
the assembly and prevents the relative rotation between the
nozzle body 2 and the tip packing 4. Each second pin hole 22 
is communicated with the corresponding second pin hole of the
nozzle holder 3 and receives the corresponding second knock-pin,
which aids in positioning between the nozzle holder 3 and the
tip packing 4 during the assembly and prevents the relative
rotation between the nozzle holder 3 and the tip packing 4.</p>
    <p num="0021">A plurality of reduced thickness portions (shaded with
oblique lines in FIG. 2) 35 in a form of a recess are provided
in the lower end surface (i.e., the contact surface that contacts
with the nozzle body 2) of the tip packing 4, which corresponds
to a first contact surface of the present invention. The reduced
thickness portions 35 act as first reduced thickness portions
of the present invention and reduce a sealing surface area of
the lower end surface of the tip packing 4 to reduce a sealing
surface pressure around a connection between the corresponding
fluid passages. The contact surface in the lower end of the tip
packing 4 except the reduced thickness portions 35 substantially
sealingly contacts with the contact surface (sealing surface)
in the upper end of the nozzle body 2 to form a sealing surface
38 that provides a tight seal around a connection between the
fuel feed passage 15 and the fuel relay passage 14.</p>
    <p num="0022">A plurality of reduced thickness portions (shaded with
oblique lines in FIG. 2) 36 in a form of a recess are provided
in the upper end surface (i.e., the contact surface that contacts
with the nozzle holder 3) of the tip packing 4, which corresponds
to a second contact surface of the present invention. The reduced
thickness portions 36 act as second reduced thickness portions
of the present invention and reduce a sealing surface area of 
the upper end surface of the tip packing 4 to reduce a sealing
surface pressure around a connection between the corresponding
fluid passages. Another reduced thickness portion (indicated
with a grid pattern in FIG. 2A) 37 in a form of a recess (acting
as another second reduced thickness portion of the present
invention) communicates between one of the reduced thickness
portions 36 in the upper end surface of the tip packing 4 and
the larger diameter bore 31. The reduced thickness portion 37
also acts as a leakage recovery passage. The leakage recovery
passage returns the fuel, which has been conducted to the spring
chamber 21, the larger diameter bore 31 and the smaller diameter
bore 32, to the low-pressure pipeline system, such as the fuel
tank. The contact surface in the upper end surface of the tip
packing 4 except the reduced thickness portions 36, 37
substantially sealingly contacts with the contact surface
(sealing surface) in the lower end of the nozzle holder 3 to form
a sealing surface 39 that provides a tight seal around a
connection between the fuel supply passage 13 and the fuel relay
passage 14.</p>
    <p num="0023">The retaining nut 5 corresponds to a fastening pipe member
of the present invention. The retaining nut 5 applies a
predetermined axial fastening force to achieve tight engagement
between the contact surface in the upper end of the nozzle body
2 and the contact surface in the lower end of the nozzle holder
3 via the tip packing 4. The retaining nut 5 has an annular
retaining portion 43 and a cylindrical sleeve portion 44. The
retaining portion 43 has an inner seat surface 42 for receiving 
a shoulder 41 provided in the lower end surface of the nozzle
body 2. The sleeve portion 44 extends upwardly in FIG. 1 from
an outer peripheral edge of the retaining portion 43. An inner
diameter of the sleeve portion 44 is larger than an inner diameter
of a thinner-walled portion 45, which is arranged above the
sleeve portion 44. The female threaded portion 25, which is
threadably engaged with the male threaded portion 26 of the lower
end side of the nozzle holder 3, is provided along an inner
peripheral surface of the thinner-walled portion 45.</p>
    <p num="0024">Operation of the fuel injection nozzle 1 of the present
embodiment will be described with reference to FIGS. 1 to 2C.</p>
    <p num="0025">The highly pressurized fuel is supplied from the common
rail (high pressure source) to the pressure chamber 16 through
the high-pressure pipeline, the fuel supply passage 13, the fuel
relay passage 14 and the fuel feed passage 15. When the hydraulic
pressure is drained from the hydraulic pressure control chamber
arranged on the other end of the hydraulic piston, the pressure
in the pressure chamber 16 becomes greater than the urging force
of the urging means, such as the spring, so that the hydraulic
piston and the nozzle needle are moved in the direction for
opening the one or more fuel injection holes. Thus, the nozzle
needle is lifted from the valve seat of the nozzle body 2, so
that the highly pressurized fuel received in the pressure chamber
16 is injected into the corresponding combustion chamber of the
diesel engine from the one or more injection holes arranged in
the distal end of the nozzle body 2.</p>
    <p num="0026">The fuel could leak from the fuel supply passage 13, the 
fuel relay passage 14, the fuel feed passage 15 and the pressure
chamber 16 to a space between the nozzle needle and the spring
chamber 21 of the nozzle holder 3, the larger diameter bore 31
of the tip packing 4 and the smaller diameter bore 32 of the tip
packing 4. Then, the leaked fuel flows through the leakage
recovery passage, which is formed between the contact surface
in the lower end of the nozzle holder 3 and the reduced thickness
portion 37 in the contact surface in the upper end of the tip
packing 4. Thereafter, the leaked fuel flows through the fuel
relief passage (leakage recovery passage) 24 in the nozzle holder
3 and is returned to the low-pressure pipeline system, such as
the fuel tank.</p>
    <p num="0027">Advantages of the above embodiment will now be described.</p>
    <p num="0028">As described above, in the fuel injection nozzle 1 of the
internal combustion engine of the present embodiment, the tip
packing 4 is clamped between the contact surface (sealing
surface) in the upper end of the nozzle body 2 and the contact
surface (sealing surface) in the lower end of the nozzle holder
3 in FIG. 1. The reduced thickness portions 35 are formed by
recessing corresponding portions of the contact surface in the
lower end of the tip packing 4, and the reduced thickness portions
36 are formed by recessing corresponding portions of the contact
surface in the upper end of the tip package 4. The reduced
thickness portions 35, 36 are processed in such a manner that
the reduced thickness portions 35, 36 do not interfere with the
fuel relay passage 14, and thus do not cause leakage of the highly
pressurized fuel from the fuel relay passage 14, and also the 
reduced thickness portions 35, 36 aid in achieving the
high-pressure resistant seal, which can withstand the higher
pressure that has been demanded in recent years.</p>
    <p num="0029">Furthermore, similar to the reduced thickness portions 36,
the reduced thickness portion 37 is formed by recessing the
corresponding portion of the contact surface of the tip packing
4, which is tightly engaged with the contact surface (sealing
surface) in the lower end of the nozzle holder 3. The reduced
thickness portion 37 is formed to communicate with the fuel
relief passage (leakage recovery passage) 24 of the nozzle holder
3. The reduced thickness portions 35-37 formed in the upper end
surface and the lower end surface of the tip packing 4 allow a
reduction of the corresponding sealing surface area without
increasing the axial fastening force, which could pose
disadvantages in terms of deformation of the component material
and in terms of the component strength. The reduced thickness
portions 35-37 are produced by a cutting operation.</p>
    <p num="0030">Thus, the sealing surface pressure around the connection
between the corresponding fluid passages is increased without
substantially increasing the axial fastening force by reducing
the sealing surface area. As a result, the increase in the
sealing surface pressure around the connection between the
corresponding fluid passages is possible to meet the recent
demand for increasing the fuel injection pressure. Furthermore,
it is not required to form the recess in a size that corresponds
to that of the previously proposed leakage recovery passage 110.
The reduced thickness portion 36 and the reduced thickness 
portion 37, which is communicated to the reduced thickness
portion 36, cooperate together to form the leakage recovery
passage. As a result, the structure of the contact surface of
the nozzle holder 3 is simplified, allowing a reduction of the
manufacturing cost.</p>
    <p num="0031">According to the present embodiment, in the fuel injection
nozzle 1 of the diesel engine that provides the higher fuel
injection pressure, the high-pressure resistant seal is achieved
at each sealing surface without requiring an increase in the
axial fastening force of the retaining nut 5, which applies the
predetermined axial fastening force to achieve tight engagement
between the contact surface in the upper end of the nozzle body
2 and the contact surface in the lower end of the nozzle holder
3 via the tip packing 4.</p>
    <p num="0032">Thus, in the tightening or fastening operation of the
retaining nut 5 for applying the predetermined axial fastening
force to achieve the tight engagement between the contact surface
in the upper end of the nozzle body 2 and the contact surface
in the lower end of the nozzle holder 3 via the tip packing 4,
the nozzle body 2 is not substantially twisted by the frictional
force generated between the shoulder 41 of the nozzle body 2 and
the inner seat surface 42 of the retaining nut 5 upon application
of the axial fastening force. As a result, it is possible to
prevent the reduction of the roundness of the sliding portion
of the nozzle needle, and thus the smooth sliding movement of
the nozzle needle is allowed. Furthermore, the above arrangement
is not only applicable to the accumulator fuel injection system 
but is also equally applicable to any device, which has a
high-pressure sealing surface.</p>
    <p num="0033">The above embodiment can be modified as follows.</p>
    <p num="0034">In the above embodiment, the present invention is described
with reference to the sealing surface pressure increasing
arrangement of the fuel injection nozzle 1 used as the injector
of the accumulator fuel injection system (common rail system),
which has both the high-pressure supply pump and the common rail.
However, the present invention is equally applicable to a sealing
surface pressure increasing arrangement of a fuel injection
nozzle of an injector used in a fuel injection system, which lifts
a nozzle needle from a valve seat when a fuel pressure in a
pressure chamber is increased beyond an urging force of an urging
means, such as a spring, upon direct injection of highly
pressurized fuel from an in-line fuel injection pump or from a
distributor type fuel injection pump to the injector.
Furthermore, the present invention is applicable to a variable
nozzle, which can vary a size of a fuel injection hole.</p>
    <p num="0035">Additional advantages and modifications will readily occur
to those skilled in the art. The invention in its broader terms
is therefore, not limited to the specific details,
representative apparatus, and illustrative examples shown and
described. </p>
    <p num="0036">Reduced thickness portions (35) in a form of a recess are
formed in a contact surface in a lower end of a tip packing (4),
which contacts with an upper end of a nozzle body (2).
Furthermore, reduced thickness portions (36, 37) in a form of
a recess are formed in a contact surface in an upper end of the
tip packing (4), which contacts with a nozzle holder (3). With
this arrangement, a sealing surface pressure around a connection
between corresponding fuel passages (13-15) is increased with
use of a reduced axial fastening force by reducing the sealing
surface area in each contact surface. Furthermore, one (37) of
the reduced thickness portions (35-37) formed in the contact
surface in the upper end of the tip packing (4) is used as a
leakage recovery passage.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A sealing surface pressure increasing arrangement of a
fluid conducting system, the arrangement being characterized by:
<claim-text><claim-text>a first fluid conducting component (2), which has a first
fluid passage (15) therein;</claim-text><claim-text>a second fluid conducting component (3), which has a second
fluid passage (13) therein; and</claim-text><claim-text>a third fluid conducting component (4), which is clamped
between the first fluid conducting component (2) and the second
fluid conducting component (3) and has a third fluid passage (14)
for communicating between the first fluid passage (15) and the
second fluid passage (13), wherein at least one reduced thickness
portion (35-37) in a form of a recess is provided in at least
one of a first contact surface between the first fluid conducting
component (2) and the third fluid conducting component (4) and
a second contact surface between the second fluid conducting
component (3) and the third fluid conducting component (4), so
that a sealing surface area of the at least one of the first and
second contact surfaces is reduced to increase a sealing surface
pressure in the at least one of the first and second contact
surfaces around at least one of the first to third fluid passages
(13-15).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A sealing surface pressure increasing arrangement
according to claim 1, characterized in that at least one (37)
of the at least one reduced thickness portion (35-37) is also
used as a leakage recovery passage for recovering a fluid
conducted from at least one of the first to third fluid passages
(13-15).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A sealing surface pressure increasing arrangement
according to claim 1 or 2, further characterized by a fastening
pipe member (5), which achieves tight contact of the first
contact surface between the first fluid conducting component (2)
and the third fluid conducting component (4) and also achieves
tight contact of the second contact surface between the second
fluid conducting component (3) and the third fluid conducting
component (4) by exerting a predetermined axial fastening force
to the first fluid conducting component (2), the third fluid
conducting component (4) and the second fluid conducting
component (3) to generate the sealing surface pressure.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A sealing surface pressure increasing arrangement
according to any one of claims 1 to 3, characterized in that the
at least one reduced thickness portion (35-37) is formed in the
third fluid conducting component (4).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A sealing surface pressure increasing arrangement
according to any one of claims 1 to 4, characterized in that:
<claim-text><claim-text>the at least one reduced thickness portion (35-37) includes
a plurality of first reduced thickness portions (35) and a
plurality of second reduced thickness portions (36, 37);</claim-text><claim-text>the first reduced thickness portions (35) are provided in
the first contact surface between the first fluid conducting
component (2) and the third fluid conducting component (4); and</claim-text><claim-text>the second reduced thickness portions (36, 37) are provided
in the second contact surface between the second fluid conducting
component (3) and the third fluid conducting component (4).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A sealing surface pressure increasing arrangement
according to any one of claims 1 to 5, characterized in that:
<claim-text><claim-text>the first fluid conducting component (2) is a nozzle body
(2), which slidably supports a nozzle needle therein, and the
first fluid passage (15) is a first fuel passage (15);</claim-text><claim-text>the second fluid conducting component (3) is a nozzle
holder (3), which receives an urging means for urging the nozzle
needle toward a valve closing position, and the second fluid
passage (13) is a second fuel passage (13); and</claim-text><claim-text>the third fluid conducting component (4) is a tip packing
(4), which limits an amount of lift of the nozzle needle at time
of valve opening.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A sealing surface pressure increasing arrangement
according to claim 6, characterized in that:
<claim-text><claim-text>the nozzle holder (3) has a fuel relief passage (24);</claim-text><claim-text>one end of the fuel relief passage (24) is communicated with
a low-pressure pipeline system; and</claim-text><claim-text>the other end of the fuel relief passage is communicated
with the at least one (37) of the at least one reduced thickness
portion (35-37), which is used as the leakage recovery passage.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A sealing surface pressure increasing arrangement
according to claim 7, characterized in that:
<claim-text><claim-text>the nozzle body (2) includes a slide bore (11), which
slidably supports the nozzle needle;</claim-text><claim-text>the nozzle holder (3) includes a spring chamber (21), which
receives the urging means;</claim-text><claim-text>the tip packing (4) includes a larger diameter bore (31),
which is communicated with the spring chamber (21) of the nozzle
holder (3), and a smaller diameter bore (32), which is
communicated with the slide bore (11) of the nozzle body (2);
and</claim-text><claim-text>the fuel relief passage (24) is communicated with the
larger diameter bore (31) of the tip packing (4) through the at
least one (37) of the at least one reduced thickness portion
(35-37), which is used as the leakage recovery passage.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
