<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1267094-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1267094" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="11446915" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021218">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1267094-A2" status="new" fvid="23637077">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1267094</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021218</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02077248-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02077248</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020610</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="IT-MI20010326-U" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>IT</country>
          <doc-number>MI20010326</doc-number>
          <kind>U</kind>
          <date>20010615</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F16G  13/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F16G  13/16        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H02G  11/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H02G  11/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F16G  13/16</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H02G  11/00C</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Kettenglied für eine kabeltragende Kette</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Cable carrying chain link</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Maillon de chaine porteuse de cable</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MAURI GIOVANNI</name>
            <address>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MAURI, GIOVANNI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Mauri, Giovanni</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Via A. Mauri, 23</street>
              <city>20052 Monza</city>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MAURI GIOVANNI</name>
            <address>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MAURI, GIOVANNI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>MAURI, GIOVANNI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Via A. Mauri, 23</street>
              <city>20052 Monza</city>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Riccardi, Sergio</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Riccardi &amp;amp; Co. Via Macedonio Melloni, 32</street>
              <city>20129 Milano</city>
              <country>IT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>Cable carrying chain link comprising a pair of lateral elements (2,3) mutually
matching through a number of link studs (4), where at least one of said lateral
elements (2) has elastic parts in the matching area with the other of such lateral
elements (3) belonging to the following link (1).
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="162" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="105"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">The present invention is about a cable carrying chain link.</p>
    <p num="0002">A number of different cable carrying chains for energy transportation through
specific mobile structures have been known for a long time.</p>
    <p num="0003">These chains usually have a number of elements or links restrained to each
other in such a way that between them there is a relative motion of the rotatory kind.
More precisely, said rotation is not free, but it is limited so that during the linear
forward/backward motion of a chain's end, the bending radius of the chain itself
would form.</p>
    <p num="0004">The previously described chains, even though they solve said technical
problem, they have an important inconvenience.</p>
    <p num="0005">This is caused by the considerable noisiness of the chains thus assembled. As
a matter of fact, in order to reduce the relative motion between them, two consecutive
links have on one of them two or more protrusions or "noses" in their contact part,
and corresponding blind or through slots on the other one. These protrusions block
the link's rotation by stopping with an impact at the bottom of the slot; the sequence
of impacts during the chain's motion is what creates its bothering noisiness.</p>
    <p num="0006">The object of the present invention is that of remedying the inconveniences
belonging to the earlier state of the art.</p>
    <p num="0007">The invention's object is thus an easily making and reliable cable carrying
chain link, that without jeopardizing the mechanical efficiency of the chain formed by
a number of such links, would make said chain significantly silent during its
operation.</p>
    <p num="0008">Briefly, according to the invention, a cable carrying chain link comprising a pair
of lateral elements mutually matching through a number of link studs, where at least
one of said lateral elements has elastic parts in the matching area with the other of
such lateral elements belonging to the following link.</p>
    <p num="0009">The cable carrying chain link according to the invention, is characterized by
the fact of having the features described in claim 1.</p>
    <p num="0010">Further advantageous characteristics are recited in the dependent claims.</p>
    <p num="0011">Other advantages, details and particulars of the cable carrying chain link
according to the invention, will be better highlighted through an examination of the
following description, with reference to the annexed drawings wherein a preferred
embodiment is shown in an explanatory but not limiting way. <sl><li>Figure 1 is a perspective view of a cable carrying chain link according to the
invention;</li><li>Figure 2 is a partial perspective view of the link illustrated in figure 1; and</li><li>Figure 3 is a further partial perspective view of the link illustrated in figure 1.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0012">Referring to the previously described figures, the cable carrying chain link 1
according to the invention comprises a pair of lateral elements 2,3, connected to
each other through two link studs 4.</p>
    <p num="0013">Said lateral elements 2,3, have a number of complementary protrusions and
grooves in order to allow the matching between two consecutive links.</p>
    <p num="0014">More specifically, in the link 1 according to the invention, the lateral element 2
(to the left in figure 1) has a central hole 5 towards the inside of the link 1 itself, and,
lateral to it in a symmetric position, two protrusions or "noses" 6.</p>
    <p num="0015">Usefully, on each protrusion 6 a housing 7 is provided in order to receive an
elastic element, preferably a packing 8 of the O-ring kind.</p>
    <p num="0016">The other lateral element identified to the right in figure 1 and indicated with
the reference number 3 has towards the outside of said link 1 a central pin 9 fit for
the matching with said central hole 5, while lateral and symmetrical to it two slots 10
are suitable for the matching with said protrusions 6 equipped with 0-ring 8.</p>
    <p num="0017">The other parts of the lateral elements 2 and 3, have, as in the links known to
the state of the art, a pin 11 and a hole 12 respectively for the corresponding
matching.</p>
    <p num="0018">During the assembly of more consecutive links the central pin 9 and the slots
10 of one link will be matched with the central hole 5 and the protrusions 6 of the
other one as also each pin 11 will be matched with the respective hole 12.</p>
    <p num="0019">During the operation of a chain made with a number of links 1 according to the
invention, each time that a protrusion 6 hits the respective slot 10, it will do it with the
part that houses an elastic element, that is the packing 8 of the O-ring kind.</p>
    <p num="0020">In such manner, the limitation of the rotation between two consecutive links
does not occur anymore with a direct impact between the two links' parts, but instead
with the interposition of the rubber packing 8, which reduces the noisiness by
absorbing the energy caused by the impact .</p>
    <p num="0021">Obviously, several modifications, additions, adjustments, variations and/or
substitutions could be made to the illustrative embodiment previously described in an
explanatory but not limiting way, without falling out of the scope of protection as also
recited in the following appended claims.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A cable carrying chain link comprising a pair of lateral elements (2,3) mutually
matching through a number of link studs (4), characterized in that at least one of said
lateral elements (2) has elastic parts in the matching area with the other of such
lateral elements (3) belonging to the following link (1).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The cable carrying chain link according to claim 1, characterized in that one of
said lateral elements (2) has a central hole (5) and a number of protrusions (6)
towards the inside of said link (1) arranged symmetrically to said central hole (5),
whereas the other of said lateral elements (3) has towards the outside of such link (1)
a central pin (9) ad a number of slots (10) that can be matched to said central hole
(5) and to the protrusions (6) respectively.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The cable carrying chain link according to claim 2, characterized in that said
protrusions (6) each have a housing (7) suitable for receiving a packing (8).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The cable carrying chain link according to claim 3, characterized in that said
packing (8) is of the O-ring kind.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
