<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1246245-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1246245" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="18947427" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021002">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1246245-A2" status="new" fvid="23561140">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1246245</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021002</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02252041-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02252041</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020321</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001093044-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001093044</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010328</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01L  27/28        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01L  27/32        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01L  51/50        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01L  51/50        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H05B  33/02        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H05B  33/02        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H05B  33/12        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H05B  33/12        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H05B  33/22        20060101AFI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H05B  33/22        20060101CFI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H01L  27/32</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Organische elektrolumineszente Anzeigevorrichtung</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Organic electroluminescence display panel</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Panneau d'affichage électroluminescent organique</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>PIONEER CORP</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>PIONEER CORPORATION</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Pioneer Corporation</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>4-1 Meguro 1-chome</street>
              <city>Meguro-ku, Tokyo</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MIYAKE TAKAKO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NAGAYAMA KENICHI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MIYAKE, TAKAKO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NAGAYAMA, KENICHI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Miyake, Takako, Corporate Res. and Development Lab</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Pioneer corporation, 1-1, Fujimi 6-chome</street>
              <city>Tsurugashima-shi, Saitama</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Nagayama, Kenichi, Corp. Res. and Development Lab.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Pioneer Corporation, 1-1, Fujimi 6-chome</street>
              <city>Tsungashima-shi, Saitama</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Haley, Stephen</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>GILL JENNINGS &amp;amp; EVERY, Broadgate House, 7 Eldon Street</street>
              <city>London EC2M 7LH</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>An organic electroluminescence (EL) display panel
comprising a plurality of EL elements arranged through an
insulating film, each of said EL elements including a first
display electrode, at least one organic functional layer
containing a light emitting layer of organic compound and a second
display electrode which are successively stacked on a substrate,
wherein said insulating film has an OD value of 0. 5 or more
in a visible light range.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="86"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">This invention relates to an organic electroluminescence
(hereinafter referred to as EL) display panel with a plurality
of organic EL elements formed in a prescribed pattern on a
substrate. Each of the EL elements is composed of at least one
thin film (hereinafter referred to as an organic functional
layer) containing a light emitting layer of an organic compound
material which exhibits EL emitting light due to current
injection.</p>
    <p num="0002">The organic EL element includes an anode transparent
electrode, an organic functional layer and a cathode metallic
layer which are successively stacked on a transparent substrate.
The organic functional layer may be e.g. a single layer of a
light emitting layer; a double layer structure composed of an
organic hole transporting layer and a light emitting layer; a
triple layer structure composed of an organic hole transporting
layer, a light emitting layer and an organic layer electron
transporting layer; or a laminated structure with an electron-or
hole-injected layer inserted between these suitable layers.</p>
    <p num="0003">The organic EL display panel with a plurality of organic
EL elements formed in a prescribed pattern on a substrate can 
constitute a matrix display panel. The matrix display panel,
as disclosed in JP-A-8-315981, can provide a full-color display.
The full-color display is a light emitting device having an image
display arrangement consisting of a plurality of light-emitting
pixels of organic EL elements arranged in rows and columns which
are orthogonal to each other. For example, the matrix display
type of display panel includes a plurality of EL elements, each
including a row electrode containing a transparent electrode
layer, an organic functional layer and a column electrode
containing a metallic electrode layer orthogonal to the row
electrode, which are successively stacked on a substrate, and
a stripe or grid-like insulating film. The row electrodes, each
being formed in a belt shape, are arranged in parallel to one
another at prescribed intervals. The column electrodes are also
arranged likewise. In this way, the matrix display type of
display panel has an image display arrangement consisting of
a plurality of light emitting pixels of organic EL elements
located at crossing points of electrodes in a plurality of rows
and columns.</p>
    <p num="0004">Traditionally, the insulating filmwas made of a relatively
transparent material such as polyimide, or material used in the
black matrix of a liquid crystal display.</p>
    <p num="0005">In the organic EL display panel, generally, the column
electrode was made of a metallic material such as Al in view
of a work function. However, since the metallic electrode layer 
of e.g. Al has a high reflectance to visible light, a part of
external light incident on the organic EL display panel from
the outside is reflected by the column electrode and is emitted
from the substrate surface. A part of the external light is
also reflected by the substrate itself and becomes reflected
light. Therefore, the organic EL display panel itself has a
high reflectance and hence could not provide the display with
high contrast.</p>
    <p num="0006">In order to solve the above problem, JP-A-7-142170
discloses an organic EL displaypanel whose contract was improved
by providing a polarized layer outside the row electrode.
However, a polarized filter which is used as the polarized layer
is not only expensive, but has high dependency of the reflectance
on an angle. This presented a problem that the contrast largely
varies according to the viewing angle.</p>
    <p num="0007">The inventors of this invention have first found the
relationship between the reflectance of an insulating film and
an OD value thereof and succeeded in specifying the OD value
which is indispensable to obtain a good reflectance for an organic
EL display panel.</p>
    <p num="0008">The invention has been accomplished to solve the above
problem, and intends to provide an organic EL display panel with
improved contrast. </p>
    <p num="0009">In order to attain the above object, according to a first
aspect of the invention, there is provided an organic
electroluminescence (EL) display panel comprising a plurality
of EL elements arranged through an insulating film, each of said
EL elements including a first display electrode, at least one
organic functional layer containing a light emitting layer of
organic compound and a second display electrode which are
successively stacked on a substrate, wherein said insulating
film has an OD value of 0. 5 or more in a visible light range.</p>
    <p num="0010">According to a second aspect of the invention, in the
organic EL display panel according to the first aspect, said
insulating film has a current density of 10<sup>-8</sup>A/mm<sup>2</sup> or less when
a voltage of 30 V is applied.</p>
    <p num="0011">According to a third aspect of the invention, in the organic
EL display panel according to the first aspect, said insulating
film has a volume resistance of 1.0 x 10<sup>12</sup>·Ωcm or more.</p>
    <p num="0012">According to a fourth aspect of the invention, in the
organic EL display panel according to any one of the first to
third aspects, an outermost surface of said insulating film has
a sloping surface which slopes at an angle smaller than a vertical
angle to said substrate in an area oriented toward the surface
of said substrate.</p>
    <p num="0013">According to a fifth aspect of the invention, in the organic
EL display panel according to any one of the first to fourth
aspects, said insulating film is formed in a grid pattern in 
at least a part between said organic EL display elements.</p>
    <p num="0014">According to a sixth aspect of the invention, in the organic
EL display panel according to anyone of the first to fifth aspects,
said insulating film has a partition on at least a portion of
the outermost surface.</p>
    <p num="0015">According to a seventh aspect of the invention, the organic
EL display panel according to anyone of the first to sixth aspects
further comprises a lightproof layer on the surface of said
substrate.</p>
    <p num="0016">According to an eighth aspect of the invention, in the
organic EL display panel according to the seventh aspect, said
lightproof layer is an ND filter.</p>
    <p num="0017">According to a ninth aspect the invention, in the organic
EL displaypanel according to anyone of the first to sixth aspects,
said substrate is a lightproof substrate.</p>
    <p num="0018">According to a tenth aspect of the invention, in the organic
EL display panel according to the ninth aspect, said lightproof
substrate is an ND filter.</p>
    <p num="0019">In the drawings:-
<sl><li>Fig. 1 is a partially enlarged front view when an organic
EL display panel according to this invention;</li><li>Fig. 2 is a partial sectional view taken in line A-A in
the organic EL display panel shown in Fig. 1;</li><li>Fig. 3 is a partial sectional view taken in line C-C in 
the organic EL display panel shown in Fig. 1;</li><li>Fig. 4 is a graph showing the relationship between the
OD value and reflectance of an insulating film;</li><li>Fig. 5 is a graph showing a change in the reflectance in
a visible light range of three insulating films having different
OD values;</li><li>Fig. 6 is a graph showing angle dependency of the
reflectance in a visible light range of a circularly polarizing
plate;</li><li>Fig. 7 is a graph showing angle dependency of the
reflectance in a visible light range of a circularly polarizing
plate;</li><li>Fig. 8 is a graph showing angle dependency of the
reflectance in a visible light range of an ND filter;</li><li>Fig. 9 is a graph showing angle dependency of the
reflectance in a visible light range of an ND filter and a
circularly polarizing plate;</li><li>Fig. 10 is a view for explaining the method of measuring
the angle dependency of the reflectance of an ND filter and a
circularly polarizing plate; and</li><li>Fig. 11 is a view for explaining the method of measuring
the angle dependency of the reflectance of a circularly
polarizing plate.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0020">Now referring to the drawings, an explanation will be given
of embodiments of this invention.</p>
    <p num="0021">Fig. 1 is a partially enlarged front view when an organic
EL display panel is viewed from the front. The organic EL display
panel has an image display arrangement region 1a including a
plurality of light emitting pixels 1, each consisting of light
emitting segments of red (R), green (G) and blue (B), arranged
in a matrix shape on a transparent substrate 2 made of e.g. glass .
The organic EL display panel has first display electrode lines
3, i.e. anodes which are a plurality of stripes of transparent
electrodes in parallel in a horizontal direction, and second
display electrodes 4, i.e. cathodes which are a plurality of
metallic electrodes in parallel in a vertical direction.
Light-emitting segments, i.e. organic EL elements are formed
at points of transparent electrodes 3a where the anodes and the
cathodes cross each other. A black insulating layers 5 are
formed in a grid pattern so as to surround each of the organic
EL elements.</p>
    <p num="0022">Fig. 2 is a partial sectional view taken in line A-A in
the organic EL display panel shown in Fig. 1. Fig. 3 is a partial
sectional view taken in line C-C in the organic EL display panel
shown in Fig. 1. As seen from Figs. 2 and 3, the organic EL
elements 7 each includes the first display electrode line 3,
at least one organic functional layer 6 and the second display
electrode line 4, which are successively stacked on the substrate 
2.</p>
    <p num="0023">The black insulating film 5 is formed between the
respective organic EL elements 7. The outermost surface has
a sloping surface which slopes at an angle  smaller than a vertical
angle to the substrate in an area oriented toward the surface
D of the substrate. Namely, the apex E of the black insulating
film 5 is "tapered". If the sloping angle of the outermost
surface of the black insulating layer 5 is vertical or more,
the organic functional layer 6 and/or the second display
electrode 4 will be separated by the apex of the black insulating
film 5. The organic functional layer 6 is peeled from the portion
or moisture invasion from this portion will generate a
non-light-emitting area. For this reason, the sloping angle
of the outermost surface of the black insulating film 5 must
be smaller than vertical, i.e. the apex must have a tapered shape.</p>
    <p num="0024">Each of the organic EL elements 7 is manufactured as follows .
First, the anode 3, which is the first display electrode which
is transparent and made of indium/tin oxide (ITO), is deposited
on a transparent glass substrate 2 by vacuum evaporation or
sputtering. The black insulating film 5 is formed on the first
display electrode except the area where the pixel is formed by
photolithography or like in the first display electload. The
organic functional layer 6 is formed on the black insulating
film 5 by successively vacuum-evaporating a hole injection layer
of copper phthalocyanine, a hole transporting layer of TPD 
(triphenylamine derivative) and a light emitting layer of Alq<sub>3</sub>
(alumi chelate complex) and an electron injection layer of
Li<sub>2</sub>O(lithium oxide). Further, by vacuum evaporation, the
cathode 4 of Al, which is the second display electrode, is
deposited on the organic functional layer 6 so that it is opposite
to the electrode pattern of the anode 3. Finally, as the measure
for humidity resistance, the organic EL element 7 and the black
insulating film 5 are covered with a sealing can on which adsorbent
capable of adsorbing water is pasted, or an inorganic passivation
film (not shown), etc. Thus, the organic EL element display
panel is completed.</p>
    <p num="0025">In practical use, the black insulating film of the organic
EL display panel has preferably reflectance of the order of 10 %
or less to visible light. Use of the black insulating film having
the reflectance larger than this value cannot provide good
contrast. In order to overcome such an inconvenience, for the
purpose of investigating the relationship between the OD value
(log value of the reciprocal of transmittance) and the
reflectance of the black insulating film, the black insulating
film and Al were successively deposited on the glass substrate
equipped with ITO. Under this condition, the OD value of the
black insulating film and the reflectance thereof from the glass
substrate corresponding to each OD value were measured in a
visible light range (400 - 700 nm) . Fig. 4 shows the relationship
therebetween. Incidentally, a spectrophotometer which is 
commercially available was used for measurement of the
reflectance.</p>
    <p num="0026">As seen from Fig. 4, at the OD value of 1.0 or more, the
reflectance is fixed to 6 - 7 % regardless with the OD value.
Even if the OD value is further enhanced, the reflectance is
not improved. On the other hand, if the OD value is lowered,
the reflectance abruptly rises at the OD value of 0.5 or less.</p>
    <p num="0027">Where the black insulating film is used as the black matrix
for a liquid crystal display, the transmitted light of backlight
must be cut off substantially completely. To this end, the black
insulating film must have the OD value of 2.0 or more. On the
other hand, in the case of the organic EL display panel, as seen
from Fig. 4, if the OD value is 0.5 or more, the black insulating
film can have the necessary and minimum reflectance of the order
of 10 % or less.</p>
    <p num="0028">In order to investigate the reflectance of the organic
EL display panel actually, using three kinds of insulating films:
a conventional insulating film having the OD value of 0.02, and
black insulating films having the OD values of 0.68 and 1.21,
respectively, organic EL display panels each having a light
emitting area of 1.15 x 10<sup>-2</sup>mm<sup>2</sup> for each pixel and opening rate
of 60 % were made. Under this condition, the reflectances and
their average were measured in the visible light range. The
measurement result is shown in Fig. 5.</p>
    <p num="0029">In the organic EL display panel using the conventional 
insulating film having the OD value of 0.02, the reflectance
is 63.7 % in the average. With the black insulating film having
the OD value of 0.68, the reflectance is 45.9 %, and with the
black insulating film having the OD value of 1.21, the reflectance
is 45.4 %. From such a result, it can be seen that like the
result of Fig. 4, the reflectance in the organic EL display panel
also falls until the OD value reaches about 0.7 but does not
almost fall even when the OD value exceeds 0.7.</p>
    <p num="0030">Meanwhile, generally, the OD value of the black insulating
film is adjusted by the density of carbon or organic pigment
which must be contained in the resin which is a material for
the black insulating film. The OD value rises as the density
of the carbon or organic pigment rises. However, as the density
of the organic pigment rises, the fluidity of the resin
deteriorates. As a result, after the black insulating film has
been formed, the sloping angle of its outermost surface becomes
vertical or more. Thus, as described above, the organic
functional layer and second display electrode formed on the black
insulating film are separated by the apex of the black insulating
film, thereby generating a non-light-emitting area.</p>
    <p num="0031">Further, as the density of carbon increases, the insulating
property of the black insulating film deteriorates. In the case
of the black matrix of the liquid crystal display, in view of
the structure, the insulating property is not required for the
black matrix. In the case of the organic EL display panel, in 
a usual light-emitting step, a forward voltage is applied between
the anode and cathode so that a current flows through the element.
Thus, the black insulating film is not required to have so high
a value as long as it is in a level not causing short-circuiting
between the cathode and anode. However, as disclosed in
JP-A-4-308687 and JP-A-6-301355, the organic EL display panel
requires a step of applying a reverse biasing voltage in which
a reverse voltage is applied between the cathode and the anode
during non-light-emission for the purpose of suppressing
attenuation of the electric characteristic and preventing false
light emission due to the leak current supplied to a non-selected
pixel. Where the reverse voltage is applied, the organic EL
element has a semiconductive characteristic. Therefore, a
current is difficult to flow to the element. In this case, if
the insulating property of the black insulating film is not
sufficient, the current flows toward the black insulating film
but not to the element. This cannot provide a sufficient effect
of applying the reverse biasing voltage.</p>
    <p num="0032">Further, where photosensitive resin is used as a material
of the black insulating film, a high density of the carbon or
pigment in the resin provides a very low transmittance of the
film. This gives rise to insufficient exposure when the black
insulating film is patterned by photolithography and difficulty
to see an alignment mark or anode pattern during mask alignment
for patterning, which results in misalignment after the 
patterning. Further, where the black substance such as the
carbon or pigment with a high density is dispersed in the resin,
owing to its precipitation and agglomeration, the can-stability
of the material deteriorates, or the remainder is apt to remain
on the ITO which constitutes the anode after development.</p>
    <p num="0033">As described above, when the density of the carbon and
pigment contained in the resin is increased to increase the OD
value, the above disadvantage occurs. For this reason, the
density must be adjusted taking this fact into consideration.</p>
    <p num="0034">In order to investigate the correlation between the OD
value of the black insulator and its insulating property and
edge shape, several samples were prepared under the conditions
described below.</p>
    <heading>Sample A</heading>
    <p num="0035">Transparent electrodes were patterned in stripes each
having a width of 2 mm on a glass substrate. A black insulating
film of resin containing carbon with a density of 7 % and organic
pigment with a density of 7 % is deposited thereon. Al films
each having a width of 2 mm were deposited substantially
perpendicularly to the transparent electrodes.</p>
    <heading>Sample B</heading>
    <p num="0036">Sample B was prepared under the same condition as sample
A except using the black insulating film of the resin containing
only carbon with a density of 12 %.</p>
    <heading>Sample C</heading>
    <p num="0037">Sample C was prepared under the same condition as sample
A except using the black insulating film of the resin containing
only organic pigment with a density of 60 %.</p>
    <heading>Sample D</heading>
    <p num="0038">Sample D was prepared under the same condition as sample
A except using the black insulating film of the resin containing
carbon with a density of 12 % and organic pigment with a density
of 38 %.</p>
    <heading>Sample E</heading>
    <p num="0039">Sample E was prepared under the same condition as sample
A except using the black insulating film of the resin containing
carbon with a density of 16 % and organic pigment with a density
of 34 %.</p>
    <heading>Sample F</heading>
    <p num="0040">Sample F was prepared under the same condition as sample
A except using the black insulating film of the resin containing
carbon with a density of 22 % and organic pigment with a density
of 28 %.</p>
    <heading>Sample G</heading>
    <p num="0041">Sample G was prepared under the same condition as sample
A except using the black insulating film of the resin containing
only carbon with a density of 30 %.</p>
    <heading>Sample H</heading>
    <p num="0042">Sample H was prepared under the same condition as sample
A except using the black insulating film of the resin containing 
carbon with a density of 30 % and an organic pigment with a density
of 25 %.</p>
    <p num="0043">For each of the samples thus prepared, a voltage of 1V
- 30 V was applied at 1V/sec between the transparent electrodes
and the Al films. At the time of the applied voltage of 30 V,
the density of the current flowing through an area of 2 mm x
2 mm of the black insulating film encircled by the transparent
electrode and Al film was measured. The maximum value of the
applying voltage was set at 30 V because this value corresponds
to the maximum driving voltage of the organic EL display panel
in matrix driving. For each sample, the shape of the apex of
the black insulating film was also observed. The result acquired
for each sample is shown in Table 1.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">OD value</entry><entry align="center">Carbon Densit y %</entry><entry align="center">Organic Pigment Density %</entry><entry align="center">Current Density (A/mm2)</entry><entry align="center">Apex Shape</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sample A</entry><entry align="center">0.69</entry><entry align="right">7</entry><entry align="right">7</entry><entry align="left">3.96x10<sup>-9</sup></entry><entry align="left">taper</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sample B</entry><entry align="center">0.81</entry><entry align="right">12</entry><entry align="right">0</entry><entry align="left">10<sup>-3</sup> or more</entry><entry align="left">taper</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sample C</entry><entry align="center">0.85</entry><entry align="right">0</entry><entry align="right">60</entry><entry align="left">2.06x10<sup>-10</sup></entry><entry align="left">non-taper</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sample D</entry><entry align="center">1.42</entry><entry align="right">12</entry><entry align="right">38</entry><entry align="left">1.08x10<sup>-10</sup></entry><entry align="left">non-taper</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sample E</entry><entry align="center">1.45</entry><entry align="right">16</entry><entry align="right">34</entry><entry align="left">2.23x10<sup>-8</sup></entry><entry align="left">non-taper</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sample F</entry><entry align="center">1.51</entry><entry align="right">22</entry><entry align="right">28</entry><entry align="left">8.37x10<sup>-6</sup></entry><entry align="left">non-taper</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sample G</entry><entry align="center">1.68</entry><entry align="right">30</entry><entry align="right">0</entry><entry align="left">10<sup>-3</sup> or more</entry><entry align="left">taper</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sample H</entry><entry align="center">1.82</entry><entry align="right">30</entry><entry align="right">25</entry><entry align="left">10<sup>-3</sup> or more</entry><entry align="left">non-taper</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0044">When a reverse voltage of 30 V was applied to the organic
EL element, the measured current density of the current flowing
through the organic EL element was an order of 10<sup>-7</sup>/mm<sup>2</sup>. 
Therefore, when the voltage of 30 V is applied to the black
insulating film, if the current density is 10<sup>-7</sup>A/mm<sup>2</sup> or more,
in the organic EL display panel, in the step of applying the
reverse voltage, the current becomes difficult to flow to the
organic EL element, but flows to the black insulating film. For
this reason, at the applied voltage of 30V, the black insulating
film must provide a current density of at least an order of 10<sup>-8</sup>A/mm<sup>2</sup>
or less.</p>
    <p num="0045">In view of the above result, it can be seen that the black
insulating film containing carbon with an increased density or
only containing the carbon in order to increase the OD value
cannot provide sufficient insulating property. If the content
density of the organic pigment is increased in order to increase
the OD value, the apex of the black insulating film cannot hold
a taper shape. In this way, where the OD value is too high,
the above bad effects occur in the black insulating film used
in the organic EL display panel.</p>
    <p num="0046">Thus, it can be seen that in practical use, the black
insulating film used in the organic EL display panel must satisfy
not only the condition that the OD value is 0.5 or more, but
also the condition of the property of high insulation and a taper
shape of the apex after it has been formed.</p>
    <p num="0047">Although examples of the measured result are illustrated
in Table 1, the OD value and content density of carbon and organic
pigment for satisfying the above conditions necessarily vary 
according to the kind and property of the carbon, organic pigment
and resin.</p>
    <p num="0048">Now, in order to decide the insulating property of the
black insulating film quantitatively, the volume resistance was
measured for each of the samples A, C and E which have sufficient
insulating property enough to be used as the black insulating
material of the organic EL display panel from the results shown
in Table 1 and the samples F and Hwhich are short of the insulating
property. The measured results are shown in Table 2.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Volume Resistance (Ω • cm)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sample A</entry><entry align="center">1.15 x 10<sup>12</sup></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sample C</entry><entry align="center">1.24 x 10<sup>12</sup></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sample E</entry><entry align="center">1.05 x 10<sup>12</sup></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sample F</entry><entry align="center">9.20 x 10<sup>11</sup></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sample H</entry><entry align="center">8.96 x 10<sup>11</sup></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0049">As seen from Table 2, in order to exclude the samples F
and H which are short of the insulating property, the black
insulating film used in the organic EL display panel must have
at least the volume resistance of 1.00 x 10<sup>12</sup> Ω • cm.</p>
    <p num="0050">Incidentally, this invention can be applied to not only
the organic EL display panel as shown in Figs. 2 and 3, but also
the organic EL display panel as disclosed in JP-A-8-315981 in
which partitions for polarizing the second electrodes are
extended in parallel between the second display electrodes. In
this case, the partition for polarizing the second display 
electrode is formed partially on the outermost surface of the
black insulating film between the second display electrodes.</p>
    <p num="0051">This invention can be applied to not only the organic EL
display panel as shown in Figs. 2 and 3, but also the organic
EL display panel in which the insulating films in stripes are
formed for only one of between the first display electrodes and
between the second display electrodes.</p>
    <p num="0052">In order to improve the contrast of the organic EL display
panel, a lightproof layer such as an ND filter may be provided
on the substrate in the organic EL display panel using the black
insulating film which satisfies the condition described above.</p>
    <p num="0053">In order to confirm the effect of improving the contrast
by the ND filter, the organic EL display panel which satisfies
the condition described later was actually prepared. The
reflectance in a visible light range (400 - 700 nm) of the organic
El display panel and the average of the transmittance of the
opening were measured.</p>
    <heading>Embodiment</heading>
    <p num="0054">An ND filter having a transmittance of 45 % is provided
on the entire outer surface of the substrate of an organic EL
display panel and the black insulting film according to this
invention in a grid pattern is provided between the organic EL
elements. Thus, the organic EL display panel having an opening
rate of 40 % was prepared. Further, the reflectance in a visible
light range (400 - 700 nm) of the organic El display panel and 
the transmittance of the opening were measured in the average.</p>
    <heading>Comparative Example 1</heading>
    <p num="0055">An organic EL display panel was prepared on the same
condition as the above embodiment except that a circularly
polarizing plate corresponding to a polarizing layer which was
usually used is provided in place of the ND filter used in the
above embodiment and an ordinary insulating film is provided
in place of the black insulating filmused in the above embodiment.
Further, the reflectance in a visible light range (400 - 700
nm) of the organic El display panel and the transmittance of
the opening were measured in the average.</p>
    <heading>Comparative Example 2</heading>
    <p num="0056">An organic EL display panel was prepared on the same
condition as the above embodiment except that an ordinary
insulating film is provided in place of the black insulating
film used in the above embodiment. Further, the reflectance
in a visible light range (400 - 700 nm) of the organic El display
panel and the transmittance of the opening were measured in the
average.</p>
    <p num="0057">The measured results are shown in Table 3
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Reflectance (%)</entry><entry align="center">Transmittanc e (%)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Embodiment (black insulating film + ND filter)</entry><entry align="center">10.7</entry><entry align="center">46.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 1 (ordinary insulating film + circularly polarizing plate)</entry><entry align="center">6.3</entry><entry align="center">43.5 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 2 (ordinary insulating film + ND filter)</entry><entry align="center">14.7</entry><entry align="center">46.2</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0058">As understood from the above measured results, the
reflectance of an order of 10 % or less that is a condition giving
good contrast was acquired in the organic EL display panel
according to the embodiment, in which the ND filter is provided
on the substrate surface of the organic EL display panel.</p>
    <p num="0059">In the embodiment, although the ND filter having a
transmittance of 45 % was adopted, the ND filter
can have a further decreased reflectance by decreasing the
transmittance. For this reason, by adopting the ND filter having
transmittance approximately equal to that in Comparative Example
1 and the black insulating film according to this invention,
the reflectance of the organic EL display panel can be restrained
to the magnitude approximately equal to that in Comparative
Example 1.</p>
    <p num="0060">Further, since the transmittance of the ND filter can be
varied to any optional value, the ND filter having an optical
density most suited to a using environment.</p>
    <p num="0061">Angle dependency of the reflectance of the circularly
polarizing plate corresponding to the ordinary polarizing layer
and the ND filter used in this invention is shown in each of
Figs. 6 to 9.</p>
    <p num="0062">Fig. 6 shows a graph of the relationship between the
reflectance for each of view angles and wavelength of the 
reflected light when a square circularly polarizing plate is
rotated around the center line connecting the centers of opposite
two sides of the square as shown in Fig. 10. Fig. 7 shows a
graph of the relationship between the reflectance for each of
view angles and wavelength of the reflected light when a square
circularly polarizing plate is rotated around the diagonal line
of the square as shown in Fig.11. Fig. 8 shows a graph of the
relationship between the reflectance for each of view angles
and wavelength of the reflected light when a square ND filter
having a transmittance of 45 % is rotated around the center line
connecting the centers of opposite two sides of the square as
shown in Fig. 10.</p>
    <p num="0063">Fig. 9 is a graph shown the reflectance and wavelength
when the reflectance of a view angle of 20 ° is normalized assuming
that the reflectance at the view angle of 85 ° is 1 on the basis
of the measured results.</p>
    <p num="0064">As seen from Fig. 9, in the range of the wavelength of
e.g. 500 - 600 nm, in the circularly polarizing plate, the
reflectance at the view angle of 20 ° is about four to six times
as large as that at the view angle of 85 °. On the other hand,
the ND filter does not have almost such angle dependency. Further,
for each spectrum of the reflected light, the circularly
polarizing plate has a larger variation in the reflectance than
the ND filter has.</p>
    <p num="0065">As understood from the above description, the organic EL 
display panel in which the light-proofing layer such as the ND
filter is formed on the substrate in place of the ordinary
polarizing layer can provide good contrast without spoiling the
merit of a wider view angle than that in liquid crystal display
because it gives self-emitting light.</p>
    <p num="0066">Incidentally, in this embodiment, although the ND filter
was formed on the substrate surface to constitute a
light-proofing layer, the substrate itself may be used as the
light-proofing layer, for example, the ND filter may be used
as the substrate, thereby providing the same effect. Further,
the ND filter or light-proofing substrate can be subjected to
AR processing (which decreases the reflectance using the
interference of light) or AG processing (which decreases the
reflectance using the scattering of light) so that the
reflectance of the organic EL display panel can be decreased,
thereby providing good contrast.</p>
    <p num="0067">In accordance with this invention, by setting an
appropriate OD value for the insulating film used in an organic
EL display panel, the organic EL display panel can be provided
which gives improved contrast with a low reflectance.</p>
    <p num="0068">By defining the volume resistance and shape of the
insulating film, a reliable organic EL display panel can be
provided.</p>
    <p num="0069">By forming a light-proofing layer on the surface of the
substrate or using a light-proofing substrate, the organic EL 
display panel can be provided which gives more improved contrast.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>An organic electroluminescence (EL) display panel
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>an insulating film; and</claim-text><claim-text>a plurality of EL elements arranged through said insulating
film, each of said EL elements including a first display electrode,
at least one organic functional layer containing a light emitting
layer of organic compound and a second display electrode which
are successively stacked on a substrate,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein said insulating film has an OD value of 0. 5 or
more in a visible light range.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The organic EL display panel according to claim 1,
wherein said insulating film has a current density of 10-8A/mm2
or less when a voltage of 30 V is applied.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The organic EL display panel according to claim 1,
wherein said insulating film has a volume resistance of 1.0 x
1012·Ωcm or more.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The organic EL display panel according to claim 1,
wherein an outermost surface of said insulating film has a sloping
surface which slopes at an angle smaller than a vertical angle
to said substrate in an area oriented toward the surface of said
substrate.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The organic EL display panel according to claim 1,
wherein said insulating film is formed in a grid pattern at least
a part between said organic EL display elements.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The organic EL display panel according to claim 1,
wherein said insulating film has a partition on at least a portion
of the outermost surface.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>The organic EL display panel according to claim 1,
further comprising a lightproof layer on the surface of said
substrate.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The organic EL display panel according to claim 7,
wherein said lightproof layer is an ND filter.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>The organic EL display panel according to claim 1,
wherein said substrate is a lightproof substrate.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>The organic EL display panel according to claim 9,
wherein said lightproof substrate is an ND filter.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
