<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1222926-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1222926" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="11075025" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020717">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1222926-A1" status="new" fvid="23491618">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1222926</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20020717</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02250178-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02250178</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020110</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="IL-14084401-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>IL</country>
          <doc-number>14084401</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010110</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  31/715       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  31/715       20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  47/48        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  47/48        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08B  37/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08B  37/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61K  31/715</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61K  47/48K8</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08B  37/00M2F</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Kationische Polysaccharid-Zusammensetzungen</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Cationic polysaccharide compositions</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Compositions à base de polysaccharides cationiques</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>POLYGENE LTD</name>
            <address>
              <country>IL</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>POLYGENE LTD.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Polygene Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Migdal Eder 16</street>
              <city>Efrat 90435</city>
              <country>IL</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>DOMB ABRAHAM J</name>
            <address>
              <country>IL</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>DOMB, ABRAHAM J.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>DOMB, ABRAHAM J.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Migdal Eder 16</street>
              <city>Efrat 90435</city>
              <country>IL</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Baldock, Sharon Claire</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>BOULT WADE TENNANT, Verulam Gardens 70 Gray's Inn Road</street>
              <city>London WC1X 8BT</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>The invention provides a polycation composition comprising a polysaccharide
chain having an amount of saccharide units ranging from 2 to 2000, at least one
oligoamine directly grafted to said polysaccharide chain per each segment of 5
saccharide units, wherein said oligoamine is selected from the group consisting of
a linear, branched and cyclic alkyl amine having at least two amino groups, and at
least one further grafted group selected from the group consisting of a hydrophobic
and an amphiphilic group directly grafted to said polysaccharide chain per each
segment of 50 saccharide units, wherein said hydrophobic or amphiphilic group
includes an aliphatic chain of at least 4 carbons atoms.</p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a biodegradable polycation composition as well as
to a biodegradable polycation complex of said composition together with a
polyanidn.</p>
    <p num="0002">More specifically, the present application is directed to cationic polysaccharide
derivatives made from the conjugation of oligoamines onto a polysacchide chain
wherein said oligoamine conjugated polysaccharide further comprises hydrophobic
or amphiphilic groups along the polymer chain. The oligoamines having at least
two amino groups are conjugated with at least one oligomer per five saccharide
units. The hydrophobic groups including saturated and unsaturated hydrocarbons
derived from for example natural and synthetic fatty acids; cholesterol derivatives,
aromatic groups such as naphthyl and benzyl groups, and the like. The
hydrophobic and amphiphilic groups are positioned with at least one group per 50
saccharide units.</p>
    <p num="0003">Gene therapy is a process by which genes are introduced into cells which then
become mini-factories which manufacture and release essential compounds in
cells and tissue which improve the life of the patient. Gene therapy has the
potential to revolutionize the treatment of genetic disorders, diseases associated
with a genetic component like cancer, AIDS, and many other diseases. Gene
therapy may be the only remedy for some individuals who would otherwise die or
be severely disabled. Gene transfer may also be employed for systemic protein
and peptide-like hormone administration. Nucleic acid sequences coding for a
protein (insulin, growth hormone) would be administered to the patient allowing
endogenous production of their own medication.</p>
    <p num="0004">Successful gene therapy requires the identification of an appropriate therapeutic
gene for treatment of the disease, in addition to a delivery system by which that
gene can be delivered to desired cell type both efficiently and accurately. Early
attempts of gene transfer involved the removal of cells from the individual, and the
alteration of the cells in the culture by the introduction of a functioning copy of the
gene. The next step included grafting the genetically engineered cells back into the 
patient. This ex vivo approach to gene therapy is obviously limited to those target
tissues that are not undergoing frequent multiplication and cell generation that
could cause progressing elimination of the grafted cells. The ability of the altered
cells to efficiently recombine with the target tissue is another limiting factor of the
ex vivo approach since many cells do not exhibit the ability to recombine.</p>
    <p num="0005">The limitation and the complexity of the ex-vivo approach facilitated the
development of direct in vivo gene transfer methods. Direct gene therapy involves
the administration of the gene into the body, targeting of the gene to the desired
cells and into the nucleus of said genes, and expression of functioning gene
products therein. Currently there are two different approaches for direct gene
transfer. One is a viral approach and the other is a non-viral approach. Viral and
non-viral gene therapies differ in the methods used to deliver genes to the target
cells and direct the uptake of gene into the nucleus. Viral gene therapies employ
genetically engineered viral particles to deliver the gene to target cell, and non-viral
gene therapies employ gene delivery systems comprised of synthetic or
semi-synthetic gene formulations. The limitations of viral therapies relate to the
residual viral elements within the viral vectors which can be immunogenic ,
cytopathic, or recombinogenic.</p>
    <p num="0006">Antisense technology has introduced the possibility of down-regulating or
specifically turning off the expression of individual genes. This technology has
enormous therapeutic potential. Antisense oligodeoxynucleotides (AON or ODN)
constitute sequences of 15 to 21 nucleotides with the order of the nucleotides
providing the molecule with the specificity to target genetic material. An
oligonucleotide whose bases are tailored to complement part of a particular
mRNA, can bind to and complex with that section of the mRNA. This can prevent
gene expression which may prevent protein synthesis by passive or reactive
inhibition of mRNA translation. Antisense ODN's to DNA seem to inhibit DNA
transcription by formation of a triple helix.</p>
    <p num="0007">Antisense oligonucleotides enter cells by pinocytosis and/or receptor-mediated
endocytosis after binding to cell surface antigens. Uncharged oligomers enter cells
by passive diffusion and charged oligomers enter by endocytosis. It seems that 
oligomers are not internalized by cells very efficiently. Methods for improving
cellular uptake and biological efficacy of ODN's have been devised, including their
conjugation to a synthetic polypeptide poly(L-lysine) tail with or without transferrin,
or encapsulation in cationic or antibody - targeted liposomes.</p>
    <p num="0008">As with other modes of contemporary gene therapy, delivery remains a central and
crucial issue. For example, Antisense oligonucleotides per se are thought not to
cross the intact Blood Brain Barrier (BBB). There are no studies analyzing the
passage of antisense oligomers across the Blood Brain Barrier. Attempts to deliver
them across the BBB by hyperosmotic BBB disruption after conjugation or by
incorporation into liposomes have, as a whole, been unsuccessful. Direct injection
of free antisense results in their rapid breakdown.</p>
    <p num="0009">Although, most research in vivo gene therapy has focused on the use of
recombinant virus vectors, progress has been made toward developing non-viral
formulations of gene for in vivo human gene therapy. The advantages of non-viral
vectors are that they can introduce DNA into non-dividing cells, do not integrate
into the chromosome, do not posses infective risk, and are potentially less
expansive than viral vectors. The principle underlying non-viral gene delivery is
that the problem of delivering DNA in vivo is not significantly different from the
problem of delivering conventional drugs or biological products to intracellular
compartment in the body. Non-viral gene therapies involve known drug delivery
methods for the administration and targeting of genes to selected cells in vivo,
where they express therapeutic products.</p>
    <p num="0010">Various methods have been described for non-viral gene therapy, ranging from the
direct administration of "naked" plasmid DNA to the systemic administration of
complex synthetic formulations. Some approaches are aimed at developing
"artificial viruses" that attempt to mimic the process of viral infection using
synthetic or semi-synthetic components. Others apply the theory and method of
advanced, particulate drug delivery to administer DNA to selected somatic targets.
These approaches employ plasmid DNA complexes containing lipids, proteins,
peptides, or polymeric carriers. The principle disadvantage associated with
non-viral systems has been insufficient levels of gene expression, irreproducibility 
and significant variations in gene expression on various cell types.</p>
    <p num="0011">The two classes of synthetic gene delivery systems that have been investigated
most actively involve the use of either cationic liposomes or polycationic polymers.
The assembly of these systems is achieved by an electrostatic condensation of
the "anionic" DNA with the "cationic" moiety of either a lipid or a synthetic polymer.
The cationic polymer-based systems have been most widely associated with the
formulation of receptor-mediated gene delivery systems. This technique employs
the ability of receptors on the surface of a variety of different cells to efficiently bind
and internalize a ligand. Several ligands have been exploited for the efficient
internalization of DNA-ligands complexes. These include: asialoorosmucoid and
other galactosylated proteins which target the hepatic asialoglycoprotein receptor;
transferrin which binds to the transferrin receptor and mannosyl which is
recognized by the mannose receptor of macrophages. Targeting ligands are
covalently linked to a polycation polymer, typically to poly(lysine) derivatives, and
then form a ligand-poly(lysine)-DNA complex by the ionic interaction between the
positively charged poly(lysine) and the negatively charged DNA. Often, an
endosomolytic agent is added to the transfection mixture to induce endosomal
lysis and enhance DNA release from the endosome in order to achieve high
transfection efficiency. The efficiency of poly(lysine)-DNA conjugates in
transfecting numerous cell types in vitro has been demonstrated, but their
potential usefulness for in vivo human gene therapy is limited due to their
cytotoxicity.</p>
    <p num="0012">More advanced polymeric gene delivery systems employ macromolecules with a
very high cationic charge density that act as an endosomal buffering system, thus
suppressing the endosomal enzymes activity and protecting the DNA from
degradation. The high cationic charge density mediates both DNA condensing and
buffering capacity, that diminish the requirement for an endosomolytic agent
addition.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Polymers used in gene transfer</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0013">The polycations used for gene complexation are polyamines that become
cationic at physiologic conditions All polymers contain either primary, secondary, 
tertiary or quaternary amino groups capable of forming electrostatic complexes
with DNA under physiologic conditions. The highest transfection activity is
obtained at a 1.1 -1.5 ratio of polycation to DNA. The most studied polyamines for
gene transfer includes, poly(lysine) and its derivatives, polyamidoamine starburst
dendrimers, polyethyleneimine, natural and modified polysaccharides, and acrylic
cationic polymers. The details for each polymer class are described in Domb et al.
(A. Domb, M. Levy, Polymers in gene therapy, Frontiers in Biological Polymer
Applications, R.M. Ottenbrite (ed), Technomic, Vol. 2, 1999,1-16.).</p>
    <p num="0014">Polycations may be more versatile for use than the liposomes and other
conventionally used spherical gene carriers. Several polycations have been
reported to induce gene expression for example diethylaminoethyl dextran and
other cationized polysaccharides [F.D. Ledley, Huiman Gene Therapy, 6, 1129,
1995; Yamaoka et al. Chemistry Letters, 1171-72, 1998]. These polymers have
little structural similarity with each other except possessing cationic groups.</p>
    <p num="0015">Cationic polysaccharides have been used for gene delivery. Chitosan, a linear
cationic polysaccharide was suggested by several authors for gene delivery [K.W.
Leong et al, DNA-Chitosan nanospheres: Transfection efficiency and cellular
uptake, Proceed. Intl. Symp. Control. Rel. Bioact. Mater. 24:75-76, 651-652,
671-674, 1997; R. Richardson, H.V.J. Kolbe, R. Buncan, Evaluation of highly
purified chitosan as a potential gene delivery vector, Proceed. Intl. Symp. Control.
Rel. Bioact. Mater. 24:649-650, 1997] DNA-chitosan nanospheres were found to
be significantly less toxic than poly(L-lysine) or Lipofectin using the MTT test.
Compared to standard Lipofectamine mediated gene transfer, these nanospheres
yield lower levels of gene expression in HEK 293 (human embryonic kidney cells),
IB3 (bronchial epithelial cells) and HTE (human tracheal epithelial cells). Surface
modification of DNA/chitosan complex nanoparticles by covalently binding
poly(ethylene glycol), transferrin and mannose-6-phosphate receptor to facilitate
entry into cells and improve storage stability was also studied. The Purified and
hydrophobized chitosan has also been suggested as carrier for genes [K.Y. Lee,
I.C. Kwon, Y.H. Kim, W.H. Jo, S.Y. Jeong, Selfaggregates of hydrophobically
modified chitosan for DNA delivery, Proceed. Intl. Symp. Control. Rel. Bioact.
Mater. 24:651-652, 1997]. </p>
    <p num="0016">Midox (WO 95/30020) describes a polypeptide such as polylysine modified at the
g-amino group with a molecule bearing hydroxyl groups. Genzyme describes in
WO 97/462 lipid derivatives of short chain alkylamines such as spermine and
spermidine for use in gene transfection. For example one or two spermine or
spermidine groups attached to cholesterol via an amide or carbamate bonds. WO
98/27209 to Emory Univ. describe a range of modified cationic polypeptides based
on lysine for use in gene transfection.</p>
    <p num="0017">The polymers described in the prior art can be grouped into two catagories: One
including linear or dendrimeric polymers with random distribution of amino groups
which are part of the polymer backbone such as poly(ethylene imines),
poly(amido-amine) dendrimers, and poly(alkylamino-glucaramide). The second
including linear polymers with a single primary secondary or tertiary amino group
attached to the polymer units. Examples of such polymers are:
poly(dimethylaminoethyl methacrylates), dimethylamino dextran, and polylysines.</p>
    <p num="0018">All of the above polymers are polycations with a random distribution of the cationic
sites. This randomness is probably the reason for the fact that these polymers may
work for some nucleotides and cell types and not for others. Most of these
polymers are toxic to cells and non-biodegradable, while the polymers based on
amino acids such as polylysines are immunogenic.</p>
    <p num="0019">It can be said that in the prior art, little attention was given to:
<sl><li>1. the structure of the polycation, the charge density and space distribution
of cationic groups in the polymer to optimize complexation with anionic
nucleotides;</li><li>2. the type of cationic groups, primary, secondary or tertiary groups were
considered as cationic sites.</li><li>3. the toxicity and immunogenicity of the polymer;</li><li>4. the biodegradability and elimination properties of the polymer carrier;</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0020">In general, it has been believed that the cationic charge of the polymers is the
main factor important for complexation and transfection. Also, these cationic 
polymers did not result in high enough transfection yield for commercial interest in
ex-vivo experiments, in addition to animal experimentation.. The degradation and
elimination of the polymer carrier was not carefully treated and most polycations
described for use in gene therapy are not biodegradable and/or toxic.</p>
    <p num="0021">In designing a universal polycation system for gene delivery one should consider
the way in which a plasmid becomes active in the cell and tissue. The plasmid has
first to be protected from DNA degrading enzymes in the extracellular medium,
then penetrate the cell wall, protected from degrading systems, i.e. the lisosome
and enzymes, in the intracellular medium until it is internalized in the nucleus,
penetrate into the nucleus and being released in its active form from the polymer
carrier.</p>
    <p num="0022">This invention describes a versatile and universal polycation system based on
oligoamine grafted on natural or synthetic polysaccharides that is capable of
complexing various plasmids and antisense, administering them into various cells
in high yields and into the nucleus in active form to produce the desired protein.</p>
    <p num="0023">It is the objective of the present invention to provide polycations that:
<sl><li>1. better fit the complexation requirements for effective delivery of a
plasmid or an antisense;</li><li>2. biodegrade into non-toxic fragments at a controlled rate;</li><li>3. non-toxic and no-immunogenic in vivo;</li><li>4. form a stable enough complex with low and high molecular weight
polynucleotides including therapeutic plasmids and antisense.</li><li>5. provide effective polymeric delivery system that result in a high transfection
yield in a range of cells and in tissues.</li><li>6. can be reproducibly prepared at an affordable cost.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0024">Another objective of this invention is to provide a controlled release of DNA in
tissue or cell by complexing DNA with designed polymers that gradually
de-complex and release the DNA or by incorporation of the complexed
polynucleotides in a biodegradable matrix which will release the DNA in the site of
insertion for periods of weeks and months. </p>
    <p num="0025">Thus, according to the present invention there is a polycation composition
comprising:
<sl><li>a) a polysaccharide chain having an amount of saccharide units ranging from 2 to
2000;</li><li>b) at least one oligoamine directly grafted to said polysaccharide chain per each
segment of 5 saccharide units, wherein said oligoamine is selected from the
group consisting of a linear, branched and cyclic alkyl amine having at least two
amino groups; and</li><li>c) at least one further grafted group selected from the group consisting of a
hydrophobic and an amphiphilic group directly grafted to said polysaccharide
chain per each segment of 50 saccharide units, wherein said hydrophobic or
amphiphilic group includes an aliphatic chain of at least 4 carbons atoms.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0026">In another aspect of the present invention, there is provided a biodegradable
polycation complex with a polyanion comprising:
<sl><li>a) a polysaccharide chain having an amount of saccharide units ranging from
2 to 2000;</li><li>b) at least one grafted oligoamine per 5 saccharide units, wherein said
oligoamine is selected from the group consisting of a linear, branched and
cyclic alkyl amine having at least two amino groups; and</li><li>c) at least one grafted hydrophobic or amphiphilic group per 50 saccharide
units, wherein said hydrophobic or amphiphilic group includes an aliphatic
chain of at least 4 carbons atoms; complexed with</li><li>d) an anionic macromolecule selected from the group consisting of polynucleic
acids, proteins and polysaccharides that are anionic.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0027">In especially preferred embodiments of the present invention, said polycation has
a structure selected from the group consisting of a comb-like chain, a branched
chain and a cross-linked chain.</p>
    <p num="0028">In a preferred embodiment of the present invention said anionic macromolecule is
selected from the group consisting of a plasmid, an open chain polynucleic acid,
an oligonucleotide, an antisense, a peptide, a protein, an anionic polysacharide
e.g. heparins and combinations thereof. </p>
    <p num="0029">In another preferred embodiment of the present invention said polysaccharide
chain is selected from the group consisting of dextrans, arabinogalactan, pullulan,
cellulose, cellobios, inulin, chitosan, alginates and hyaluronic acid.</p>
    <p num="0030">In a further preferred embodiment of the present invention said saccharide units
are connected by a bond selected from the group consisting of acetal, hemiacetal,
ketal, orthoester, amide, ester, carbonate and carbamate.</p>
    <p num="0031">In an even further preferred embodiment of the present invention said
polysaccharide is a synthetic polysaccharide formed from the condensation of an
aldaric acid and a diaminoalkane.</p>
    <p num="0032">In a preferred embodiment of the present invention said grafted oligoamine is
grafted to said polysaccharide chain by a bond selected from the group consisting
of amine, amide and carbamate. In another preferred embodiment the oligoamine
has the formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/">NH<sub>2</sub>-[CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>x</sub>-N-(R)-CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>y</sub>-N-(R')-(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>z</sub>-]<sub>n</sub>-NH<sub>2</sub></st32:che>
wherein x, y, z are an integer between 0 and 4 and x+y+z is between 1 and 4 and
n is at least 1 when x+y+z=2 or more, or at least 2 when x+y+z=1 and wherein R
and R' groups are H or an aliphatic side group of 1 to 6 carbons.</p>
    <p num="0033">In an especially preferred embodiment of the present invention, said oligoamine is
a peptide of up to 20 amino acids wherein at least 50% of the amino acids are
cationic including lysine, ornithine and arginine.</p>
    <p num="0034">In a further preferred embodiment of the present invention said oligoamine is
selected from the group consisting of spermine and derivatives thereof.</p>
    <p num="0035">In an even further preferred embodiment of the present invention said oligoamine
is selected from the group consisting of a linear and branched ethyleneimine
oligomer having up to 10 ethylene imine units.</p>
    <p num="0036">In an even further preferred embodiment of the present invention said oligoamine
is selected from the group consisting of a a peptide consisting of up to 20 amino 
acids with at least 50% contain a cationic side group including, lysine, ornithine,
and diphthamic acid.</p>
    <p num="0037">In a preferred embodiment of the present invention said amphiphilic residue is
selected from the group consisting of fatty chains, phospholipids, cholesterol
derivatives, ethylene glycol oligomers and propylene glycol oligomers, wherein
said ethylene and propylene glycol oligomers have a fatty chain block on one. side.</p>
    <p num="0038">In a further preferred embodiment of the present invention said amphiphilic residue
is connected to said polysaccharide chain by a bond selected from the group
consisting of an amine, amide, imine, ester, ether, urea, carbamate and carbonate.</p>
    <p num="0039">In an even further preferred embodiment of the present invention said amphiphilic
residue facilitates the crossing of the polycation through biological membranes.</p>
    <p num="0040">In a preferred embodiment of the present invention said polycation composition is
not toxic or immunogenic.</p>
    <p num="0041">In an even further preferred embodiment, the composition of the invention further
comprises a ligand for facilitating the binding of said composition to a
predetermined type of cell or tissue.</p>
    <p num="0042">In further preferred embodiments of the present invention, there is provided a
biodegradable polycation composition as hereinbefore defined in combination with
cationic and nonionic lipids or in combination with polymers for enhanced cell
transfection.</p>
    <p num="0043">The invention further provides a pharmaceutical composition comprising a
polycation composition as described above, in combination with a
pharmaceutically acceptable carrier, said composition being prepared by methods
known per se utilizing standard pharmaceutically acceptable carriers as is known
in the art.</p>
    <p num="0044">In a preferred embodiment of the present invention said biodegradable polycation
composition can be used as a scaffold for cell growth.

Furtheremore said composition can be used for non-medical applications such as 
to provide cationic coating in the printing and electronic industry.</p>
    <p num="0045">The invention also provides a pharmaceutical composition comprising the
composition described above, in combination with amphiphilic cationic and/or
nonionic lipids and cationic and nonionic polymers generally used for nucleotide
delivery. Examples of lipids include DOTMA, DOTAP, DMRIE, GAP-DLRIE,
DODHF, aklylated spermine, and other derivatives described in: G. Byk and D.
Scherman, Exp. Opin. Ther. (1998) 8(9):1125-1141; D.A. Treco and R.F. Selden,
non viral gene therapy, Molec. Med. Today, 1995, 1(7):299-348)</p>
    <p num="0046">The present invention provides a range of biodegradable polycations based on
grafted oligoamine residues on synthetic or a natural polysaccharides which are
effective in delivering plasmids and antisense for a high biological effect. The
grafting concept where side chain oligomers are attached to either a linear or
branched hydrophilic polysaccharide backbone, allows two/three dimensional
interaction with an anionic surface area typical to the double or single strand DNA
chain. This type of flexible cationic area coverage is not available with non-grafted
polycations or low molecular weight cations. Low molecular weight amines and
their lipid derivatives such as the lipofectin and lipofectamine have a localized
effect on the DNA which the degree of complexation is dependent on how these
small molecules organized around the anionic DNA. Each molecule has to be
synchronized with the other molecules at all times of the transferction process
whereas when the oligoamines are grafted on a polymer they are already
synchronized and each side chain helps the other side chains to be arranged to fit
the anionic surface of the given DNA. By grafting the functional groups is an
average distribution along a polymer chain at a certain distance between each
other (for example, grafting an oligoamine chain every one, two, three or four
polymer unit may provide optimal complexation with various DNAs.</p>
    <p num="0047">The use of biodegradable cationic polyol carriers is especially suitable for
transfection and biological applications because they are water soluble and
miscible in aqueous vehicles. The resultant grafted polymers are water soluble or
dispersible in water, it can be readily transported to cells <i>in vivo</i> by known
biological processes, and acts as an effective vehicle for transporting agents 
complexed with it.</p>
    <p num="0048">The compositions of the present invention are composed of a natural or synthetic
polysaccharide backbone with a grafted complexation functionality, i.e. aliphatic
organic cationic residues containing at least two amino groups. The alkyl amino
cationic residues are distributed in an optimal charge distribution tailored for as
many plasmid or oligonucleotide for optimal transfection results. The polymer has
hydrophobic/hydrophilic side groups that allow penetration of the polymer-plasmid
complex into cells for transfection.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>Detailed Description of the Invention:</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0049">The present invention provides a new class of non-viral polymeric vectors that can
be used for both <i>in vitro</i> and <i>in vivo</i> transfer of biologically active molecules. In
particular, these vectors can be used for gene transfer applications. The
polycationic compositions of the present invention can achieve gene transfer
efficiencies <u style="single">in vitro</u> that are superior to commercially available cationic liposome
preparations. Further, the low toxicity and lack of serum inhibition of the
compositions is suitable for <i>in vivo</i> use. The present invention provides a vector
that can achieve <i>in vivo</i> gene transfer efficiencies that compare favorably to viral
vector systems. The present invention further provides a method to increase the
capacity of solutions to carry complexes of nucleic acids and the polymeric vector
without precipitation or toxic ionic effects on cells.</p>
    <p num="0050">Furthermore, the unique polycationic structure of this class of polymers associates
with many suitable bioactive molecules, including proteins and other compounds
that possess multiple anionic sites. The polymer can act as a carrier to deliver the
associated bioactive molecule, <i>in vivo</i> or <i>in vitro,</i> to the cells of interest for the
bioactive molecule.</p>
    <p num="0051">In addition, the unique polycationic structure of this class of polymers are
biodegradable and readily eliminated from the body after administration.</p>
    <p num="0052">In one aspect the invention provides a complex comprising a nucleic acid and a
transfection agent, wherein: <sl><li>i) the transfection agent is obtained by the conjugation of short aliphatic
oligoamine to a polysaccharide containing hydrophobic and/or amphiphilic side
groups to allow penetration into cells.</li><li>ii) the short aliphatic oligoamine conjugated to the polymer contains at
least two amino groups.</li><li>iii) The hydrophobic and/or amphiphilic sites attached to the polymer
are for example fatty chains, phospholipids or cholesterol derivatives or
ethylene or propylene glycol oligomers with or without a fatty residue block,
which have the capacity to allow penetration into cells. The density and quality
of the hydrophobic side groups are selected to allow optimal transfection both
in vitro (cells) and in vivo (humans).</li><li>iv) The transfection agent is able to deliver a gene, antisense or nucleic
acids into cells and/or nucleus, release them in active from to allow substantial
biological effect by the gene or antisense and, biodegrade into non-toxic
fragments that are eliminated from the cell or the body.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0053">As used herein the term "transfection agent" means any chemical agent capable
of facilitating the entry of a nucleic acid into a eukaryotic cell.</p>
    <p num="0054">As used herein the term "nucleic acid" means a polymer of nucleotides, and
specifically includes plasmids, coding DNA sequences, mRNAs, and antisense
RNA molecules. A nucleic acid can be single - or double - stranded. The nucleic
acids can also contain one or more substitute linkages. These substitute linkages
include conventional alternative linkages such as phosphorothioate and
phosphoramidate, and are synthesized as described in generally available
literature. Nucleic acids also include those nucleotides in which the sugar moiety
has been modified by, for example, substitution of one or more hydroxyl groups
with halogen, aliphatic groups, or functionalized as ethers, amines, or wherein the
ribose or deoxyribose is replaced with other functionally equivalent structures. In
particular, the sugar-phosphate backbone may be replaced with a
non-carbohydrate backbone such as a peptide or other type of polymer.</p>
    <p num="0055">As used herein the term "primary amine" means any amine that possesses one or
more primary amine functionality. </p>
    <p num="0056">As used herein the term "secondary amine" includes amine moieties having at
least two pendent hydrocarbon groupings, and also includes, in the appropriate
context, tertiary and quaternary amines.</p>
    <p num="0057">As used herein "a" can mean one or more, depending upon the context in which it
is used.</p>
    <p num="0058">As used herein "aliphatic" and "aromatic hydrocarbons" include both substituted
and unsubstituted compounds, wherein the substitution can occur in the backbone
or pendent groupings of the hydrocarbon. Aliphatic compounds may be branched
or straight chained.</p>
    <p num="0059">As used herein "polysaccharide" means, linear, branched or crosslinked natural or
chemically modified polysaccharides. It also includes synthetic copolymers having
at least 40% saccharide units in the polymer backbone. A particular example is
polyamides of glucaric acid with alkanediamines.</p>
    <p num="0060">As used here "oligoamine" means a linear, cyclic and branched alkaneamine that
contain at least two amino groups. The molecular weight of the oligoamine is
limited to about 2,000 Daltons.</p>
    <p num="0061">The present invention relates to a novel class of polycationic polysaccharides
having effective nucleic acid transfection properties and bioactive agent delivery
attributes. The polymers are obtained from the conjugation of an oligoamine to a
polysaccharide chain. The polysaccharide carrier, the oligoamine and the grafting
ratio bond type are selected to enhance the degree and efficiency of transfection.
For example, polymers can be selected based upon the density and distribution of
the cationic sites on the polymer to obtain transfection agents that are tailored to
the anionic charge distribution of the nucleic acid being transfected, and the
anionic charge distribution of the type cell being targeted. Various substituents can
also be incorporated into the polymer to affect the properties of the polymer by
improving the transfection efficiency thereof.</p>
    <p num="0062">The present invention provides (1) a class of polycationic polymers, (2) a class of
complexes comprising these polymers with nucleic acids, and (3) a class of 
complexes comprising these polymers with suitable anionically charged bioactive
agents. The class of polycationic polymers comprises products obtained by the
grafting of an oligoalkaneamine onto a suitable polysaccharide, wherein the
grafted oligoamine contains at least Two amines. in a particularly preferred
embodiment, the grafted primary amine has one primary amine and three
secondary amines.</p>
    <p num="0063">Examples of suitable polysaccharides include, for example, dextrans,
arabinogalactan, pullulan, cellulose, chitosan, inuline, hyaluronic acid, and
alginates having from 2 to 2,000 saccharide units. Other classes of
polysaccharides are polyureas or polyamides of aldaric acids such as mucic acid,
glucaric acid, galactaric acid, xylaric acid, and their various isomers
polycondenced with aliphatic diamines. The copolymerization of the comonomers
may be performed generally by methods known in the art, including by
condensation reactions. Examples of suitable polycondensation techniques are
described in detail in Kieley et al., <u style="single">J. American Chemical Society</u>, 116, 571-578
(1994), Kieley et al., U.S. Pat. Nos. 3,225,012; 5,434,233; 5,312,967; 5,473,035;
5,833,230; and 5,329,044; and Dewar et al.</p>
    <p num="0064">The ionic association of the polymer/nucleic acid charges neutralizes the anionic
charges on the nucleic acid and allows the complex to interact and bind more
favorably with the negatively charged cell surface. If an excess of cationic sites are
present on the polymer, i.e. more than are necessary to neutralize the anionic
charges on the nucleic acids, these excess cationic charges may facilitate the
attraction of the complex to the ionically charged surface of the cell, thereby
facilitating entry of the complex into the cell. The polymers may also compact the
nucleic acids upon complexation, which further enhances the likelihood of entry.</p>
    <p num="0065">Although the present invention is limited to grafted oligoalkylamines, various
substitutents can be incorporated into the polymer carrier. For example, the
hydroxyl groups on the aliphatic chain of the monosaccharides can be substituted
with aliphatic hydrocarbons, amides, azo, carbamate, carboxylic esters, ethers,
thioethers, thiols, fluorescent derivatives, and sulfonic acids. One is often able to
increase the hydrophobicity of the polymer (where hydrophobicity is desired) by 
alkylating the secondary amines with long chain hydrocarbons. Alternatively, one
may increase the amphiphilicity by attaching a polyethylene glycol (PEG) chain.</p>
    <p num="0066">The structure of the polymer can also be altered, by known techniques, to optimize
the transfection and delivery efficiency of the polymer for each cellular target on
the basis of the physiological and biological characteristics of that target. For
example, the efficiency of gene delivery to cells can be enhanced by the addition
of peptides with the nuclear targeting signal of simian virus 40 to the polymer.
Several protein ligands are also known that can be covalently coupled to the
polymer and then incorporated into a ligand-nucleic acid complex. The resulting
complexes retain their ability to interact specifically with cognate receptors on the
target cell.</p>
    <p num="0067">Another method for improving the efficiency of gene delivery is to enhance the
release of DNA from the endosome after it has entered the cell. Adenoviral
particles can be coupled to the polymer to increase this efficiency. Synthetic
peptides can also be designed and incorporated into the polymer in order to
enhance endosomal release.</p>
    <p num="0068">The biodegradable polycation compositions of the present invention are of general
use for gene transfer and bioactive agent delivery with respect both to cell type
and size of nucleic acid or bioactive agent because the transfection is driven by
ionic interactions. Any selected cell into which transfection of a nucleic acid or
delivery of a bioactive agent (via transfection or other means) would be useful can
be targeted by this method, by administering the composition in a suitable manner
to bring the complosition into contact with the selected cell, as is known in the art.
Cells can be within a tissue or organ, for example, supplied by a blood vessel into
which the composition is administered. The composition of the present invention
can be formulated into a slab, pellet, microsphere and nanosphere made of a
biodegradable component such as a biodegradable polymer or fat to allow
targeting and/or controlling long term release of the gene complex to the blood
system or to a specific site as known in the literature for common bioactive
molecules. Alternatively, for example, the composition can be directly injected into
the target tissue or organ. As a further example, the lungs can be targeted by 
inhalation or intratracheal injection of the complex or particles containing the
complex. The invention has application to all eukaryotic cells; it can be used
particularly for mammalian cells and subjects, such as humans, cows, horses,
sheep, pigs, rats and mice. Some examples of cells that can be targeted by the
composition of the present invention include fibroblasts, epithelial cells, endothelial
cells, blood cells and tumor cells.</p>
    <p num="0069">Due to the fact that the polyol backbone according to one of the embodiments of
the invention is both biodegradable and regularly imported into living cells as part
of normal biosynthetic processes, it is nontoxic and nonimmunogenic, which offers
a distinct advantage over viral vectors when used as transfection agents. Similarly
because polyols do not generally contain natural binding sites for serum, the polyol
backbone is not negatively impacted by circulating serum proteins such as
herparin and albumin. Complexes formed with the polymers thus reach targeted
cells intact without significant serum inhibition, in contrast to polycationic lipids
which are substantially impacted by natural systemic serums.</p>
    <p num="0070">The amount of DNA that is carried in solution can also influence the degree of
transfection of the composition. The concentration of DNA in solution is often
limited by its tendency to precipitate at higher concentrations. In some
applications, the DNA concentration in solution is limited to about 1.0 g/l.
Increased amounts of DNA-polymer in solution which does not precipitate, may be
achieved if proper methods of preparation and optimal polymer to DNA ratio and
polymer structure are used. In such preparations it may be possible to obtain
solutions carrying 20 grams of DNA per litter of solution.</p>
    <p num="0071">Suitable delivery and transfection conditions are when the cell and composition
temperature is between about 18°C and about 42°C, with a preferred temperature
being between about 22°C and about 37°C. For administration to a cell in a
subject, the complex, once in the subject, will of course adjust to the subject's
body temperature. For <i>ex vivo</i> administration, the complex can be administered by
any standard method that would maintain viability of the cells, such as by adding
the complex to a culture medium (appropriate for the target cells) and adding this
medium directly to the cells. The medium used in this method should be aqueous 
and non-toxic so as not to render the cells non-viable. In addition, the medium can
contain nutrients for maintaining viability of cells, if desired.</p>
    <p num="0072">The composition can be administered <i>in vivo</i> by parenteral administration, e.g., by
intravenous injection including regional perfusion through a blood vessel supplying
the tissue(s) or organ(s) having the target cell(s). Injectables can be prepared in
conventional forms, such as liquid solutions, suspensions, or emulsions. A slow
release or sustained release system can also be used, allowing the maintenance
of a constant dosage level.</p>
    <p num="0073">Other means of administration can include inhalation of an aerosol, subcutaneous,
intraperitoneal or intramuscular injection, topical administration such as to skin
wounds and lesions, direct transfection into, e.g., bone marrow cells prepared for
transplantation and subsequent transplantation into the subject, and direct
transfection into an organ that is subsequently transplanted into the subject.
Further administration methods can include oral administration, particularly when
the complex is encapsulated, or rectal administration, particularly when the
complex is in suppository form.</p>
    <p num="0074">A pharmaceutical composition according to the present invention can include the
composition and a pharmaceutically acceptable carrier suitable for the selected
mode of administration. A pharmaceutically acceptable carrier includes any
material that will not cause any undesirable biological effects or interact in a
deleterious manner with the biological host or with the components within the
pharmaceutical composition. A pharmaceutical composition can further include
other medicinal agents, pharmaceutical agents, adjuvant, diluents, stabilizers, etc.,
as long as they do not interfere with the action of the composition. Actual methods
of preparing such dosage forms are known or will be apparent to those skilled in
the art, (for example - Martin, E.W. <i>Remington's Pharmaceutical Sciences,</i> latest
edition, Mack Publishing Co., Easton, PA.)</p>
    <p num="0075">Transfections using combinations of a plasmid:polycation complex of this invention
and various cationic, anionic and amphiphilic polymers and molecules. the plasmid
dna complex consisted of plasmid dna, oligoamine polysaccharide condensing
agent and a peptide (a peptide described in u.s. patent application ser. no. 
07/913,669, filed jul. 14, 1992). addition of amphipathic polymers: polyethylene
glycol (PEG); polypropylene glycol (PPG) and PEG-PPG copolymers,
phosphatidyl choline, cholesterol derivatives, and non-ionic surfactants, the
transfection efficiency of the plasmid dna complex was significantly enhanced over
the plasmid dna complex alone or the polymers alone. The addition of an anionic
polymer or lipid may result in destabilization of the net positively charged plasmid
dna complex by its negative charge and thus may better release the plasmid in the
nucleus or in the other hand may de-complex the plasmid and the activity may be
reduced. Several mechanisms of action of amphipathic polymers may account
including: stabilization of plasmid dna complexes due to coating; increased cell
membrane permeability, thereby allowing easier passage of the plasmid dna
complex through the cell; membrane and/or volume exclusion, increasing the
concentration of plasmid dna complexes at the cell surface.</p>
    <p num="0076">Another objective of this invention is to provide a controlled release of biologically
active dna in tissue or cell by complexing them with the polycations of this
invention that gradually de-complex and release the biomacromolecule, DNA,
antisence, and a protein or a polysaccharide (heparin) or by incorporation of the
complex in a biodegradable matrix, which will release the DNA or DNA complex in
the site of insertion for periods of weeks and months.</p>
    <p num="0077">The following polymers, oils and surfactants may be suitable for use as
compounds which enhance gene transfection and/or prolong the localized
bioavailability of a nucleic acid: salts of hyaluronates; salts of alginates;
heteropolysaccharides (pectins); poloxamers (pluronics); poloxamines (tetronics);
polyethylene glycols; dextrans; polyvinylpyrrolidones; chitosans; polyvinylalcohols;
propylene glycols; phosphatidylcholines (lecithins); xanthan gum, polyethylene
glycol-polylactic -glycolic acid (PEG-PLA), polyethylene glycol-polyhydroxybutyric
acid (PEG-PHB), fatty acid and alcohols and their esters, glycofurol, cremophors,
and oil mixtures. These substances may be prepared as solutions, suspensions,
gels, emulsions or microemulsions of a water/oil (w/o), water/oil/water (w/o/w),
oil/water (o/w) or oil/water/oil (o/w/o) type. Oil suspensions of lyophilized nucleic
acid, such as plasmid DNA may be utilized. Carriers for these oil suspensions
include, but are not limited to, sesame oil, cottonseed oil, soybean oil, lecithins, 
tweens, spans and miglyols. by "solutions" is meant water soluble polymers and/or
surfactants in solution with nucleic acids. By "suspensions" is meant water
insoluble oils containing suspended nucleic acids. By "gels" is meant high viscosity
polymers containing nucleic acids. By "emulsion" is meant a dispersed system
containing at least two immiscible liquid phases. Emulsions usually have dispersed
particles in the 0.02 to 100 micron range. Nucleic acids in the water phase can be
dispersed in oil to make a w/o emulsion. This w/o emulsion can be dispersed in a
separate aqueous phase to yield a w/o/w emulsion. Alternatively, a suitable oil
could be dispersed in an aqueous phase to form an o/w emulsion. A
"microemulsion" has properties intermediate to micelles and emulsions and is
characterized in that they are homogenous, transparent and thermodynamically
stable. They form spontaneously when oil, water, surfactant and cosurfactant are
mixed together. Typically, the diameter of the dispersed phase is 0.01 to 0.1
microns, usually of the w/o and o/w type.</p>
    <p num="0078">The compounds which prolong the bioavailability of a nucleic acid may also
interact or associate with the nucleic acid by intermolecular forces and/or valence
bonds such as: van der waals forces, ion-dipole interactions, ion-induced dipole
interactions, hydrogen bonds, or ionic bonds. These interactions may serve the
following functions: (1) stereoselectively protect nucleic acids from nucleases by
shielding; (2) facilitate the cellular uptake of nucleic acid by endocytosis. To
achieve the desired effects set forth it is desirable, but not necessary, that the
compounds which prolong the bioavailability of a nucleic acid have amphipathic
properties; that is, have both hydrophilic and hydrophobic regions. The hydrophilic
region of the compounds may associate with the largely ionic and hydrophilic
regions of the nucleic acid, while the hydrophobic region of the compounds may
act to retard diffusion of nucleic acid and to protect nucleic acid from nucleases.
Additionally, the hydrophobic region may specifically interact with cell membranes,
possibly facilitating endocytosis of the compound and thereby nucleic acid
associated with the compound. This process may increase the pericellular
concentration of nucleic acid. Agents which may have amphipathic properties and
are generally regarded as being pharmaceutically acceptable are the following:
methylcelluloses, hydroxypropylcelluloses, hydroxypropylmethylcelluloses;
heteropolysaccharides (pectins); poloxamers (pluronics); poloxamines (tetronics); 
ethylene vinyl acetates; polyethylene glycols; polyvinylpyrrolidones; chitosans;
polyvinylalcohols; polyvinylacetates; phosphatidylcholines (lecithins); propylene
glycol; miglyols; polylactic acid; polyhydroxybutyric acid; xanthan gum. Also,
copolymer systems such as polyethylene glycol-polylactic acid (PEG-PLA),
polyethylene glycol-polyhydroxybutyric acid (PEG-PHB),
polyvinylpyrrolidone-polyvinylalcohol (PVP-PVA), and derivatized copolymers such
as copolymers of n-vinyl purine (or pyrimidine) derivatives and n-vinylpyrrolidone.
Nucleic acids may be loaded into biodegradable hydrogels such as crosslinked
polysaccharides, and PEG based gels by placing swellable hydrogel systems in
nucleic acid or complex solutions. Swellable hydrogels include but are not limited
to crosslinked oxidized arabinogalactan and dextran with a polyamine ;
calcium-crosslinked alginate, poloxamines (tetronics) and poloxamers (pluronics).</p>
    <p num="0079">While the invention will now be described in connection with certain preferred
embodiments in the following examples so that aspects thereof may be more fully
understood and appreciated, it is not intended to limit the invention to these
particular embodiments. On the contrary, it is intended to cover all alternatives,
modifications and equivalents as may be included within the scope of the invention
as defined by the appended claims. Thus, the following examples which include
preferred embodiments will serve to illustrate the practice of this invention, it being
understood that the particulars shown are by way of example and for purposes of
illustrative discussion of preferred embodiments of the present invention only and
are presented in the cause of providing what is believed to be the most useful and
readily understood description of formulation procedures as well as of the
principles and conceptual aspects of the invention.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>Example 1: Synthesis of Polycations</b>
    </heading>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Experimental section</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0080">All solvents and reagents were the best commercial grade available and were 
used as received. A sage-metering pump (model-365) was used. NMR spectra
were recorded on a Varian 300MHz instrument using CDCl3, D2O or d6-DMSO as
solvents. Values were recorded as (ppm) relative to internal standard (TMS).
Molecular weights of starting polymers and conjugates were determined on GPC
instrument (Spectra physics program) containing a pump, column (Shodex KB-804
or KB-803, Japan) and refractive index (RI) detector. Mw were determined using
pullulan standards of known molecular weights. Eluent used were: 0.05M NaNO3
for uncharged polymers and 5%(w/v) sodium phosphate monobasic in 3%
acetonitrile (pH=4.0) for the polycationic polymers.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Oxidation of Dextran</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0081">Dialdehyde Dextran (1) was obtained by reacting dextran (1, Mw=9.3 to 500 Kd) in
water with potassium periodate at 1:1, 1:3 and 1:5 (KIO4:Saccharide units) molar
ratio. The mixture was stirred at room temperature in the dark for 5h until a clear
solution was obtained. The resulting polyaldehyde derivatives were purified from
iodate (IO3<sup>-</sup>) and unreacted periodate ions (IO4<sup>-</sup>) by DOWEX-1 anion exchange
chromatography (acetate form), following an extensive dialysis against DDW
(12,000 cut-off cellulose tubing) for 2 days . The purified polyaldehyde was then
freeze-dried to obtain a white powder in 85% average yield. Aldehyde content of
oxidized polymers were determined by the hydroxylamine hydrochloride method
(table 1).</p>
    <p num="0082">Aldehyde content was determined by the hydroxylamine hydrochloride method.
Oxidation of pullulan, arabinogalactan, soluble cellulose, dextrin, and other
polytsaccharides was performed using the above procedure. Oxidation degrees
from 30 to about 60% of the saccharide units were obtained.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Dextran-Spermine conjugate (2)</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0083">1.0 gr. of dialdehyde Dextran (Mw=29 Kd, 50% dialdehyde) dissolved in 100 ml
DDW, was slowly added during 4h (Sage metering pump) into a Spermine solution
containing 1.25 gr. Spermine (1.0 equimolar to aldehyde) dissolved in 50 ml
Borate buffer (0.1M Boric-acid, pH=11.0). The purpose of the slow addition was to
minimize crosslinking of Spermine into the polyaldehyde chains. The mixture was
stirred gently at room temperature for 24h and 1.0 gr. of NaBH4 (10 molar excess 
to aldehyde) was added and stirring was continued at the same conditions for 48h.</p>
    <p num="0084">Then, another portion of borohydride (1.0 gr.) was added and stirring was
continued for another 24h at room temperature. The resulting light-yellow solution
was poured into a dialysis membrane (3.5K MWCO) and dialyzed against DDW
(3x5L) at 4oC changing the water every 8h. The purified solution was filtered to
remove insolubles, and freeze-dried.</p>
    <p num="0085">The synthesis was repeated several times and reproducible results were obtained
(table 2).</p>
    <p num="0086">Yield: 0.5 gr. (~25%, w/w). %N=12.0 ± 0.5% (elemental analysis) and 1.2-1.5
(mole amine per (g conjugate (TNBS).</p>
    <p num="0087">Alternatively, the resulted polysaccharide derivatives were purified at each step by
lyophilization and extraction of the low molecular weight components using
ethanol:water mixtures, dimethylsulfoxide and other solvents and mixtures that
dissolve the unwanted molecules without dissolving or affecting the
polysaccharide. Another procedure for purification of the desired polysaccharide,
either after oxidation or after conjugation of the oligoamine, or after reduction with
sodium borohydride, is by precipitation in a water miscible anti-solvent that
dissolves the low molecular weight molecules (i.e unreacted reagent or reaction
by-producgts) but precipitate the polymer. Usually, for an efficient purification the
reaction solution is concentrated to minimize the amount of anti-solvent needed for
effective precipitation. Suitable solvents include ethanol, propanols, and butanols.
Oxidizing agents may include sodium periodate, osmium tetraoxide,
permanganate, chromates and the like. Reducing agents such as sodium
cyanoborohydride and borane-amine complexes can be used.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Synthesis of Cholesteric acid N-hydroxy succinimide ester (3)</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0088">To 0.5 gr. of Cholesteryl chloroformate (1.12 mmole) dissolved in 25.0 ml of
anhydrous THF, was added 0.4 ml of anhydrous DIEA (2.5 eq.). The mixture was
cooled to OoC and 200.0 mg of solid N-hydroxy succinimide (1.5 eq.) were added
and stirring was continued for 2h at OoC and over-night at room temperature.
Solvent was removed under reduced pressure and the crude was redissolved in
50.0 ml of diethyl-ether. Then, the ethereal solution was washed with DDW 
(2x20ml) and brine (2x20ml), dried over anhydrous MgSO4, filtered and
evaporated to dryness. The crude was crystallized in DCM:MeOH (1:5), stored at
-20oC for 24h, filtered and dried in vacuum over P2O5.</p>
    <p num="0089">Yield = 0.5 g. (~85%). Rf (SiO2, 1% MeOH in DCM) = 0.65.</p>
    <p num="0090">1H-NMR (CDCl<sub>3</sub>): 5.422 (d, 1H, vinyl hydrogen of Chol), 4.597 (m, 1H, hydrogen
bearing substituted hydroxyl of Chol), 2.828 (s, 4H, -CH2CH2- of NHS group),
2.045 (m, 2H), 1.006 (s, 3H), 0.915 (s, 3H), 0.873 (s, 3H), 0.869 (s, 3H) and 0.675
ppm (s, 3H).</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Synthesis of Oleic acid (cis-9-octadecenoic acid) N-hydroxy succinimide
ester (4)</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0091">1.33 gr. of N-hydroxy succinimide (11.56 mmole, 1.5 eq.) and DIEA (1.35 ml),
were dissolved in 50.0 ml of anhydrous THF and gently stirred at 0°C under
nitrogen atmosphere. Then, Oleoyl chloride (3.0 ml, 85% tech., 7.8 mmole, 1.0
eq.) dissolved in 50 ml of anhydrous THF was added dropwise during 1h. The
mixture was gently stirred for 2h at 0°C and over-night at room temperature. The
resulting precipitate were discarded by filtration and the filtrate was evaporated
under reduced pressure, redissolved in small amount of DCM and purified over
silica-gel column using DCM as eluent. Fractions containing the product were
combined and solvent was removed under reduced pressure. The resulting white
solid was dried in vacuum over NaOH-pellets.</p>
    <p num="0092">Yield = 2.733 gr. (~92%).</p>
    <p num="0093"><sup>1</sup>H-NMR(CDCl<sub>3</sub>):0.874(3H, t,

C<u style="single">H</u><sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>5</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH=CH-CH<sub>2</sub>(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>5</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>CO-NHS), 1.38 (20H, m,
CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>(C<u style="single">H</u><sub>2</sub>)<sub>5</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH=CH-CH<sub>2</sub>(C<u style="single">H</u><sub>2</sub>)<sub>5</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>CO-NHS), 1.74 (2H, m,
CH<sub>3</sub>C<u style="single">H</u><sub>2</sub>(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>5</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH=CH-CH<sub>2</sub>(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>5</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>CO-NHS), 2.004 (4H, m,
CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>5</sub>-C<u style="single">H</u><sub>2</sub>-CH=CH-C<u style="single">H</u><sub>2</sub>(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>5</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>CO-NHS), 2.594 (2H, t,
CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>(C<sub>2</sub>)<sub>5</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH=CH-CH<sub>2</sub>(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>5</sub>-C<u style="single">H</u><sub>2</sub>CO-NHS), 2.83 (4H, s, NHS hydrogens)
and 5.34 ppm (2H, m, CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>5</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-C<u style="single">H</u>=C<u style="single">H</u>-CH<sub>2</sub>(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>5</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>CO-NHS).</p>
    <p num="0094">N-hydroxy succinimide derivatives of pivalic acid (C5-branched, 5), Hexanoic acid 
(C6-Linear, 6), Octanoic acid (C8-Linear, 7), Myristic acid (C14-Linear, 9)
were prepared similarly.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Synthesis of Lauric acid N-hydroxy succinimide (C12-Linear, 8)</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0095">It was prepared exactly in a similar way as in the preparation of oleic acid
N-hydroxy succinimide. In brief, 1.33 gr. of N-hydroxy succinimide (11.56 mmole,
1.5 eq.) and DIEA (1.35 ml) were dissolved in 50.0 ml of anhydrous THF and
gently stirred at 0°C under nitrogen atmosphere. Then, Lauroyl chloride (1.8 ml,
99% Sigma, 7.8 mmole, 1.0 eq.) dissolved in 50 ml of anhydrous THF was added
dropwise during 1h. The mixture was gently stirred for 2h at 0°C and over-night at
room temperature. The resulting precipitate were discarded by filtration and the
filtrate was evaporated under reduced pressure, redissolved in small amount of
DCM and purified over silica-gel column using DCM as eluent. Fractions
containing the product were combined and solvent was removed under reduced
pressure. The resulting white solid was dried in vacuum over NaOH-pellets.</p>
    <p num="0096"><sup>1</sup>H-NMR (CDCl<sub>3</sub>): 0.875 (3, t, C<u style="single">H</u><sub>3</sub>(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>9</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CO-NHS), 1.214-1.435 (18H, m,
CH<sub>3</sub>(C<u style="single">H</u><sub>2</sub>)<sub>9</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CO-NHS), 1.736 (2H, m, CH<sub>3</sub>(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>9</sub>C<u style="single">H</u><sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CO-NHS), 2.594
(2H, t, CH<sub>3</sub>(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>9</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>C<u style="single">H</u><sub>2</sub>CO-NHS) and 2.827 ppm (4H, s, NHS hydrogens).</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Synthesis of Stearic acid N-hydroxy succinimide (C18-Linear, 10)</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0097">1.33 g. of N-hydroxy succinimide (11.56 mmole) and DIEA (1.5 ml, 8.62 mmole)
were dissolved in 50 ml of anhydrous THF and gently stirred at 0°C under nitrogen
atmosphere. To this were added dropwise and during 1h a solution of stearoyl
chloride (2.35 g, 7.7 mmole) in 50 ml of anhydrous THF. After, the mixture was
stirred at 0°C for 2h and overnight at room temperature. Solvent was removed
under reduced pressure and the remaining white solid was redissoloved in 200 ml
of DCM. The organic phase were washed with DDW (2x100 ml), dried over
.anhydrous MgSO<sub>4</sub>, filtered and evaporated to dryness. The reaming solid was
dissolved in 100 ml of ethyl acetate and 200 ml of hexane and kept at -20°C
overnight. The resulting white crystals were collected by filtration and dried in
vacuum over NaOH-pellets. The crystallized product was free from unreacted acid
chloride as determined by <sup>1</sup>H-NMR. The remaining filtrate was also evaporated to 
yield the product contaminated with 10% of the starting acid as determined by
<sup>1</sup>H-NMR.</p>
    <p num="0098"><sup>1</sup>H-NMR of crystallized product (CDCl<sub>3</sub>): 0.867 (3H, t,
C<u style="single">H</u><sub>3</sub>(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>14</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CO-NHS), 1.234-1.453 (28H, m, CH<sub>3</sub>(C<u style="single">H</u><sub>2</sub>)<sub>14</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CO-NHS),
1.735 (2H, m, CH<sub>3</sub>(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>14</sub>C<u style="single">H</u><sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CO-NHS), 2.589 (2H, t,
CH<sub>3</sub>(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>14</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>C<u style="single">H</u><sub>2</sub>CO-NHS) and 2.828 (4H, s, NHS hydrogens).</p>
    <p num="0099">N-hydroxy succinimide derivatives of pivalic acid (C5-branched, 5), Hexanoic acid
(C6-Linear, 6), Octanoic acid (C8-Linear, 7), Myristic acid (C14-Linear, 9), Linoleic
acid (cis,cis-9,12-octadecedienoic acid) (11), and Linolenic acid
(cis,cis,cis-9,12,15-octadecatrienoic acid) (12) were prepared similarly.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Synthesis of di-Chol-L-Lysine-NHS (13)</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Synthesis of di-Chol-L-Lysine-OMe</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0100">0.122 gr. of L-Lysine monomethyl ester (5.05x10<sup>-4</sup> mole) was dispersed in 10.0 ml
of anhydrous DMF under nitrogen atmosphere. To this mixture was added 0.7 ml
of anhydrous TEA (4.5 eq.) and the mixture was cooled to 0°C using ice bath.
Then, 0.5 gr. of Cholesteryl chloroformate (2.2 eq.) was added and stirring was
continued for 2h at 0°C and over-night at ROOM TEMPERATURE. The mixture
was diluted with DDW (30.0 ml) and the product was extracted with diethyl ether
(4x50ml). The ethereal extracts were combined and washed with brine (2x50ml),
dried over anhydrous MgSO<sub>4</sub>, filtered and evaporated to dryness. The crude
product was purified by column chromatography over silica gel using DCM as
eluent.

Yield = 380 mg (~75%).
<sup>1</sup>H-NMR (CDCl<sub>3</sub>): 5.371 (d, 2H, vinyl hydrogen of Chol x 2); 4.757 (m, 2H,
MeOCOCH(<u style="single">CH</u><sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>NHChol)NHChol), 4.523 (m, 4H, MeOCOCH
(CH<sub>2</sub><u style="single">CH</u><sub>2</sub><u style="single">CH</u><sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>NHChol)NHChol), 4.316 (m, 2H, MeOCO-CH
(CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub><u style="single">CH</u><sub>2</sub>-NHChol)NHChol), 3.736 (s, 3H, methyl ester group), 3.154 (m,
2H, hydrogen bearing substituted hydroxyl of Chol x 2), 2.295 (m, 4H, x2 Chol),
1.003 (s, 6H, x2 Chol), 0.92 (s, 6H, x2 Chol), 0.871 (s, 6H, x2 Chol), 0.849 (s, 6H,
x2 Chol) and 0.671 (s, 6H, x2 Chol) ppm. </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Removal of the monomethyl ester group</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0101">200.0 mg of di-Chol-L-Lysine-OMe (0.2 mmole) were dissolved in 5.0 ml of THF.
To this was added 3.0 ml of 1 N NaOH aqueous solution (5 fold molar excess) and
the mixture was stirred over-night at ROOM TEMPERATURE. Then, pH was
adjusted to 1.0 using 1M aqueous HCI and THF was removed under a stream of
nitrogen. The resulting white suspension was extracted with diethyl ether (3x20ml),
dried over anhydrous MgSO<sub>4</sub> and evaporated to dryness. The crude was
crystallized in DCM:MeOH (1:5), stored at -20°C for 24h, filtered and dried in
vacuum over P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>.

Yield = 180.0 mg (~95%).
<sup>1</sup>H-NMR (CDCl<sub>3</sub>) showed a full removal of the methyl ester-protecting group.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Synthesis of di-Chol-L-Lvsine-NHS</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0102">150.0 mg of 5 (0.158 mmole), 5.0 mg of HOBT (0.2 eq.) and 70.0 µl of DIEA (2.5
eq.) were dissolved in 10.0 ml of anhydrous DCM. The mixture was cooled to 0°C
and 60.0 mg of EDC (2.0 eq.) were added and stirring was continued for 2h at 0°C
and over-night at room temperature. The mixture was diluted with DCM (15 ml)
and washed with DDW and brine (2x5ml, each), dried over anhydrous MgSO<sub>4</sub>,
filtered and evaporated to dryness. The crude product was purified by column
chromatography over silica-gel using DCM as eluent

Yield = 120.0 mg (~73%). The stracture was confirmed by <sup>1</sup>H-NMR.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Synthesis of di-Oleate-L-Lysine-NHS (14)</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0103">Di-Oleate-L-Lysine-NHS was prepared in a similar manner to
di-Chol-L-Lysine-NHS.

Yield: 76%, The stracture was confirmed by <sup>1</sup>H-NMR.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Hydrophobization of Dextran-Spermine conjugates with Cholestic acid
N-hydroxy succinimide (NHS-Chol, 15)</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0104">20.0 mg of Dextran-Spermine conjugate (2, ~26 µmol of free amine, TNBS
method) were dissolved in 0.5 ml DDW and diluted with THF (1.0 ml). The mixture
was vigorously stirred at room temperature using micro-stirrers and 1-20%
mol/mol of stock NHS-Chol solution in anhydrous tetrahydrofuran (THF) was
added. The mixture was stirred at room temperature for 24h and THF was 
removed by a flush of nitrogen at 40°C. Remaining mixture was freeze-dried and
the lyophilizate was suspended in 5.0 ml of diethyl ether to discard unbound Chol
groups, filtered and dried in vacuum.

Yield = 18.0 mg (~90% w/w).
<sup>1</sup>H-NMR (D<sub>2</sub>O:d<sub>6</sub>-DMSO 1:1) showed the existing of Cholesterol (Chol) peaks in
the region of 0.6-1.2 ppm. Peaks of Dextran-Spermine conjugates were not shifted
as a result of hydrophobization.

Content of bound Chol moieties in conjugates was determined by the degree of
reduction of amino-functionality using the TNBS method.
<sup>1</sup>H-NMR technique using external standard (benzene) was used for the
determination of Chol moieties in the hydrophobized conjugates.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Hydrophobization of Dextran-Spermine conjugate with Oleic acid N-hydroxy
succinimide (NHS-Oleate, 16)</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0105">Hydrophobization of Dextran-Spermine conjugate with oleate moieties was
prepared in a similar manner to the above, using NHS-Oleate (Sigma®) instead of
NHS-Chol.
<sup>1</sup>H-NMR (D<sub>2</sub>O:d<sub>6</sub>-DMSO 1:1) showed the existing of oleate peaks in the region of
0.87-1.74 ppm.

Content of Oleate moieties in conjugates was determined by the reduction in
amino-functionality using the TNBS method.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Synthesis of mPEG2000-PNF</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0106">10.0 g of mPEG2000 (5 mmol) were dried over-night with azetropic distillation in
toluene (100 ml). The crude was dissolved in anhydrous DCM (25 ml) and TEA
(2.8 ml, 4.0 equimolar). The mixture was cooled to 0°C and 2.8 g of p-nitro-phenyl
chloroformate (2.8 equimolar) were added. The mixture was stirred 4h at 0°C and
3 days at ROOM TEMPERATURE. Then, 150 ml of DCM were added and the
mixture was extracted with DDW (2x50 ml). The organic phase was dried over
anhydrous MgSO<sub>4</sub>, filtered and evaporated to dryness. The resulting oily product
was dissolved in small amount of DCM and added dropwise to a large volume of
diethyl ether (400 ml) and stored overnight at -20°C. Precipitate were collected by
filtration and dried in vacuum over P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>.
 
Yield = 9.0 g (~90% by weight to starting PEG).
<sup>1</sup>H-NMR (CDCl<sub>3</sub>): 3.566 (m,2H,CH<sub>3</sub>O<u style="single">CH</u><sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub> (OCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>n</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>OCOPhNO<sub>2</sub>);
3.618-3.793 (m, br, Hydrogen of repeating unit -(CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>n</sub>), 3.892 (m, 2H,
CH<sub>3</sub>OCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub> (OCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>n</sub><u style="single">CH</u><sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>OCOPhNO<sub>2</sub>) and 4.453 (m, 2H,
CH<sub>3</sub>OCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub> (OCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>n</sub>CH<sub>2</sub><u style="single">CH</u><sub>2</sub>OCOPhNO<sub>2</sub>) ppm.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Grafting of mPEG2K-PNF on Dextran-Spermine conjugates (17)</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0107">15.0 mg of Dextran-Spermine conjugate (<b>2</b>, ~19.5 mmol of free amine as
determined by the TNBS method) was dissolved in 0.5 ml DDW. To this was
added 195 µmol (1% mol/mol) of mPEG2K-PNF (195 µl of a stock in DDW, 1
µmol/µl). The mixture was stirred overnight at ROOM TEMPERATURE. The
mixture was purified by G-25 Sepahdex column using water as eluent. Fractions
containing product (ninhyrin test detection) were collected and lyophilized to
dryness.

Yield = 14.0 mg (~90%).
<sup>1</sup>H-NMR (D<sub>2</sub>O) failed to identify the existence of grafted PEG chains because the
ethyleneglycol units are shifted in the same regions of the polysaccharide
hydrogens. A method will be developed for the quantification of grafted PEG
chains.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Results and discussion</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Synthesis</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0108">Dextran, a naturally occurring poly-β(1-6) dextrose, was oxidized at room
temperature with equimolar amount of KIO<sub>4</sub>. The resulting polyaldehyde was
purified by anion-exchange chromatography following extensive dialysis against
DDW and lyophilization to dryness. The aldehyde content of oxidized polymers
was determined using the hydroxylamine hydrochloride method<sup>17</sup> (table 1). <tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry nameend="6" namest="1">Aldehyde content and molecular weight of Dex and oxidized Dex derivatives.</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Polymer</b><b>code</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>mole ratio</b><b>(KIO<sub>4</sub>:Saccharides)</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>%</b><b>di-aldehyde content</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Mw</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Mn</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>P</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dex</entry><entry align="left">------------</entry><entry align="left">----------</entry><entry align="center">36,200</entry><entry align="center">20,125</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ox:Dex (1:1)</entry><entry align="left">1:1</entry><entry align="left">50</entry><entry align="center">24,960</entry><entry align="center">14,260</entry><entry align="center">1.75</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ox:Dex (1:3)</entry><entry align="left">1:3</entry><entry align="left">22</entry><entry align="center">28,430</entry><entry align="center">15,370</entry><entry align="center">1.85</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ox:Dex (1:5)</entry><entry align="left">1:5</entry><entry align="left">14</entry><entry align="center">29,960</entry><entry align="center">17,830</entry><entry align="center">1.68</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0109">A water solution of oxidized polysaccharide was added dropwise to an equimolar
amount of Spermine (naturally occurring tetramine) under basic conditions to
obtain the desired imine product (Schiff-base). A sage-metering pump (Model 365)
was used to maintain a slow and reproducible rate of addition. The purpose of the
slow addition was to minimize crosslinking and to facilitate grafting of Spermine
moieties onto the polymer chain. After, sufficient amount of sodium borohydride (5
equimolar excess) was added to obtain the stable amine conjugate. The reduced
conjugates were purified by extensive dialysis against DDW, freezed and
lyophilized to dryness.</p>
    <p num="0110">Nearly 250 different polycations were prepared starting from various
polysaccharides and oligoamines. Polysaccharides used in this study were the
branched Arabinogalactan (20Kd), linear Pullulan (~50 Kd) and Dextran with 9.3,
18.0, 40, 74 and 500 Kd in molecular weighs. Oligoamines used were mainly
Spermine and Spermidine, and more synthetic oligoamines, i.e. polyethyleneimine
and various diamines with different lengths. Although, most of these conjugates
formed stable complexes with various plasmids as determined by turbidity
experiments (data not shown), <u style="single">only</u> certain polycations based on
Dextran-Spermine conjugates were found to be active in transfecting cells.</p>
    <p num="0111">The optimal conditions for the preparation of active Dextran-Spermine conjugates
were as the follows: <ul list-style="bullet"><li>1:1 mole ratio between aldehydes and Spermine.</li><li>Initial high basic conditions (pH=11).</li><li>Slow addition of the polyaldehyde to Spermine.</li><li>Sufficient reduction with sodium borohydride.</li></ul></p>
    <p num="0112">Under these conditions, extensive aminolysis of glycoside linkages occurred
resulting in drastic chain session and low yields (25-30%).</p>
    <p num="0113">All polycations were mainly characterized by nitrogen elemental analysis, free
amino functionality (TNBS) and molecular weight. Table 2 summarizes a
representative group of conjugates (Dextran-Spermine) separately prepared using
identical conditions. Nitrogen content of these polycations showed near values in
the range of 9.7-12.77. Free amino contents of conjugates were also determined
(TNBS method) and found to be in the range of 0.9-1.515 µmol free amine per mg
conjugate. Average molecular weights of conjugates were determined by GPC
using 3% acetonitril (Acn) in 5% sodium phosphate (pH=4.0) as eluent. The
existence of phosphate ions in the mobile phase was found to be important to
prevent undesirable interaction between polycations and column resin. All
calculated molecular weights were in the region of 6-13 Kd and below the Mw of
starting polysaccharide (~36 Kd, table 1). These drastic changes in molecular
weight are explained by the extensive aminolysis of glycoside linkages during
conjugation step. <tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry nameend="6" namest="1">representative Dextran-Spermine conjugates.</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Code</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>%N <sup>a</sup></b></entry><entry align="left"><b>µmol/µg <sup>b</sup></b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Mw <sup>c</sup></b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Mn <sup>c</sup></b></entry><entry align="left"><b>P <sup>c</sup></b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">G1-TA-129A</entry><entry align="left">11.19</entry><entry align="left">1.050</entry><entry align="left">6,165</entry><entry align="left">5,600</entry><entry align="left">1.09</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G1-TA-6A</entry><entry align="left">10.37</entry><entry align="left">0.930</entry><entry align="left">7,080</entry><entry align="left">6,600</entry><entry align="left">1.07</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G1-TA-35/1</entry><entry align="left">10.84</entry><entry align="left">0.810</entry><entry align="left">8,255</entry><entry align="left">7,400</entry><entry align="left">1.11</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G1-TA-40/2</entry><entry align="left">7.65</entry><entry align="left">0.920</entry><entry align="left">6,380</entry><entry align="left">5,600</entry><entry align="left">1.14</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G1-TA-43A</entry><entry align="left">12.77</entry><entry align="left">1.493</entry><entry align="left">5,815</entry><entry align="left">5,500</entry><entry align="left">1.05</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Seph17</entry><entry align="left">9.91</entry><entry align="left">0.960</entry><entry align="left">9,940</entry><entry align="left">8,000</entry><entry align="left">1.24</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Seph18</entry><entry align="left">10.4</entry><entry align="left">1.100</entry><entry align="left">9,610</entry><entry align="left">8,800</entry><entry align="left">1.09</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-53A</entry><entry align="left">10.11</entry><entry align="left">0.749</entry><entry align="left">11,772</entry><entry align="left">10,167</entry><entry align="left">1.158</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-53B</entry><entry align="left">10.04</entry><entry align="left">0.785</entry><entry align="left">13,328</entry><entry align="left">10,858</entry><entry align="left">1.228</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-53C</entry><entry align="left">10.39</entry><entry align="left">0.675</entry><entry align="left">14,394</entry><entry align="left">11,618</entry><entry align="left">1.239</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-58A</entry><entry align="left">10.27</entry><entry align="left">0.915</entry><entry align="left">14,734</entry><entry align="left">11,330</entry><entry align="left">1.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-58B</entry><entry align="left">9.71</entry><entry align="left">0.766</entry><entry align="left">14,535</entry><entry align="left">10,398</entry><entry align="left">1.398</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-58C</entry><entry align="left">9.62</entry><entry align="left">0.935</entry><entry align="left">13,656</entry><entry align="left">11,093</entry><entry align="left">1.231</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-58D</entry><entry align="left">9.76</entry><entry align="left">0.883</entry><entry align="left">14,012</entry><entry align="left">11,252</entry><entry align="left">1.245</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-58E</entry><entry align="left">10.03</entry><entry align="left">0.982</entry><entry align="left">13,631</entry><entry align="left">10,570</entry><entry align="left">1.289</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-46IV</entry><entry align="left">10.76</entry><entry align="left">1.115</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-82</entry><entry align="left">12.07</entry><entry align="left">1.292</entry><entry align="left">11,140</entry><entry align="left">9160</entry><entry align="left">1.216</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-96</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry><entry align="left">1.576</entry><entry align="left">8,856</entry><entry align="left">7735</entry><entry align="left">1.145</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-98</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry><entry align="left">1.515</entry><entry align="left">9,618</entry><entry align="left">8543</entry><entry align="left">1.126</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-104</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry><entry align="left">1.24</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-110</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry></row><row><entry>(i) Found elemental analysis; (b) TNBS method; (c) GPC.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0114">Penetration of complexes (DNA-Polycation) is believed to be the most crucial step
in transfection. Hydrophobization of cationic polymers are believed to enhance
cell-membrane penetration (indocytosis) and therefore increase in transfection
efficacy. In literature, a unique fusogenic group was found to enhance cell
penetration of complexes. This group contains two oleate moities (T-shape)
connected to the polycation backbone. With the agreement of these findings, we
decided to attach our polycations with various fusogenic moities and to investigate 
their influence on transfection efficacies.</p>
    <p num="0115">For hydrophobization purposes we used the Chol and Oleate derivatives. NHS
active ester derivative of Chol was prepared starting from the commercial
Cholesteryl chloroformate and reaction with N-Hydroxy succinimide (NHS) in the
presence of DIEA (Scheme 1). Cholesteryl chloroformate is considered to be an
extreme reactive derivative and may reacts with primary and secondary amines or
even hydroxyl groups yielding a mixture of products. In the contrary, NHS-Chol
derivative (Scheme 1) are considered to be a moderate active ester and reacts
predominantly with primary amines.
<img id="img-00330001" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00330001.tif" inline="no" he="139"/>
Hydrophobization of Dextran-Spermine conjugate (Scheme 4, <b>15</b>) was obtained in
a mixture of THF:H<sub>2</sub>O (2:1) without the use of external base. After, THF was
removed and the remaining was lyophilized to dryness. Trituration of the
lyophilizate mixture with diethyl ether purified the hydrophobized derivatives of 
polycations from unreacted Chol moieties. <sup>1</sup>H-NMR of the Chol-hydrophobized
conjugates in a mixture of d<sub>6</sub>-DMSO:D<sub>2</sub>O (1:1) showed relative peaks of Chol
moieties shifted in the region of 0.6-1.2 ppm. Content of hydrophobization was
determined by the reduction in amino content (as a result of amidation) using
TNBS method (Table 3). By the same manner, a series of Chol-hydrophobized
Dex-Spermine were prepared containing 1-20% mol/mol Cholesterate.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">reduction in free amine content as a function of Chol-hydrophobization.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Code</entry><entry align="left">% NHS-Chol (mol/mol)</entry><entry align="left">? mole / mg (TNBS)</entry><entry align="left">% Reduction in free amino content</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-98</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="center">1.515</entry><entry align="left">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-100A</entry><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="center">1.542</entry><entry align="left">+ 1.78</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-100B</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="center">1.495</entry><entry align="left">- 1.30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-100C</entry><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="center">1.446</entry><entry align="left">-4.55</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-100D</entry><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="center">1.308</entry><entry align="left">-13.66</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-100E</entry><entry align="left">20</entry><entry align="center">1.178</entry><entry align="left">-22.25</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0116">Table 3 summarized the reduction of amino content as a result of
Chol-hydrophobization. 1-3% mol/mol hydrophobization (G4-TA-100A and
G4-TA-100B) cause no change in TNBS values probably to low and undetected
hydrophobization. Higher degree of hydrophobization (5-20% mol/mol,
G4-TA-100C to G4-TA-100E) cause to almost a quantatative reduction in amino
content indicating a complete amidation.</p>
    <p num="0117">Hydrophobization of Dextran-Spermine conjugate with oleate derivative (Scheme
<b>5, 16)</b> was obtained in a similar way to <b>15.</b> The starting polycation (<b>2</b>) was mixed in
THF:H<sub>2</sub>O (2:1) solution, with a commercial or synthetic NHS-Oleate. Unreacted
oleate moieties were purified as in <b>15</b> by triturating the lyophilizate in diethyl ether.</p>
    <p num="0118">Oleate content of hydrophobized polycations was also determined by the reduction
of amino content using TNBS method (table 4). </p>
    <p num="0119">Unlike the starting polycations, which gives a clear solution in water,
hydrophobized polycations (Oleate and chloesterate) produced a turbid solution
probably due to reduction in solubility caused by hydrophobization.
<img id="img-00350001" orientation="unknown" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00350001.tif" inline="no" he="109"/><tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">reduction in free amine content as a function of Oleate-hydrophobization.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Code</entry><entry align="left">% NHS-Oleate (mol/mol)</entry><entry align="left">? mole / mg (TNBS)</entry><entry align="left">% Reduction in free amino content</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-98</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="center">1.515</entry><entry align="left">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-105C</entry><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="center">1.463</entry><entry align="left">- 3.44</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-105D</entry><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="center">1.339</entry><entry align="left">-11.62</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G4-TA-105E</entry><entry align="left">20</entry><entry align="center">1.224</entry><entry align="left">-19.20</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0120">As in Chol-hydrophobization, table 4 summarizes the reduction of amino content
as a result of Oleate-hydrophobization. Hydrophobized polycations (5-20%
mol/mol, G4-TA-105C to G4-TA-105E) cause to almost a quantitative reduction in
amino content indicating a complete amidation. </p>
    <p num="0121">Dextran-Spermine was also hydrophobized by other fatty acid. These acids
include: Pivaloic (C5-branched), Hexanoic (C6-linear), Octanoic (C8-linear), Lauric
(C12-linear), Myristic (C14-linear) and Stearic acid (C18-linear). These acids were
converted to their NHS active ester derivatives as described earlier and attached
to the desired polycation in a mixture of THF:DDW medium. Scheme 3 illustrates a
possible structure of Dextran-Spermine polycation hydrophobized with saturated
fatty acids.
<img id="img-00360001" orientation="unknown" wi="141" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00360001.tif" inline="no" he="156"/></p>
    <p num="0122">Unsatured fatty acids (oleic, linoleic and linolenic) were also derivatized to their
NHS active ester and attached in a similar way to Dextran-Spermine conjugates
(Scheme 4). </p>
    <p num="0123">Also, T-shape active esters containing hydrophobic moieties (Cholesterate or
oleate) in each side were developed and used for hydrophobization (Scheme 5
<img id="img-00370001" orientation="unknown" wi="146" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00370001.tif" inline="no" he="162"/>
and 6). In brief, L-Lysine-O-methyl ester dihydrochloride was reacted with 2.2
equimoles of Cholesteryl chloroformate or Oleic acid N-hydroxy succinimide, in the
presence of TEA as hydrochloride acceptor. The resulted
diChol-L-Lysine-O-methyl ester or diOleate-L-Lysine-O-methyl ester, were
converted to their active esters according to the procedure described in
experimental section. <img id="img-00380001" orientation="unknown" wi="147" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00380001.tif" inline="no" he="91"/></p>
    <p num="0124">diOleate-L-Lysine-O-methyl ester, were converted to their active esters according
to the procedure described in experimental section.
<img id="img-00380002" orientation="unknown" wi="117" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00380002.tif" inline="no" he="104"/></p>
    <p num="0125">Hydrophobization of Dextran-Spermine conjugate (<b>2</b>) with the
diChol-L-Lysine-NHS or diOleate-L-Lysine-NHS (Scheme 9) will be prepared as
described in <b>8</b> and <b>9</b>. Unreacted diChol moieties will be also discarded from the
hydrophobized conjugates by triturating the lyophilizate product with diethyl ether.
<img id="img-00390001" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00390001.tif" inline="no" he="140"/></p>
    <p num="0126">The complexes of DNA formed with simple cationic polymers, similarly to other
colloidal particles (e.g., lipososmes) show very low stability in bloodstream<sup>21-22</sup>.
They are rapidly removed from bloodstream by RES, which decreases their
potential for specific targeting in-vivo. It has been proposed that an interaction of
the complexes with plasma proteins can be the major obstacle in their successful
in-vivo use. In analogy with stealth liposomes<sup>23-24</sup>. </p>
    <p num="0127">Polyethylene glycols (PEGs) are considered to be attractive for this purpose. They
are safe, non-toxic, cheap and do not interact with plasma components. For
purpose of attachment of PEG chain onto the polycation, we prepared an active
ester of PEG capable for direct conjugation to free amino functionality. In brief,
monomethyl ether PEG2000 (mPEG2000) was reacted under anhydrous
conditions with p-nitro-phenyl-chloroformate in the presence of TEA as base. The
resulting mPEG2000-PNF was isolated in pure form by precipitation in large
volume of diethyl ether. The degree of modification was found to be 100% as
shown in <sup>1</sup>H-NMR. The active ester was then reacted with the polycation (<b>2</b>) in
DDW and at room temperature. The resulting grafted-PEG polycation (Scheme
10) was purified by sephadex G-25 column chromatography using DDW as eluent.</p>
    <p num="0128">The overall yield was nearly 85%.
<img id="img-00400001" orientation="unknown" wi="144" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00400001.tif" inline="no" he="100"/></p>
    <heading>
      <b>Example 2: Hydrazide derivatives</b>
    </heading>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Preparation of hydrazide-oligoamine derivatives for conjugation to
polysaccharides</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0129">Hydrazine derivatives (R-NHNH<sub>2</sub>) are attractive compounds for the purpose of
reductive-amination. The resulting hydrazone bond (R-NHN=CR') is considered to
be much stable than simple imine (R-N=CR'). Hydrazide-oligoamine derivatives 
were synthesized and attached to oxidized dextran.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>a) <u style="single">Spermine-hydrazide</u></b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0130">TriBoc-Spermine were mixed with ethyl bromoacetate and the resulting product
was treated with hydrazine hydrochloride to obtain the hydrazide product:
<img id="img-00410001" orientation="unknown" wi="144" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00410001.tif" inline="no" he="43"/></p>
    <heading>
      <b>b) <u style="single">Lysine-hydrazide</u></b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0131">L-Lysine-OMe was Bocylated using di-tert butyl dicarobonate to the corresponding
di-Boc-L-Lysine-OMe. The obtained product was treated with excess of hydrazine
and the protecting group (Boc) is removed using gaseous HCI.
<img id="img-00410002" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00410002.tif" inline="no" he="42"/></p>
    <heading>
      <b>c) <u style="single">N<sup>α</sup>, N<sup>ε</sup>-tetra (3-amino propyl)-L-Lysine</u></b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0132">A branched tetramine is prepared by tetra-alkylation of L-Lysine-OMe with
N-Boc-propyl-bromide, following hydrazinolysis and cleavage of Boc groups using
gaseous HCI in dry methanol.
<img id="img-00410003" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00410003.tif" inline="no" he="45"/></p>
    <heading>
      <b>d) <u style="single">(L-arginine)-hydrazide drivative</u></b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0133">
      <img id="img-00420001" orientation="unknown" wi="139" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00420001.tif" inline="no" he="47"/>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Example 3: Combination of quaternary and regular Spermine in conjugates</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0134">Totally quaternarized polycations gave no transfection activity probably due to
strong complexation and large aggregate size of formed complex (&gt;10,000 nm).
Thus mixtures of 10%, 20% or 30% of quaternarized spermine was used in
combination to native spermine in conjugation to dextran and other
polysaccharides. Under these conditions, quaternary spermine functions as the
major complexing units and regular spermine functions as a buffering system.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Example 4: Synthesis of hydrophilic headgroup of quaternary spermine</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0135">Monoquaternary spermine containing hydrophilic head-group was prepared in a
similar way to compound <b>3</b>. Briefly, TriBoc-Spermine was reacted with excess of
1-azido-3-iodo-propane in the presence of excess TBA. The resulting
quaternarized derivative was hydrogenised under (Pd-C) and Boc protecting group
were removed using gaseous HCI in dry methanol.

The hydrophilic-mono-quaternary Spermine was attached to polyaldehydes under
the classical method (reductive amination described above).</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Example 5: Targeting experiments</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0136">Ligand for targeting purposes were conjugated to active polycations with
tetraethylene glycol as spacer-arm. These ligands include: mannose, glusose and
galactose for targeting to liver cells, or folic acid and avidin for targeting to certain
cancer cells. </p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Example 6: Conjugation to the polysaccharide chain</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0137">Oxidized dextran (45% degree of oxidation) was reacted with oleylamine, at a ratio
of 1, 5, and 10 oleylamine per 50 saccharide units, in water:tetrahydrofuran 1:1 v/v
mixture at room temperature. After 5 hours of stirring, spermine was added to the
mixture at a 1:1 molar ratio to the remaining aldehyde groups along with excess of
cyanoborohydride as reducing agents. The reaction was continued at room
temperature over night and the polycation was purified by dialysis or Sephadex
chromatography to yield hydrophobized polycation at an overall yield of 75%. A
similar procedure was used for the preparation of polycations made from
butanediamine, spermidine, and oligoethylene imine, Mw=600.</p>
    <p num="0138">Other methods for conjugation of fatty groups onto a polysaccharide include the
reaction of oleoyl chloride with the hydroxyl groups of either oxidized or
non-oxidized dextran or arabinogalactan in a water:THF mixture at room
temperature. In a typical experiment, dextran (100 mg) is dispersed in water:THF
1:1 v/v mixture containing 10mg of sodium bicarbonate (10ml) and a THF solution
of oleoyl chloride (10 mg in 1 ml THF) was added and mixed rapidly for two hours.
After 2 hours 10 ml THF was added and the reaction continued for another 3
hours. The mixture was lyophilized to dryness and the white residue was purified
by precipitation in methanol from water. The hydrophobized oxidized dextrean was
then reacted with spermine or spermidine by reductive amination at a
aldehyde:amine 1:1 ratio to obtain the desired cationic polymer.</p>
    <p num="0139">Hydrophobic or hydrophilic residues can be conjugated to polysacharide units by
tosylate or mesylate activation of the hydroxyl groups on the polysaccharides.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Example 7: Chitosan-oligoamine derivatives</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0140">Spermine and spermidine were conjugated to chitosan by reacting N-ethyliodide
spermine with chitosan in a mixture of water pH5 and THF at a 1:1 v/v ratio. Fatty
chains were conjugated to the polymer in a similar way by reacting oleyl chloride
with chitosan or spermine chitosan under similar conditions. </p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Example 8: Grafting of hydrophobic or amphiphilic residues:</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0141">The attachment of hydrophobic or amphiphilic residues can be carried-out by
various methods adopted from the literature (for example, Y.Takakura, et al.
Control of pharmaceutical properties of soybean tyrosine inhibitor by conjugation
with dextran I: synthesis and characterization, J. Pharm. Sci. 78, 117-121, 1989;
G.H. Hermanson, Bioconjugate techniques, Academic Press, 1996). The following
methods were used by the present inventor.</p>
    <p num="0142">The hydrophobic residue was generally conjugated by an ester, amide, imine,
amine, urethane or carbonate bonds depending on the availability of the functional
groups on the conjugated component. For example, fatty acids such as hexanoic
acid or oleic acid are bound to hydroxyl or amine groups on the polymer carrier
using activated acids such as anhydride or acid chloride derivatives or activating
agents such as dicyclohexylcarbodiimide (DCC) and its derivatives that are more
suitable for aqueous mediums. Alternatively, hexyl or oleyl alcohols or amines
have been conjugated via carbonate or urethane bonds using phosgene
derivatives. Polyethylene glycol oligomers and derivatives were conjugated either
directly via the hydroxyl end or by converting the hydroxyl end group to a
carboxylic acid (by reacting the alcohol with succinic, glutaric or maleic anhydride)
or to a reactive epoxide group (by reacting with epichlorhydrine). The grafting
reactions are conducted in hydrophilic solutions where the polymer carrier is
soluble in or at least dispersed in fine particles with large surface area. Typical
mediums are dimethylformamide (DMF), N-methyl pyrrolidone, dimethylsulfoxide
(DMSO) and their mixtures with water.</p>
    <p num="0143">The amount of grafting suitable for cell penetration and transfection is in the range
of 1 to 10% of the repeated units building the polymer carrier, i.e. saccharide units.
This amount is dependent on the nature of the attached group, the nature of the
final product and the polymer carrier.</p>
    <p num="0144">In a typical experiment Triton-X100 (7g, 10 mmol) was dried by azeotropic
distillation with toluene. After solvent evaporation, SnCl4 (5 ?l) and epichlorhydrin
(1.4g, 15 mmol) and the mixture was kept at 100oC overnight. The solvent was 
evaporated and mixed with ether and extracted with cold 1N NaOH. The etheric
layer was dried over MgSO4 and evaporated to dryness to yield the epoxy
terminated Triton (70% yield). The product was identified by TLC (silica,
toluene:chloroform) and by H NMR (aromatic protons 5.9-6.7 ppm).</p>
    <p num="0145">Alternatively, dry Triton-X100 was reacted with succinic anhydride (1:1.1 mole
ratio) in toluene at reflux overnight to yield the corresponding succinate derivative
as determined by H-NMR, IR and titration.</p>
    <p num="0146">The chloroformate derivative of Triton was prepared from the reaction of the
hydroxyl terminal with diphosgene using known procedures. Grafting of these
functionalized Triton was conducted in DMF or DMF:water solutions under the
proper conditions. For example, epoxide terminated Triton (0.5g) was reacted with
dextran (2g) in 1N NaOH (10 ml) overnight at room temperature. The polymer was
purified by dialysis against water and lyophilization. The derivatization rate was
about 5% of the saccharide groups.</p>
    <p num="0147">Carboxylic acid Triton-X100 reacted with arabinogalactan in a mixture of DMF and
water using water soluble DCC. Chloroformate Triton was reacted with a
suspension of polysaccharides in dry DMF for 3 days at room temperature. Triton
was reacted in access relative to the saccharide groups in order to obtain a 5%
conjugation.</p>
    <p num="0148">Similar procedures were applied for the conjugation of methoxy-PEG-OH or
Lipo-PEG (a diblock polymer of a fatty acid such as stearyl, oleyl or hexanoyl
groups with (PEG)<sub>10-100</sub>).</p>
    <p num="0149">The conjugation of highly hydrophobic residues such as fatty acids and cholesterol
to hydrophilic polysaccharides was conducted in an organic solvent such as DMF
or DMSO, the conjugation yield was low (1-5% of saccharide units) but suitable for
gene formulation.</p>
    <p num="0150">Hydrophobic or amphiphilic residues were conjugated to oxidized polysaccharide
via an amine or imine bonds. In this cases, the hydroxyl terminal of Triton and
PEG derivatives were converted to amino terminals by esterification with glycine or 
alanine or by replacing the hydroxyl group with an amine using the
tosylate/ammonia procedure as described below for the amination of
polysaccharides.</p>
    <p num="0151">The amine terminated PEG derivatives, cholesteryl amine or fatty amines are
reacted with oxidized polysaccharides in basic buffer solutions (pH9-11) or
mixtures of DMF with water over night, similar to the procedures used for the
grafting of spermine. The grafting can be conducted during the conjugation of the
oligoamines by adding both the oligoamine and the amphiphilic derivative to the
reaction mixture. The imine derivatives were hydrogenated to the corresponding
amine bond using NaBH4 in water for 24 hours at room temperature.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Example 9 - Oleic acid modification of low activity Spermine-dextran
polymers</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0152">The purpose of this experiment was to show that hydrophobization improves
significantly the transfection yield.

Ten batches of spermine-dextran conjugates of molecular weights between 15,000
and 25,000, nitrogen content between 7-11% w/w and various branching degrees
(20 to 60% branching) were conjugated with oleic acid at a 20% of the free amino
side chains of the conjugated spermine. The conjugation procedure was as
described above. Five of these polymers showed a high transfection activity while
the other 5 showed a medium or low transfection efficiencies.

In this study, dextran-spermidine (3 amino groups) was derivatized with 20% oleic
acid using the above procedure,
Another experiment was conducted to determine the effect of crosslinking on the
trasnfection efficacy. The reaction between oxidized dextran and spermine was
conducted at concentrated solutions which increases crosslinking. Insoluble
crosslinked polymer particles of 1 to about 100 microns which were used for
transfection studies.

Transfection studies using the methods described below show a significant
increase in the transfection efficiency for all polymers which was higher or
comparable to the effficacy obtained with DOTAP/Cholesterol lipid system. The
crosslinking decreased the efficacy compared to the branched polymers usually
obtained. </p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Example 10: Transfection experiments</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <i>
          <u style="single">General procedure</u>
        </i>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0153">1 ml of cell suspension at the concentration of 6*10<sup>5</sup> cells/ml was preincubated for
24h in 6 wells dish, after adherence the medium was replaced by 1 ml SFM
(Serum Free Medium). Either polyplexes or lipoplexes were added to the dish for
4h, then SFM was replaced by 1 ml complete medium and the cells undergo
incubation for 20 more hours. Two different kinds of plasmid DNA were used
(pCMV-β encoding to production of β-gal enzyme and pCMVhGH encoding to the
production of human growth hormone). We also used 2 different kind of cells (NIH
and EPC).</p>
    <heading>
      <i>
        <u style="single">In vitro transfection using pCMV-β and EPC cells.</u>
      </i>
    </heading>
    <p num="0154">We used 6*10<sup>5</sup> EPC cells per well in L-15 medium. The amount of pCMV-β
plasmid in complex was 2µg per well and the amount of polymer (G4TA46/IV,
G4TA82) was vary between 5.5-24 µg. We used dotap/cholesterol as control. All
incubation were done at 20°C. Quantification of β-gal enzyme produced by the
cells was done by β-gal elisa kit.</p>
    <heading>
      <i>
        <u style="single">In vitro transfection using pCMV-hGH and NIH cells.</u>
      </i>
    </heading>
    <p num="0155">1.3*10<sup>5</sup> NIH cells per well in DMEM medium was used. The amount of pCMV-hGH
plasmid in complex was 1.62 µg per well and the amount of polymer (TA1-129A,
G1TA6A) was vary between 5.5-22 µg. Dotap/cholesterol was used as control. All
incubations were at 37°C. Quantification of hGH produced by the cells was done
by hGH elisa kit.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">a. Transfection efficacies of different polycations prepared from various
polysaccharides and oligoamines.</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0156">
      <ul list-style="bullet">
        <li>Cells: HEK293.</li>
        <li>Plasmid: GFP.</li>
        <li>Tested Polycations: PEI600, AG-PEI, D-PEI, D-Spermidine, AG-Sperminem,
D-Spermine, P-Spermine.</li>
        <li>Control: Calcium Phosphate</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Results:</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0157">Most of tested polycations possesed low to modarate transfection efficiency. Only
one polycation (TA1-129A) was found to be very active. This polycation is
composed of Dextran-Spermine conjugate of about 10,000 molecular weight and
nitrogen content of about 10%. The transfection efficacy of TA1-129A was
compared to the tested control (calcium phosphate) and found to be in the same
range. The % transfection was determined visually by fluorescence microscopy,
counting fluorescenting cells in a certain field.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">b. Transfection efficacy of TA1-129A in comparison to the commercial
Transfast® and Calcium phosphate.</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0158">
      <ul list-style="bullet">
        <li>Cells: HEK293, HeLa human cancer cells</li>
        <li>Plasmid: GFP.</li>
        <li>Tested Polycations: TA1-129A composed of unique Dextran-Spermine
conjugate.</li>
        <li>Control: Transfast® and Calcium phosphate.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Results:</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0159">
      <ul list-style="bullet">
        <li>Transfection efficacy of TA1-129A was not affected by the presence/absence
of glycerol. Transfection efficacy of TA1-129A was found to be in the same range
as in Transfast® and Calcium phosphate. The % of cells transfected using
plasmid:TA1-129A at a 0.2, 0.1, 0.07 and 0.05 nucleotide:nitrogen molar ration
was 15, 38, 17, and 34% for the experiment with glycerol shock and 18, 47, 20,
and 42% without glycerol shock, respectively. Transfast and calcium phosphate
showed 40 and 46% transfection yield, respectively. HeLa cells were used in this
study for the purpose to demonstrate that the efficacy of transfection</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">c. Transfection efficacy of TA1-129A and G1-TA6 in NIH-3T3 cells.</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0160">
      <ul list-style="bullet">
        <li>Cells: NIH-3T3.</li>
        <li>Plasmid: hGH-CMV (Human Growth Hormone).</li>
        <li>Tested Polycations: Dextran-Spermine conjugates similarly prepared in two
different batches (TA1-129A and G1-TA6). </li>
        <li>Control: commercial cationic liposome (DOTAP:Chol 1:1, Avanti®).</li>
        <li>Content of liberated h-GH protein was quantified using a commercial h-GH
Elisa kit.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Results:</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0161">
      <ul list-style="bullet">
        <li>Transfection efficacy of TA1-129A and G1-TA6 was found to be in the same
range as in DOTAP:Chol (1:1).</li>
        <li>Maximum transfection was found in 0.1-0.05 (-/+), charge ratio. Around 22
to 28 ng/ml of hGH were quantified in this range of charge ratio.
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>The relative transfection of several batches of the optimal polymer in
several ratios (-/+) in comparison with the values obtained for dotap/chol in
each experiment. Data for TA1-129A and G1TA6A obtained from transfection
in NIH cells using pCMVhGH, and dotap/chol as control. Data for G4TA82
obtained from transfection in EPC cells using pCMVβ, and dotap/chol as
control. The relative transfection activity was 150%, 170%, and 280% for
TA1-129A, G1TA6A, and G4TA82, respectively (Dotap/cholesterol is 100%).</li><li>A high transfection yield of more than 40% was obtained when using HeLa
cells</li></ul></li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">d. Effect of Oleate moieties on transfection.</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0162">
      <ul list-style="bullet">
        <li>Cells: HEK293.</li>
        <li>Plasmid: GFP.</li>
        <li>Tested Polycations: Dextran-Spermine (G4-TA-82, G4-TA-96, G4-TA-98,
G4-TA-104 and G4-TA-110) and oleate-hydrophobiozed Dextran-Spermine (10%
and 20% mol/mol).</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Results:</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0163">
      <ul list-style="bullet">
        <li>All non-hydrophobized polycations (G4-TA-82, G4-TA-96, G4-TA-98,
G4-TA-104 and G4-TA-110) gave the best transfection values at 0.1 charge ratio
(-/+). Hydrophobized polycations (10% or 20% oleate, mol/mol) gave the best
transfection efficacy at 0.25 charge ratio (-/+).</li>
        <li>Hydrophobized polycations remarkably increase transfection, by at least 2
fold.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">e. Effect of Oleate moieties on transfection (batch #1).</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0164">
      <ul list-style="bullet">
        <li>Cells: HEK293.</li>
        <li>Plasmid: x-Gal.</li>
        <li>Tested Polycations: Dextran-Spermine (G4-TA-98) and hydrophobiozed
G4-TA-98 containing 1-20% mol/mol oleate (batch #1).</li>
        <li>Content of liberated x-Gal protein was quantified using a commercial x-Gal
Elisa kit in 10% serum containing medium.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Results:</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0165">
      <ul list-style="bullet">
        <li>0 and 1% oleate (mol/mol) gave no transfection. This is explained by the
high serum content which cause a remarkable decomplexation and hence in
drastic decrease in transfection efficacy.</li>
        <li>3 and 5% (mol/mol) oleate gave low transfection values probably due to
partial-extent stabilization of oleate moieties.</li>
        <li>Higher oleate content (10 and 20%, mol/mol) gave the best transfection
values. These excellent transfection values were found to be similar to the values
obtained from Fugen®.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">f. Effect of Oleate moieties on transfection (batch #2).</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0166">
      <ul list-style="bullet">
        <li>Cells: HEK293.</li>
        <li>Plasmid: x-Gal.</li>
        <li>Tested Polycations: Dextran-Spermine (G4-TA-98) and hydrophobized
G4-TA-98 containing 1-20% mol/mol oleate (batch #2).</li>
        <li>Content of liberated x-Gal protein was quantified using a commercial x-Gal
Elisa kit in 10% serum containing medium.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Results:</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0167">
      <ul list-style="bullet">
        <li>Similar data were obtained as in batch #1.</li>
        <li>Increasing the oleate content from 5 to 20% gave a remarkable increase in
tranfection values. A transfection yield (determined by the optical density of the
formed b-Gal dye) of the 0, 10, 20, and 30 % oleate per primary amino groups was 
0.35, 0.62, 1.42, and 0.2, respectively.</li>
        <li>At 30% (mol/mol) a decrease in transfection value was obtained. This could
be explained by the high oleate content which results in slow decomplexation and
hence decrease in transfection.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">g. Effect of other fatty moieties on transfection.</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0168">
      <ul list-style="bullet">
        <li>Cells: HEK293.</li>
        <li>Plasmid: GFP.</li>
        <li>Tested Polycations: Dextran-Spermine (G4-TA-82) and stearate, myristate,
and octanoate -hydrophobiozed Dextran-Spermine (10% and 20% mol/mol).</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Results:</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0169">
      <ul list-style="bullet">
        <li>All hydrophobized spermine-dextran polycations gave transfection values at
0.2 charge ratio (-/+). Hydrophobized polycations (10% or 20% fatty chain,
mol/mol) gave the best transfection efficacy at 0.25 charge ratio (-/+).

Hydrophobized polycations remarkably increase transfection, by at least 2 fold.
However, the fatty acid side groups, stearate, octanoate, and myristate were less
active than oleate derivatives.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">h. Transfection efficacies of hydrophobized Dextran-Spermine as a function of
serum content in medium.</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0170"><ul list-style="bullet"><li>Cells: NIH-3T3.</li><li>Plasmid: x-Gal.</li><li>Tested Polycations: Dextran-Spermine (G4-TA-98) and hydrophobized
G4-TA-98 containing 1-20% mol/mol oleate (batch #2). The</li><li>Content of liberated x-Gal protein was quantified (Pg/ml) using a
commercial x-Gal Elisa kit in 10% serum containing medium.</li></ul>
Results: The results are given in the following Table. <tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">Effect of serum on the transfection efficacy of oleate bearing spermine-Dex.</entry></row><row><entry align="left" namest="1">Polymer</entry><entry nameend="4" align="left" namest="2">x-Gal protein (Pg/ml)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">% oleic acid (+/- ratio)</entry><entry align="left">0% serum</entry><entry align="left">25% serum</entry><entry align="left">50% serum</entry></row><row><entry align="left">0%, 0.1</entry><entry align="left">370</entry><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="left">10</entry></row><row><entry align="left">10%, 0.25</entry><entry align="left">120</entry><entry align="left">800</entry><entry align="left">130</entry></row><row><entry align="left">20%, 0.25</entry><entry align="left">180</entry><entry align="left">1600</entry><entry align="left">250</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dotap/chol 1:1, 0.5</entry><entry align="left">150</entry><entry align="left">200</entry><entry align="left">10</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0171">As can be seen, the oleate had a dramatic effect on the transfection yield in
serum. These results indicate that fatty acid chain may improve the in-vivo
transfection yield.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Example 11: Toxicity in-vitro.</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <heading>
      <i>
        <u style="single">Procedure</u>
      </i>
    </heading>
    <p num="0172">200µl of cell suspension at the concentration of 2.5*10<sup>4</sup> cells/ml was preincubated
for 24h in 96 wells dish. Different concentration of polyplexes (complexes of
G4TA46/IV or G4TA82 with DNA) and different amount of polymer were added to
the wells. Complexes of dotap/chol were used as control. The charge ratio (-/+)
that was chosen for this experiment was the one that gave the best results in
transfection in vitro (G4TA82 0.2 (-/+), G4TA46/IV (-/+)). 36 h post transfection the
cells undergo fixation with glutaraldehyde and stained with methylene blue. U.V
measurement at 620 nm indicate the vitality of the cells (high value of O.D indicate
low toxicity). The polymers did not affect the cell viability at concentrations of 1-6
microgram per ml. To the contrary, Dotap/cholesterol killed about 50% of the cells
at concentrations of less than 1 micgram/ml with more than 80% at concentrations
of 3 microgram per ml.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <i>
          <u style="single">Example 12: Toxicity in-vitro II</u>
        </i>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <heading>
      <i>
        <u style="single">Procedure</u>
      </i>
    </heading>
    <p num="0173">200µl of cell suspension at the concentration of 2*10<sup>4</sup> cells/ml was preincubated
for 24h in 96 wells dish. Different concentration of polyplexes (complexes of 
G4TA98 or G4TA98-10%-ol, G4TA98-20%-ol with DNA) and different amount of
polymer were added to the wells. We used complexes of dotap/chol as control.
The charge ratio (-/+) that was chosen for this experiment was the one that gave
the best results in transfection in vitro (G4TA82 0.2 (-/+), G4TA98 0.1 (-/+),
G4TA98, 10, 20 % OL 0.25 (-/+). DOTAP/CHOL 0.5 (-/+)). 42h post transfection
the cells undergo fixation with glutaraldehyde and stained with methylene blue.
U.V measurement at 620 nm indicate the vitality of the cells (high value of O.D
indicate low toxicity). Similar results were obtained which indicates that the
polymers are safe to cells at the transfection concentrations.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Example 13: Transfection</u>
        <i>
          <u style="single">in vivo</u>
        </i>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Transplantation of matrices containing complexes in mice</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0174">Matrices of chitosan crosslinked with 20% arabinogalactan and absorbed them
with complexes that were prepared from the optimal polymer-DNA,
dotap/chol-DNA or naked DNA. pCMVβ at the amount of 70 µg were loaded into
each matrix. The matrices were transplanted subcutaneous in C3H/HEN mice. 4
weeks post transplantation the area around the matrix was stained. The X-gal
staining results showed qualitative expression of β-gal enzyme in all groups.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Injection of complexes to fish</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0175">Archocentrus nigrofaciatum fish at approximate weight of 5 g were used.
Complexes contain G5TA46/IV-DNA at 2 different ratios (1.28 (-/+), 0.64 (-/+)),
lipoplexes contain dotap/chol-DNA and naked DNA were injected to the dorsal
muscle (2 µg pCMVβ per fish). 5 days post injection the fish were sacrificed and
were tested for presence of β-gal enzyme by staining. Again the X-gal staining
results showed qualitative expression of β-gal enzyme in all groups.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Example 14: Other applications for polysaccharide-oligoamine conjugates of
this invention:</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0176">The polycations described in this application were used for a range of applications
as follows:
<sl><li>i. Complexation with heparin

Aqueous solutions of Heparin and arabinogalactan-spermine were mixed at a 1:1 
cation to anion ratio for a few hours at room temperature. The formed complex was
lyophilized to form a white powder which when dispersed in water very little free
heparin was found in the solution. This system can be used for control
concentration of heparins in aqueous solutions both in vitro and in vivo.</li><li>ii. Combination with hyaluronic acid

Aqueous solutions of hyaluronic acid (MW=2 million daltons, 1% solution) and
arabinogalactan-spermine (MW=20,000, 5%) were mixed at a 10:1 and 1:1 anion
to cation ratio for a few hours at room temperature. A significant increase in the
viscosity of hyaluronic acid was obtained which was used for the injection of
condors cells in mice for cell growth and cartilage formation. The 1:1 mixture
became more viscous than the 10% mixture. Alternatively, the formed complex was
lyophilized to form a white porous matrix which when dispersed in a medium
containing condors cells, the matrix particles swelled and allowed the cell ingrowth
into the swollen matrix.

Other anionic polymers such as alginic acid, carboxymethyl cellulose and a 1:1
copolymer of acrylic acid and methyl methacrylate (Eugragit) formed an
electrostatic complex with the spermine-dextran or arabinogalactan conjugates.</li><li>iii. Scaffolds for cell growth were prepared by conjugating a concentrated solutions
of spermine and oxidized arabinogalactan at a amine:aldehyde ratio of 1:20,
1:10 and 1:5 at room temperature. After 24 hours of mixing the resulting
compound was freeze dried to form a white porous matrix suitable for cell
growth for tissue engineering purposes.</li><li>iv. Non-medical applications for these polycations was found in the design of
electronic circuits based on repeated alternating coating of monolayers of
cationic polymers and anionic polymers. The polycations of this invention are
used in other applications in electro-optics and conducting polymers where
cationic polymers are used.

A different application is the use of the cationic polymer as semi-natural
conditioner which is composed of a polycation polymer. The high water
solubility, the safety and easy to make makes this class of polycations ideal for
cosmetic and toiletry applications.

These polycations can replace polycations that are used in the printing industry,
paper industry and others.</li></sl></p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Example 15 - Conjugation of Dansylhydrazine Onto Dextran-Spermine</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0177">Dansylhydrazine (available from Aldrich Chemicals) was mixed with spermine at a
ratio between 1 and 10 mole % and reacted with oxidized dextran (50% degree of
oxidation) in water solution as described above. A high yield of Dansyl
conjugation to the polymer was obtained. This dansyl derivative can improve the
interaction with cell membranes which improves transfection of genes or cell
attachment.</p>
    <p num="0178">Another procedure was used for the conjugation of dansyl chloride onto the
spermine-dextran conjugate where the dansyl chloride was mixed with a solution
of spermine-dextran in tetrahydrofural-water 1:1 mixture.</p>
    <p num="0179">It will be evident to those skilled in the art that the invention is not limited to
the details of the foregoing illustrative examples and that the present invention
may be embodied in other specific forms without departing from the essential
attributes thereof, and it is therefore desired that the present embodiments and
examples be considered in all respects as illustrative and not restrictive, reference
being made to the appended claims, rather than to the foregoing description, and
all changes which come within the meaning and range of equivalency of the claims
are therefore intended to be embraced therein.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">Example 16: Biodegradation of the polycations</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <heading>
      <b>In-vitro degradation of spermine-dextran</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0180">Experimental: spermine-dextran polymers were weighted and incubated in
phosphate buffer 0.1 M, pH=7.4 at 37°C. At fixed time points the molecular weight
of the polymers was determined by GPC and by viscosity measurements. The
extent of degradation was determined as the percentage of the molecular weight
loss over time.

Results: There is a slow degradation of the polymers in aqueous solution in-vitro.
After 4 weeks in buffer solution the polymers decreased in molecular weight by
about 40% with the 20% oleate derivatives degraded the least. </p>
    <heading>
      <b>In-vivo implantation and histological observation of chitosan-AG gels in
BALB/c mice:</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0181">Experimental: Scaffolds of crosslinked spermine-dextran and Oxycell® (as a
reference compound) were implanted sub-cutaneously in the back of BALB/c mice.

The scaffolds at size of 5x5mm were sterilized by U.V., and soaked in sterile saline
solution prior to implantation. After 3 days, 1 and 4 weeks the mice were sacrificed
and the scaffolds were explanted without loss from the mice together with the
surrounding tissue. Following fixation with 10% formalin the gels were sectioned
and stained with haematoxylin-eosin.

Results: The scaffolds cause local reaction at the surrounding tissue as can be
seen after 3 days and one week, however this reaction disappear after one month,
and can no longer be seen at the surrounding tissue. After one month a significant
amount of the polymer was degraded and eliminated from the implantation site.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A polycation composition comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) a polysaccharide chain having an amount of
saccharide units ranging from 2 to 2000;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) at least one oligoamine directly grafted to said
polysaccharide chain per each segment of 5
saccharide units, wherein said oligoamine is
selected from the group consisting of a linear,
branched and cyclic alkyl amine having at least
two amino groups; and</claim-text><claim-text>(c) at least one further grafted group selected from
the group consisting of a hydrophobic and an
amphiphilic group directly grafted to said
polysaccharide chain per each segment of 50
saccharide units, wherein said hydrophobic or
amphiphilic group includes an aliphatic chain of
at least 4 carbon atoms.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A biodegradable polycation complex with a
polyanion comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) a polysaccharide chain having an amount of
saccharide units ranging from 2 to 2000;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) at least one oligoamine directly grafted to said
polysaccharide chain per each segment of 5
saccharide units, wherein said oligoamine is
selected from the group consisting of a linear,
branched and cyclic alkyl amine having at least
two amino groups; and</claim-text><claim-text>(c) at least one further grafted group selected from
the group consisting of a hydrophobic and an
amphiphilic group directly grafted to said
polysaccharide chain per each segment of 50
saccharide units, wherein said hydrophobic or
amphiphilic group includes an aliphatic chain of
at least 4 carbon atoms; complexed with</claim-text><claim-text>(d) an anionic macromolecule selected from the group
consisting of polynucleic acids, proteins and
polysaccharides that are anionic.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A biodegradable polycation composition according
to claim 2, wherein said anionic macromolecule is
selected from the group consisting of a plasmid, an
open chain polynucleic acid, an oligonucleotide, an
antisense, a peptide, a protein, a polysaccharide and
combinations thereof.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A biodegradable polycation composition according
to any of claims 1 to 3, wherein said polysaccharide
chain is selected from the group consisting of
dextrans, arabinogalactan, pullulan, cellulose,
cellobios, inulin, chitosan, alginates and hyaluronic
acid.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A biodegradable polycation composition according
to any of claims 1 to 4, wherein said saccharide units
are connected by a bond selected from the group
consisting of acetal, hemiacetal, ketal, orthoester,
amide, ester, carbonate and carbamate.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A biodegradable polycation composition according
to any of claims 1 to 5, wherein said polysaccharide
is a synthetic polysaccharide formed from the
condensation of an aldaric acid and a diaminoalkane.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A biodegradable polycation composition according
to any of claims 1 to 6, wherein said grafted
oligoamine is grafted to said polysaccharide chain by
a bond selected from the group consisting of an amine
bond, an imine bond, an amide bond and a carbamate
bond.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A biodegradable polycation composition according
to any of claims 1 to 7, wherein said oligoamine has
the formula:
NH2-[CH2)x-N-®-CH2)y-N-(R')-(CH2)z-]n-NH2
wherein x, y, z are an integer between 0 and 4 and
x+y+z+ is between 1 and 4 and n is at least 1 when
x+y+z=2 or more, or at least 2 when x+y+z+=1 and
wherein R and R' groups are H or an aliphatic side
group of 1 to 6 carbons.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>A biodegradable polycation composition according
to any of claims 1 to 8, wherein said oligoamine is a
peptide of up to 20 amino acids with at least 50% of
the amino acid are cationic including lysine,
ornithine, and arginine.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>A biodegradable polycation composition according
to any of claims 1 to 9, wherein said oligoamine is
selected from the group consisting of spermine and
derivatives thereof.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>A biodegradable polycation composition according
to any of claims 1 to 10, wherein said oligoamine is
selected from the group consisting of a linear and
branched ethyleneimine oligomer having up to 10
ethylene imine units.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>A biodegradable polycation composition according
to any preceding claim, having an amphiphilic residue
wherein said amphiphilic residue is selected from the
group consisting of fatty chains, phospholipids,
cholesterol derivatives, ethylene glycol oligomers,
propylene glycol oligomers and combinations thereof.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>A biodegradable polycation composition according
to claim 12, wherein said ethylene and propylene
glycol oligomers have a fatty chain block on one side.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>A biodegradable polycation composition according
to claim 12 or 13, wherein said amphiphilic residue is
connected to said polysaccharide chain by a bond
selected from the group consisting of an amine, amide,
imine, ester, ether, urea, carbamate and carbonate.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>A biodegradable polycation composition according
to any of claims 12 to 14, wherein said amphiphilic
residue is an oleic chain.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>A biodegradable polycation composition according
to any of claims 12 to 15, wherein said amphiphilic
residue facilitates the crossing of the polycation
through biological membranes.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>A biodegradable polycation composition according
to any preceding claim, wherein said polycation
composition is not toxic or immunogenic.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="18">
      <claim-text>A biodegradable polycation composition according
to any preceding claim, wherein said composition
further comprises a ligand for facilitating the
binding of said composition to a predetermined type of
cell or tissue.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="19">
      <claim-text>A biodegradable composition according to any
preceding claim, in combination with cationic and
nonionic lipids or polymers for enhanced cell
transfection.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="20">
      <claim-text>A biodegradable composition according to any
preceding claim, wherein said polycation has a
structure selected from the group consisting of a
comb-like chain, a branched chain and a cross-linked
chain.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="21">
      <claim-text>A pharmaceutical composition, comprising the
composition of any preceding claim, in combination
with a pharmaceutically acceptable carrier.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="22">
      <claim-text>A pharmaceutical composition according to claim
21, in combination with a biodegradable polymer matrix
or capsule for controlled, timed and extended delivery
of the complex.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="23">
      <claim-text>Use of a polycation composition according to
any preceding claim, as a scaffold for cell growth.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="24">
      <claim-text>Use of a polycation composition according to any
of claims 1 to 20, in non-medical coatings in the
printing and electronic industry.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="25">
      <claim-text>A composition according to any of claims 1 to 22
for use in a method of treatment of the human or
animal body.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
