<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1251058-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1251058" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="18967719" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021023">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1251058-A2" status="new" fvid="23591031">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1251058</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021023</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02007967-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02007967</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020410</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001117092-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001117092</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010416</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B62D   5/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B62D   5/04        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B62D   6/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B62D   6/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B62D   6/08        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B62D   6/10        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B62D  15/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B62D  15/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B62D 111/00        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B62D 113/00        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B62D 119/00        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G01L   3/10        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G01L   3/10        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G01L   5/22        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G01L   5/22        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B62D  15/02D2</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B62D   5/04B2</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B62D   5/04P2B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B62D   5/04P6</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B62D   6/00D2</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B62D   6/10</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G01L   3/10A</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G01L   5/22B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L60G400:42</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L60G800:702</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Elektrische Servolenkung</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Electric power steering system</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Direction assistée électrique</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KOYO SEIKO CO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KOYO SEIKO CO., LTD.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Koyo Seiko Co., Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>5-8, Minamisemba 3-chome, Chuo-ku</street>
              <city>Osaka-shi, Osaka 542-0081</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HIGASHIRA HIDEKI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NAKANO YOSHIAKI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HIGASHIRA, HIDEKI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NAKANO, YOSHIAKI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>HIGASHIRA, HIDEKI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>c/o Koyo Seiko Co., Ltd., 5-8, Minamisemba 3-chome</street>
              <city>Chuo-ku, Osaka-shi, Osaka 542-0081</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>NAKANO, YOSHIAKI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>c/o Koyo Seiko Co., Ltd., 5-8, Minamisemba 3-chome</street>
              <city>Chuo-ku, Osaka-shi, Osaka 542-0081</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Gahlert, Stefan, Dr.-Ing.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Witte, Weller &amp;amp; Partner, Patentanwälte, Postfach 105462</street>
              <city>70047 Stuttgart</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>An electric power steering system according to the
present invention comprises: a sensor module (1) including
a steering torque sensor (12) and a control circuit (13)
housed therein; and a motor module (2) including an electric
motor (M) and a motor driving circuit (14) housed therein.
The sensor module (1) and the motor module (2) are physically
separately mounted in the electric power steering system.
Since the sensor module (1) and the motor module (2) are
physically separated, these modules can separately be
produced, and the steering torque sensor (12) and the
electric motor (M) can independently be adjusted (Fig. 1).
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="102" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="89"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">This application is based on application No.
2001-117092 filed in Japan, the content of which is
incorporated hereinto by reference.</p>
    <heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <heading>Field of the Invention</heading>
    <p num="0002">The present invention relates to an electric power
steering system which controls the driving of an electric
motor on the basis of the steering state of a motor vehicle
represented by a steering torque, a steering angle, a yaw
rate and the like.</p>
    <heading>Description of the Related Art</heading>
    <p num="0003">In an electric power steering system, the rotation
of a steering wheel is transmitted to a steering mechanism
via a steering shaft. A steering assist force is
transmitted to the steering mechanism from an electric motor
in accordance with a steering angle, a steering torque,
a yaw rate and the like.</p>
    <p num="0004">There has been proposed an electric power steering
system in which a housing accommodating a steering torque
sensor, a steering torque sensor signal processing circuit
(sensor module) and an electric motor driving circuit (motor
module) is mounted integrally on an electric motor so that 
a wiring distance is reduced for easy assembling thereof
(see Japanese Unexamined Patent Publication No.8-11730
(1996)).</p>
    <p num="0005">In this electric power steering system, the sensor
module and the motor module are mounted together with a
single microprocessor on the same board. Therefore, the
entire board should be redesigned every time the
specifications of the steering torque sensor or the electric
motor (e.g., the capacity of the electric motor for a vehicle
model) are changed. Hence, there is a need for designing
a board for each vehicle model, requiring a greater effort
for the designing. This leads to cost increase.</p>
    <p num="0006">It is therefore an object of the present invention
to provide an electric power steering system which includes
a sensor module and a motor module physically separately
provided therein, so that the sensor module and the motor
module can separately be produced, and a sensor such as
a steering torque sensor, a steering angle sensor or a yaw
rate sensor and an electric motor can independently be
adjusted for correction of variations thereof.</p>
    <heading>BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0007">The electric power steering system according to the
present invention comprises a first module including a
steering state detector and a control circuit housed therein,
and a second module including an electric motor and a motor 
driving circuit housed therein. The first module and the
second module are separately mounted in the electric power
steering system.</p>
    <p num="0008">With this arrangement, the first module is adapted
to detect a steering state and compute a target assist amount,
and the second module is adapted to control the rotation
of the electric motor on the basis of the target assist
amount. Thus, variations in the capacity of the electric
motor can be accommodated simply by modifying the second
module. Therefore, the electric power steering system is
applicable to various vehicle models, thereby allowing for
cost reduction.</p>
    <p num="0009">Where the computation of the target assist amount
is based on a steering torque, the steering state detector
is a steering torque sensor for detecting the steering
torque. Where the computation of the target assist amount
is based on a steering angle or a vehicle yaw rate, the
steering state detector is a steering angle sensor or a
yaw rate sensor.</p>
    <p num="0010">The steering torque sensor may be a steering torque
sensor of phase difference type. The phase difference type
steering torque sensor is capable of detecting a phase
difference between a steering angle on a steering wheel
side and a steering angle on a motor side as well as an
absolute steering angle on the steering wheel side and an 
absolute steering angle on the motor side. Thus, the
steering angle can be detected by the steering torque sensor
as well as by a steering angle sensor generally provided
on the motor side. Even if one of the steering torque sensor
and the steering angle sensor happens to malfunction, data
inputted from the other sensor can be employed for
continuously performing an assist operation (steering
assist operation).</p>
    <p num="0011">It is preferred that the first module and the second
module individually include central processing circuits.
Thus, the adjustment of the steering state detector and
the adjustment of the electric motor can easily and
separately be achieved within the first module and the
second module, respectively.</p>
    <p num="0012">The central processing circuit of the first module
and the central processing circuit of the second module
are preferably connected to each other via a communication
line so as to be mutually monitored by each other to check
for malfunction thereof.</p>
    <p num="0013">The first module preferably has a function of
correcting the steering state detector. Thus, variations
in the detection by the steering state detector can be
corrected which may occur due to intrinsic errors and
assembly errors of the steering state detector, an
environmental change and aging. </p>
    <p num="0014">The second module preferably has a function of
correcting the electric motor. Thus, variations in the
operation of the electric motor can be corrected which may
occur due to intrinsic errors and assembling errors of the
electric motor, an environmental change and aging.</p>
    <p num="0015">A specific embodiment of the present invention will
hereinafter be described with reference to the following
drawings.</p>
    <heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
    <p num="0016">
      <sl>
        <li>Fig. 1 is a diagram illustrating connection between
a control circuit 13 mounted on a housing of a steering
torque sensor 12 and a motor driving circuit 14 mounted
on a housing of an electric motor M via a communication
line in accordance with an embodiment of the present
invention;</li>
        <li>Fig. 2 is a perspective view illustrating a steering
torque sensor 12 of phase difference type;</li>
        <li>Fig. 3 is a block diagram for explaining the function
of the control circuit 13;</li>
        <li>Fig. 4 is a block diagram for explaining the function
of the motor driving circuit 14;</li>
        <li>Fig. 5A is a perspective view illustrating
connection to be established between the motor driving
circuit 14 and the electric motor M with the use of a connector
alone in a motor module; </li>
        <li>Fig. 5B is a perspective view illustrating
connection to be established between the motor driving
circuit 14 and the electric motor M with the use of a connector
alone in the motor module;</li>
        <li>Fig. 6A is a perspective view illustrating
connection to be established between the motor driving
circuit 14 and the electric motor M with the use of screws
in the motor module;</li>
        <li>Fig. 6B is a perspective view illustrating
connection to be established between the motor driving
circuit 14 and the electric motor M with the use of screws
in the motor module;</li>
        <li>Fig. 7A is a perspective view illustrating
connection to be established between the motor driving
circuit 14 and the electric motor M by way of welding in
the motor module; and</li>
        <li>Fig. 7B is a perspective view illustrating
connection to be established between the motor driving
circuit 14 and the electric motor M by way of welding in
the motor module.</li>
      </sl>
    </p>
    <heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0017">In an electric power steering system, the rotation
of a steering wheel is mechanically transmitted to a
steering mechanism via a steering shaft. A steering assist
force is transmitted from an electric brushless motor 
(hereinafter referred to simply as "electric motor") to
either the steering mechanism or the steering shaft.</p>
    <p num="0018">The steering mechanism includes a pinion provided
at an end of the steering shaft, and a rack shaft threadingly
engaged with the pinion and extending transversely of a
motor vehicle (along the width of the motor vehicle) . Tie
rods are respectively coupled with opposite ends of the
rack shaft, and further coupled with knuckle arms which
respectively support right and left front wheels as
steerable wheels.</p>
    <p num="0019">With this arrangement, when the steering wheel is
operated to rotate the steering shaft, the rotation of the
steering shaft is converted into a linear movement
transverse to the motor vehicle by the pinion and the rack
shaft. Thus, the right and left front wheels are turned.</p>
    <p num="0020">The steering shaft is divided into an input shaft
connected to the side of the steering wheel and an output
shaft connected to the side of the steering mechanism. The
input shaft and the output shaft are coupled with each other
by a torsion bar. The torsion bar is twisted according
to a steering torque, and the amount and direction of the
resulting torsion is detected by a steering torque sensor.</p>
    <p num="0021">A steering angle sensor is provided in association
with the output shaft for detecting a rotation angle of
the output shaft for detection of a steering angle of the 
steering mechanism.</p>
    <p num="0022">A yaw rate sensor (e.g., a vibration gyro, a fiber
optic gyro or the like) is provided in the electric power
steering system for detecting a turning angle of the motor
vehicle about a vertical axis.</p>
    <p num="0023">In the following embodiment of the present invention,
a sensor module incorporating the steering torque sensor
is taken as an example. However, it should be understood
that the present invention be not limited to the embodiment,
but may be applied to a sensor module incorporating the
steering angle sensor or the yaw rate sensor.</p>
    <p num="0024">Fig. 1 is a diagram illustrating a sensor module
(corresponding to the first module) 1 and a motor module
(corresponding to the second module) 2 connected to each
other via a communication line 3. The sensor module 1
incorporates therein a steering torque sensor 12 and a
control circuit 13, while the motor module 2 incorporates
therein an electric motor M and a motor driving circuit
14.</p>
    <p num="0025">A cable (not shown) for transmitting a signal from
the steering torque sensor 12 to the control circuit 13
is incorporated in the sensor module 1. A cable and
terminals for transmitting a motor driving signal from the
motor driving circuit 14 to the electric motor M will be
described later with reference to Figs. 5A and 5B, Figs. 
6A and 6B, and Figs. 7A and 7B.</p>
    <p num="0026">Fig. 2 is a perspective view illustrating a steering
torque sensor of phase difference type as a specific example
of the steering torque sensor 12. A metal fan 23 to be
detected is fitted around a cylindrical portion 22 coupled
with an upper end of the torsion bar 21, and a metal fan
24 to be detected is fitted around a cylindrical portion
25 coupled with a lower end of the torsion bar 21. A
rotational phase difference between the fans 23 and 24 is
detected by two MR sensors (magneto-resistive effect
devices) provided in the steering torque sensor 12, whereby
the torque applied to the torsion bar 21 is detected. Even
if one of the two MR sensors malfunctions, the detection
of the torque is possible. Therefore, the assist operation
can continuously be performed.</p>
    <p num="0027">Further, the absolute rotational position of the
metal fan 23 or 24 can be detected, so that an absolute
steering angle can also be detected. Thus, the steering
angle sensor and the absolute steering angle sensor
constitute a duplex detection system. Even if one of the
steering angle sensor and the absolute steering angle sensor
malfunctions, the detection of the steering angle is
possible.</p>
    <p num="0028">An output signal of the steering torque sensor 12
is inputted to the control circuit 13. The control circuit 
13 determines a target assist electric current of the
electric motor M in accordance with the steering torque
detected by the steering torque sensor 12, and outputs a
target assist electric current signal via the communication
line 3 (see Fig. 1).</p>
    <p num="0029">On the other hand, the motor driving circuit 14 is
mounted on a housing of the electric motor M (see Fig. 1).
The motor driving circuit 14 controls the driving of the
electric motor M on the basis of the target assist electric
current signal applied through the communication line 3
so as to apply a steering assist force according to the
steering torque to the steering shaft.</p>
    <p num="0030">Fig. 3 is a block diagram for explaining the function
of the control circuit 13. The control circuit 13 includes
two CPUs including a main CPU 30a and a sub CPU 30b. The
sub CPU 30b is provided for a case where the main CPU 30a
malfunctions (or fails).</p>
    <p num="0031">Next, an explanation will be given to the function
of the main CPU 30a. The sub CPU 30b has substantially
the same function as the main CPU 30a.</p>
    <p num="0032">A phase difference detection signal transmitted from
the steering torque sensor 12 is converted into a digital
signal by an A/D converter 31. On the basis of the digital
signal, a target assist electric current computing section
32 computes the target assist electric current to be 
supplied to the electric motor M for assisting a steering
operation. A signal indicative of the value of the electric
current thus computed is serially converted by a serial
communication interface circuit 33, and outputted to a
serial communication line 3a via a driver 34.</p>
    <p num="0033">The control circuit 13 further includes a
nonvolatile memory (EEPROM) 35 which stores therein
correction values for correction of intrinsic errors such
as variations in the gain of the output signal of the steering
torque sensor 12 and the offset of the output signal, which
are required for the computation of the target assist
electric current in the target assist electric current
computing section 32. Writing of the correction values
in the EEPROM 35 is carried out at pre-shipment adjustment
of the control circuit 13 connected to the steering torque
sensor 12. The values written in the EEPROM 35 are values
according to the intrinsic characteristics of the steering
torque sensor 12.</p>
    <p num="0034">The EEPROM 35 is rewritable, so that the writing
can be carried out not only at the pre-shipment adjustment
but also after prolonged use. Thus, the errors of the
steering torque sensor 12 can be corrected on the basis
of an environmental change and aging associated with the
steering torque sensor 12.</p>
    <p num="0035">The steering angle, a steering angular speed, the 
steering toque, failure information, the target assist
electric current and like information used in the target
assist electric current computing section 32 are collected
by a CAN (control area network) controller 36, and outputted
to a CAN bus via a CAN driver 37. Vehicle speed information
is supplied to the target assist electric current computing
section 32 from the CAN bus via the CAN controller 36, and
used for the computation of the target assist electric
current.</p>
    <p num="0036">Fig. 4 is a block diagram for explaining the function
of the motor driving circuit 14. The motor driving circuit
14 includes a CPU 40. The motor driving circuit 14 is
connected to the control circuit 13 via serial communication
lines 3a, 3b. Signals from the serial communication lines
3a, 3b are inputted to an electric current control computing
circuit 43 via drivers 41a, 41b and a serial communication
interface circuit 42. In the electric current control
computing circuit 43, an output signal is generated
according to the target assist electric current, and applied
to a motor driving section 44. The motor driving section
44 converts the output signal into a PWM-modulated electric
current signal, and drives the electric motor M on the basis
of this signal. An electric current flowing through the
electric motor M, a rotor position and failure detection
information are outputted to a CAN bus through a CAN 
controller 45 and a CAN driver 46.</p>
    <p num="0037">The CPUs 30a, 30b shown in Fig. 3 and the CPU 40
are mutually monitored by each other via the serial
communication lines 3a, 3b to check for malfunction thereof.</p>
    <p num="0038">The motor driving circuit 14 includes an EEPROM 47,
which stores therein correction values for correction of
variations in the cogging torque ripple and induced voltage
of the electric motor (brushless motor) M employed in
combination with the motor driving circuit. Writing of
the correction values in the EEPROM 47 is carried out at
the pre-shipment adjustment. The values written in the
EEPROM 47 are values according to the intrinsic
characteristics of the electric motor M.</p>
    <p num="0039">The EEPROM 47 is rewritable, so that the writing
can be carried out not only at the pre-shipment adjustment
but also after prolonged use. Thus, the errors of the
electric motor M can be corrected on the basis of an
environmental change and aging associated with the electric
motor.</p>
    <p num="0040">Figs. 5A and 5B, Figs. 6A and 6B, and Figs. 7A and
7B are perspective views illustrating the connection
between the motor driving circuit 14 and the electric motor
M in the motor module 2.</p>
    <p num="0041">Figs. 5A and 5B each illustrate the connection to
be established through terminals 51 alone. The connection 
is established on an upper side face of the electric motor
M in Fig. 5A, and on a side face of the electric motor M
in Fig. 5B.</p>
    <p num="0042">Figs. 6A and 6B each illustrate the connection to
be established through terminals 52 with the use of screws
53. The connection is established on the upper side face
of the electric motor M in Fig. 6A, and on the side face
of the electric motor M in Fig. 6B. By fixing the terminals
with the use of the screws 53, the terminals 52 are kept
in press contact with each other, so that the connection
is firmly established.</p>
    <p num="0043">Figs. 7A and 7B each illustrate the connection to
be established through terminals 54 by way of partial
welding. The connection is established on the upper side
face of the electric motor M in Fig. 7A, and on the side
face of the electric motor M in Fig. 7B. By the welding,
the terminals 54 are kept in press contact with each other,
so that the connection is further firmly established.</p>
    <p num="0044">Since a high amperage electric current flows through
the terminals, the connection with the use of the screws
(Figs. 6A and 6B) or the connection by way of the welding
(Figs. 7A and 7B) is more preferable than the connection
with the use of the connector (Figs. 5A and 5B).</p>
    <p num="0045">While the embodiment of the present invention has
thus been described, it should be understood that the 
invention be not limited to these embodiments.
<sl><li>(1) The present invention is applicable to a sensor
module including a steering angle sensor. In this case,
the control circuit 13 has a function of computing the target
assist electric current on the basis of a steering angle
detected by the steering angle sensor.</li><li>(2) The present invention is applicable to a sensor
module including a yaw rate sensor. In this case, the
control circuit 13 has a function of computing the target
assist electric current on the basis of a yaw rate detected
by the yaw rate sensor.</li><li>(3) The present invention is applicable to a case where
the target assist electric current is computed by employing
two or more of the steering torque sensor, the steering
angle sensor and the yaw rate sensor in combination. In
this case, the two or more sensors are housed in the sensor
module.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0046">Besides, various modifications may be made within
the scope of the present invention.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>An electric power steering system including a steering
state detector for detecting a steering state of a motor vehicle,
a control circuit (13) which generates a control signal
for controlling an electric motor (M) on the basis of the
steering state of the motor vehicle detected by the steering
state detector, and a motor driving circuit (14) which generates
a signal for driving the electric motor (M) on the basis
of an output of the control circuit (13);
   characterized by:
<claim-text><claim-text>a first module (1) in which the steering state detector
and the control circuit (13) are housed; and</claim-text><claim-text>a second module (2) in which the electric motor (M) and
the motor driving circuit (14) are housed,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the first module (1) and the second module (2) are
separately mounted in the electric power steering system.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The electric power steering system of claim 1, wherein the
steering state detector is a steering torque sensor (12) for
detecting a steering torque.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The electric power steering system of claim 2, wherein the
steering torque sensor (12) is a steering torque sensor of
phase difference type.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The electric power steering system of any of claims 1
to 3, characterized in that the steering state detector is a
steering angle sensor for detecting a steering angle.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The electric power steering system of any of claims 1
to 4, characterized in that the steering state detector is a
yaw rate sensor for detecting a yaw rate of the motor vehicle.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The electric power steering system of any of claims 1
to 5, characterized in that the first module (1) includes a
central processing circuit (30a, 30b), and the second module
(2) includes a central processing circuit (40).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>The electric power steering system of claim 6, characterized
in that the central processing circuit of the first module
and the central processing circuit of the second module are mutually
monitored by each other to check for malfunction
thereof.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The electric power steering system of any of claims 1
to 7, characterized in that the first module (1) has a function
of correcting the steering state detector.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>The electric power steering system of any of claims 1
to 8, characterized in that the second module (2) has a function
of correcting the electric motor (M).</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
