<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1233414-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1233414" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="18901995" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020821">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1233414-A2" status="new" fvid="23546569">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1233414</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20020821</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02003372-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02003372</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020213</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001039140-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001039140</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010215</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G06F  12/14        20060101AFI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G06F  12/14        20060101CFI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G06F  21/00        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G06F  21/24        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G06Q  50/00        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G06Q  50/00        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B  20/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B  20/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B  20/10        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B  20/10        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04L   9/08        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04L   9/08        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04N   5/765       20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04N   5/765       20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04N   5/781       20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04N   5/781       20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04N   5/84        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04N   5/85        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04N   5/91        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04N   5/91        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04N   7/16        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04N   7/16        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G11B  20/00P</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G11B  20/10</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Vorrichtung zum Ungültigmachen von Daten um den auf einem Aufzeichnungsmedium aufgezeichneten digitalen Inhalt ungültig zu machen</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Data nullification device for nullifying digital content recorded on a recording medium</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Dispositif de nullification de données pour nullifier des contenus digitaux enregistrés sur un support d'enregistrement</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MATSUSHITA ELECTRIC IND CO LTD</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MATSUSHITA ELECTRIC INDUSTRIAL CO., LTD.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Matsushita Electric Industrial Co., Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1006, Oasa Kadoma</street>
              <city>Kadoma-shi, Osaka-fu 571-8501</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ITO YOSHIKATSU</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MIYAZAKI MASAYA</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MOTOHASHI YOSHIHIKO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MURASE KAORU</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ITO, YOSHIKATSU</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MIYAZAKI, MASAYA</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MOTOHASHI, YOSHIHIKO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MURASE, KAORU</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>ITO, YOSHIKATSU</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>2-9-15-1303, Makinosaka, Hirakata-shi</street>
              <city>Osaka-fu 573-1146</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Miyazaki, Masaya,</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1-6-14, Asahigaoka, Ikeda-shi</street>
              <city>Osaka-fu 563-0022</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Motohashi, Yoshihiko,</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1-5-12-706, Tomobuchi-cho, Miyakojima-ku</street>
              <city>Osaka-shi, Osaka-fu 534-0016</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Murase, Kaoru, Purejierukurihara 105,</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>2-8-29, Meyasukita, Ikaruga-cho,</street>
              <city>Ikoma-gun, Nara-ken 636-0133</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Grünecker, Kinkeldey, Stockmair &amp;amp; Schwanhäusser Anwaltssozietät</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Maximilianstrasse 58</street>
              <city>80538 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A data nullification device for nullifying target
data recorded on a recording medium is provided. The
target data is made up of a plurality of data blocks. A
judging unit (111) judges, in units of data blocks, whether the
target data needs to be nullified. A nullifying unit
nullifies, when a predetermined number of data blocks are
judged as needing to be nullified or when one or more data
blocks whose total amount of data reaches a predetermined
amount are judged as needing to be nullified, the judged
data blocks.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="76" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="102"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">This application is based on an application No.
2001-039140 filed in Japan, the contents of which are
hereby incorporated by reference.</p>
    <heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Field of the Invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0002">The present invention relates to a device for
nullifying data to protect its copyright, and in
particular relates to techniques for enhancing user
convenience while protecting copyrighted data.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Related Art</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0003">The digitization of information is increasing in
recent years. Since digitized information (hereafter
referred to as "digital content") not only is relatively
easy to handle but also does not degrade in quality with
time, information such as audio and video data is
becoming more and more digitized. </p>
    <p num="0004">On the other hand, digital content can be copied
perfectly with no decrease in quality. This provokes
unauthorized acts such as illegal duplication or
tampering of copyrighted information.</p>
    <p num="0005">To discourage such unauthorized acts, a method may
be employed that encrypts digital content, and provides
a decryption key for decrypting the encrypted digital
content (hereafter simply referred to as "encrypted
content") only to devices of authorized users who have
agreed to pay a usage fee to the copyright holder.</p>
    <p num="0006">This prohibits the encrypted content from being
decrypted using devices other than those of the
authorized users. Hence the digital content can be
protected from unauthorized use.</p>
    <p num="0007">Also, there is a method for indicating the
copyright protection status of digital content.
According to this method, copy control information (CCI)
that shows whether copying of the digital content is
permitted or not is attached to the digital content.</p>
    <p num="0008">In more detail, the copy control information
carries one of the four instructions "Copy Never", "Copy
one Generation", "Copy No more", and "Copy Free".</p>
    <p num="0009">"Copy Never" means no copies of digital content are
permitted.</p>
    <p num="0010">"Copy one Generation" means only a first generation 
copy of digital content is permitted. The first
generation copy of the digital content is given copy
control information "Copy No more".</p>
    <p num="0011">"Copy No more" is copy control information that is
attached to digital content which is a first generation
copy of digital content whose copy control information
is "Copy one Generation". "Copy No more" means copying
is not permitted any more though it was previously.</p>
    <p num="0012">"Copy Free" means digital content can be copied
freely.</p>
    <p num="0013">In commercial digital broadcasting and the like,
digital content is transmitted via a transmission line
in the following manner. If the copy control
information of the digital content is "Copy Never", "Copy
one Generation", or "Copy No more", it is definitely
transmitted in an encrypted form, to ensure security on
the transmission line. If the copy control information
of the digital content is "Copy Free", it is usually
transmitted in an unencrypted form.</p>
    <p num="0014">When the user obtains digital content whose copy
control information is "Copy Never" via a transmission
line and reproduces it, the user is prohibited from
copying the obtained digital content to a recording
medium. Also, when the user obtains digital content
whose copy control information is "Copy one Generation" 
and records it onto a recording medium thereby generating
digital content whose copy control information is "Copy
No more", the user cannot copy the digital content
recorded on the recording medium to another recording
medium. In such cases where copying of digital content
is completely prohibited, the user is likely to encounter
a lot of inconveniences.</p>
    <p num="0015">If copying of digital content transmitted via a
transmission line is permitted, the user can perform time
shifting, i.e., the user can record the digital content
to a recording medium for later reproduction, or the user
can record the digital content to a recording medium such
as an HDD (hard disk drive) and at the same time reproduce
it. However, in the case of digital content marked as
"Copy Never", once the user breaks off viewing the
digital content to go to the bathroom or to answer the
telephone or bell, he or she cannot view the missed part
unless the digital content is rebroadcast. Many movie
films run for about two hours, and some feature length
films even run for more than four hours. Also,
commercial digital broadcasting and the like are usually
commercial-free. Therefore, to view an entire movie
film or the like which is marked as "Copy Never", the
user cannot answer the phone or bell and cannot even go
to the bathroom for the running time of the movie film 
that lasts two to four hours. This causes a great deal
of inconvenience to the user.</p>
    <p num="0016">Also, if copying of digital content is still
permitted after the user acquires the digital content
and records it to a recording medium, the user can freely
copy or move the recorded digital content to another
recording medium. However, in the case of digital
content marked as "Copy one Generation", once the user
has acquired the digital content and recorded it onto
some recording medium, the user cannot move that digital
content to another recording medium. Since it is
convenient to use a fixed recording medium such as an
HDD that is easy to use and quick to access, the user
is likely to record the acquired digital content first
of all to such a fixed recording medium. However, fixed
recording media have only limited capacities. Also,
general fixed recording media such as HDDs are more
susceptible to breakage than removable recording media,
as they tend to be constantly used. For these reasons,
if the user views the digital content and wants to store
it long-term, it is desirable to move the digital content
to a removable recording medium, such as a DVD-RW or a
digital videotape, that has a larger capacity and is more
preferable for long-term storage.</p>
    <p num="0017">However, it is not acceptable, in terms of 
copyright protection, to alter the non-copyable status
of the copyrighted digital content so as to improve
user-friendliness.</p>
    <p num="0018">Under copyright protection, digital content whose
copy control information is "Copy Never" can be viewed
but cannot be copied, whilst digital content whose copy
control information is "Copy one Generation" can be
copied only once.</p>
    <p num="0019">In view of this, it is desirable to allow copying
of digital content under a specific condition but then
reliably nullify the digital content. In this way,
user-friendliness can be improved without departing
from the principle of copy prohibition.</p>
    <heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0020">The present invention has an object of providing
a data nullification device, a data nullification method,
a data nullification program, and a computer-readable
recording medium recording a data nullification program
which enable user-friendliness to be improved without
departing from the principle of copy prohibition.</p>
    <p num="0021">The stated object can be achieved by a data
nullification device for nullifying target data
recorded on a recording medium, the target data being
made up of a plurality of data blocks, the data 
nullification device including: a judging unit operable
to judge, for each data block recorded on the recording
medium, whether the data block needs to be nullified;
and a nullifying unit operable to nullify, when a
predetermined number of data blocks are judged as needing
to be nullified or when one or more data blocks whose
total amount of data reaches a predetermined amount are
judged as needing to be nullified, the judged data
blocks.</p>
    <p num="0022">With this construction, when a predetermined
number of data blocks satisfy a specific condition or
one or more data blocks whose total amount of data reaches
a predetermined amount satisfy the specific condition,
the data blocks are nullified.</p>
    <p num="0023">Accordingly, when the target data is marked as
"Copy Never" or "Copy No more", a copy can be made but
then the copy or the original is reliably nullified. In
this way, user-friendliness can be improved without
departing from the principle of copy prohibition.</p>
    <p num="0024">Also, since the target data is nullified in a
predetermined data unit, even if an unauthorized user
tries to obtain the copy by powering off the device
halfway through the operation, he or she cannot obtain
the whole target data. By employing an appropriate data
unit for the nullification, security can be improved. </p>
    <p num="0025">Here, the recording medium may store sequence
information that shows a sequence in which the plurality
of data blocks were recorded onto the recording medium,
wherein the judging unit judges, in succession, the
plurality of data blocks in the sequence shown by the
sequence information, as needing to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0026">With this construction, the plurality of data
blocks are judged, in the recording sequence, as needing
to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0027">This allows only new data to be retained on the
recording medium.</p>
    <p num="0028">Here, the target data may be data which is
continuously transmitted from an external device and
recorded on the recording medium, wherein the data
nullification device further includes: a receiving unit
operable to receive data from the external device, and
having set the received data as a new data block, the
nullifying unit writes the new data block to a recording
area on the recording medium that stores a data block
which is judged as needing to be nullified, to nullify
the recorded data block and at the same time record the
new data block.</p>
    <p num="0029">With this construction, the new data block is
written to the recording area of the old data block which
is judged as needing to be nullified. </p>
    <p num="0030">In other words, recording the new data block has
the effect of nullifying the old data block.
Accordingly, the load on the device hardly increases
despite the execution of the nullification.</p>
    <p num="0031">Here, each data block may have a length
corresponding to a fixed transmission time period,
wherein a specified number of recording areas which are
each used as a recording area of a data block are reserved
on the recording medium.</p>
    <p num="0032">With this construction, the specified number of
recording areas each for recording data of the fixed
transmission time period is reserved on the recording
medium.</p>
    <p num="0033">Here, if the length corresponding to the fixed
transmission time period is variable and if part of the
recorded data block remains even after the new data block
is written, the nullifying unit may further write
arbitrary data over the part of the recorded data block.</p>
    <p num="0034">With this construction, arbitrary data is written
over the part of the old data block which was not
destroyed by the overwriting with the new data block.</p>
    <p num="0035">This enables the whole old data block to be
destroyed.</p>
    <p num="0036">Here, if there is not a new data block which is to
be recorded, the nullifying unit may write arbitrary data 
to the recording area.</p>
    <p num="0037">With this construction, even when there is not a
new data block, arbitrary data is written over each old
data block.</p>
    <p num="0038">This enables each old data block to be destroyed.</p>
    <p num="0039">Here, the recording medium may store time limit
information showing a recording time limit of each data
block recorded on the recording medium, the recording
time limit being a time limit after which retention of
the data block on the recording medium is prohibited,
wherein the judging unit judges that each data block
whose recording time limit is reached needs to be
nullified, based on the time limit information, and
whenever any data block is judged as needing to be
nullified because a recording time limit of the data
block is reached, the nullifying unit nullifies the data
block irrespective of whether the predetermined number
of data blocks are judged as needing to be nullified or
whether one or more data blocks whose total amount of
data reaches the predetermined amount are judged as
needing to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0040">With this construction, each data block whose
recording time limit is reached is judged as needing to
be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0041">Since each data block is nullified based on its 
recording time limit, it is possible to make such setting
that gives a priority to each data block. This increases
flexibility.</p>
    <p num="0042">Here, the data nullification device may further
include: a utilizing unit operable to utilize the target
data recorded on the recording medium, in units of data
blocks, wherein the judging unit further judges that each
data block which was utilized by the utilizing unit needs
to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0043">With this construction, each utilized data block
is judged as needing to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0044">This improves user-friendliness without departing
from the principle of copy prohibition.</p>
    <p num="0045">Here, the data nullification device may further
include: a utilizing unit operable to utilize the target
data recorded on the recording medium, in units of data
blocks, wherein the judging unit judges that each data
block which was utilized by the utilizing unit needs to
be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0046">With this construction, each utilized data block
is judged as needing to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0047">Since each data block which was reproduced, copied,
or moved is nullified, user-friendliness can be improved
without departing from the principle of copy
prohibition. </p>
    <p num="0048">Here, the target data may be content data which is
transmitted from an external device and recorded on the
recording medium, wherein the content data is
accompanied with copy control information showing
whether copying of the content data is permitted or
prohibited, the utilizing unit reproduces the content
data recorded on the recording medium, in units of data
blocks, and only if the copy control information
accompanying the content data shows that the copying of
the content data is prohibited, the judging unit judges
that each data block which was reproduced by the
utilizing unit needs to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0049">With this construction, if the copy control
information shows that the copying of the content data
is prohibited, each reproduced data block is judged as
needing to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0050">In other words, when the content data is "Copy
Never", a copy of the content data is allowed but then
the copy is reliably nullified.</p>
    <p num="0051">Here, the target data may be accompanied with copy
control information showing whether copying of the
target data is permitted or prohibited, wherein the
utilizing unit records the target data recorded on the
recording medium, to another recording medium, in units
of data blocks, and only if the copy control information 
accompanying the target data shows that the copying of
the target data is prohibited, the judging unit judges
that each data block on the recording medium which was
recorded by the utilizing unit needs to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0052">With this construction, if the copy control
information shows that the copying of the content data
is prohibited, each copied data block is judged as
needing to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0053">In other words, when the content data is "Copy No
more", a second generation copy of the content data is
allowed but then a first generation copy of the content
data is reliably nullified.</p>
    <p num="0054">Here, the nullifying unit may destroy all parts of
a data block which is judged as needing to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0055">With this construction, all parts of the data block
judged as needing to be nullified are destroyed.</p>
    <p num="0056">This enhances security.</p>
    <p num="0057">Here, the nullifying unit may destroy at least a
part of a data block which is judged as needing to be
nullified, the part of the data block being necessary
to utilize remaining parts of the data block.</p>
    <p num="0058">With this construction, at least the part of the
data block which is needed to utilize the other parts
of the data block is destroyed.</p>
    <p num="0059">This makes the data block unusable while minimizing 
the increase in the load of the device.</p>
    <p num="0060">Here, the target data may be MPEG data including
I pictures, wherein the part of the data block necessary
to utilize the remaining parts of the data block is an
I picture.</p>
    <p num="0061">With this construction, the part of the data block
which is needed to utilize the other parts of the data
block is an I picture in MPEG data.</p>
    <p num="0062">B pictures and P pictures cannot be utilized if the
I picture which these B pictures and P pictures refer
to is destroyed. By destroying only the I picture while
leaving the B and P pictures as they are, the increase
in the load of the device is reduced.</p>
    <p num="0063">Here, the target data may be MPEG data including
I pictures, wherein the part of the data block necessary
to utilize the remaining parts of the data block is a
first sector of an I picture.</p>
    <p num="0064">With this construction, the part of the data block
which is needed to utilize the other parts of the data
block is the first sector of the I picture.</p>
    <p num="0065">This makes it impossible to properly reproduce the
I picture, so that the remaining B and P pictures cannot
be reproduced. Thus, by destroying only the first
sector of the I picture, the increase in the load of the
device can be reduced. </p>
    <p num="0066">Here, when the data nullification device does not
have an enough processing capacity, the nullifying unit
may destroy only the part of the data block necessary
to utilize the remaining parts of the data block.</p>
    <p num="0067">With this construction, when there is not an enough
processing capacity, only the part of the data block
which is needed to utilize the other parts is destroyed.</p>
    <p num="0068">This enhances security without increasing the load
of the device.</p>
    <p num="0069">Here, the nullifying unit may destroy the remaining
parts of the data block within a range where a processing
capacity of the data nullification device allows.</p>
    <p num="0070">With this construction, the other parts of the data
block are destroyed within a range where the processing
capacity of the device allows.</p>
    <p num="0071">This enhances security without increasing the load
of the device.</p>
    <p num="0072">Here, the data nullification device may further
include: a destroying unit operable to destroy remaining
parts of data blocks which were not destroyed by the
nullifying unit, when the data nullification device has
an enough processing capacity.</p>
    <p num="0073">With this construction, when there is an enough
processing capacity, remaining parts of data blocks
which were not destroyed by the nullifying unit are all 
destroyed.</p>
    <p num="0074">This enhances security without increasing the load
of the device.</p>
    <p num="0075">Here, each data block recorded on the recording
medium may be encrypted using an individual encryption
key, wherein a decryption key for decrypting the
encrypted data block is stored on the recording medium,
and the nullifying unit destroys at least a decryption
key corresponding to a data block which is judged as
needing to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0076">With this construction, at least the decryption key
corresponding to the data block is destroyed. As a
result, the data block remaining on the recording medium
becomes unusable, since the data block cannot be
decrypted without the decryption key.</p>
    <p num="0077">Thus, the data block is made unusable with a minimum
increase in the load of the device.</p>
    <p num="0078">Here, the data nullification device may further
include: an acquiring unit operable to acquire the target
data in an encoded form; a decoding unit operable to
decode the encoded target data using a user key which
has been provided to authorized users in advance, to
obtain the target data; a key generating unit operable
to generate an arbitrary encryption key and a decryption
key corresponding to the encryption key, for each data 
block of the target data; a data encrypting unit operable
to encrypt the data block using the encryption key so
that the encrypted data block can be decrypted using the
corresponding decryption key; a key encrypting unit
operable to encrypt the decryption key using an
identifier unique to the data nullification device; and
a recording unit operable to record the encrypted data
block and the encrypted decryption key onto the recording
medium.</p>
    <p num="0079">With this construction, the encoded target data is
decoded using the user key, and each data block of the
decoded target data is encrypted using an encryption key.
Further, a decryption key corresponding to the
encryption key is encrypted using an identifier unique
to the device, and the encrypted data block and the
encrypted decryption key are recorded onto the recording
medium.</p>
    <p num="0080">Since the encrypted decryption key cannot be
decrypted without the identifier unique to the device
and so cannot be used by other devices, security can be
enhanced.</p>
    <p num="0081">Here, at least the decoding unit, the key
generating unit, the data encrypting unit, and the key
encrypting unit may be contained in a single
semiconductor chip. </p>
    <p num="0082">With this construction, the decoding unit, the key
generating unit, the data encrypting unit, and the key
encrypting unit can be contained in the same
semiconductor chip. This keeps the target data in an
unencrypted form from being transferred over wiring of
a circuit board.</p>
    <p num="0083">In other words, an unauthorized user cannot
retrieve the unencrypted target data during the
operation. This enhances security.</p>
    <p num="0084">The stated object can also be achieved by a data
nullification program for nullifying target data
recorded on a recording medium, the target data being
made up of a plurality of data blocks, the data
nullification program having a computer execute the
steps of: judging, for each data block recorded on the
recording medium, whether the data block needs to be
nullified; and nullifying, when a predetermined number
of data blocks are judged as needing to be nullified or
when one or more data blocks whose total amount of data
reaches a predetermined amount are judged as needing to
be nullified, the judged data blocks.</p>
    <p num="0085">With this construction, when a predetermined
number of data blocks satisfy a specific condition or
one or more data blocks whose total amount of data reaches
a predetermined amount satisfy the specific condition, 
the data blocks are nullified.</p>
    <p num="0086">Accordingly, when the target data is marked as
"Copy Never" or "Copy No more", a copy can be made but
then the copy or the original is reliably nullified. In
this way, user-friendliness can be improved without
departing from the principle of copy prohibition.</p>
    <p num="0087">Also, since the target data is nullified in a
predetermined data unit, even if an unauthorized user
tries to obtain the copy by powering off the device
halfway through the operation, he or she cannot obtain
the whole target data. By employing an appropriate data
unit for the nullification, security can be improved.</p>
    <p num="0088">Here, the recording medium may store sequence
information that shows a sequence in which the plurality
of data blocks were recorded onto the recording medium,
wherein the judging step judges, in succession, the
plurality of data blocks in the sequence shown by the
sequence information, as needing to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0089">With this construction, the plurality of data
blocks are judged, in the recording sequence, as needing
to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0090">This allows only new data to be retained on the
recording medium.</p>
    <p num="0091">Here, the target data may be data which is
continuously transmitted from an external device and 
recorded on the recording medium, wherein the data
nullification program further having the computer
execute the step of: receiving data from the external
device, and having set the received data as a new data
block, the nullifying step writes the new data block to
a recording area on the recording medium that stores a
data block which is judged as needing to be nullified,
to nullify the recorded data block and at the same time
record the new data block.</p>
    <p num="0092">With this construction, the new data block is
written to the recording area of the old data block which
is judged as needing to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0093">In other words, recording the new data block has
the effect of nullifying the old data block.
Accordingly, the load on the device hardly increases
despite the execution of the nullification.</p>
    <p num="0094">Here, the recording medium may store time limit
information showing a recording time limit of each data
block recorded on the recording medium, the recording
time limit being a time limit after which retention of
the data block on the recording medium is prohibited,
wherein the judging step judges that each data block
whose recording time limit is reached needs to be
nullified, based on the time limit information, and
whenever any data block is judged as needing to be 
nullified because a recording time limit of the data
block is reached, the nullifying step nullifies the data
block irrespective of whether the predetermined number
of data blocks are judged as needing to be nullified or
whether one or more data blocks whose total amount of
data reaches the predetermined amount are judged as
needing to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0095">With this construction, each data block whose
recording time limit is reached is judged as needing to
be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0096">Since each data block is nullified based on its
recording time limit, it is possible to make such setting
that gives a priority to each data block. This increases
flexibility.</p>
    <p num="0097">Here, the data nullification program may further
have the computer execute the step of: utilizing the
target data recorded on the recording medium, in units
of data blocks, wherein the judging step further judges
that each data block which was utilized in the utilizing
step needs to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0098">With this construction, each utilized data block
is judged as needing to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0099">This improves user-friendliness without departing
from the principle of copy prohibition.</p>
    <p num="0100">Here, the data nullification program may further 
have the computer execute the step of: utilizing the
target data recorded on the recording medium, in units
of data blocks, wherein the judging step judges that each
data block which was utilized in the utilizing step needs
to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0101">With this construction, each utilized data block
is judged as needing to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0102">Since each data block which was reproduced, copied,
or moved is nullified, user-friendliness can be improved
without departing from the principle of copy
prohibition.</p>
    <p num="0103">Here, the nullifying step may destroy all parts of
a data block which is judged as needing to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0104">With this construction, all parts of the data block
judged as needing to be nullified are destroyed.</p>
    <p num="0105">This enhances security.</p>
    <p num="0106">Here, the nullifying step may destroy at least a
part of a data block which is judged as needing to be
nullified, the part of the data block being necessary
to utilize remaining parts of the data block.</p>
    <p num="0107">With this construction, at least the part of the
data block which is needed to utilize the other parts
of the data block is destroyed.</p>
    <p num="0108">This makes the data block unusable while minimizing
the increase in the load of the device. </p>
    <p num="0109">Here, each data block recorded on the recording
medium may be encrypted using an individual encryption
key, wherein a decryption key for decrypting the
encrypted data block is stored on the recording medium,
and the nullifying step destroys at least a decryption
key corresponding to a data block which is judged as
needing to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0110">With this construction, at least the decryption key
corresponding to the data block is destroyed. As a
result, the data block remaining on the recording medium
becomes unusable, since the data block cannot be
decrypted without the decryption key.</p>
    <p num="0111">Thus, the data block is made unusable with a minimum
increase in the load of the device.</p>
    <p num="0112">The stated object can also be achieved by a data
nullification method for nullifying target data
recorded on a recording medium, the target data being
made up of a plurality of data blocks, the data
nullification method including the steps of: judging,
for each data block recorded on the recording medium,
whether the data block needs to be nullified; and
nullifying, when a predetermined number of data blocks
are judged as needing to be nullified or when one or more
data blocks whose total amount of data reaches a
predetermined amount are judged as needing to be 
nullified, the judged data blocks.</p>
    <p num="0113">With this construction, when a predetermined
number of data blocks satisfy a specific condition or
one or more data blocks whose total amount of data reaches
a predetermined amount satisfy the specific condition,
the data blocks are nullified.</p>
    <p num="0114">Accordingly, when the target data is marked as
"Copy Never" or "Copy No more", a copy can be made but
then the copy or the original is reliably nullified. In
this way, user-friendliness can be improved without
departing from the principle of copy prohibition.</p>
    <p num="0115">Also, since the target data is nullified in a
predetermined data unit, even if an unauthorized user
tries to obtain the copy by powering off the device
halfway through the operation, he or she cannot obtain
the whole target data. By employing an appropriate data
unit for the nullification, security can be improved.</p>
    <p num="0116">Here, the recording medium may store sequence
information that shows a sequence in which the plurality
of data blocks were recorded onto the recording medium,
wherein the judging step judges, in succession, the
plurality of data blocks in the sequence shown by the
sequence information, as needing to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0117">With this construction, the plurality of data
blocks are judged, in the recording sequence, as needing 
to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0118">This allows only new data to be retained on the
recording medium.</p>
    <p num="0119">Here, the target data may be data which is
continuously transmitted from an external device and
recorded on the recording medium, wherein the data
nullification method further including the step of:
receiving data from the external device, and wherein
having set the received data as a new data block, the
nullifying step writes the new data block to a recording
area on the recording medium that stores a data block
which is judged as needing to be nullified, to nullify
the recorded data block and at the same time record the
new data block.</p>
    <p num="0120">With this construction, the new data block is
written to the recording area of the old data block which
is judged as needing to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0121">In other words, recording the new data block has
the effect of nullifying the old data block.
Accordingly, the load on the device hardly increases
despite the execution of the nullification.</p>
    <p num="0122">Here, the recording medium may store time limit
information showing a recording time limit of each data
block recorded on the recording medium, the recording
time limit being a time limit after which retention of 
the data block on the recording medium is prohibited,
wherein the judging step judges that each data block
whose recording time limit is reached needs to be
nullified, based on the time limit information, and
whenever any data block is judged as needing to be
nullified because a recording time limit of the data
block is reached, the nullifying step nullifies the data
block irrespective of whether the predetermined number
of data blocks are judged as needing to be nullified or
whether one or more data blocks whose total amount of
data reaches the predetermined amount are judged as
needing to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0123">With this construction, each data block whose
recording time limit is reached is judged as needing to
be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0124">Since each data block is nullified based on its
recording time limit, it is possible to make such setting
that gives a priority to each data block. This increases
flexibility.</p>
    <p num="0125">Here, the data nullification method may further
include the step of: utilizing the target data recorded
on the recording medium, in units of data blocks, wherein
the judging step further judges that each data block
which was utilized in the utilizing step needs to be
nullified. </p>
    <p num="0126">With this construction, each utilized data block
is judged as needing to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0127">This improves user-friendliness without departing
from the principle of copy prohibition.</p>
    <p num="0128">Here, the data nullification method may further
include the step of: utilizing the target data recorded
on the recording medium, in units of data blocks, wherein
the judging step judges that each data block which was
utilized in the utilizing step needs to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0129">With this construction, each utilized data block
is judged as needing to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0130">Since each data block which was reproduced, copied,
or moved is nullified, user-friendliness can be improved
without departing from the principle of copy
prohibition.</p>
    <p num="0131">Here, the nullifying step may destroy all parts
of a data block which is judged as needing to be
nullified.</p>
    <p num="0132">With this construction, all parts of the data block
judged as needing to be nullified are destroyed.</p>
    <p num="0133">This enhances security.</p>
    <p num="0134">Here, the nullifying step may destroy at least a
part of a data block which is judged as needing to be
nullified, the part of the data block being necessary
to utilize remaining parts of the data block. </p>
    <p num="0135">With this construction, at least the part of the
data block which is needed to utilize the other parts
of the data block is destroyed.</p>
    <p num="0136">This makes the data block unusable while minimizing
the increase in the load of the device.</p>
    <p num="0137">Here, each data block recorded on the recording
medium may be encrypted using an individual encryption
key, wherein a decryption key for decrypting the
encrypted data block is stored on the recording medium,
and the nullifying step destroys at least a decryption
key corresponding to a data block which is judged as
needing to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0138">With this construction, at least the decryption key
corresponding to the data block is destroyed. As a
result, the data block remaining on the recording medium
becomes unusable, since the data block cannot be
decrypted without the decryption key.</p>
    <p num="0139">Thus, the data block is made unusable with a minimum
increase in the load of the device.</p>
    <heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
    <p num="0140">These and other objects, advantages and features
of the invention will become apparent from the following
description thereof taken in conjunction with the
accompanying drawings which illustrate specific 
embodiments of the invention.</p>
    <p num="0141">In the drawings:
<sl><li>FIG. 1 shows an example hardware construction of
a reception/reproduction/nullification system to which
the first embodiment of the invention relates;</li><li>FIG. 2 is a functional block diagram of a
reception/reproduction/nullification device of the
first embodiment;</li><li>FIG. 3 shows an example operation of the
reception/reproduction/nullification device of the
first embodiment;</li><li>FIG. 4 shows another example operation of the
reception/reproduction/nullification device of the
first embodiment;</li><li>FIG. 5 is a functional block diagram of a
reception/reproduction/nullification device of the
second embodiment of the invention;</li><li>FIG. 6 shows an example operation of the
reception/reproduction/nullification device of the
second embodiment;</li><li>FIG. 7 is a functional block diagram of a
reception/reproduction/nullification device of the
third embodiment of the invention; and</li><li>FIG. 8 shows an example operation of the
reception/reproduction/nullification device of the 
third embodiment.</li></sl></p>
    <heading>DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">First Embodiment</u>
    </heading>
    <heading>(Overview)</heading>
    <p num="0142">The first embodiment of the present invention is
the following device. When digital content which is
copy-prohibited ("Copy Never") is received, the device
allows the digital content to be recorded onto a
recording medium, but nullifies the recorded digital
content once the recorded digital content has been
reproduced or a predetermined time period has passed from
the time at which the digital content was recorded. This
enables time shifting to be performed only for one
reproduction or only within the predetermined time
period after the reception.</p>
    <heading>(Construction)</heading>
    <p num="0143">FIG. 1 shows an example hardware construction of
a reception/reproduction/nullification system to which
the first embodiment of the present invention relates.</p>
    <p num="0144">In addition to a system LSI 800, the drawing shows
an antenna 901, a reception device 902, a monitor 903,
a RAM 904, an HDD 905, a DVD recorder 906, and a ROM 907
for purposes of illustration. The system LSI 800, the
RAM 904, the HDD 905, and the ROM 907 are generally 
contained in the same case called an STB (set-top box) .</p>
    <p num="0145">The system LSI 800 includes a transport stream
decoder 801, an AV decoder 802, an encryption engine 803,
and a microcomputer 804. These construction elements
are enclosed within the same semiconductor chip, to
prevent unencrypted digital data which is obtained by
decoding a transport stream from being transferred over
wiring of a circuit board. This strengthens security.</p>
    <p num="0146">The reception device 902 receives a desired carrier
wave from a broadcast station via the antenna 901 and
demodulates it, to produce a transport stream (hereafter
a "TS stream") made up of packets storing desired digital
content and control data for the digital content. If
the desired digital content requires copyright
protection, information that indicates prohibition of
copies is attached to the digital content. As one
example, copy control information "Copy Never" is
attached to the digital content. The TS stream has a
header unit and a payload unit. The header unit includes
control information and the like and is unencrypted,
whereas the payload unit includes data that need be
delivered to its destination and is encrypted using a
cipher called scrambling.</p>
    <p num="0147">The transport stream decoder 801 descrambles the
scrambled part of the generated TS stream using a 
descramble key which has been given to authorized users
beforehand, and decodes the result. The transport
stream decoder 801 also decodes the unscrambled part of
the TS stream. Hence the transport stream decoder 801
obtains the desired digital content. As one example,
the digital content obtained here is an MPEG stream of
audio and video.</p>
    <p num="0148">The AV decoder 802 generates a video output signal
and an audio output signal from the digital content
obtained by the transport stream decoder 801, and has
the monitor 903 reproduce the video and audio.</p>
    <p num="0149">The encryption engine 803 operates as follows. If
the digital content requires copyright protection and
yet need be recorded to a recording medium such as the
RAM 904, the HDD 905, or the DVD recorder 906, the
encryption engine 803 encrypts the digital content
obtained by the transport stream decoder 801. Here, the
digital content is handled in units of data blocks which
each correspond to a predetermined broadcast time period
expressed, for example, in minutes. The encryption
engine 803 encrypts each data block using a
randomly-generated encryption key. The encryption
engine 803 also encrypts a decryption key corresponding
to the encryption key using a device ID, and records the
encrypted data block and the encrypted decryption key 
as a pair. To use the digital content, the encryption
engine 803 decrypts the encrypted decryption key using
the device ID, and decrypts the encrypted data block
using the obtained decryption key. The device ID is a
value which is unique to the semiconductor chip. In the
present example, the device ID cannot be referred to from
outside the semiconductor chip.</p>
    <p num="0150">The microcomputer 804 controls the overall
operation of the STB, by reading a control program stored
on the ROM 907 and executing it. Here, the control
program has been scrambled to prevent unauthorized users
from altering it, so that the microcomputer 804
descrambles the control program before executing it.</p>
    <p num="0151">Suppose the user who is viewing copy-prohibited
digital content indicates time shifting for some reason.
Then the microcomputer 804 exercises control so that the
following three operations are simultaneously carried
out repeatedly: (1) recording an encrypted data block
to the HDD 905; (2) decrypting an encrypted data block
which was recorded onto the HDD 905 a shift time earlier,
and reproducing the decrypted data block; and (3)
nullifying an encrypted data block on the HDD 905 which
has just been reproduced so that the data block can no
longer be reproduced.</p>
    <p num="0152">Here, the encrypted data block is nullified once 
it has been reproduced, but this condition for
nullification may be replaced by or used in combination
with the condition of whether a predetermined time period
has passed since the time at which the data block was
recorded. Most movie films run about two hours.
Accordingly, if the predetermined time period is set at
around 90 minutes, it is highly possible to keep a whole
movie film from being stored on a recording medium even
in one second. As a result, even if the power is turned
off halfway through the processing, the user cannot
obtain the whole movie film in its entirety, and so cannot
reproduce the whole movie film later. Hence time
shifting can be performed only within the predetermined
time period.</p>
    <p num="0153">FIG. 2 is a functional block diagram of a
reception/reproduction/nullification device of the
first embodiment.</p>
    <p num="0154">The reception/reproduction/nullification device
100 shown in the drawing includes a user interface unit
101, a receiving unit 102, a descrambling unit 103, a
key generating unit 104, a data encrypting unit 105, a
key encrypting unit 106, a recording unit 107, a key
decrypting unit 108, a data decrypting unit 109, a
reproducing unit 110, a nullification judging unit 111,
a processing capacity judging unit 112, a sequential 
nullifying unit 113, and a total nullifying unit 114.
In actuality, the function of the receiving unit 102
corresponds to the function of the reception device 902
shown in FIG. 1. The function of the descrambling unit
103 corresponds to the function of the transport stream
decoder 801 in FIG. 1. The functions of the key
generating unit 104, data encrypting unit 105, key
encrypting unit 106, recording unit 107, key decrypting
unit 108, and data decrypting unit 109 correspond to the
function of the encryption engine 803 in FIG. 1. The
function of the reproducing unit 110 corresponds to the
function of the AV decoder 802 in FIG. 1. The functions
of the nullification judging unit 111, processing
capacity judging unit 112, sequential nullifying unit
113, and total nullifying unit 114 correspond to the
function of the microcomputer 804 in FIG. 1.</p>
    <p num="0155">It should be noted here that an explanation on
functions which are not directly related to the present
invention has been omitted in this specification for
simplicity's sake, so that the following description may
differ with the actual practice to some extent.</p>
    <p num="0156">The user interface unit 101 receives various
indications from the user. The indications include a
view indication, a pause indication, a time shift
indication, a stop indication, and an indication to move 
digital content.</p>
    <p num="0157">The receiving unit 102 receives transmission data
broadcast from a broadcast station or the like. In the
present example, the receiving unit 102 receives digital
content which has been scrambled and is accompanied with
copy control information.</p>
    <p num="0158">The descrambling unit 103 descrambles the
scrambled digital content received by the receiving unit
102, using a descramble key which has been given to
authorized users beforehand.</p>
    <p num="0159">The key generating unit 104 operates as follows.
While the user is indicating a pause, the key generating
unit 104 arbitrarily generates a unique encryption key
and a decryption key corresponding to the encryption key
using a random number or the like, for each data block
corresponding to the predetermined broadcast time
period which is descrambled by the descrambling unit 103.
Here, an algorithm that uses the same key for encryption
and decryption is employed, so that an encryption key
and a decryption key corresponding to the encryption key
can be collectively referred to as a "unique key". For
example, a unique key is randomly generated for each data
block that corresponds to the broadcast time period of
10 minutes.</p>
    <p num="0160">The data encrypting unit 105 operates as follows. 
While the user is indicating a pause, the data encrypting
unit 105 encrypts each data block descrambled by the
descrambling unit 103 using an encryption key generated
by the key generating unit 104 for the data block, so
that the encrypted data block can be decrypted using a
decryption key corresponding to the encryption key. In
the present example, each data block corresponding to
the broadcast time period of 10 minutes is encrypted
using a corresponding unique key.</p>
    <p num="0161">The key encrypting unit 106 encrypts the decryption
key corresponding to the encryption key used by the data
encrypting unit 105, using the device ID. In the present
example, the unique key is encrypted using the device
ID.</p>
    <p num="0162">The recording unit 107 records the data block
encrypted by the data encrypting unit 105 and the
decryption key encrypted by the key encrypting unit 106,
to a predetermined recording medium as a pair. In the
present example, the pair of encrypted data block
corresponding to the broadcast time period of 10 minutes
and encrypted unique key is recorded to the HDD 905.
Here, if the digital content does not require copyright
protection, the data block may be recorded in an
unencrypted form.</p>
    <p num="0163">The key decrypting unit 108 operates as follows. 
While the user is indicating time shifting, the key
decrypting unit 108 reads an encrypted decryption key
corresponding to each encrypted data block which is to
be reproduced, from the recording medium. The key
decrypting unit 108 then decrypts the encrypted
decryption key using the device ID. In the present
example, an encrypted unique key that is paired with each
encrypted data block which was recorded a shift time
earlier (hereafter a "shift-time-old data block") is
decrypted using the device ID.</p>
    <p num="0164">The data decrypting unit 109 operates as follows.
While the user is indicating time shifting, the data
decrypting unit 109 decrypts each encrypted data block
to be reproduced, using a corresponding decryption key
decrypted by the key decrypting unit 108. In the present
example, each shift-time-old data block is decrypted
using a corresponding unique key.</p>
    <p num="0165">The reproducing unit 110 operates as follows.
While the user is indicating viewing, the reproducing
unit 110 reproduces each data block descrambled by the
descrambling unit 103. While the user is indicating
time shifting, the reproducing unit 110 reproduces each
data block decrypted by the data decrypting unit 109.</p>
    <p num="0166">The nullification judging unit 111 operates as
follows. When digital content is received and recorded 
despite its copy prohibition status, the nullification
judging unit 112 judges, for each pair of encrypted data
block and encrypted decryption key recorded on the
recording medium, whether the pair should be nullified,
based on a specific condition. In the present example,
the nullification judging unit 111 judges, for each pair
of encrypted data block corresponding to the broadcast
time period of 10 minutes and encrypted unique key which
are recorded on the HDD 905, whether the pair should be
nullified.</p>
    <p num="0167">The specific condition here is whether the data
block has been reproduced by the reproducing unit 110,
or whether a predetermined time period has passed from
the time at which the data block was received by the
receiving unit 102 or recorded by the recording unit 107.
In the case where the lapse of the predetermined time
period is used as the condition for nullification, the
recording unit 107 records time limit information to the
recording medium together with each pair of encrypted
data block and encrypted decryption key. The time limit
information shows the reception time or recording time
of the data block, and is used to manage the recording
time limit of the data block. The nullification judging
unit 111 judges whether the recording time limit is
reached, according to this time limit information. </p>
    <p num="0168">The processing capacity judging unit 112 judges
whether the device 100 has an enough processing capacity
to destroy all parts of the pair of encrypted data block
and encrypted decryption key which is judged as needing
to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0169">The sequential nullifying unit 113 operates as
follows. When the nullification judging unit 111 judges
that a predetermined number of encrypted data blocks and
their corresponding encrypted decryption keys should be
nullified or that one or more encrypted data blocks whose
total amount of data reaches a predetermined amount and
their corresponding encrypted decryption keys should be
nullified, the sequential nullifying unit 113 nullifies
the judged pairs of encrypted data blocks and encrypted
decryption keys. Here, the predetermined number is an
integer no less than 1.</p>
    <p num="0170">To nullify a pair of encrypted data block and
encrypted decryption key by the sequential nullifying
unit 113 means to make the pair on the recording medium
unusable. Ordinary data deletion merely deletes link
information of a data file or rewrites several bits of
the header unit of the data file, so that the data unit
of the data file remains as it is. This being so, the
data can be recovered in some cases even after it is
supposed to be deleted. Such data deletion cannot be 
regarded as making the data unusable. On the other hand,
the nullification performed by the sequential
nullifying unit 113 destroys the pair of encrypted data
block and encrypted decryption key itself, by writing
arbitrary data to a recording area of the pair or by
initializing the recording area.</p>
    <p num="0171">Here, the sequential nullifying unit 113 may
destroy both the encrypted data block and the encrypted
decryption key. In reality, however, writing arbitrary
data of the same size over each pair which is judged as
needing to be nullified may cause a problem to the
processing capacity of the device 100.</p>
    <p num="0172">For instance, in time shifting it is necessary to
simultaneously perform the following two sequence of
operations. The first sequence of operations is
receiving, descrambling, encrypting, and recording
broadcast digital content. The second sequence of
operations is reading, decrypting, and reproducing
recorded digital content. This puts a heavy load on the
control system, the recording medium, and the like.
This being so, to further execute an operation of writing
arbitrary data of the same size over each pair which needs
to be nullified, it is necessary to increase the
processing capacity of the device 100 or to restrict
other functions. </p>
    <p num="0173">However, the act of nullifying data itself does not
contribute user convenience at all. For this reason,
it is undesirable to increase the processing capacity
which would cause an increase in cost, or to limit other
functions.</p>
    <p num="0174">Accordingly, the sequential nullifying unit 113
may destroy at least an important part of the pair of
encrypted data block and encrypted decryption key. The
important part referred to here is data that is necessary
to reproduce the other parts of the pair. In more detail,
the important part is the decryption key. In the case
of MPEG data, the important part is an I picture or the
first sector of such an I picture.</p>
    <p num="0175">As an alternative, the sequential nullifying unit
113 may destroy all parts of the pair when the processing
capacity judging unit 112 judges that there is an enough
processing capacity, and destroy only the important part
of the pair when the processing capacity judging unit
112 judges that there is not an enough processing
capacity.</p>
    <p num="0176">The total nullifying unit 114 destroys all
remaining parts of the pairs of encrypted data blocks
and encrypted decryption keys which have not been
destroyed by the sequential nullifying unit 113, when
there is an enough processing capacity. Also, when the 
user indicates to stop time shifting, the total
nullifying unit 114 destroys all remaining parts which
have not been destroyed.</p>
    <heading>(First Operation Example)</heading>
    <p num="0177">FIG. 3 shows an example operation of the
reception/reproduction/nullification device 100 of the
first embodiment.</p>
    <p num="0178">Sequential reproduction, recording, time shifting,
and nullifying of the present invention are explained
with reference to FIG. 3.
<sl><li>(1) In the stopped state, the user interface unit
101 waits for receiving the user's indication to view
some program (S1).</li><li>(2) Upon receiving the view indication (S1:Yes),
the sequential reproduction starts (S2).
The receiving unit 102 starts receiving
transmission data of the program which the user wants
to view. In the present example, scrambled digital
content with copy control information "Copy Never" is
received.The descrambling unit 103 starts descrambling the
scrambled digital content received by the receiving unit
102.The reproducing unit 110 starts reproducing the
digital content descrambled by the descrambling unit 
103.</li><li>(3) During the sequential reproduction, the user
interface unit 101 waits for the user's indication to
stop (S3).</li><li>(4) Upon receiving the stop indication (S3:Yes),
the operations of the receiving unit 102, descrambling
unit 103, and reproducing unit 110 are stopped to end
the sequential reproduction and return to the stopped
state (S4).</li><li>(5) During the sequential reproduction, the user
interface unit 101 waits for the user's indication to
pause (S5).</li><li>(6) Upon receiving the pause indication (S5:Yes),
the recording starts (S6).
The key generating unit 104 randomly generates an
encryption key and a decryption key corresponding to the
encryption key using a random number or the like, for
each data block corresponding to the predetermined
broadcast time period which is descrambled by the
descrambling unit 103. In the present example, a unique
key is randomly generated for each data block
corresponding to the broadcast time period of 10 minutes .The data encrypting unit 105 encrypts the data
block descrambled by the descrambling unit 103 using the
encryption key generated by the key generating unit 104, 
so that the encrypted data block can be decrypted using
the corresponding decryption key. In the present
example, the data block corresponding to the broadcast
time period of 10 minutes is encrypted using the unique
key.The key encrypting unit 106 encrypts the decryption
key corresponding to the encryption key used by the data
encrypting unit 105, using the device ID. In the present
example, the unique key is encrypted using the device
ID.The recording unit 107 records the data block
encrypted by the data encrypting unit 105 and the
decryption key encrypted by the key encrypting unit 106,
to the recording medium. In the present example, the
pair of encrypted data block corresponding to the
broadcast time period of 10 minutes and encrypted unique
key is recorded to the HDD 905.The reproducing unit 110 stops the sequential
reproduction of the digital content.</li><li>(7) During the recording, the nullification
judging unit 111 judges, for each pair of encrypted data
block and encrypted decryption key recorded on the
recording medium, whether the recording time limit of
the pair is reached. In the present example, the
recording time limit is set at 90 minutes, so that once 
90 minutes have passed since a pair of encrypted data
block corresponding to the broadcast time period of 10
minutes and encrypted unique key was recorded onto the
HDD 905, the nullification judging unit 111 judges that
the recording time limit of the pair is reached (S7).</li><li>(8) When the recording time limit of the pair is
reached, the sequential nullifying unit 113 writes
arbitrary data to a recording area of the encrypted
decryption key to nullify the pair. Here, if the
processing capacity judging unit 112 judges that there
is an enough processing capacity, the sequential
nullifying unit 113 further writes arbitrary data to a
recording area of the encrypted data block (S8).</li><li>(9) During the recording, the user interface unit
101 waits for the user's indication to stop (S9).</li><li>(10) Upon receiving the stop indication (S9:Yes),
the operations of the receiving unit 102, descrambling
unit 103, key generating unit 104, data encrypting unit
105, key encrypting unit 106, and recording unit 107 are
stopped to end the recording. Also, the total
nullifying unit 114 destroys all remaining data which
has not been destroyed by the sequential nullifying unit
113, before returning to the stopped state (S10).</li><li>(11) During the recording, the user interface unit
101 waits for the user's indication to perform time 
shifting (S11).</li><li>(12) Upon receiving the time shift indication
(S11:Yes), the time shifting starts (S12).
The key decrypting unit 108 reads an encrypted
decryption key paired with each shift-time-old data
block from the recording medium, and decrypts the
encrypted decryption key using the device ID. In the
present example, the shift time is 30 minutes, so that
an encrypted unique key which is paired with each
encrypted data block that was recorded 30 to 20 minutes
earlier is decrypted. If the shift time is longer than
the recording time limit, time shifting cannot be
performed, as the shift-time-old data block has already
been nullified by the time the time shifting starts. In
such a case, the shift time is set as the recording time
limit to continue the operation.The data decrypting unit 109 decrypts the encrypted
data block using the decryption key decrypted by the key
decrypting unit 108. In the present example, the
encrypted data block that was recorded 30 to 20 minutes
earlier is decrypted using the decrypted unique key.The reproducing unit 110 reproduces the data block
decrypted by the data decrypting unit 109.</li><li>(13) During the time shifting, the nullification
judging unit 111 judges, for each pair of encrypted data 
block and encrypted decryption key recorded on the
recording medium, whether the recording time limit of
the pair is reached or whether the data block has been
reproduced by the reproducing unit 110. In the present
example, the recording time limit is 90 minutes, so that
the nullification judging unit 111 judges, for each pair
of encrypted data block corresponding to the broadcast
time period of 10 minutes and encrypted unique key which
are recorded on the HDD 905, whether 90 minutes have
passed since the recording or whether the data block has
been reproduced (S13).</li><li>(14) When the pair is judged as needing to be
nullified, the sequential nullifying unit 113 writes
arbitrary data to a recording area of the encrypted
decryption key to nullify the pair. Here, if the
processing capacity judging unit 112 judges that there
is an enough processing capacity, the sequential
nullifying unit 113 further writes arbitrary data to a
recording area of the encrypted data block (S14).</li><li>(15) During the time shifting, the user interface
unit 101 waits for the user's indication to stop (S15).</li><li>(16) Upon receiving the stop indication (S15:Yes),
the operations of the receiving unit 102, descrambling
unit 103, key generating unit 104, data encrypting unit
105, key encrypting unit 106, recording unit 107, key 
decrypting unit 108, data decrypting unit 109, and
reproducing unit 110 are stopped to end the time shifting.
Also, the total nullifying unit 114 destroys all
remaining data which has not been destroyed by the
sequential nullifying unit 113, before returning to the
stopped state (S16).</li><li>(17) During the time shifting, the user interface
unit 101 waits for the user's indication to pause (S17).</li><li>(18) Upon receiving the pause indication (S17:Yes),
the operations of the key decrypting unit 108, data
decrypting unit 109, and reproducing unit 110 are stopped,
while the recording continues (S18).</li></sl></p>
    <heading>(Second Operation Example)</heading>
    <p num="0179">In the first operation example, the recording is
not performed during the sequential reproduction.
Instead, upon receiving the user's indication to pause,
the sequential reproduction is stopped and the recording
is commenced. In the second operation example, on the
other hand, the recording is performed during the
sequential reproduction, so as to make it possible to
perform time shifting even if the user does not indicate
to pause. Moreover, an automatic pause clear function
is added in the second operation example. This function
automatically clears the pause when the pause time
reaches an upper limit, and proceeds to the time 
shifting.</p>
    <p num="0180">FIG. 4 shows another example operation of the
reception/reproduction/nullification device 100 of the
first embodiment.</p>
    <p num="0181">Here, it is assumed that digital content received
by the receiving unit 102 is accompanied with information
showing a recording time limit and a reproduction time
limit.</p>
    <p num="0182">The recording time limit is a time period which
begins when a pair is recorded and after which the
retention of the pair on the recording medium is
prohibited. The reproduction time limit is a time
period which begins when a pair is first reproduced and
after which the retention of the pair on the recording
medium is prohibited. A pair whose recording time limit
or reproduction time limit is reached is judged as
needing to be nullified.</p>
    <p num="0183">Sequential reproduction/recording, recording,
time shifting, nullification, and automatic pause
clearing of the present invention are explained by
referring to FIG. 4. Note here that steps which are the
same as those in the first operation example are given
the same step numbers.
<sl><li>(1) In the stopped state, the user interface unit
101 waits for the user's indication to view some program 
(S1).</li><li>(2) Upon receiving the view indication (S1:Yes),
the sequential reproduction/recording starts (S102).
The receiving unit 102 starts receiving
transmission data of the program which the user wants
to view. In the present example, scrambled digital
content with copy control information "Copy Never" is
received.The descrambling unit 103 starts descrambling the
scrambled digital content received by the receiving unit
102.The reproducing unit 110 starts reproducing the
digital content descrambled by the descrambling unit
103.The key generating unit 104 randomly generates an
encryption key and a decryption key corresponding to the
encryption key using a random number or the like, for
each data block corresponding to the predetermined
broadcast time period which is descrambled by the
descrambling unit 103. In the present example, a unique
key is randomly generated for each data block
corresponding to the broadcast time period of 10 minutes .The data encrypting unit 105 encrypts the
descrambled data block using the encryption key
generated by the key generating unit 104, so that the 
encrypted data block can be decrypted using the
corresponding decryption key. In the present example,
the data block corresponding to the broadcast time period
of 10 minutes is encrypted using the corresponding unique
key.The key encrypting unit 106 encrypts the decryption
key corresponding to the encryption key used by the data
encrypting unit 105, using the device ID. In the present
example, the unique key is encrypted using the device
ID.The recording unit 107 records the data block
encrypted by the data encrypting unit 105 and the
decryption key encrypted by the key encrypting unit 106,
to the recording medium. In the present example, the
pair of encrypted data block corresponding to the
broadcast time period of 10 minutes and encrypted unique
key is recorded to the HDD 905.Here, the pair is accompanied with the recording
time limit and the reproduction time limit together with
time limit information. When the data block is first
reproduced, the time at which the data block is first
reproduced is added to the time limit information.</li><li>(3) During the sequential reproduction/recording,
the nullification judging unit 111 refers to time limit
information to judge, for each pair of encrypted data 
block and encrypted decryption key recorded on the
recording medium, whether the recording time limit of
the pair is reached. Also, the nullification judging
unit 111 judges, for each pair of encrypted data block
and encrypted decryption key which has been reproduced,
whether the reproduction time limit of the pair is
reached. In the present example, the recording time
limit is set at 90 minutes after the recording, and the
reproduction time limit is set at 60 minutes after the
first reproduction. This being so, when 90 minutes have
passed since a pair of encrypted data block corresponding
to the broadcast time period of 10 minutes and encrypted
unique key was recorded, the recording time limit of the
pair is judged as being reached. Also, when 60 minutes
have passed since the pair was first reproduced, the
reproduction time limit of the pair is judged as being
reached (S103).</li><li>(4) When there is any pair of encrypted data block
and encrypted decryption key whose recording time limit
or reproduction time limit is reached, the sequential
nullifying unit 113 writes arbitrary data to a recording
area of the encrypted decryption key to nullify the pair.
Here, if the processing capacity judging unit 112 judges
that there is an enough processing capacity, the
sequential nullifying unit 113 further writes arbitrary 
data to a recording area of the encrypted data block
(S104).</li><li>(5) During the sequential reproduction/recording,
the user interface unit 101 waits for the user's
indication to stop (S105).</li><li>(6) Upon receiving the stop indication (S105:Yes),
the operations of the receiving unit 102, descrambling
unit 103, reproducing unit 110, key generating unit 104,
data encrypting unit 105, key encrypting unit 106, and
recording unit 107 are stopped to end the sequential
reproduction/recording. Also, the total nullifying
unit 114 destroys all remaining data which has not been
destroyed by the sequential nullifying unit 113, before
returning to the stopped state (S106).</li><li>(7) During the sequential reproduction/recording,
the user interface unit 101 waits for the user's
indication to perform time shifting (S107).</li><li>(8) During the sequential reproduction/recording,
the user interface unit 101 waits for the user's
indication to pause (S108).</li><li>(9) Upon receiving the pause indication (S108:Yes),
the reproduction is stopped while the recording
continues (S109).
The reproducing unit 110 stops the sequential
reproduction of the digital content. </li><li>(10) During the recording, the nullification
judging unit 111 refers to time limit information to
judge, for each pair of encrypted data block and
encrypted decryption key recorded on the recording
medium, whether the recording time limit of the pair is
reached. Also, the nullification judging unit 111
judges, for each pair of encrypted data block and
encrypted decryption key which has been reproduced,
whether the reproduction time limit of the pair is
reached (S110).</li><li>(11) When there is any pair of encrypted data block
and encrypted decryption key whose recording time limit
or reproduction time limit is reached, the sequential
nullifying unit 113 writes arbitrary data to a recording
area of the encrypted decryption key to nullify the pair.
Here, if the processing capacity judging unit 112 judges
that there is an enough processing capacity, the
sequential nullifying unit 113 further writes arbitrary
data to a recording area of the encrypted data block
(S111).</li><li>(12) During the recording, the user interface unit
101 waits for the user's indication to stop (S9).</li><li>(13) Upon receiving the stop indication (S9:Yes),
the operations of the receiving unit 102, descrambling
unit 103, key generating unit 104, data encrypting unit 
105, key encrypting unit 106, and recording unit 107 are
stopped to end the recording. Also, the total
nullifying unit 114 destroys all remaining data which
has not been destroyed by the sequential nullifying unit
113, before returning to the stopped state (S10).</li><li>(14) During the recording, the user interface unit
101 waits for the user's indication to perform time
shifting (S11) .</li><li>(15) During the recording, the sequential
nullifying unit 113 judges whether the shift time reaches
an upper limit. If the shift time reaches the upper
limit, the sequential nullifying unit 113 sets the shift
time as the upper limit and automatically clears the
pause, so that the time shifting is commenced (S115).
In the present example, the upper limit is set at 90
minutes which are the same as the recording time limit.
In this way, even if the recording time limit of data
which has never been reproduced is reached, that data
will not be nullified.</li><li>(16) When the automatic pause clearing occurs
(S115:Yes) or when the time shift indication is received
(S107:Yes, S11:Yes), the time shifting starts (S116).
The key decrypting unit 108 reads an encrypted
decryption key paired with each shift-time-old data
block from the recording medium, and decrypts the 
encrypted decryption key using the device ID. In the
present example, the shift time is 30 minutes, so that
an encrypted unique key paired with each data block which
was recorded 30 to 20 minutes earlier is decrypted. Here,
if the shift time exceeds the recording time limit, time
shifting cannot be performed, as the shift-time-old data
block has already been nullified by the time the time
shifting starts. In this case, the shift time is set
as the recording time limit to continue the operation.The data decrypting unit 109 decrypts the encrypted
data block using the decryption key decrypted by the key
decrypting unit 108. In the present example, the
encrypted data block of 30 to 20 minutes earlier is
decrypted using the decrypted unique key.The reproducing unit 110 reproduces the data block
decrypted by the data decrypting unit 109.</li><li>(17) During the time shifting, the nullification
judging unit 111 refers to time limit information to
judge, for each pair of encrypted data block and
encrypted decryption key recorded on the recording
medium, whether the recording time limit of the pair is
reached. Also, the nullification judging unit 111
judges, for each pair of encrypted data block and
encrypted decryption key which has been reproduced,
whether the reproduction time limit of the pair is 
reached (S117).</li><li>(18) When there is any pair of encrypted data block
and encrypted decryption key whose recording time limit
or reproduction time limit is reached, the sequential
nullifying unit 113 writes arbitrary data to a recording
area of the encrypted decryption key to nullify the pair.
Here, if the processing capacity judging unit 112 judges
that there is an enough processing capacity, the
sequential nullifying unit 113 further writes arbitrary
data to a recording area of the encrypted data block
(S118).</li><li>(19) During the time shifting, the user interface
unit 101 waits for the user's indication to stop (S15) .</li><li>(20) Upon receiving the stop indication (S15:Yes),
the operations of the receiving unit 102, descrambling
unit 103, key generating unit 104, data encrypting unit
105, key encrypting unit 106, recording unit 107, key
decrypting unit 108, data decrypting unit 109, and
reproducing unit 110 are stopped to end the time shifting.
Also, the total nullifying unit 114 destroys all
remaining data which has not been destroyed by the
sequential nullifying unit 113, before returning to the
stopped state (S16).</li><li>(21) During the time shifting, the user interface
unit 101 waits for the user's indication to pause (S17). </li><li>(22) Upon receiving the pause indication (S17:Yes),
the operations of the key decrypting unit 108, data
decrypting unit 109, and reproducing unit 110 are stopped,
while the recording continues (S18).</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0184">According to the first embodiment of the present
invention, copy-prohibited digital content can be
recorded to enable time shifting, but the recorded
digital content is promptly nullified to protect its
copyright. This allows user-friendliness to be
improved without departing from the principle of copy
prohibition.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Second Embodiment</u>
    </heading>
    <heading>(Overview)</heading>
    <p num="0185">The second embodiment of the present invention is
the following device. When digital content which is
copy-prohibited ("Copy Never") is received, the device
allows the digital content to be recorded, but nullifies
the recorded digital content once a predetermined time
period has passed. Here, by writing new data blocks over
old data blocks which need be nullified, the old data
blocks which have been stored for more than the
predetermined time period can be nullified without
affecting the processing capacity of the device. As a
result, time shifting can be performed only within the 
predetermined time period from the reception.</p>
    <heading>(Construction)</heading>
    <p num="0186">A reception/reproduction/nullification device of
the second embodiment has the same hardware construction
as that of the first embodiment.</p>
    <p num="0187">FIG. 5 is a functional block diagram of the
reception/reproduction/nullification device of the
second embodiment.</p>
    <p num="0188">The reception/reproduction/nullification device
200 shown in the drawing includes the user interface unit
101, the receiving unit 102, the descrambling unit 103,
the key generating unit 104, the data encrypting unit
105, the key encrypting unit 106, a recording unit 201,
the key decrypting unit 108, the data decrypting unit
109, the reproducing unit 110, a nullification judging
unit 202, the processing capacity judging unit 112, a
sequential nullifying unit 203, and a total nullifying
unit 204. In actuality, the function of the receiving
unit 102 corresponds to the function of the reception
device 902 shown in FIG. 1. The function of the
descrambling unit 103 corresponds to the function of the
transport stream decoder 801 in FIG. 1. The functions
of the key generating unit 104, data encrypting unit 105,
key encrypting unit 106, recording unit 201, key
decrypting unit 108, and data decrypting unit 109 
correspond to the function of the encryption engine 803
in FIG. 1. The function of the reproducing unit 110
corresponds to the function of the AV decoder 802 in FIG.
1. The functions of the nullification judging unit 202,
processing capacity judging unit 112, sequential
nullifying unit 203, and total nullifying unit 204
correspond to the function of the microcomputer 804 in
FIG. 1.</p>
    <p num="0189">Construction elements which are the same as those
in the first embodiment are given the same reference
numerals and their explanation has been omitted.</p>
    <p num="0190">The recording unit 201 sequentially records pairs
of encrypted data blocks and encrypted decryption keys
of digital content, onto the predetermined recording
medium. Here, if the digital content is copy-prohibited,
the recording unit 201 reserves a plurality of recording
areas that are each capable of storing data of the
predetermined broadcast time period, on the recording
medium. The recording unit 201 then sequentially
records the pairs to the reserved recording areas. In
the present example, the recording unit 201 reserves nine
recording areas that can each store data corresponding
to the broadcast time period of 10 minutes, on the HDD
905. The recording unit 201 then records pairs of
encrypted data blocks and encrypted unique keys, 
sequentially to the reserved recording areas. Here, if
the recording areas already store pairs of encrypted data
blocks and encrypted unique keys, the recording unit 201
writes the new pairs over the old pairs. If the digital
content does not require copyright protection, on the
other hand, the recording unit 201 can record the digital
content in an unencrypted form.</p>
    <p num="0191">The nullification judging unit 202 operates as
follows. When digital content is received and recorded
despite its copy-prohibition status, the nullification
judging unit 202 judges, for each pair of encrypted data
block and encrypted decryption key recorded on the
recording medium, whether the pair should be nullified,
based on a specific condition. In the present example,
the nullification judging unit 202 judges, for each pair
of encrypted data block corresponding to the broadcast
time period of 10 minutes and encrypted unique key which
are recorded on the HDD 905, whether the pair should be
nullified.</p>
    <p num="0192">The specific condition used here is whether the
data block has been reproduced by the reproducing unit
110 or whether a predetermined time period has passed
since the data block was received by the receiving unit
102 or recorded by the recording unit 201. In this
embodiment, sequence information showing a sequence in 
which pairs of encrypted data blocks and encrypted
decryption keys were recorded is stored on the recording
medium. This being so, the nullification judging unit
202 makes the judgement such that the pairs are nullified
in the recording sequence, and the recording unit 201
writes the new pairs to the recording areas storing the
old pairs which are judged as needing to be nullified.
In the present example, nine pairs of encrypted data
blocks corresponding to the broadcast time period of 10
minutes and encrypted unique keys which are recorded in
the nine recording areas on the HDD 905 are each nullified
90 minutes after it was written, as a result of
overwriting with a new pair.</p>
    <p num="0193">The sequential nullifying unit 203 operates as
follows. Whenever the nullification judging unit 202
judges that a predetermined number of encrypted data
blocks and their corresponding encrypted decryption
keys should be nullified or that one or more encrypted
data blocks whose total amount of data reaches a
predetermined amount and their corresponding encrypted
decryption keys should be nullified, the sequential
nullifying unit 203 nullifies the judged pairs of
encrypted data blocks and encrypted decryption keys.
Here, if there are new pairs of encrypted data blocks
and encrypted decryption keys which need to be recorded, 
the old pairs can be nullified by overwriting with the
new pairs. If there is no new pair, the sequential
nullifying unit 203 destroys each old pair by, for
example, overwriting with arbitrary data.</p>
    <p num="0194">Here, if the digital content has a fixed bit rate,
i.e., the amount of data per unit time is constant, an
old pair can completely be nullified by the overwriting
with a new pair. However, if the digital content has
a variable bit rate as in MPEG, the old pair may not be
able to be completely nullified by the overwriting with
the new pair.</p>
    <p num="0195">In such a case, the sequential nullifying unit 203
may destroy the old pair by writing meaningless data over
the remaining parts of the old pair which have not been
overwritten with the new pair. As an alternative, the
sequential nullifying unit 203 may destroy the remaining
parts of the old pair when the processing capacity
judging unit 112 judges that there is an enough
processing capacity, and leave the remaining parts as
they are when the processing capacity judging unit 112
judges that there is not an enough processing capacity.</p>
    <p num="0196">The total nullifying unit 204 destroys all
remaining parts of the pairs of encrypted data blocks
and encrypted decryption keys which have not been
destroyed by the sequential nullifying unit 203, when 
there is an enough processing capacity. Also, the total
nullifying unit 204 destroys all remaining parts when
the user indicates to stop time shifting.</p>
    <heading>(Operation)</heading>
    <p num="0197">FIG. 6 shows an example operation of the
reception/reproduction/nullification device 200 of the
second embodiment.</p>
    <p num="0198">Sequential reproduction, recording, time shifting,
and nullification of the present invention are explained
by referring to FIG. 6. Note here that steps which are
the same as those in the first embodiment are given the
same step numbers and their explanation has been omitted.</p>
    <p num="0199">(1)-(5) Same as (1)-(5) of the first operation
example in the first embodiment (S1-S5).</p>
    <p num="0200">(6) Upon receiving the pause indication (S5:Yes),
the recording starts (S21).</p>
    <p num="0201">The key generating unit 104 randomly generates an
encryption key and a decryption key corresponding to the
encryption key using a random number of the like, for
each data block corresponding to the predetermined
broadcast time period which is descrambled by the
descrambling unit 103. In the present example, a unique
key is randomly generated for each data block
corresponding to the broadcast time period of 10 minutes.</p>
    <p num="0202">The data encrypting unit 105 encrypts the 
descrambled data block using the encryption key
generated by the key generating unit 104, so that the
encrypted data block can be decrypted by the
corresponding decryption key. In the present example,
the data block corresponding to the broadcast time period
of 10 minutes is encrypted using the corresponding unique
key.</p>
    <p num="0203">The key encrypting unit 106 encrypts the decryption
key corresponding to the encryption key used by the data
encrypting unit 105, using the device ID. In the present
example, the unique key is encrypted using the device
ID.</p>
    <p num="0204">The recording unit 201 reserves a plurality of
recording areas which can each store data of the
predetermined broadcast time period, on the recording
medium. The recording unit 201 then sequentially
records pairs of encrypted data blocks and encrypted
decryption keys to the recording areas. In the present
example, nine recording areas each capable of storing
data corresponding to the broadcast time period of 10
minutes are reserved on the HDD 905, and pairs of
encrypted data blocks corresponding to the broadcast
time period of 10 minutes and encrypted unique keys are
sequentially recorded to the nine recording areas. Here,
if the recording areas already store pairs of encrypted 
data blocks and encrypted unique keys, the new pairs are
written over the old pairs.</p>
    <p num="0205">If any old pair was not completely destroyed by
overwriting with a new pair, the sequential nullifying
unit 203 destroys the remaining parts of the old pair
by, for example, overwriting with meaningless data.</p>
    <p num="0206">The reproducing unit 110 stops the sequential
reproduction of the digital content.</p>
    <p num="0207">(7) Same as (9) of the first operation example in
the first embodiment (S9).</p>
    <p num="0208">(8) Upon receiving the stop indication (S9:Yes),
the operations of the receiving unit 102, descrambling
unit 103, key generating unit 104, data encrypting unit
105, key encrypting unit 106, and recording unit 201 are
stopped to end the recording. Also, the total
nullifying unit 204 destroys all remaining data which
has not been destroyed by the sequential nullifying unit
203, before returning to the stopped state (S22).</p>
    <p num="0209">(9)-(10) Same as (11)-(12) of the first operation
example in the first embodiment (S11-S12).</p>
    <p num="0210">(11) Same as (15) of the first operation example
in the first embodiment (S15).</p>
    <p num="0211">(12) Upon receiving the stop indication (S15:Yes),
the operations of the receiving unit 102, descrambling
unit 103, key generating unit 104, data encrypting unit 
105, key encrypting unit 106, recording unit 201, key
decrypting unit 108, data decrypting unit 109, and
reproducing unit 110 are stopped to end the time shifting.
Also, the total nullifying unit 204 destroys all
remaining data which has not been destroyed by the
sequential nullifying unit 203, before returning to the
stopped state (S23).</p>
    <p num="0212">(13)-(14) Same as (17)-(18) of the first operation
example in the first embodiment (S17-S18).</p>
    <p num="0213">According to the second embodiment of the invention,
copy-prohibited digital content can be recorded to
enable time shifting, but the recorded digital content
is nullified by overwriting with new data once a
predetermined time period has passed. This enables
user-friendliness to be improved without departing from
the principle of copy prohibition. Furthermore, the
sequential nullification is executed without increasing
the load on the device.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Third Embodiment</u>
    </heading>
    <heading>(Overview)</heading>
    <p num="0214">The third embodiment of the present invention is
the following device. When digital content whose
copying is permitted only once ("Copy one Generation")
is received and recorded on a recording medium, the 
digital content can be moved to another recording medium,
but the digital content on the original recording medium
is nullified little by little upon being copied, so that
the digital content will not remain on the original
recording medium.</p>
    <heading>(Construction)</heading>
    <p num="0215">A reception/reproduction/nullification device of
the third embodiment has the same hardware construction
as that of the first embodiment, except for the following
new functions of the microcomputer 804.</p>
    <p num="0216">When the user receives digital content only one
generation copy of which is permitted and records it to
the HDD 905 in an encrypted form, the microcomputer 804
sequentially copies data blocks of the digital content
which correspond to the predetermined broadcast time
period and at the same time nullifies the copied data
blocks on the HDD 905 so that they cannot be reproduced.</p>
    <p num="0217">FIG. 7 is a functional block diagram of the
reception/reproduction/nullification device of the
third embodiment.</p>
    <p num="0218">This reception/reproduction/nullification device
300 includes the user interface unit 101, the receiving
unit 102, the descrambling unit 103, the key generating
unit 104, the data encrypting unit 105, the key
encrypting unit 106, the recording unit 107, the key 
decrypting unit 108, the data decrypting unit 109, the
reproducing unit 110, a moving unit 301, a nullification
judging unit 302, the processing capacity judging unit
112, the sequential nullifying unit 113, and the total
nullifying unit 114. In actuality, the function of the
receiving unit 102 corresponds to the function of the
reception device 902 shown in FIG. 1. The function of
the descrambling unit 103 corresponds to the function
of the transport stream decoder 801 in FIG. 1. The
functions of the key generating unit 104, data encrypting
unit 105, key encrypting unit 106, recording unit 107,
key decrypting unit 108, and data decrypting unit 109
correspond to the function of the encrypting engine 803
in FIG. 1. The function of the reproducing unit 110
corresponds to the function of the AV decoder 802 in FIG.
1. The functions of the moving unit 301, nullification
judging unit 302, processing capacity judging unit 112,
sequential nullifying unit 113, and total nullifying
unit 114 correspond to the function of the microcomputer
804 in FIG. 1.</p>
    <p num="0219">Construction elements which are the same as those
in the first embodiment are given the same reference
numerals and their explanation has been omitted.</p>
    <p num="0220">The moving unit 301 moves pairs of encrypted data
blocks and encrypted decryption keys which have been 
recorded on the recording medium, sequentially to
another recording medium. The movement referred to here
is an operation of (1) copying data from one recording
medium to another recording medium and (2) rewriting data
management information of the data on the original
recording medium to show that the data has been deleted,
without deleting the data itself on the original
recording medium. In the present example, pairs of
encrypted data blocks corresponding to the broadcast
time period of 10 minutes and encrypted unique keys which
are recorded on the HDD 905 are moved one by one to another
recording medium.</p>
    <p num="0221">The nullification judging unit 302 operates as
follows. When digital content is recorded to one
recording medium and then further recorded to another
recording medium despite that only one generation copy
of the digital content is permitted, the nullification
judging unit 302 judges whether the digital content
should be nullified, based on a specific condition. In
the present example, the nullification judging unit 302
judges, for each pair of encrypted data block
corresponding to the broadcast time period of 10 minutes
and encrypted unique key, whether the pair should be
nullified.</p>
    <p num="0222">The specific condition here is whether the pair has 
been moved by the moving unit 301.</p>
    <heading>(Operation)</heading>
    <p num="0223">FIG. 8 shows an example operation of the
reception/reproduction/nullification device 300 of the
third embodiment.</p>
    <p num="0224">Movement and nullification of the present
invention are explained by referring to FIG. 8.</p>
    <p num="0225">Suppose scrambled digital content whose copy
control information is "Copy one Generation" is received,
and a plurality of pairs of encrypted data blocks
corresponding to the predetermined broadcast time
period and encrypted unique keys are recorded on the HDD
905 with copy control information "Copy No more".
<sl><li>(1) In the stopped state, the user interface unit
101 waits for the user's indication to move digital
content (S31).</li><li>(2) Upon receiving the move indication (S31:Yes),
the nullification judging unit 302 judges whether the
digital content is copy-prohibited, by referring to its
copy control information (S32).</li><li>(3) If the digital content is not copy-prohibited
(S32:No), the moving unit 301 moves all pairs of
encrypted data blocks and encrypted decryption keys of
the digital content to another recording medium (S33).</li><li>(4) If the digital content is copy-prohibited (e.g. 
if the copy control information is "Copy No more")
(S32:Yes), the moving unit 301 moves one pair of
encrypted data block and encrypted decryption key to
another recording medium. In the present example, one
pair of encrypted data block corresponding to the
broadcast time period of 10 minutes and encrypted unique
key which are recorded on the HDD 905 is moved to another
recording medium.</li><li>(5) The nullification judging unit 302 judges
whether there is any pair which has been moved but not
been nullified (S35).</li><li>(6) If there is any pair which has been moved but
not been nullified (S35:Yes), the sequential nullifying
unit 113 nullifies the pair (S36).</li><li>(7) It is judged whether all pairs of encrypted data
blocks and encrypted decryption keys have been moved
(S37).</li><li>(8) If all pairs have been moved (S37:Yes), the
total nullifying unit 114 destroys all remaining data
which has not been destroyed by the sequential nullifying
unit 113 (S38).</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0226">According to the third embodiment of the invention,
copy-prohibited digital content can be moved to another
recording medium but the digital content recorded on the
original recording medium is then promptly nullified. 
This enables user-friendliness to improve without
departing from the principle of copy prohibition.</p>
    <p num="0227">The first to third embodiments describe the case
where a different encryption key is generated for each
data block corresponding to the predetermined broadcast
time period. However, a plurality of data blocks may
be encrypted using the same encryption key. Also, the
predetermined broadcast time period is not limited to
the above example but may be in any length. Furthermore,
digital content which is recorded on the same recording
medium may be encrypted using a single encryption key
unique to the recording medium.</p>
    <p num="0228">The first to third embodiments describe the case
where only decryption keys are sequentially destroyed
when there is not an enough processing capacity.
However, when the same key is used for encrypting a
plurality of data blocks as mentioned above, if a
decryption key of one data block is destroyed, the other
data blocks that use the same decryption key cannot be
decrypted. In this case, the decryption key is not
destroyed and instead the data blocks that use the
decryption key are partly or completely destroyed. The
decryption key can be destroyed after the data blocks
that use the same decryption key are nullified.</p>
    <p num="0229">Also, since data is usually recorded and managed 
in the form of files, each pair of encrypted data block
and encrypted decryption key may be recorded as a file
or a plurality of pairs may be recorded as a file. When
each pair is recorded as an individual file,
nullification can be performed in units of files.
However, when a plurality of pairs are recorded as a
single file, nullification needs to be performed for part
of the file. In such a case, access to the nullified
part should be restricted so as to keep the nullified
part from being accessed by mistake. Access to part of
a file can be restricted by, for example, using a seek
restriction function of a file pointer mounted on a
typical operating system.</p>
    <p num="0230">In the second embodiment, the plurality of
recording areas reserved by the recording unit 201 need
not be consecutive. As one example, AV data of 4Mbps
is 300MB per ten minutes. It is not efficient to reserve
consecutive recording areas that can store such an amount
of data on the HDD. In this case, each recording area
is made up of a plurality of small consecutive areas.
The relationship between each recording area and its
small consecutive areas is independently managed by a
file system, which provides each recording area to higher
applications as a consecutive recording area to realize
access using a file pointer. </p>
    <p num="0231">Programs that can execute the operations of the
first to third embodiments on computer may be recorded
on computer-readable recording media and distributed
for transaction. Such programs may also be distributed
via network.</p>
    <p num="0232">Examples of the computer-readable recording media
include a removable recording medium such as a floppy
disk, a CD, an MO, a DVD, or a memory card, and a fixed
recording medium such as a hard disk and a semiconductor
memory.</p>
    <p num="0233">Although the present invention has been fully
described by way of examples with reference to the
accompanying drawings, it is to be noted that various
changes and modifications will be apparent to those
skilled in the art.</p>
    <p num="0234">Therefore, unless such changes and modifications
depart from the scope of the present invention, they
should be construed as being included therein.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A data nullification device for nullifying target
data recorded on a recording medium, the target data being
made up of a plurality of data blocks, the data
nullification device comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a judging unit operable to judge, for each data block
recorded on the recording medium, whether the data block
needs to be nullified; and</claim-text><claim-text>a nullifying unit operable to nullify, when a
predetermined number of data blocks are judged as needing
to be nullified or when one or more data blocks whose total
amount of data reaches a predetermined amount are judged
as needing to be nullified, the judged data blocks.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 1,
   wherein the recording medium stores sequence
information that shows a sequence in which the plurality
of data blocks were recorded onto the recording medium,
and
   the judging unit judges, in succession, the
plurality of data blocks in the sequence shown by the
sequence information, as needing to be nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 2,
   wherein the target data is data which is continuously
transmitted from an external device and recorded on the
recording medium,
   the data nullification device further comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a receiving unit operable to receive data from the
external device, and</claim-text><claim-text>having set the received data as a new data block,
the nullifying unit writes the new data block to a
recording area on the recording medium that stores a data
block which is judged as needing to be nullified, to
nullify the recorded data block and at the same time record
the new data block.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 3,
   wherein each data block has a length corresponding
to a fixed transmission time period, and
   a specified number of recording areas which are each
used as a recording area of a data block are reserved on
the recording medium.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 4,
   wherein if the length corresponding to the fixed
transmission time period is variable and if part of the
recorded data block remains even after the new data block
is written, the nullifying unit further writes arbitrary
data over the part of the recorded data block.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 4,
   wherein if there is not a new data block which is
to be recorded, the nullifying unit writes arbitrary data
to the recording area.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 2, further
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a utilizing unit operable to utilize the target data
recorded on the recording medium, in units of data blocks,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the judging unit further judges that each
data block which was utilized by the utilizing unit needs
to be nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 7,
   wherein the target data is content data which is
transmitted from an external device and recorded on the
recording medium,
   the content data is accompanied with copy control
information showing whether copying of the content data
is permitted or prohibited,
   the utilizing unit reproduces the content data
recorded on the recording medium, in units of data blocks,
and
   only if the copy control information accompanying
the content data shows that the copying of the content
data is prohibited, the judging unit judges that each data
block which was reproduced by the utilizing unit needs
to be nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 1,
   wherein the recording medium stores time limit
information showing a recording time limit of each data
block recorded on the recording medium, the recording time
limit being a time limit after which retention of the data
block on the recording medium is prohibited,
   the judging unit judges that each data block whose
recording time limit is reached needs to be nullified,
based on the time limit information, and
   whenever any data block is judged as needing to be
nullified because a recording time limit of the data block
is reached, the nullifying unit nullifies the data block
irrespective of whether the predetermined number of data
blocks are judged as needing to be nullified or whether
one or more data blocks whose total amount of data reaches
the predetermined amount are judged as needing to be
nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 9, further
comprising:<claim-text><claim-text>a utilizing unit operable to utilize the target data
recorded on the recording medium, in units of data blocks,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the judging unit further judges that each
data block which was utilized by the utilizing unit needs
to be nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 10,
   wherein the target data is content data which is
transmitted from an external device and recorded on the
recording medium,
   the content data is accompanied with copy control
information showing whether copying of the content data
is permitted or prohibited,
   the utilizing unit reproduces the content data
recorded on the recording medium, in units of data blocks,
and
   only if the copy control information accompanying
the content data shows that the copying of the content
data is prohibited, the judging unit judges that each data
block which was reproduced by the utilizing unit needs
to be nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 1, further
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a utilizing unit operable to utilize the target data
recorded on the recording medium, in units of data blocks,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the judging unit judges that each data block
which was utilized by the utilizing unit needs to be
nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 12,
   wherein the target data is content data which is
transmitted from an external device and recorded on the
recording medium,
   the content data is accompanied with copy control
information showing whether copying of the content data
is permitted or prohibited,
   the utilizing unit reproduces the content data
recorded on the recording medium, in units of data blocks,
and
   only if the copy control information accompanying
the content data shows that the copying of the content
data is prohibited, the judging unit judges that each data
block which was reproduced by the utilizing unit needs
to be nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 12,
   wherein the target data is accompanied with copy
control information showing whether copying of the target
data is permitted or prohibited,
   the utilizing unit records the target data recorded
on the recording medium, to another recording medium, in
units of data blocks, and
   only if the copy control information accompanying
the target data shows that the copying of the target data
is prohibited, the judging unit judges that each data block
on the recording medium which was recorded by the utilizing
unit needs to be nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 1,
   wherein the nullifying unit destroys all parts of
a data block which is judged as needing to be nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 1,
   wherein the nullifying unit destroys at least a part
of a data block which is judged as needing to be nullified,
the part of the data block being necessary to utilize
remaining parts of the data block.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 16,
   wherein the target data is MPEG data including I
pictures, and
   the part of the data block necessary to utilize the
remaining parts of the data block is an I picture.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="18">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 16,
   wherein the target data is MPEG data including I
pictures, and
   the part of the data block necessary to utilize the
remaining parts of the data block is a first sector of
an I picture.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="19">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 16,
   wherein when the data nullification device does not
have an enough processing capacity, the nullifying unit
destroys only the part of the data block necessary to
utilize the remaining parts of the data block.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="20">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 19,
   wherein the nullifying unit destroys the remaining
parts of the data block within a range where a processing
capacity of the data nullification device allows.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="21">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 19,
further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a destroying unit operable to destroy remaining
parts of data blocks which were not destroyed by the
nullifying unit, when the data nullification device has
an enough processing capacity.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="22">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 1,
   wherein each data block recorded on the recording
medium has been encrypted using an individual encryption
key,
   a decryption key for decrypting the encrypted data
block is stored on the recording medium, and
   the nullifying unit destroys at least a decryption
key corresponding to a data block which is judged as
needing to be nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="23">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 22,
further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>an acquiring unit operable to acquire the target data
in an encoded form;</claim-text><claim-text>a decoding unit operable to decode the encoded target
data using a user key which has been provided to authorized
users in advance, to obtain the target data;</claim-text><claim-text>a key generating unit operable to generate an
arbitrary encryption key and a decryption key
corresponding to the encryption key, for each data block
of the target data;</claim-text><claim-text>a data encrypting unit operable to encrypt the data
block using the encryption key so that the encrypted data
block can be decrypted using the corresponding decryption
key;</claim-text><claim-text>a key encrypting unit operable to encrypt the
decryption key using an identifier unique to the data
nullification device; and</claim-text><claim-text>a recording unit operable to record the encrypted
data block and the encrypted decryption key onto the
recording medium.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="24">
      <claim-text>The data nullification device of Claim 23,
   wherein at least the decoding unit, the key
generating unit, the data encrypting unit, and the key
encrypting unit are contained in a single semiconductor
chip.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="25">
      <claim-text>A data nullification program for nullifying
target data recorded on a recording medium, the target
data being made up of a plurality of data blocks, the data
nullification program having a computer execute the steps
of:
<claim-text><claim-text>judging, for each data block recorded on the
recording medium, whether the data block needs to be
nullified; and</claim-text><claim-text>nullifying, when a predetermined number of data
blocks are judged as needing to be nullified or when one
or more data blocks whose total amount of data reaches
a predetermined amount are judged as needing to be
nullified, the judged data blocks.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="26">
      <claim-text>The data nullification program of Claim 25,
   wherein the recording medium stores sequence
information that shows a sequence in which the plurality
of data blocks were recorded onto the recording medium,
and
   the judging step judges, in succession, the
plurality of data blocks in the sequence shown by the
sequence information, as needing to be nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="27">
      <claim-text>The data nullification program of Claim 26,
   wherein the target data is data which is continuously
transmitted from an external device and recorded on the
recording medium,
   the data nullification program further having the
computer execute the step of:
<claim-text><claim-text>receiving data from the external device,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein having set the received data as a new data
block, the nullifying step writes the new data block to
a recording area on the recording medium that stores a
data block which is judged as needing to be nullified,
to nullify the recorded data block and at the same time
record the new data block.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="28">
      <claim-text>The data nullification program of Claim 26,
further having the computer execute the step of:
<claim-text><claim-text>utilizing the target data recorded on the recording
medium, in units of data blocks,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the judging step further judges that each
data block which was utilized in the utilizing step needs
to be nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="29">
      <claim-text>The data nullification program of Claim 25,
   wherein the recording medium stores time limit
information showing a recording time limit of each data
block recorded on the recording medium, the recording time
limit being a time limit after which retention of the data
block on the recording medium is prohibited,
   the judging step judges that each data block whose
recording time limit is reached needs to be nullified,
based on the time limit information, and
   whenever any data block is judged as needing to be
nullified because a recording time limit of the data block
is reached, the nullifying step nullifies the data block
irrespective of whether the predetermined number of data
blocks are judged as needing to be nullified or whether
one or more data blocks whose total amount of data reaches
the predetermined amount are judged as needing to be
nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="30">
      <claim-text>The data nullification program of Claim 29,
further having the computer execute the step of:
<claim-text><claim-text>utilizing the target data recorded on the recording
medium, in units of data blocks,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the judging step further judges that each
data block which was utilized in the utilizing step needs
to be nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="31">
      <claim-text>The data nullification program of Claim 25,
further having the computer execute the step of:
<claim-text><claim-text>utilizing the target data recorded on the recording
medium, in units of data blocks,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the judging step judges that each data block
which was utilized in the utilizing step needs to be
nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="32">
      <claim-text>The data nullification program of Claim 25,
   wherein the nullifying step destroys all parts of
a data block which is judged as needing to be nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="33">
      <claim-text>The data nullification program of Claim 25,
   wherein the nullifying step destroys at least a part
of a data block which is judged as needing to be nullified,
the part of the data block being necessary to utilize
remaining parts of the data block.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="34">
      <claim-text>The data nullification program of Claim 25,
   wherein each data block recorded on the recording
medium has been encrypted using an individual encryption
key,
   a decryption key for decrypting the encrypted data
block is stored on the recording medium, and
   the nullifying step destroys at least a decryption
key corresponding to a data block which is judged as
needing to be nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="35">
      <claim-text>A data nullification method for nullifying
target data recorded on a recording medium, the target
data being made up of a plurality of data blocks, the data
nullification method comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>judging, for each data block recorded on the
recording medium, whether the data block needs to be
nullified; and</claim-text><claim-text>nullifying, when a predetermined number of data
blocks are judged as needing to be nullified or when one
or more data blocks whose total amount of data reaches
a predetermined amount are judged as needing to be
nullified, the judged data blocks.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="36">
      <claim-text>The data nullification method of Claim 35,
   wherein the recording medium stores sequence
information that shows a sequence in which the plurality
of data blocks were recorded onto the recording medium,
and
   the judging step judges, in succession, the
plurality of data blocks in the sequence shown by the
sequence information, as needing to be nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="37">
      <claim-text>The data nullification method of Claim 36,
   wherein the target data is data which is continuously
transmitted from an external device and recorded on the
recording medium,
   the data nullification method further comprising the
step of:
<claim-text><claim-text>receiving data from the external device,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein having set the received data as a new data
block, the nullifying step writes the new data block to
a recording area on the recording medium that stores a
data block which is judged as needing to be nullified,
to nullify the recorded data block and at the same time
record the new data block.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="38">
      <claim-text>The data nullification method of Claim 36,
further comprising the step of:<claim-text><claim-text>utilizing the target data recorded on the recording
medium, in units of data blocks,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the judging step further judges that each
data block which was utilized in the utilizing step needs
to be nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="39">
      <claim-text>The data nullification method of Claim 35,
   wherein the recording medium stores time limit
information showing a recording time limit of each data
block recorded on the recording medium, the recording time
limit being a time limit after which retention of the data
block on the recording medium is prohibited,
   the judging step judges that each data block whose
recording time limit is reached needs to be nullified,
based on the time limit information, and
   whenever any data block is judged as needing to be
nullified because a recording time limit of the data block
is reached, the nullifying step nullifies the data block
irrespective of whether the predetermined number of data
blocks are judged as needing to be nullified or whether
one or more data blocks whose total amount of data reaches
the predetermined amount are judged as needing to be
nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="40">
      <claim-text>The data nullification method of Claim 39,
further comprising the step of:
<claim-text><claim-text>utilizing the target data recorded on the recording
medium, in units of data blocks,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the judging step further judges that each
data block which was utilized in the utilizing step needs
to be nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="41">
      <claim-text>The data nullification method of Claim 35,
further comprising the step of:
<claim-text><claim-text>utilizing the target data recorded on the recording
medium, in units of data blocks,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the judging step judges that each data block
which was utilized in the utilizing step needs to be
nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="42">
      <claim-text>The data nullification method of Claim 35,
   wherein the nullifying step destroys all parts of
a data block which is judged as needing to be nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="43">
      <claim-text>The data nullification method of Claim 35,
   wherein the nullifying step destroys at least a part
of a data block which is judged as needing to be nullified,
the part of the data block being necessary to utilize
remaining parts of the data block.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="44">
      <claim-text>The data nullification method of Claim 35,
   wherein each data block recorded on the recording
medium has been encrypted using an individual encryption
key,
   a decryption key for decrypting the encrypted data
block is stored on the recording medium, and
   the nullifying step destroys at least a decryption
key corresponding to a data block which is judged as
needing to be nullified.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
