<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1241417-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1241417" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="25205532" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020918">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1241417-A1" status="new" fvid="23569871">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1241417</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20020918</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02250266-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02250266</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020115</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="US-81109201-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>81109201</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010316</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F04C  18/02        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F04C  18/02        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F04C  23/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F04C  23/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F04C  28/00        20060101AFI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F04C  28/00        20060101C I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F04C  28/18        20060101A I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F04C  28/24        20060101ALI20061130BMKR        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F04C  28/26        20060101A I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F04C  28/28        20060101A I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F04C  29/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F04C  29/04        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F25B   1/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F25B   1/04        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F25B   5/00        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F25B   5/02        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F25B  49/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F25B  49/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F04C  23/00D</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F04C  28/18</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F04C  28/26B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F04C  28/28</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F04C  29/04</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F04C  29/04B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F25B   1/04</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F25B  49/02B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">R04C18:02B2</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">R04C28:26B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">R25B5:02</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Digitaler Regler für eine Spiralverdichter-Kondensationseinheit</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Digital controller for scroll compressor condensing unit</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Régulateur digital pour une unité de condensation avec compresseur à spirales</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>COPELAND CORP</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>COPELAND CORPORATION</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>COPELAND CORPORATION</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1675 W Campbell Road</street>
              <city>Sidney Ohio 45365-0669</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>JAYANTH NAGARAJ</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>PHAM HUNG H</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>VOGH III RICHARD P</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>JAYANTH, NAGARAJ</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>PHAM, HUNG H</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>VOGH III, RICHARD P.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>JAYANTH, NAGARAJ</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1256 E. Parkwood Street</street>
              <city>Sidney, Ohio 45365</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>PHAM, HUNG H</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>6671 Stillmead Drive</street>
              <city>Dayton, Ohio 45414</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>VOGH III, RICHARD P.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>150 Westwood Drive</street>
              <city>Marietta, Georgia 30064</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Price, Nigel John King</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>J.A. KEMP &amp;amp; CO. 14 South Square Gray's Inn</street>
              <city>LONDON WC1R 5JJ</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A cooling system controller (60) controls the capacity of a variable capacity
compressor (44/244a-d) based upon the temperature of a housing being cooled, the suction
pressure of the compressor or both of these criteria. The cooling system controller is
capable of controlling either single-evaporator (54/254) or multiple-evaporator (54a,54,54c) refrigeration
systems. The multiple-evaporator systems can have evaporators of similar
temperatures or of mixed temperatures. The controller (60) also allows the use of one or
more condenser fans (202,204) that are operated in a lead/lag fashion to control the cooling
capability of the system.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="75" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="119"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates generally to a controller for a condensing unit
for a refrigeration system or for other cooling systems. More particularly, the present
invention relates to a condensing unit employing a variable capacity compressor which is
controlled by pulse width modulation using a variable duty cycle signal derived from one
or more system sensors. The condensing unit controller is capable of controlling a single
evaporator or multiple evaporators of similar or mixed temperatures.</p>
    <p num="0002">The present invention is being described associated with a refrigeration
system. It is to be understood that the condensing unit of the present invention could be
utilized for any other cooling system if desired.</p>
    <p num="0003">Conventionally, refrigeration systems for refrigeration cases have employed
air-cooled or water-cooled condensers fed by a rack of compressors. The compressors
are coupled in parallel so that they may be switched on and off in stages to adjust the
system cooling capacity to the demands of the load. Typically, the compressors and
condensers are located outside of the building on the roof or in a machine room adjacent
the area where the refrigeration cases are located.</p>
    <p num="0004">Within each refrigeration case is an evaporator fed by refrigerant lines from
the condensers through which the expanded refrigerant circulates to cool the case.
Typically, a closed-loop control system regulates refrigerant flow through the evaporators 
to maintain the desired case temperatures. Proportional-Integral-Derivative (PID) closed
loop control systems are popular for this purpose, with temperature and/or pressure
sensors providing the sensed condition inputs.</p>
    <p num="0005">It is common practice with retail outlets to use separate systems to supply
different individual cooling temperature ranges; low temperature (for frozen foods, ice
cream, nominally -25 F); medium temperature (for meat, dairy products, nominally
+20 F); and high temperature (for floral, produce, nominally +35 to +40 F). The
separate low, medium and high temperature systems are each optimized to their
respective temperature ranges. Normally, each will employ its own rack of compressors
and its own set of refrigerant conduits to and from the compressors, condensers and
evaporators.</p>
    <p num="0006">The conventional arrangement, described above, is very costly to construct
and maintain. Much of the cost is associated with the long refrigerant conduit runs. Not
only are long conduit runs expensive in terms of hardware and installation costs, but the
quantity of refrigerant required to fill the conduits is also a significant cost factor. The
longer the conduit run, the more refrigerant required. Adding to these added costs are
environmental factors. Eventually fittings leak, allowing the refrigerant to escape to the
atmosphere. Invariably, long conduit runs involve more conduit joints that may potentially
leak. When a leak does occur, the longer the conduit run, the more refrigerant lost.</p>
    <p num="0007">One solution to the above described problems is disclosed in Assignee's U.S.
Patent 6,047,557, the disclosure of which is incorporated herein by reference. The solution
presented in the above patent is a distributed refrigeration system in which the condenser
is disposed on the refrigeration case and serviced by a special pulse-width modulated 
compressor that may be also disposed within the case. If desired, the condenser and
compressor can be coupled to service a group of adjacent refrigerant cases, each case
having its own evaporator. Further, multiple compressors with at least one pulse-width
modulated compressor can be used to handle large evaporator load line-up. Also, the
condenser can be disposed in a housing with the evaporator to provide a self-contained
package, or can be disposed remotely, as in a split system. The pulse-width modulated
compressor is driven by a control system that supplies a variable duty cycle control signal
based on measured system load.</p>
    <p num="0008">While the above described pulse-width modulated compressor and
refrigeration system have performed satisfactorily, the continued development of these
systems has been directed toward controlling the capacity of the compressor, the
condenser and other components within the condensing unit.</p>
    <p num="0009">The present invention will be further described by way of example only,
with reference to the accompanying drawings, in which:-</p>
    <p num="0010">Figure 1 is a system block diagram of a prior art refrigeration system
configuration;</p>
    <p num="0011">Figure 2 is a system block diagram of a condensing unit or cooling system
in accordance with the present invention; </p>
    <p num="0012">Figure 3 is a cross-sectional view of an embodiment of a pulse-width
modulated compressor shown in the loaded state;</p>
    <p num="0013">Figure 4 is a cross-sectional view of the compressor of Figure 3, shown in the
unloaded state;</p>
    <p num="0014">Figure 5 is a vertical cross-sectional view of the piston assembly shown in
Figures 3 and 4;</p>
    <p num="0015">Figure 6 is a cross-sectional top view of the non-orbiting scroll shown in
Figures 3 and 4;</p>
    <p num="0016">Figure 7 is another embodiment of a condensing unit or cooling system in
accordance with the present invention;</p>
    <p num="0017">Figure 8 is a schematic view illustrating the controller shown in Figure 7;</p>
    <p num="0018">Figure 9 is a flow diagram for the control system of the present invention;</p>
    <p num="0019">Figure 10 is a plan view of the controls for the controller shown in Figures 7
and 8;</p>
    <p num="0020">Figure 11 is a schematic view illustrating a case controller and system
controller in accordance with the present invention; and</p>
    <p num="0021">Figure 12 is a system block diagram of a condensing unit or cooling system
in accordance with an alternative embodiment of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0022">Referring now to the drawings in which like reference numerals designate like
or corresponding parts throughout the several views, there is shown in Figure 1 a
conventional refrigeration system that is identified generally by reference numeral 10. 
Refrigeration system 10 includes a plurality of compressors 12 and a condenser 14 located
remote from a plurality of refrigeration cases 16. In this illustration, compressors 12 are
configured in a parallel bank located in a machine room or on a roof 18 of a building.
Compressors 12 supply condenser 14 that may be air cooled or water cooled. Condenser
14 supplies liquid refrigerant to a receiver 20. Receiver 20, in turn, supplies refrigerant to
the individual refrigeration cases 16, which are connected in parallel, as illustrated. In most
implementations, a liquid line solenoid valve 22 is used to regulate the flow of refrigerant
to the associated evaporator 24. The refrigerant is supplied to evaporator 24 through a
suitable expansion device such as expansion valve 26. Expansion valve 26 provides a
restricted orifice that causes the liquid refrigerant to atomize into liquid droplets that are
introduced into the inlet side of evaporator 24. Evaporator 24, located within refrigerant
case 16, extracts heat from case 16 and its contents by vaporization of the liquid droplets
into a gas. Compressors 12 extract this gas by suction and compress the gas. The high-temperature
compressed gas is then cooled by condenser 14 back into the liquid state and
returned to receiver 20, whereupon the cycle continues.</p>
    <p num="0023">To match cooling capacity to the load, compressors 12 may be switched on
and off individually or in groups as required. In a typical retail outlet installation, there may
be several independent systems, each configured as shown in Figure 1, to handle different
operating temperature ranges. Note that a liquid line 28 and a suction line 30 may each
need to be quite lengthy (e.g., up to 150 feet) to span the distance from refrigeration cases
16 to a machine room or roof 18.</p>
    <p num="0024">Figure 2 shows a condensing unit or cooling system 40 configured in
accordance with the principles of the present invention. Cooling system 40 includes a 
refrigeration case 42, a compressor 44, a condenser 46, a first expansion valve 48, an
economizer 50, a second expansion valve 52 and an evaporator 54. While cooling system
40 is being illustrated in conjunction with refrigeration case 42, it is within the scope of the
present invention to use cooling system 40 in conjunction with other cooling devices if
desired.</p>
    <p num="0025">Condenser 46 and compressor 44 are both disposed within case 42 or
attached thereto. Evaporator 54 and the associated expansion valves 48 and 52 are
likewise disposed within case 42. Condenser 46 includes a heat removal mechanism 56
by which heat is transferred to ambient. Heat removal mechanism 56 can be a water
jacket connected to suitable plumbing for carrying waste heat to a water cooling tower
located on the building roof or elsewhere exterior to the building. Alternately, heat removal
mechanism 56 can be a forced-air cooling system or a passive convection-air cooling
system. Cooling system 40 also uses a liquid-line shut off valve 58 for controlling the flow
of refrigerant to evaporator 54. Valve 58 communicates with control sensors to supply the
refrigerant to evaporator 54 on demand.</p>
    <p num="0026">Figure 12 shows an alternative embodiment of a condensing unit or cooling
system 240 configured in accordance with the principles of the present invention. Cooling
system 240 includes a series of refrigeration cases 242a, 242b and 242c, as well as a
group of compressors 244a, 244b, 244c and 244d. The group of compressors 244a-d
includes at least one pulse-width modulated compressor 244d. Cooling system 240 is a
split system wherein compressors 244a-d are on a roof or in a machine room 18 of a
building, while refrigeration cases 242a-c are disposed in a retail area of the building. In
machine room 18 along with compressors 244a-d are a condenser 246, a first expansion 
valve 248, and an economizer 250. Along with the refrigeration cases 242a-c, cooling
system 240 includes a second expansion valve 252 and an evaporator 254. While cooling
system 240 is illustrated in Figure 12 in conjunction with refrigeration cases 242a-c, it is
within the scope of the present invention to use cooling system 240 in conjunction with
other cooling devices it desired.</p>
    <p num="0027">Condenser 246 includes a heat removal mechanism 256 by which heat is
transferred to ambient. Heat removal mechanism 256 can be a water jacket connected to
suitable plumbing for carrying waste heat to a water cooling tower located on the building
roof or elsewhere exterior to the building. Alternatively, heat removal mechanism 256 can
be a forced-air cooling system or a passive convection-air cooling system. Cooling system
240 also uses a liquid-lined shut-off valve 258 for controlling the flow of refrigerant to each
evaporator 254. Valve 258 communicates with control sensors to supply the refrigerant
to evaporator 254 on demand.</p>
    <p num="0028">Cooling system 240, like cooling system 40, employs the compressor
controller 60 to supply a pulse-width modulated control signal on a capacity signal line 62
to a capacity solenoid valve 64 for compressor 244d. Again, controller 60 adjusts the pulse
width of the control signal for valve 64 using an algorithm described below. While only one
pulse-width modulated compressor 244d is shown in Figure 12, more compressors can
include a capacity solenoid valve 64 for pulse-width modulation by controller 60. Further,
while not shown in Figure 12, controller 60 may also supply a pulse-width modulated
vapor-injection signal on an injection signal line to an injection solenoid valve for any of
compressors 244a-d. Controller 60 adjusts the pulse width of the control signal for the
injection solenoid valve using an algorithm described below. </p>
    <p num="0029">Cooling system 40 employs a condensing unit or system controller 60 that
supplies a pulse-width modulated control signal on a capacity signal line 62 to a capacity
solenoid valve 64 for compressor 44. Controller 60 adjusts the pulse width of the control
signal for valve 64 using an algorithm described below. Controller 60 also supplies a
pulse-width modulated vapor-injection signal on an injection signal line 66 to an injection
solenoid valve 68 for compressor 44. Controller 60 adjusts the pulse width of the control
signal for valve 68 using an algorithm described below.</p>
    <p num="0030">Figures 3 and 4 show the details of compressor 44. Scroll compressor 44
comprises an outer shell 70 within which is disposed a driving motor including a stator 72
and a rotor 74, a crankshaft 76 to which rotor 74 is secured, an upper bearing housing 78
and a lower bearing housing 80 for rotatably supporting crankshaft 76 and a compressor
assembly 82.</p>
    <p num="0031">Compressor assembly 82 includes an orbiting scroll member 84 supported
on upper bearing housing 78 and drivingly connected to crankshaft 76 via a crankpin 86
and a drive bushing 88. A non-orbiting scroll member 90 is positioned in meshing
engagement with orbiting scroll member 84 and is axially movably secured to upper
bearing housing 78 by means of a plurality of bolts (not shown) and associated sleeve
members (not shown). An Oldham coupling 92 cooperates with scroll members 84 and 90
to prevent relative rotation therebetween. A partition plate 94 is provided adjacent the
upper end of shell 70 and serves to divide the interior of shell 70 into a discharge chamber
96 at the upper end thereof and a suction chamber 98 at the lower end thereof.</p>
    <p num="0032">In operation, as orbiting scroll member 84 orbits with respect to scroll
member 90, suction gas is drawn into suction chamber 98 of shell 70 via a suction fitting 
100. From suction chamber 98, suction gas is sucked into compressor 82 through an inlet
102 provided in non-orbiting scroll member 90. The intermeshing scroll wraps provided on
scroll members 84 and 90 define moving pockets of gas that progressively decrease in size
as they move radially inwardly as a result of the orbiting motion of scroll member 84, thus
compressing the suction gas entering via inlet 102. The compressed gas is then
discharged into discharge chamber 96 via a discharge port 104 provided in non-orbiting
scroll member 90 and a passage 106 formed in partition 94. A pressure responsive
discharge valve 108 is preferably seated within discharge port 104.</p>
    <p num="0033">Non-orbiting scroll member 90 is also provided with an annular recess 110
formed in the upper surface thereof. A floating seal 112 is disposed within recess 110 and
is biased by intermediate pressurized gas against partition 94 to seal suction chamber 98
from discharge chamber 96. A passage 114 extends through non-orbiting scroll member
90 to supply the intermediate pressurized gas to recess 110.</p>
    <p num="0034">A capacity control system 120 is shown in association with compressor 44.
Control system 120 includes a discharge fitting 122, a piston 124, a shell fitting 126 and
solenoid valve 64. Discharge fitting 122 is threadingly received or otherwise secured within
discharge port 104. Discharge fitting 122 defines an internal cavity 130 and a plurality of
discharge passages 132. Discharge valve 108 is disposed below fitting 122 and below
cavity 130. Thus, pressurized gas overcomes the biasing load of discharge valve 108 to
open discharge valve 108 and allowing the pressurized gas to flow into cavity 130, through
passages 132, and into discharge chamber 96.</p>
    <p num="0035">Referring now to Figures 3, 4 and 5, the assembly of discharge fitting 122
and piston 124 is shown in greater detail. Discharge fitting 122 defines an annular flange 
134. Seated against flange 134 is a lip seal 136 and a floating retainer 138. Piston 124
is press fit or otherwise secured to discharge fitting 122 and piston 124 defines an annular
flange 140 that sandwiches seal 136 and retainer 138 between flange 140 and flange 134.
Discharge fitting 122 defines a passageway 142 and an orifice 144 that extends through
discharge fitting 122 to fluidically connect discharge chamber 96 with a pressure chamber
146 defined by discharge fitting 122, piston 124, seal 136, retainer 138 and shell 70. Shell
fitting 126 is secured within a bore defined by shell 70 and slidingly receives the assembly
of discharge fitting 122, piston 124, seal 136 and retainer 138. Pressure chamber 146 is
fluidically connected to solenoid 64 by a tube 148 and with suction fitting 100 and thus
suction chamber 98 through a tube 150. The combination of piston 124, seal 136 and
floating retainer 138 provides a self-centering sealing system to provide accurate alignment
with the internal bore of shell fitting 126. Seal 136 and floating retainer 138 include
sufficient radial compliance such that any misalignment between the internal bore of fitting
126 and the internal bore of discharge port 104 within which discharge fitting 122 is
secured is accommodated by seal 136 and floating retainer 138.</p>
    <p num="0036">In order to bias non-orbiting scroll member 90 into sealing engagement with
orbiting scroll member 84 for normal full-load operation, solenoid valve 64 is deactivated
(or it is activated) by controller 60 to block fluid flow between tube 148 and tube 150. In
this position, chamber 146 is in communication with discharge chamber 96 through
passageway 142 and orifice 144. The pressurized fluid at discharge pressure within
chambers 96 and 146 will act against opposite sides of piston 124, thus allowing for the
normal biasing of non-orbiting scroll member 90 towards orbiting scroll member 84 to
sealingly engage the axial ends of each scroll member with the respective end plate of the 
opposite scroll member. The axial sealing of the two scroll members 84 and 90 causes
compressor 44 to operate at 100% capacity.</p>
    <p num="0037">In order to unload compressor 44, solenoid valve 64 will be actuated (or it will
be deactuated) by controller 60 to the position shown in Figure 4. In this position, suction
chamber 98 is in direct communication with chamber 146 through suction fitting 100, tube
150, solenoid valve 64 and tube 148. With the discharge pressure pressurized fluid
released to suction from chamber 146, the pressure difference on opposite sides of piston
124 will move non-orbiting scroll member 90 upward to separate the axial end of the tips
of each scroll member with its respective end plate and the higher pressurized pockets will
bleed to the lower pressurized pockets and eventually to suction chamber 98. Orifice 144
is incorporated to control the flow of discharge gas between discharge chamber 96 and
chamber 146. Thus, when chamber 146 is connected to the suction side of the
compressor, the pressure difference on opposite sides of piston 124 will be created. A
wave spring 152 is incorporated to maintain the sealing relationship between floating seal
112 and partition 94 during modulation of non-orbiting scroll member 90. When a gap 154
is created between scrolls 84 and 92, the continued compression of the suction gas will be
eliminated. When this unloading occurs, discharge valve 108 will move to its closed
position, thereby preventing the backflow of high pressurized fluid from discharge chamber
96 on the downstream refrigeration system. When compression of the suction gas is to be
resumed, solenoid valve 64 will be deactuated (or it will be actuated) to again block fluid
flow between tubes 148 and 150 allowing chamber 146 to be pressurized by discharge
chamber 96 through passageway 142 and orifice 144. </p>
    <p num="0038">Referring now to Figures 3, 4 and 6, a fluid injection system 158 for
compressor 44 is shown in greater detail. Compressor 44 includes the capability of having
fluid injected into the intermediate pressurized moving chambers at a point intermediate
suction chamber 98 and discharge chamber 96. A fluid-injection fitting 160 extends
through shell 70 and is fluidically connected to an injection tube 162, which is in turn
fluidically connected to an injection fitting 164 secured to non-orbiting scroll member 90.
Non-orbiting scroll member 90 defines a pair of radial passages 166, each of which extend
between injection fitting 164 and a pair of axial passages 168. Axial passages 168 are
open to the moving chambers on opposite sides of non-orbiting scroll member 90 of
compressor assembly 82 to inject the fluid into these moving chambers as required by
controller 60.</p>
    <p num="0039">Figure 2 illustrates vapor injection system 158, which provides the fluid for
the fluid injection system of compressor 44. Compressor 44 is shown in a cooling system
including condenser 46, first expansion valve or throttle 48, economizer 50, a second
expansion valve or throttle 52, an evaporator 54 and a series of piping interconnecting the
components as shown in Figure 2. Compressor 44 is operated by the motor to compress
the refrigerant gas. The compressed gas is then liquefied by condenser 46. The
economizer 50 can be a flash-tank or heat-exchanger type economizer. As shown, the
liquefied refrigerant passes through expansion valve 48 to flash-tank type economizer 50
where it is separated into gas and liquid. The gaseous refrigerant further passes through
additional piping to be introduced into compressor 44 through fitting 160. On the other
hand, the remaining liquid refrigerant further expands in expansion valve 52, is then
vaporized in evaporator 54 and is again taken into compressor 44. </p>
    <p num="0040">Referring again to Figure 2, the incorporation of flash-tank economizer 50
and the remainder of the vapor injection system allows the capacity of the compressor 44
to increase above the fixed capacity of compressor 44. Typically, at standard refrigeration
conditions, the capacity of the compressor 44 can be increased by approximately 30% to
provide a compressor with 130% of its capacity. In order to be able to control the capacity
of compressor 44, solenoid valve 68 is positioned between economizer 50 and fitting 160.
The increased capacity of compressor 44 can be controlled by controller 60, which
operates solenoid valve 68 either in a pulse width injection or continuous injection mode.
Solenoid valve 68, when operated in a pulse width modulation mode, in combination with
capacity control system 120 of compressor 44 allows the capacity of compressor 44 to be
positioned anywhere between 0% and 130% of its fixed capacity to accommodate faster
load pull down.</p>
    <p num="0041">Referring to Figure 7, a single compressor 44 and condenser 46 can service
several distributed refrigeration cases or several distributed cooling units in a heating and
cooling (HVAC) system. In Figure 7, the refrigeration cases or cooling system housings
are shown as dashed boxes designated 42a, 42b and 42c. Conveniently, compressor 44
and condenser 46 may be disposed within or attached to one of the refrigeration cases or
housings, such as refrigerant case or housing 42a or disposed remotely, such as in a split
system as shown in Figure 12, wherein the compressor 46 and condenser 44 are in a
machine room or in a building roof 18. Each refrigeration case or housing has its own
evaporator and associated second expansion valve as illustrated at 54 (a, b, c) and 52 (a,
b, c) as well as a liquid line shut off valve 58 (a, b, c) and a thermostat 172 (a, b, c), which
controls a respective liquid line shut off valve 58 (a, b, c). In addition, one of the 
refrigeration cases or housings, typically the lowest temperature case or housing, may
have a temperature sensor 174 as illustrated for refrigeration case or housing 42a. When
temperature sensor 174 is included, it supplies output information to controller 60 as
described below. Finally, a pressure sensor 176 can be included which monitors the
pressure of the refrigerant entering suction fitting 100. Pressure sensor 176 supplies this
information to controller 60 as described below.</p>
    <p num="0042">Alternatively, each evaporator 54 can have its own case controller 300 to
perform defrost, fan, and electronic expansion valve control based on the case
temperature and case outlet pressure, as shown in Figures 2, 7 and 11. Referring
specifically to Figure 11, a group of refrigeration cases 42a, 42b, 42c each included a case
controller 300a, 300b, 300c, respectively. Temperature sensors 174a, 174b and 174c and
pressure sensors 176a, 176b and 176c provide temperature and case outlet pressure
measurements to the respective case controllers 300a, 300b and 300c. The case
controllers 300a, 300b and 300c are connected via a digital two-way communication path
310 to the system controller 60, whereby temperature and pressure sensor values and
case demand loading state (1 or 0) can be provided to system controller 60 by case
controllers 300a, 300b and 300c. Further, each case controller 300a, 300b and 300c
performs defrost, electronic expansion valve, and fan control locally based on the receive
temperature and pressure sensor values.</p>
    <p num="0043">The multiple case or multiple cooling unit embodiment of Figure 7 shows how
a single compressor 44 can be pulse-width modulated for capacity control and vapor
injection by controller 60 to supply the instantaneous demand for cooling. Temperature
sensor 174 and/or pressure sensor 176 provide an indication of the load on the system. 
Controller 60 adjusts the pulse width modulation of both the capacity control system 120
and the vapor injection system to modulate the compressor between its high capacity and
low capacity states to meet the instantaneous demand for refrigerant as described below.</p>
    <p num="0044">Controller 60 is capable of controlling the capacity of compressor 44 by using
pulse width modulation of solenoid valve 64. The capacity of compressor 44 can be
controlled from 0% to 100% but for this embodiment, the capacity is modulated from 10%
to 100% by pulse width modulation operation. In addition, the capacity of compressor 44
can be increased anywhere from 100% to approximately 130% by pulse width modulation
of solenoid valve 68, which controls the vapor injection system of the present invention.
It is also possible for controller 60 to operate solenoid valve 68 in an on/off manner if
desired. The operational characteristics and algorithms incorporated into controller 60 are
detailed below.</p>
    <p num="0045">Controller 60 is capable of controlling either single-evaporator (Figure 2) or
multi-evaporator (Figure 7) refrigeration systems. The multi-evaporator systems could
have evaporators at similar temperatures or at mixed temperatures by employing electronic
pressure regulators in the higher temperature evaporators.</p>
    <p num="0046">Referring now to Figures 7 and 8, controller 60 is shown in greater detail.
Controller 60 controls an alarm output 200 that will remain on during any alarm condition.
Alarm output 200 will reset itself when all alarm conditions are gone.</p>
    <p num="0047">Controller 60 controls the operation of a first condenser fan 202 and a second
condenser fan 204. Cooling system 40 includes two condenser fan motors and fans for
condenser 46. Controller 60 controls the operation of the motor for compressor 44 as 
shown at 206, it controls the operation of vapor injection solenoid valve 68 as shown at 208
and it controls the operation of capacity control solenoid valve 64 as shown at 210.</p>
    <p num="0048">Various inputs are provided to controller 60. These inputs include control
power at 212, an optional suction pressure input from pressure sensor 176 at 214, an
optional load case temperature input from temperature sensor 174 at 216, the temperature
of refrigerant at the mid-coil or the coil return of condenser 46 from a temperature sensor
218 at 220 and the temperature of the discharge gas of compressor 44 from a temperature
sensor 222 at 224. Using the various inputs, controller 60 can control the capacity of
compressor 44 based on either case air temperature, compressor suction pressure, or both
as detailed below. Controller 60 and the various terminal blocks are housed in an
enclosure (not shown) suitable for mounting on cooling system 40.</p>
    <p num="0049">While not specifically detailed, cooling system 40 also includes a low
pressure cutout electromechanical switch to stop compressor 44 at very low suction
pressure for vacuum protection; and a high head pressure cutout electromechanical switch
to stop compressor 44 at very high discharge pressure, if such protection is required. As
detailed above, each evaporator 54 (a, b, c) has associated with it their own liquid line
solenoid valve 58 (a, b, c), their own temperature sensors 172 (a, b, c) and their own
thermostatic expansion valve 52 (a, b, c). None of these valves or sensors are in
communication with controller 60. The only communication with controller 60 is through
lead case temperature sensor 174 and/or suction pressure sensor 176. Finally, controller
60 is capable of being switched between refrigerants, including, but not limited to, R-404A,
R-407C, R-22, R-134a and R-410A as detailed below. </p>
    <heading><u style="single">Compressor Capacity Control Algorithms</u> (Figure 9).</heading>
    <p num="0050">Controller 60 modulates the capacity of compressor 44 through pulse width
modulation control of solenoid valve 64 and/or solenoid valve 68. There are two different
Proportional-lntegral-Derivative control loops. Controller 60 can be set to use suction
pressure control using sensor 176, lead case temperature control using sensor 174 or a
combination of lead case temperature control with suction control backup using sensors
174 and 176. Each will be described in turn.</p>
    <p num="0051">Suction Pressure Control: During suction pressure control, compressor 44
will be operated with the loading time adjusted to maintain an average suction pressure at
a suction pressure set point 230. Determining the average suction pressure will be done
by taking many samples of suction pressure during each load/unload cycle time of
compressor 44 and then filtering this suction pressure data using a digital filter 232. The
digital filter will produce a useful average pressure for control purposes by removing almost
all of the pressure fluctuations caused by the loading and unloading of compressor 44.
Preferably, the sampling rate of the digital filter will be inversely proportional to the pulse-width-modulation
(PWM) cycle time so that regardless of the PWM cycle time selected, the
digital filter will operate with twenty samples during each PWM cycle. The filtering thus
achieved will have appropriate timing to match the PWM cycle time selected. Control of
the suction pressure is by PID algorithm. The suction pressure set point is settable at
controller 60 as described below. The signal from suction pressure sensor 176 is first
routed through the digital filter and then to the suction pressure PID algorithm. If suction
pressure control is chosen, then the lead case temperature PID algorithm is ignored. </p>
    <p num="0052">Lead Case Temperature Control: During lead case temperature control,
compressor 44 will be operated with the loading duty cycle percentage adjusted to maintain
the temperature of air in the chosen lead case at a lead case temperature set point 234.
Control of this lead case temperature will be by PID algorithm. The lead case temperature
set point will be settable on controller 60 as described below. The signal from temperature
sensor 174 will go directly to the lead case temperature PID algorithm. If lead case
temperature control is chosen, the suction pressure PID algorithm will be ignored.</p>
    <p num="0053">Combination Control: During combination control, compressor 44 will be
operated to achieve both suction pressure set point 230 and lead case temperature set
point 234. The capacity of compressor 44 will be increased until both of these set points
are satisfied. The combination control is accomplished by allowing both suction pressure
PID control and lead case temperature PID control to function simultaneously. Controller
60 gives dominance to whichever PID control calls for the lowest compressor capacity.
The determination of which one controls will be recalculated during each unloaded cycle
for compressor 44. The preferred intent of this combination control is that lead case
temperature will be the dominant control most of the time, so it must require the lesser
compressor capacity. Thus, the lead case temperature set point will usually be set to a
slightly higher refrigeration temperature than the suction pressure set point by itself would
achieve. The outputs of the two PID control functions (one for suction pressure and one
for lead case temperature) will be combined in a selector 236 that will pass on the lesser
of the two. The selector will supply the signal to a capacity modulation generator 238. The
capacity modulation generator generates the timing of PWM solenoid valve 64 which is
provided to a solenoid driver 240. The reason for preferring dominance of the lead case 
temperature is that if the suction pressure set point were set to achieve a lower
temperature than the lead case temperature set point, then the suction pressure control
would dominate and the temperature of the lead case would be held at a temperature
lower than the lead case temperature set point. Such settings essentially disable the
usefulness of the lead case temperature measurement. The presence of suction pressure
control during a dominant lead temperature control is useful during defrosts of the lead
case because the suction pressure is lower than the lead case temperature during defrost.
In addition, the pressure of suction pressure sensor 176 enables better condenser control
and better protection against short cycling the compressor motor when suction pressure
goes too low. The combination control mode will have no inner loop and no outer loop.
The two PID control paths are equals, both active, with selector 236 determining which
has controlling effect at the moment.</p>
    <p num="0054">To convert to pulse width modulation, the output of the selector algorithm of
selector 236 will be converted to a duty cycle value of a repeating pulse by capacity
modulation generator 238. The output of capacity modulation generator 238 will control
solenoid valve 64 of compressor 44. More capacity will cause solenoid valve 64 to be
energized (or de-energized) during a smaller proportion of the cycle time to increase
compressor 44's capacity. The output capacity is calculated as follows:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">Output = <st32:italic>K<st32:sub pos="post">p</st32:sub></st32:italic>*<st32:italic>e</st32:italic>(<st32:italic>t</st32:italic>)+<st32:italic>K<st32:sub pos="post">i</st32:sub></st32:italic>*<st32:frac align="centre">1<st32:over>π</st32:over></st32:frac><st32:italic>∫e</st32:italic>(<st32:italic>t</st32:italic>)<st32:italic>dt+K<st32:sub pos="post">d</st32:sub>*</st32:italic><st32:frac align="centre"><st32:italic>de</st32:italic>(<st32:italic>t</st32:italic>)<st32:over><st32:italic>dt</st32:italic></st32:over></st32:frac></st32:df>
where <i>e(t)</i> is the error signal between the sensed value and the set point, <i>K<sub>p</sub></i> is the
proportional constant, <i>K<sub>d</sub></i> is the derivative constant, and  <i>K<sub>i</sub></i> / π is the integral constant. The
two PID (Proportional-lntegral-Derivative) algorithms may be simplified to PI (Proportional-Integral) 
algorithms with no derivative function. In relation to the output equation above,
the proportional and integral constants are divided by 100 to arrive at P and I as used here.
PID (or PI) constants for the suction pressure control will be adjustable and they will have
default values. There will also be minimum and maximum values, beyond which they
cannot be set. Preferably, the default values are P = 0.3, I = 0.15; and the adjustment
ranges are P = 0.1 to 0.6, I = 0.05 to 0.03. These PI constants for the lead case
temperature control will be adjustable and they will have default values. There will also be
minimum and maximum values, beyond which they cannot be set. Preferably, the default
values are P = 0.3, I = 0.3; and the adjustment ranges are P = 0.1 to 0.6, I = 0.05 to 0.03.</p>
    <p num="0055">The PWM maximum cycle time will be user selectable as described below.
Preferably the default value will be 20 seconds, the minimum value will be 10 seconds and
the maximum value will be 60 seconds.</p>
    <p num="0056">A low compressor capacity limit is also provided. Even though the capacity
of compressor 44 can be reduced to 0%, controller 60 will turn off the motor of compressor
44 if the required compressor capacity value goes below 10%. Restarting of the motor will
be governed by the capacity requirement rising to 10% or more and by the motor start
logic.</p>
    <p num="0057">Control for low capacity with short PWM cycle time is also provided. The
loaded time for compressor 44 will be controlled to be no less than two seconds. For a
PWM maximum cycle time setting of twenty seconds (the default value) or more, this
condition is met by the minimum loaded duty cycle of 10%. For a PWM maximum cycle
time setting of less than twenty seconds (ten-twenty seconds), the PWM cycle time will be
increased when the capacity is at a low value so that the minimum loaded time condition 
of two seconds is maintained. If the PWM maximum cycle time is set to ten seconds, then
while PWM is 20% or more, the minimum loaded time of two seconds is satisfied. If the
capacity decreased to 15%, then to maintain the minimum loaded time of two seconds, the
PWM cycle time will increase automatically to thirteen and one-third seconds. (15% of
thirteen and one-third seconds is two seconds). If capacity decreases to 10%, the PWM
cycle time will increase automatically to twenty seconds (10% of twenty seconds is two
seconds). When the calculated capacity is less than 10% (which causes the compressor
motor to turn off), the PWM cycle time will not be increased beyond the time value for PWM
at 10%. This permits other control functions to operate normally, so that the correct time
to resume pumping can be determined by the control algorithms without excessive delay.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Vapor Injection</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0058">Controller 60 is programmed to operate injection solenoid valve 68. This will
increase the capacity of compressor 44 to approximately 130%. Controller 60 will only
operate solenoid valve 68 when capacity solenoid valve 64 is de-energized. Thus, before
vapor injection by controller 60 can proceed, the capacity of compressor 44 must be at
100%. Controller 60 will then operate solenoid valve 68 using pulse width modulation to
increase the capacity of compressor 44 from 100% up to approximately 130% depending
on the requirements determined by controller 60.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Motor Start Logic</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0059">Delay - Controller 60 includes motor start logic which prohibits the
compressor motor from being started until after an appropriate time delay. The time delay
will begin at the most recent moment that the compressor motor was stopped. Preferably 
the compressor motor will have a start delay of two minutes and this delay time is not
adjustable. This prevents more than thirty motor starts in any given hour.</p>
    <p num="0060">Start Unloaded - Controller 60 includes additional motor start logic which
unloads compressor 44 at the time of starting by energizing (or de-energizing) solenoid
valve 64. The unloaded starting of the motor will reduce motor inrush current and enable
more motor starts without excessive wear on the motor contactor. Preferably, solenoid
valve 64 will be energized (or de-energized) one second before energizing the motor
contactor to unload compressor 44 and it will remain energized (or de-energized) for three
seconds after the motor starts keeping compressor 44 unloaded. After this unloaded
running, control of solenoid valve 64 is returned to the normal PID control algorithms
assuming controller 60 is operating. If controller 60 has failed or is not powered, then
application of power to the rest of cooling system 40 will cause all motors and vapor
injection to run without delay. The PWM output will be off and compressor 44 will operate
at 100% capacity with the vapor injection increasing the capacity to approximately 130%.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Pump Down</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0061">Controller 60 may include suction pressure sensor 176. When sensor 176
is included, pump down when an individual case 42 goes into defrost (stopping refrigerant
flow) will generally not occur because the pressure control algorithm will reduce
compressor capacity to maintain the suction pressure at set point 230. However, suction
pressure sensor 176 is positioned in front of digital filter 232 and thus pressure sensor 176
can monitor excessively low suction pressure. Preferably, if instantaneous suction
pressure goes below five PSIG, the compressor motor will be stopped immediately, and
restart logic will be invoked. Preferably, the electromechanical low pressure cutout switch 
should be set to zero PSIG. In this manner, it will prevent vacuum but it will also allow
suction pressure sensor 176 to prevent low pressure conditions. The electromechanical
switch then becomes a backup control. When suction pressure sensor 176 is not included
with controller 60, then controller 60 cannot prevent pump down. The external
electromechanical low pressure cutout switch must control compressor 44 under such
conditions. Restart logic (the delay) within controller 60 cannot be invoked.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">High Discharge Temperature Compressor Protection</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0062">Conditions Detected - As shown in Figure 8, cooling system 40 includes
temperature sensor 222 which monitors the discharge temperature for compressor 44.
Controller 60 includes two set points for the discharge gas temperature of compressor 44.
Preferably, the Very High Discharge Temperature Condition (VHDTC) will be set to be true
above 280 F(138 C) and false below 270 F(132 C). Preferably, the High Discharge
Temperature Condition (HDTC) will be true above 260 F (127 C) and false below 250 F
(121 C). These two set points are not adjustable. If a VHDTC is sensed as true (above
280 F) for larger than fifteen seconds, the compressor motor will be turned off.</p>
    <p num="0063">Vapor Injection During High Discharge Temperature - If the compressor
motor is running and the HDTC is true but the VHDTC is false, the capacity for compressor
44 will be forced to 100% by ending the pulse width modulation for solenoid valve 64 and
vapor injection solenoid 68 will be energized (or de-energized) to provide full vapor
injection. Then, if the compressor motor is running and the HDTC returns to false (and the
VHDTC remains false), the compressor capacity will return to normal control and vapor
injection solenoid 68 will be de-energized (or energized) to end vapor injection. The ending
of vapor injection assumes the compressor capacity is below 100%. </p>
    <p num="0064">Automatic Restarts - As discussed above, an automatic restart will occur after
the motor has been stopped and after a specified delay time. Controller 60 allows for an
automatic restart but this automatic restart may be locked out, requiring a manual reset as
detailed below. When the compressor motor is turned off due to high discharge
temperature (as detailed above), controller 60 keeps a count of these High Discharge
Temperature Shutdown Events (HDTSE). The HDTSE counter will be at zero until a
HDTSE occurs. The counter will increment by one each time a HDTSE occurs at the time
the condition is detected. A thirty minute high discharge temperature restart delay timer
will be started each time a HDTSE occurs. When both the VHDTC and the HDTC are false
(compressor 44 has cooled) and the temperature restart delay timer has completed its
timing and if the counter is less than four, a motor restart will occur assuming controller 60
determines the need. The net effect is that only three automatic restarts are allowed after
high discharge temperature events and these automatic restarts are allowed only after
compressor 44 has cooled down as indicated by sensor 222 and the motor has not been
running for thirty seconds. If a fourth HDTSE occurs, the motor will not automatically
restart until the counter is manually reset to zero at controller 60. While a HDTSE is in
progress, an error code will be displayed by controller 60. Preferably, E11 will indicate the
first event, E12 will indicate the second event, E13 will indicate the third event and E14 will
indicate the fourth event. For E11, E12 and E13, an automatic restart will occur. E14
indicates that a manual restart is necessary. The counter for the high discharge
temperature events will be retained through power outages. The state of the high
temperature delay timer will be retained during power outages (to the nearest five minutes).
The states of the HDTC and the VHDTC, if either is true, will also be retained during power 
outages. This information will be written to non-volatile memory at five minute intervals.
Once both conditions are false and the thirty minute timer has expired, the writing of this
information to the non-volatile memory will cease. This non-writing of information during
normal operation of cooling system 40 avoids the "wearing out" of the non-volatile memory.</p>
    <p num="0065">Manual Reset - The counter for the high discharge temperature events may
be reset to zero any time, even if its count is less than four. Manual reset of the counter
will clear both the count and any time remaining on the thirty minute delay timer. After a
manual reset, the motor will restart only if (or after) the temperature of the discharge gas
has decreased as sensed by sensor 222. This arrangement will allow factory test of the
high temperature shutdown feature without undue time loss for delays and without wasting
allowed automatic restarts. Preferably, controller 60 will include a separate push-button
250 (Figure 10) for Manual Reset and push-button 250 must be pressed and held for two
seconds to achieve manual restart. A yellow LED 252 beside push-button 250 indicates
the need for a manual restart. LED 252 will be turned on when E14 is being displayed and
LED 252 will turn off when the manual restart process has begun.</p>
    <p num="0066">Operation With Failed Discharge Temperature Sensor - If discharge
temperature sensor 222 appears to controller 60 to be disconnected or shorted out, this
will constitute a detection of a failed sensor 222 and error code E04 will be displayed by
controller 60. When sensor 222 failure is detected, controller 60 will continue to operate
normally except that the capacity of compressor 44 will be limited to 75% and alarm 200
will be turned on. There will be no other compressor protection by sensor 222 under such
conditions. However, compressors internal line break function for excessive temperature
will still be active. </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Condenser Fan Control</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0067">Condenser Fan Control Algorithm - As shown in Figure 8, controller 60
operates two condenser fans 202 and 204. Fans 202 and 204 will be operated in a lead
and lag fashion, with control based primarily on condensing temperature and partially upon
the running capacity of compressor 44 and partially upon Saturated Suction Temperature
(SST). The condenser fan control algorithm will use the following six test control fans 202
and 204. These values are chosen to preferably maintain at least seventy-five PSI
pressure difference across compressor 44 to ensure good performance even at very low
outdoor ambient and condensing temperatures. The condenser control algorithms do not
have adjustable set points other than the type of refrigerant. In the tests below, SCT is
Saturated Condenser Temperature, SST is Saturated Suction Temperature and CapC is
the capacity of the compressor within limits for condenser 46.
<sl><li>1. Turn <b>ON</b> the <b>LEAD</b> condenser fan when
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">SCT &gt; {[SST - (40 F)] x [0.5] + (+53 F)}</st32:df></li><li>2. Turn <b>ON</b> the <b>LAG</b> condenser fan when
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">SCT &gt; {[SST - (40 F)] x [0.5] - [CapC / 100%] x [(+112 F) - (+32 F)] +<st32:break type="required"/>
(+113 F)}</st32:df></li><li>3. Turn <b>OFF</b> the <b>LAG</b> condenser fan when
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">SCT &lt; {[SST - (-40 F)] x [0.5] - [CapC / 100%] x [(+112 F) - (+32 F)] +<st32:break type="required"/>
(+93 F)}</st32:df></li><li>4. Turn <b>OFF</b> the <b>LEAD</b> condenser fan when
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">SCT &lt; {[SST - (-40 F)] x [0.5] + (+33 F)}</st32:df></li><li>5. Turn <b>ON</b> the <b>LEAD</b> condenser fan when
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">SCT &gt; {(+105 F)}</st32:df></li><li>6. Turn <b>ON</b> the <b>LAG</b> condenser fan when
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">SCT &gt; {(+125 F)}</st32:df></li></sl> 
The above equations are written so that all of the Fahrenheit temperature values can be
replaced with the equivalent Celsius temperature values and still produce the same control
results. Controller 60 determines SCT by reading temperature sensor 218. SST is a
calculated temperature that will be determined by converting the output of digital filter 232
(suction pressure) to a corresponding refrigerant vapor/liquid saturation temperature. If
suction pressure sensor 176 is not included with controller 60, the lead case temperature
reading from sensor 174 will be used. The sensed temperature minus 9 F (5 C) will be
used as SST. CapC for the condenser fan control algorithm is equal to the capacity value
currently driving capacity solenoid 64 except that CapC is limited to no less than 25% and
no more than 50%. Fan control tests five and six above cause fans 202 and 204 to turn
on at specific SCT maximum values regardless of other conditions to prevent excessive
discharge pressures and temperature. This is a necessary backup operating mode for
installations where suction pressure sensor 176 is not present and lead case temperature
sensor 172 is being used to determine SST. In these installations defrosting of the lead
case would cause controller 60 to turn fans 202 and 204 off allowing condenser
temperature to rise. Tests five and six above override tests one through four.</p>
    <p num="0068">Condenser Fan Delays - Preferably, each condenser fan 202 and 204 will
stay on for sixty seconds after it starts and stay off for thirty seconds after it stops. This
time delay prevents excessive fan cycling.</p>
    <p num="0069">Condenser Fan Alternation - Which condenser fan leads and which one lags
in the above described control scheme is alternated by a fan alternation timer. Preferably,
the lead/lag fan is alternated about once every twenty hours. If at the time for alternation
and only one fan is on, the alternation will not occur. The fan alternation timer will wait until 
the next time both fans are on or both fans are off to make the change. However, if the
alternation favorable condition (both on or off) does not occur after a long period of time,
then the change of lead and lag fans will be forced to happen. Preferably, an alternation
suspend timer will run for five hours before forcing the change. The timer is started by
timeout of the fan alternation timer (twenty hours) and it is reset by successful alternation
of lead and lag fans. This alternation method reduces wear stress by evening out run time
for each fan.</p>
    <p num="0070">Operation With Failed Sensors - Normal condenser fan operation depends
upon signals from two sensors. Normal condenser fan operation will be suspended and
a backup control algorithm will take over if failure of a sensor used by the condenser
control is detected. When there is a sensor failure affecting the condenser control, the lead
fan will be on any time the compressor is running. The lag fan will turn on any time the
compressor capacity exceeds 35% and turn off when the compressor capacity is below
25%.</p>
    <p num="0071">One Condenser Fan - If there is just one condenser fan, the two condenser
fan outputs of controller 60 must be connected in parallel to ensure that the single fan will
always be the lead fan. There is no override provided for the periodic alternating between
lead and lag.</p>
    <p num="0072">Output States at Power Up - At initial power up, the compressor motor will
run, capacity solenoid valve 64 will be de-energized (or energized) to provide a compressor
capacity of 100% and both condenser fans 202 and 204 will be on. Controller 60 will
initially be in a non-functional reset state immediately after power up. After controller 60
begins functioning, items which should not be on will be staged off, otherwise they will be 
left on. Capacity solenoid valve 64 will begin operating after controller 60 begins
functioning. In addition, alarm 200 will be turned on until controller 60 begins functioning
after which it will be turned off.</p>
    <p num="0073">Suction Pressure Sensor Failure - If suction pressure set point 230 is not 99
and suction pressure sensor 176 appears to controller 60 to be disconnected, this will
constitute a detection of a failed sensor 176 and an error code E01 will be displayed and
alarm 200 will be turned on. The compressor capacity will be set at 100% and vapor
injection solenoid 68 will be energized (or de-energized) to increase the capacity above
100%. Compressor 44 will remain in this state until the failed sensor condition is no longer
detected. If suction pressure set point 230 is set to 99, this signals controller 60 that
suction pressure control is not to be used and alarm 200 will not be turned on.</p>
    <p num="0074">Lead Case Temperature Sensor Failure - If lead case temperature set point
234 is not 99 and lead case temperature sensor 174 appears to controller 60 to be either
disconnected or shortened out, this will constitute a detection of a failed sensor 174 and
an error code E02 will be displayed and alarm 200 will be turned on. The compressor
capacity will be set at 100% and vapor injection solenoid 68 will be energized (or de-energized)
to increase the capacity above 100%. Compressor 44 will remain in this state
until the failed sensor condition is no longer detected. If lead case temperature set point
234 is set to 99, this signals controller 60 that lead case temperature control is not to be
used and alarm 200 will not be turned on.</p>
    <p num="0075">Condenser Temperature Sensor Failure - If condenser temperature sensor
218 appears to controller 60 to be disconnected or shorted out, this will constitute a 
detection of a failed sensor 218 and an error code E03 will be displayed and alarm 200 will
be turned on.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Display</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0076">In order to keep controller 60 simple, the display will comprise three seven
segment digits 254, 256 and 258; four push-buttons 250, 260, 262 and 264; and seventeen
point lights 252 and 266-296, all Light Emitting Diodes as shown in Figure 10.</p>
    <p num="0077">Digits - Controller 60 displays the various set points and error codes
discussed above using "seven segment" digits 254, 256 and 258. The illuminated part of
digits 254-258 is preferably three-tenths of an inch high. The various error codes
discussed above (E01 through E14) will be indicated on the display briefly along with the
operating values. This display of error codes and values will continue to repeat if alarm
200 is turned on. Preferably, if there is one alarm condition, the error code will be shown
for one-half second and the selected operating value will be shown for 1.95 seconds. If
there are multiple alarm conditions, they will be shown in numerical order for 0.45 seconds
each with the selected operating valve being shown for two seconds each. Each alarm
code display time will be surrounded by a blank display for one-half second. This will
achieve a flash effect to call attention to the alarm.</p>
    <p num="0078">Point Lights (LED) - The seventeen point lights (LEDs) are either green, red
or yellow in color. Each output will have a point light associated with it. Green point lights
indicate that the item is display-only. Red point lights indicate that the item has a set point
that can be changed. Yellow lights indicate manual mode and alarm. LED 252 is a yellow
point light which indicates manual reset of the counter for auto restarts must be manually
set. LED 266 is a red point light which indicates a combination control of suction pressure 
and lead case temperature control is being used. LED 268 is a red point light which
indicates that LEAD case temperature control is being used. LED 270 is a red point light
that indicates that suction pressure control is being used. (Only one of LEDs 266-270 will
be lit at one time). LED 272 is a green point light which indicates that the display is
showing the suction pressure directly from suction pressure sensor 176. LED 274 is a red
point light which indicates that the display is showing the average suction pressure from
digital filter 232. LED 276 is a red point light which indicates that the display is showing
the calculated saturation temperature (SST) of the refrigerant. LED 278 is a red point light
which indicates that the display is showing the lead case temperature. LED 280 is a green
point light which indicates that the display is showing the discharge temperature based on
sensor 222. LED 282 is a yellow point light which indicates that the display is showing the
current compressor capacity in the manual mode. LED 284 is a red point light which
indicates that the display is showing the current compressor capacity in the automatic
mode. LED 286 is a red point light which indicates the display is showing the total time for
one PWM cycle of solenoid valve 64. LEDS 288-294 are each red point lights which
indicate that the display is showing the four constants detailed above under "Compressor
Capacity Control Algorithms". LED 296 is a red point light which indicates that the display
is showing the type of refrigerant being used.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Set Points</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0079">Various set points can be changed by operating push-buttons 260-264. The
same push-buttons which select the display of operating values (262 and 264) will also
select the underlying set points. Pushing these buttons will select the various set points
and which set point is being displayed will be indicated by LEDS 272-296. The displayed 
value will be shown on digits 254-258. When a specific set point is being displayed,
pressing and holding push-button 260 will then allow push-buttons 262 and 264 to
decrease and increase, respectively, the value of the set point. If there is no associated
set point with the operating value being displayed, then pushing push-button 260 will have
no effect on buttons 262 and 264. All set points are maintained while power is off. The
adjustable set points include Suction Pressure (LED 274), SST (LED 276), Lead Case
Temperature (LED 278), Compressor Capacity (LEDs 282 and 284), PWM Cycle Time
(LED 286), the four PID constants (LEDs 288-294) and the refrigerant type (LED 296).</p>
    <p num="0080">Suction Pressure - This is the target average suction pressure to be achieved
by the compressor. Setting this to 99 will disable the suction pressure control mode (LED
268 will lite) and controller 60 will assume pressure sensor 176 is not connected. Suction
Pressure and SST are the views of the same set point assuming one adjusts the other.</p>
    <p num="0081">SST - This is the calculated saturation temperature of the refrigerant. This
is tied into suction pressure as indicated above.</p>
    <p num="0082">Lead Case Temperature - This is the set point for lead case temperature.
Setting it to 99 will disable the lead case temperature control mode (LED 270 will lite) and
controller 60 will assume temperature sensor 174 is not connected. Setting both suction
pressure and lead case temperature to lower values than 99 will cause the combination
control mode to be used (LED 266 will lite).</p>
    <p num="0083">Compressor Capacity - This allows for the manual mode of compressor 44
to be set. Merely selecting this item (LED 284) with buttons 262 or 264 will leave the
control automatic under PID and the display will show the operating value of compressor
capacity. Pressing and holding push-button 260 while this is selected (LED 284) will lock 
controller 60 at the capacity last calculated by the PID control loops and manual control of
capacity will begin (LED 282 will lite, LED 284 will be turned off). The manual capacity may
then be charged using push-buttons 262 or 264. Selecting a different set point using push-buttons
262 and 264 after releasing push-button 260 after changing the manual capacity
allows observing of the operating values while in the manual PWM mode. Selecting a
different set point and then pressing push-button 260 puts controller 60 back into the
automatic mode.</p>
    <p num="0084">PWM Cycle Time - This allows for the setting of the total time for one PWM
cycle of capacity solenoid valve 64.</p>
    <p num="0085">PID Pan I - These allow for the setting of the four constants described above
for the PID constants under "Compressor Capability Control Algorithms".</p>
    <p num="0086">Refrigerant - This allows for the setting of the type of refrigerant being used
in the system. Preferably these choices are R-404A, R-407C, R-22, R-134a and R-140.
These will be shown in the display as 404, 407, 22, 134 and 410, respectively. These
settings allow for the proper conversion between pressure and temperature. Controller 60
will include all five refrigerant settings even if compressor 44 is not qualified initially for all
five refrigerants.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Display Operating Values</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0087">Display Digits 254-258 on controller 60 can indicate any one of several
operating values. Push-buttons 262 and 264 are used to scroll through the various
operating values.</p>
    <p num="0088">Instantaneous Suction Pressure (LED 272) - This LED indicates that the
display is showing the suction pressure which is being read by suction pressure sensor 
176. This will indicate the up and down swings of suction pressure during each unloader
cycle.</p>
    <p num="0089">Average Suction Pressure (LED 274) - This LED indicates that the display
is showing the average suction pressure which is the output of digital filter 232. This will
not indicate the swings in pressure due to operation of the unloader cycle.</p>
    <p num="0090">Lead Case Temperature (LED 278) - This LED indicates that the current air
temperature in the lead case is being displayed. This reading comes directly from
temperature sensor 174.</p>
    <p num="0091">Discharge Temperature (LED 280) - This LED indicates that the current
compressor gas discharge temperature is being displayed. This reading comes directly
from temperature sensor 222.</p>
    <p num="0092">Compressor Capacity (LED 284) - This LED indicates that the current
compressor running capacity is being displayed. This value is calculated by controller 60
and is used to operate capacity modulation generator 238, solenoid driver 240 and
solenoid 64.</p>
    <p num="0093">PWM Cycle Time (LED 286) - This LED indicates the current value for the
PWM cycle time set point.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Operating Mode</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0094">As discussed above, controller 60 has a manual operating mode and an
automatic operating mode. In the automatic mode, controller 60 will operate with capacity
solenoid valve 64 controlled by the PID control loops. In the manual mode, compressor
44 will run with a constant fixed capacity. The capacity is set on controller 60 as detailed
above. The condenser fan control and the compressor protection schemes will continue 
to operate in the manual mode just as in the automatic mode. The manual mode is
intended for test purposes. Controller 60 will begin its operation in the automatic mode
after a reset.</p>
    <p num="0095">While the above detailed description describes the preferred embodiment of
the present invention, it should be understood that the present invention is susceptible to
modification, variation and alteration without deviating from the scope of
the subjoined claims.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A compressor control system comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a compressor that is selectively operable while energized in at least
two states including a first state correspondence to a first capacity and a second state
corresponding to a second capacity lower than said first capacity, said compressor
operable to compress a gas between a suction pressure and a discharge pressure;</claim-text><claim-text>a pressure sensor for sensing said suction pressure; and</claim-text><claim-text>a controller coupled to said pressure sensor for producing a variable
duty cycle control signal in which said duty cycle control signal is a function of said
suction pressure, said controller being coupled to said compressor for causing said
compressor to selectively alternate between said first and second states in response to
said variable duty cycle control signal, thereby adjusting capacity of said compressor
based upon said suction pressure.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A cooling system comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a housing;</claim-text><claim-text>an evaporator disposed in said housing;</claim-text><claim-text>a condenser coupled in fluid communication with said evaporator;</claim-text><claim-text>a compressor coupled in fluid communication with said evaporator
and said condenser, said compressor being a pulse-width modulated variable capacity
compressor;</claim-text><claim-text>a temperature sensor disposed in said housing, said temperature sensor
operable to read a temperature within said housing;</claim-text><claim-text>a system controller responsive to said temperature sensor and coupled
to said compressor for providing a variable duty cycle control signal to said
compressor whereby said compressor is modulated between a first capacity state and
a second capacity state while operating to thereby adjust the operating capacity of
said compressor based on said temperature within said housing to maintain a
specified temperature in said housing.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The cooling system according to claim 2, further comprising a first
and a second condenser fan, said controller being coupled to said condenser fans to
control said fans based upon a temperature sensed by said temperature sensor,
percent duty cycle and a calculated minimum pressure differential.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The cooling system according to claim 2 or 3, wherein said
compressor compresses a gas between a suction pressure and a discharge pressure,
and said cooling system further comprises a pressure sensor for sensing said suction
pressure, said system controller being coupled to said pressure sensor for controlling
said capacity of said compressor based on said suction pressure and said temperature
within said housing.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A cooling system comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a housing;</claim-text><claim-text>an evaporator disposed in said housing;</claim-text><claim-text>a condenser coupled in fluid communication with said evaporator;</claim-text><claim-text>a compressor coupled in fluid communication with said evaporator
and said condenser, said compressor compressing a gas between a suction pressure
and a discharge pressure;</claim-text><claim-text>a pressure sensor for sensing said suction pressure; and</claim-text><claim-text>a controller responsive to said suction pressure sensor and coupled to
said compressor for providing a variable duty cycle control signal to said compressor
whereby said compressor is modulated between a first capacity state and a second
capacity state while operating to thereby adjust the operating capacity of said
compressor based on said suction pressure to maintain a specified suction pressure.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The cooling system according to claim 5, further comprising a
temperature sensor and a first and a second condenser fan, said controller being
coupled to said condenser fans to control said fans based upon a temperature sensed
by said temperature sensor, percent duty cycle, and a calculated minimum pressure
differential.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A compressor control system for a multiple compressor rack with at
least one compressor having a pulse-width modulated capacity, said compressor
control system comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a pressure sensor for sensing a suction pressure of a gas; and</claim-text><claim-text>a system controller responsive to said suction pressure sensor and
coupled to the at least one compressor for providing a variable duty cycle control
signal to the at least one compressor, whereby said at least one compressor is
modulated between a first capacity state and a second capacity state while operating
to thereby adjust the operating capacity of the at least one compressor based on said
suction pressure to maintain a specified suction pressure.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The compressor control system according to claim 7, wherein said
system controller is coupled to a condenser fan to control the fan.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>The compressor control system according to claim 7 or 8, further
comprising an evaporator controller for controlling an evaporator and a temperature
sensor connected to said evaporator controller, said temperature sensor
communicating temperature data to said evaporator controller, and said evaporator
controller communicating said temperature data to said system controller.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>The compressor controller system according to claim 9, wherein said
evaporator controller further communicates demand loading state data to said system
controller.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>A compressor control system comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a multiple compressor rack with at least one compressor selectively
operable while energized in at least two states including a first state corresponding to
a first capacity and a second state corresponding to a second capacity lower than said
first capacity, said at least one compressor operable to compress a gas between a
suction pressure and a discharge pressure;</claim-text><claim-text>a pressure sensor for sensing said suction pressure; and</claim-text><claim-text>a controller coupled to said pressure sensor for producing a variable duty
cycle control signal in which the duty cycle control signal is a function of said
suction pressure, said controller being coupled to said compressor for causing said
compressor to selectively alternate between said first and second states in response to
said variable duty cycle control signal, thereby adjusting capacity of said at least one
compressor based upon said suction pressure.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>The compressor control system according to any one of claims 1 or 7
to 11 or the cooling system according to any one of claims 2 to 6, further comprising
a vapor injection system for injecting vapor into said compressor at a position
intermediate said suction pressure and said discharge pressure, said controller being
coupled to said vapor injection system for controlling injection of said gas.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>The compressor control system according to any one of claims 1 or 7
to 12 or the cooling system of any one of claims 2 to 6 or 12, further comprising a
temperature sensor for sensing a temperature of said gas at said discharge pressure,
said controller being coupled to said temperature sensor for controlling injection of
said vapor based on said temperature of said gas at said discharge pressure.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>The compressor control system according to any one of claims 1 or 7
to 13 or the cooling system of any one of claims 2 to 6, 12 or 13, wherein said
controller includes start logic, said start logic selecting said second state of said
compressor when said compressor is energized.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>A cooling system comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a housing;</claim-text><claim-text>an evaporator disposed in said housing;</claim-text><claim-text>a condenser coupled in fluid communication with said evaporator;</claim-text><claim-text>a compressor rack coupled in fluid communication with said
evaporator and said condenser, said compressor rack including at least one
compressor having a pulse-width modulated variable capacity and being operable
between two states;</claim-text><claim-text>a pressure sensor for sensing a suction pressure of a gas;</claim-text><claim-text>a system controller responsive to said suction pressure sensor and
coupled to the at least one compressor for providing a variable duty cycle control
signal to the at least one compressor, whereby said at least one compressor is
modulated between a first capacity state and a second capacity state while operating
to thereby adjust the operating capacity of the at least one compressor based on said
suction pressure to maintain a specified suction pressure.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>The cooling system according to claim 15, wherein said at least one
compressor compresses said gas between a suction pressure and a discharge pressure,
and said cooling system further comprises a temperature sensor for sensing a
temperature in said housing, said system controller being coupled to said temperature
sensor for controlling said capacity of said compressor based on said suction pressure
and said temperature within said housing.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>The compressor control system according to any one of claims 1 or 7
to 14 or the cooling system according to any one of claims 2 to 6 or 12 to 16, wherein
the or said at least one compressor is a scroll compressor.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="18">
      <claim-text>The compressor control system according to any one of claims 1, 7 to
14 or 17 or the cooling system according to any one of claims 2 to 6 or 12 to 16,
wherein the or said at least one compressor has two mechanical elements separated
by a seal, said mechanical elements being movable relative to one another to develop
fluid pressure and wherein the or said at least one compressor includes mechanism to
selectively break said seal in response to said control signal to thereby alter said fluid
pressure developed while allowing said mechanical elements to maintain
substantially constant relative movement with one another.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="19">
      <claim-text>The compressor control system or cooling system according to claim
18, wherein the or said at least one compressor is a scroll compressor and said two
mechanical elements are scroll members.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="20">
      <claim-text>The compressor control system according to any one of claims 1, 7 to
14, 17 or 18 or the cooling system according to any one of claims 2 to 6 or 12 to 18,
wherein said system controller determines an average suction pressure over a
specified period of time within a or each control cycle time.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="21">
      <claim-text>The cooling system according to any one of claims 2 to 6, 15 or 16,
further comprising a plurality of housings each having a respective evaporator
disposed therein, the or a temperature sensor being disposed in at least one of said
housings.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="22">
      <claim-text>The cooling system according to any one of claims 2 to 4, 15 or 16,
further comprising a plurality of housings, each having an evaporator, an evaporator
controller, and a temperature sensor in each of said plurality of housings, each said
temperature sensor connected to said evaporator controller in said each of said
plurality of housings, each said evaporator controller communicating temperature
sensor and demand loading state values to said system controller.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
