<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1229366-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1229366" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="25100906" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020807">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1229366-A2" status="new" fvid="23516861">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1229366</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20020807</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02002189-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02002189</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020129</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="US-77432601-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>77432601</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010131</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G02B   6/36        20060101AFI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G02B   6/36        20060101CFI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G02B   6/38        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G02B   6/38        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G02B   6/38D10A6L</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G02B   6/38D10G</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">S02B6:38D14P</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">S02B6:38D16</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">S02B6:38D8</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Faseroptisches Steckermodul</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Fiber optic connector module</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Module connecteur à fibre optique</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MOLEX INC</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MOLEX INCORPORATED</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>MOLEX INCORPORATED</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>2222 Wellington Court</street>
              <city>Lisle, IL 60532</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>CHEN WENZONG</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GROIS IGOR</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MATASEK JEFFREY A</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>CHEN, WENZONG</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GROIS, IGOR</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MATASEK, JEFFREY A.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>CHEN, WENZONG</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>959 Honest Pleasure Drive</street>
              <city>Naperville, IL 60540</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>GROIS, IGOR</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>4010 Greenacre Drive</street>
              <city>Northbrook, IL 60062</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>MATASEK, JEFFREY A.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>N40 W7153 Wilson Street</street>
              <city>Cedarburg, Wisconsin 53012</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Kampfenkel, Klaus</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Blumbach, Kramer &amp;amp; Partner GbR, Alexandrastrasse 5</street>
              <city>65187 Wiesbaden</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>IT</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A fiber optic connector module (24) is provided for
terminating a fiber optic cable (26) which includes at least
one inner optical fiber (54,110) surrounded by an outer
jacket (56). A ferrule (58) is terminated to an end of the
optical fiber stripped of the jacket. A fixing body (62) is
fixed to the jacket rearwardly of the ferrule. A housing (68)
includes a front portion (86) within which the ferrule (58)
is mounted and a rear portion (88) within which the fixing
body (62) is mounted. The front portion has an open front end
(86a) through which a mating end of the ferrule is exposed.
The rear portion has an open rear end (88a) through which the
fiber optic cable extends.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="154" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="101"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Field of the Invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0001">This invention generally relates to the art of fiber
optic transmission and particularly, to a fiber optic
connector module.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Background of the Invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0002">Fiber optic connectors of a wide variety of designs have
been employed to terminate optical fiber cables and to
facilitate connection of the cables to other cables or other
optical fiber transmission devices. A typical fiber optic
connector includes a ferrule which mounts and centers an
optical fiber or fibers within the connector. The ferrule may
be fabricated of such material as ceramic. A ferrule holder
or other housing component of the connector embraces the
ferrule and may be fabricated of such material as molded
plastic. A spring may be disposed with the housing or ferrule
holder such that the ferrule is yieldably biased forwardly
for engaging another fiber-mounting ferrule of a mating
connecting device.</p>
    <p num="0003">A pair of fiber optic connectors or a connector and
another optical fiber transmission device often are mated in
an adapter which centers the fibers to provide low insertion
losses. The adapter may be an in-line component, or the
adapter can be designed for mounting in an opening in a
panel, backplane, circuit board or the like.</p>
    <p num="0004">Various problems continue to be encountered in designing
fiber optic connector assemblies or other connector 
assemblies, including applications involving backplanes,
motherboards, daughterboards and the like. Such problems
often involve efforts to simplify the design of the connector
assemblies, particularly, the modules which terminate the
optical fibers. Such designs heretofore tend to be unduly
complicated and expensive. The present invention is directed
to solving these problems and to providing various
improvements in such connector assemblies, particularly in
the fiber optic connector modules.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Summary of the Invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0005">An object, therefore, of the invention is to provide a
new and improved connector assembly, particularly a fiber
optic connector module.</p>
    <p num="0006">Another object of the invention is to provide a new and
improved fiber optic connector module for terminating a fiber
optic cable which includes at least one inner optical fiber
surrounded by strength members and an outer jacket.</p>
    <p num="0007">In the exemplary embodiment of the invention, the module
includes a ferrule terminated to an end of the optical fiber
stripped of the jacket. A fixing body is fixed to the jacket
rearwardly of the ferrule. A housing includes a front portion
within which the ferrule is mounted and a rear portion within
which the fixing body is mounted. The front portion has an
open front end through which a mating end of the ferrule is
exposed. The rear portion has an open rear end through which
the fiber optic cable extends.</p>
    <p num="0008">As disclosed herein, the front portion of the housing
includes stop means engageable by the ferrule. Therefore, the
ferrule and terminated fiber optic cable can be inserted into
the open end of the housing and into abutment with the stop
means. Complementary interengaging latch means are provided
between the fixing body and the rear portion of the housing
to hold the fixing body and terminated fiber optic cable
within the housing. In the preferred embodiment, the latch 
means is provided by complementary interengaging snap-latch
members on the fixing body and the housing engageable
automatically in response to inserting the fixing body into
the housing through the open rear end thereof at the same
time that the ferrule and terminated fiber optic cable are
inserted into the housing in abutment with the stop means.</p>
    <p num="0009">According to one aspect of the invention, the fixing
body includes a crimp section through which the optical fiber
extends, with the strength members and outer jacket
positioned on the outside of the crimp section. A crimp ring
clamps the strength members and the jacket to the crimp
section of the fixing body.</p>
    <p num="0010">According to another aspect of the invention, a flexible
strain relief boot surrounds the fiber optic cable and
extends away from the rear portion of the housing.
Complementary interengaging latch means are provided between
the boot and the fixing body. In the preferred embodiment,
the latch means is provided by complementary interengaging
snap-latch members on the boot and the fixing body engageable
automatically in response to mounting the boot on the fixing
body. Therefore, the fixing body is latched at one end
thereof to the housing and at another end thereof to the
boot.</p>
    <p num="0011">Finally, the housing includes a flexible latch arm for
holding the connector within an opening in a panel, such as a
backplane, circuit board or the like. The latch arm includes
a latch hook on the outside thereof, along with serrations on
the outside of the latch arm engageable by an operator's
fingers.</p>
    <p num="0012">Other objects, features and advantages of the invention
will be apparent from the following detailed description
taken in connection with the accompanying drawings.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Brief Description of the Drawings</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0013">The features of this invention which are believed to be
novel are set forth with particularity in the appended
claims. The invention, together with its objects and the
advantages thereof, may be best understood by reference to
the following description taken in conjunction with the
accompanying drawings, in which like reference numerals
identify like elements in the figures and in which:
<dl compact="compact" tsize="14"><dt>FIGURE 1</dt><dd>is a perspective view of a mating connector
assembly according to the invention, with the
assembly in unmated condition;</dd><dt>FIGURE 2</dt><dd>is a side elevational view of the connector
assembly as shown in Figure 1;</dd><dt>FIGURE 3</dt><dd>is a perspective view of the connector assembly of
Figure 1, in mated condition;</dd><dt>FIGURE 4</dt><dd>is a side elevational view of the connector
assembly in the mated condition of Figure 3;</dd><dt>FIGURE 5</dt><dd>is an exploded perspective of the backplane
connector assembly as seen to the left in Figures
1-4; and</dd><dt>FIGURES 6
to 9</dt><dd>are sequential views showing the details and
assembly of one of the fiber optic connector
modules of the backplane connector assembly of
Figure 5.</dd></dl></p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Detailed Description of the Preferred Embodiment</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0014">Referring to the drawings in greater detail, and first
to Figures 1-4, the invention is embodied in a mating
connector assembly, generally designated 10, which includes a
backplane connector assembly, generally designated 12,
mateable with a daughterboard connector assembly, generally
designated 14. The backplane connector assembly is mounted in
an aperture 16 in a substrate, panel or backplane 18 which,
in the preferred embodiment, is a printed circuit board.
Specifically, backplane 18 can be considered the 
"motherboard" herein. The daughterboard connector assembly is
mounted on a top surface of a second printed circuit board 20
which is considered the "daughterboard" herein.</p>
    <p num="0015">Backplane connector assembly 12 includes an adapter,
generally designated 22, which is mounted in aperture 16 in
motherboard 18. Four fiber optic connector modules, generally
designated 24, are inserted into adaptor 22, through aperture
16, from the front of backplane 18. Each fiber optic
connector module is terminated to a multi-fiber cable 26. As
will be seen hereinafter, each cable 26 is a flat or "ribbon"
cable, having a plurality of optical fibers in a ribbon and
surrounded by an outer cladding.</p>
    <p num="0016">After daughterboard connector assembly 14 is mounted on
daughterboard 20, four fiber optic connector modules,
generally designated 28, are inserted into the back of a
connector housing 30. Each module 28 is terminated to a flat,
multi-fiber cable 32 which is a "bare" fiber optic cable in
that it does not include an outer jacket. The fibers are
terminated in ferrules 34, with mating ends of the ferrules
and fibers exposed at a mating end 36 of connector housing
30. The connector housing is secured to daughterboard 20 by
appropriate fasteners 38. A plurality of guides 40 project
forwardly of connector housing 30.</p>
    <p num="0017">Referring to Figure 5 in conjunction with Figures 1-4,
adapter 22 includes a housing 42 which may be fabricated of
molded plastic material. The housing defines a front mating
end 42a and a rear terminating end 42b. The front mating end
is open and through which the ferrules (described
hereinafter) of fiber optic connector modules 24 can project.
Terminating end 42b is open, as at 42c, for receiving
connector modules 24 in the direction of arrow "A". Housing
42 of adapter 22 has an outwardly projecting alignment rib 44
on each opposite side thereof and extending in the mating
direction of the connector assembly for riding in slots 46
(Fig. 1) of side guides 40 of daughterboard connector housing 
30. A pair of flexible, cantilevered latch arms 46 are
provided on opposite sides of housing 42 for interengagement
with complementary latch means (not visible in the drawings)
within daughterboard connector housing 30. A pair of
fasteners 48 extend through holes 50 in backplane 18 and into
a pair of fastener nuts 52 on housing 42 to secure adapter 22
to the backplane, with mating end 42b extending into aperture
16 in the backplane as seen in Figures 1 and 3.</p>
    <p num="0018">After backplane connector assembly 12 is secured to
backplane 18 and daughterboard connector assembly 14 is
secured to daughterboard 20, the backplane connector assembly
and the daughterboard connector assembly are mateable in the
direction of arrows "B" in Figures 1 and 2 wherein the fibers
of cables 26 and 32 are functionally connected in the mated
condition of the connectors shown in Figures 3 and 4.
Typically, fiber optic connector modules 24 are inserted into
adapter 22 and fiber optic connector modules 28 are inserted
into daughterboard connector housing 30 before the connector
assemblies are mated.</p>
    <p num="0019">Figures 6-9 show the details and assembly of one of the
fiber optic connector modules 24 of backplane connector
assembly 12. As stated above, each module terminates a multi-fiber
optic cable 26. The cable includes a multi-fiber ribbon
54 (Fig. 6) surrounded by strength members (not shown) and an
outer jacket 56. Fiber ribbon 54 includes a plurality of
individual inner optical fibers surrounded by a flat
dielectric. Outer jackets 56 is stripped to expose the fiber
ribbon and to leave jacket ends 56a. A ferrule 58 terminates
the ends of the individual optical fibers, and the ferrule
has a peripheral stop shoulder 60 which faces a forward
mating end 58a of the ferrule.</p>
    <p num="0020">Fiber optic connector module 24 further includes a
fixing body, generally designated 62, along with a crimp ring
64, a strain relief boot 66 and a housing, generally
designated 68. Figures 6-9 show the sequence of assembling 
these components of connector module 24. Before proceeding
with the assembly sequence, further details of the components
first will be described.</p>
    <p num="0021">Specifically, fixing body 62 includes a front end 70 in
front of an outwardly projecting rectangular flange 72. An
oblong crimp section 74 projects rearwardly of flange 72. A
pair of chamfered or ramped latch bosses 76 are formed on
opposite sides of front end 70, it being understood that the
opposite side of fixing body 62 is substantially identical to
the side of the fixing body visible in the drawings. A pair
of chamfered or ramped latch bosses 78 are provided at the
top and bottom of crimp section 74. The entire fixing body is
a one-piece structure which may be molded of plastic material
or die cast of zinc alloys.</p>
    <p num="0022">Crimp ring 64 of connector module 24 is oblong in shape
and is sized to fit over crimp section 74 of fixing body 62,
with jacket ends 56a positioned between the crimp section and
the crimp ring. The ring is fabricated of deformable
material, such as metal, for clamping the jackets ends to the
crimp section as seen hereinafter.</p>
    <p num="0023">Strain relief boot 66 of connector module 24 is
fabricated of elastomeric material and includes a front open
end 80 sized to fit over crimp ring 64 and crimp section 74
of fixing body 62. The boot has a rear open end 82 sized for
embracing fiber optic cable 26 which extends entirely through
the boot and out of the rear end thereof. A pair of latch
apertures 84 are formed in the top and bottom of the boot
near the front end thereof for snap-latch engagement with
chamfered latch bosses 78 of fixing body 62, as will be seen
hereinafter.</p>
    <p num="0024">Housing 68 of connector module 24 includes a front
portion 86 within which ferrule 58 is mounted and a rear
portion 88 within which fixing body 62 is mounted. The front
portion has an open front end 86a through which mating end
58a of the ferrule is exposed along with the exposed ends of 
the optical fibers. The rear portion has an open rear end 88a
through which boot 66 and fiber optic cable 26 extend. The
housing is a one-piece structure which may be molded of
plastic material. A pair of stop hooks 90 are molded
integrally with the front portion of the housing and are
directed inwardly for engaging stop shoulder 60 of ferrule
58. A pair of latch apertures 92 are formed in opposite sides
of the housing in rear portion 82 for engaging latch bosses
76 on opposite sides of fixing body 62. The opposite side of
the housing is substantially identical to the side visible in
the drawings. An upwardly stepped latch arm 94 is formed at
the top of the housing and includes a ramped latch boss 96
spaced from a shoulder 98. Shoulder 98 is positioned close to
the front mating end 42b (Fig. 5) of adapter housing 42 with
sufficient clearance to allow latch bosses 96 to interengage
within latch apertures 100 (Fig. 5) of the adapter housing.
Finally, serrations 102 are formed on the outside of latch
arm 94, and serrations 104 are formed on the outside of the
opposite side of the housing for grasping the entire
connector module between an operator's fingers.</p>
    <p num="0025">The assembly of fiber optic connector module 24 in
conjunction with Figures 6-9 now will be described. Referring
first to Figure 6, strain relief boot 66 and crimp ring 64
first are threaded onto fiber optic cable 26 as shown. Either
before or after assembly of the boot and crimp ring, outer
jacket 56 of the cable is stripped back to leave exposed
fiber ribbon 54 and jackets ends 56a, as shown. Fixing body
62 then is threaded onto fiber ribbon 54. Ferrule 58 then is
terminated to the individual fibers of fiber ribbon 54 by
known processes.</p>
    <p num="0026">Either before or after ferrule 58 is terminated to the
fibers, crimp ring 64 is positioned over crimp section 74 of
fixing body 62, sandwiching strength members and jacket ends
56a between the crimp section and the crimp ring as shown in
Figure 7. The deformable crimp ring then is crimped to clamp 
the jacket ends to the fixing body.</p>
    <p num="0027">The subassembly of Figure 7 then is inserted into
housing 68 in the direction of arrow "C" to the assembled
position of Figure 8. When fully inserted, stop hooks 90 at
the front of housing 68 abut against stop shoulder 60 of
ferrule 58, and flange 72 of fixing body 62 abuts against the
rear of the housing. When in this fully inserted position,
ramped latch bosses 76 at opposite sides of the fixing body
are snapped into latch apertures 92 at opposite sides of the
housing.</p>
    <p num="0028">The final step is to move strain relief boot 66
forwardly in the direction of arrow "D" (Fig. 8) until latch
apertures 84 snap into engagement with ramped latch bosses 78
on fixing body 62 as seen in Figure 9. Of course, it should
be understood that boot 66 could be attached to the fixing
body before inserting the fixing body and ferrule 58 into
open rear end 88a of housing 68.</p>
    <p num="0029">Four fiber optic connector modules 24 are inserted in
the direction of arrow "E" (Fig. 1) into adapter 22, after
the four modules are assembled as described above. Backplane
connector assembly 12 then can be mated with daughterboard
connector assembly 14 in the direction of arrows "B" (Figs. 1
and 2). During mating, alignment pins 106 (Fig. 1) from the
ferrules of the daughterboard connector assembly enter
alignment holes 108 (Fig. 9) in mating ends 58a of ferrules
58 of the backplane connector assembly. Figure 9 also shows a
plurality or line of optical fiber ends 110 which have been
terminated in the ferrule from fiber ribbon 54 of fiber optic
cable 26.</p>
    <p num="0030">It will be understood that the invention may be embodied
in other specific forms without departing from the spirit or
central characteristics thereof. The present examples and
embodiments, therefore, are to be considered in all respects
as illustrative and not restrictive, and the invention is not
to be limited to the details given herein.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A fiber optic connector module (24) for terminating
a fiber optic cable (26) which includes at least one
inner optical fiber (54,110) surrounded by an outer
jacket (56), comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a ferrule (58) terminated to an end of the optical
fiber stripped of said jacket;</claim-text><claim-text>a fixing body (62) fixed to the jacket rearwardly
of the ferrule; and</claim-text><claim-text>a housing (68) including a front portion (86)
within which the ferrule (58) is mounted and a rear
portion (88) within which the fixing body (62) is
mounted, the front portion having an open front end
(86a) through which a mating end (58a) of the ferrule is
exposed, and the rear portion having an open rear end
(88a) from which the fiber optic cable (26) extends.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The fiber optic connector of claim 1 wherein the
front portion (86) of said housing (68) includes stop
means (90) engageable by the ferrule (58), wherein the
ferrule and terminated fiber optic cable can be inserted
into the open rear end (88a) of the housing and into
abutment with the stop means (90).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The fiber optic connector of claim 1, including
complementary interengaging latch means (76,92) between
the fixing body (62) and the rear portion (88) of the
housing (68) to hold the fixing body and terminated
fiber optic cable within the housing.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The fiber optic connector of claim 3 wherein said
latch means comprise complementary interengaging snap-latch
members (76,92) on the fixing body (62) and the
housing (68) engageable automatically in response to
inserting the fixing body into the housing through said
open rear end (88a) thereof.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The fiber optic connector of claim 1 wherein said
fixing body (62) includes a crimp section (74) through
which the at least one optical fiber extends with the
outer jacket (56a) positioned on the outside of the
crimp section, and including a crimp ring (64) for
clamping the jacket to the crimp section.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The fiber optic connector of claim 1, including a
flexible strain relief boot (66) surrounding the fiber
optic cable (26) and extending away from the rear
portion (88) of the housing (68).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>The fiber optic connector of claim 6, including
complementary interengaging latch means (78,84) between
said boot (66) and the fixing body (62).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The fiber optic connector of claim 7 wherein said
latch means comprise complementary interengaging snap-latch
members (78,84) on the boot (66) and the fixing
body (62) engageable automatically in response to
mounting the boot on the fixing body.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>The fiber optic connector of claim 1 wherein said
housing (68) includes a flexible latch arm (94) for
holding the connector within an opening in a panel.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>The fiber optic connector of claim 9 wherein said
latch arm (94) includes a latch hook (96) on the outside
thereof, and including serrations (102) on the outside
of the latch arm engageable by an operator's fingers.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>A fiber optic connector module (24) for terminating
a fiber optic cable (26) which includes at least one
inner optical fiber (54,110) surrounded by an outer
jacket (56), comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a ferrule (58) terminated to an end of the optical
fiber stripped of said jacket, the ferrule including
forwardly facing stop means (60);</claim-text><claim-text>a fixing body (62) fixed to the jacket rearwardly
of the ferrule;</claim-text><claim-text>a housing (68) including a front portion (86)
within which the ferrule (58) is mounted and a rear
portion (88) within which the fixing body (62) is
mounted, the front portion having an open front end
(86a) through which a mating end (58a) of the ferrule is
exposed, and the rear portion having an open rear end
(88a) from which the fiber optic cable (26) extends, the
housing including stop means (90) engageable with the
stop means (60) of the ferrule; and</claim-text><claim-text>complementary interengaging snap-latch means
(76,92) between the fixing body (62) and the rear
portion (88) of the housing (68),</claim-text><claim-text>whereby the interengaging snap-latch means (76,92)
automatically engage in response to inserting the fixing
body (62) into the housing (68) through said open rear
end (88a) thereof as the stop means (60) on the ferrule
(58) engages the stop means (90) on the housing when the
ferrule and terminated fiber optic cable are inserted
into the housing.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>The fiber optic connector of claim 11 wherein said
fixing body (62) includes a crimp section (74) through
which the at least one optical fiber extends with the
outer jacket (56a) positioned on the outside of the
crimp section, and including a crimp ring (64) for
clamping the jacket to the crimp section.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>The fiber optic connector of claim 11, including a
flexible strain relief boot (66) surrounding the fiber
optic cable (26) and extending away from the rear
portion (88) of the housing (68).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>The fiber optic connector of claim 13, including
complementary interengaging second latch means (78,84)
between said boot (66) and the fixing body (62).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>The fiber optic connector of claim 14 wherein said
second latch means comprise complementary interengaging
snap-latch members (78,84) on the boot (66) and the
fixing body (62) engageable automatically in response to
mounting the boot on the fixing body.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>The fiber optic connector of claim 11 wherein said
housing (68) includes a flexible latch arm (94) for
holding the connector within an opening in a panel.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>The fiber optic connector of claim 16 wherein said
latch arm (94) includes a latch hook (96) on the outside
thereof, and including serrations (102) on the outside
of the latch arm engageable by an operator's fingers.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="18">
      <claim-text>A fiber optic connector module (24) for terminating
a fiber optic cable (26) which includes at least one
inner optical fiber (54,110) surrounded by an outer
jacket (56), comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a fixing body (62) fixed to the jacket of the fiber
optic cable;</claim-text><claim-text>a housing (68) including a rear portion (88) within
which the fixing body is mounted, the rear portion
having an open rear end (88a) from which the fiber optic
cable extends;</claim-text><claim-text>complementary interengaging first latch means
(76,92) between the fixing body (62) and the rear
portion of the housing to hold the fixing body within
the housing;</claim-text><claim-text>a flexible strain relief boot (66) surrounding the
fiber optic cable (26) and extending away from the rear
portion of the housing; and</claim-text><claim-text>complementary interengaging second latch means
(78,84) between said boot (66) and the fixing body (62).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="19">
      <claim-text>The fiber optic connector of claim 18 wherein said
first latch means comprise complementary interengaging
snap-latch members (76,92) on the fixing body (62) and
the housing (68) engageable automatically in response to
inserting the fixing body into the housing through said
open rear end (88a) thereof.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="20">
      <claim-text>The fiber optic connector of claim 18 wherein said
second latch means comprise complementary interengaging
snap-latch members (78,84) on the boot (66) and the
fixing body (62) engageable automatically in response to
mounting the boot on the fixing body.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="21">
      <claim-text>The fiber optic connector claim 20 wherein said
first latch means comprise complementary interengaging
snap-latch members (76,92) on the fixing body (62) and
the housing (68) engageable automatically in response to
inserting the fixing body into the housing through said
open rear end (88a) thereof.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="22">
      <claim-text>The fiber optic connector of claim 18 wherein said
fixing body (62) includes a crimp section (74) through
which the at least one optical fiber extends with the
outer jacket (56a) positioned on the outside of the
crimp section, and including a crimp ring (64) for
clamping the jacket to the crimp section.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
