<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1255101-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1255101" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="18978493" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021106">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1255101-A2" status="new" fvid="23583808">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1255101</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021106</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02009240-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02009240</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020425</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001130053-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001130053</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010426</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B60R  16/02        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B60R  16/02        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B60S   5/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B60S   5/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G01M  15/00        20060101AFI20020814BHEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G01M  15/00        20060101CFI20020814BHEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G01M  17/007       20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G01M  17/007       20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G05B  15/02        20060101ALI20070425BHEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G05B  15/02        20060101CLI20070425BHEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G05B  23/02        20060101ALI20070425BHEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G05B  23/02        20060101CLI20070425BHEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G07C   5/00        20060101ALI20070425BHEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G07C   5/00        20060101CLI20070425BHEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G07C   5/08        20060101ALI20070425BHEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G05B  15/02</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G05B  23/02</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G07C   5/00T</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G07C   5/08R2</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Kraftfahrzeug-Führungssystem</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Vehicle management system</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Système de gestion de véhicule</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>FUJI HEAVY IND LTD</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>FUJI JUKOGYO KABUSHIKI KAISHA</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>FUJI JUKOGYO KABUSHIKI KAISHA</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>7-2, Nishi-Shinjuku 1-chome Shinjuku-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo-to</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YAMAKI MASAHITO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YAMAKI, MASAHITO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>YAMAKI, MASAHITO</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Fuji Jukogyo K.K., 1-7-2, Nishishinjuku</street>
              <city>Shinjuku-ku, Tokyo</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>VOSSIUS &amp;amp; PARTNER</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Siebertstrasse 4</street>
              <city>81675 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
        <ep-extended-states>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>AL</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>AT</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>BE</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>CH</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>CY</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>DE</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>DK</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>ES</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>FI</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>FR</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>GB</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>GR</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>IE</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>IT</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>LI</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>LT</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>LU</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>LV</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>MC</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>MK</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>NL</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>PT</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>RO</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>SE</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>SI</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
          <ep-extended-state-data>
            <country>TR</country>
          </ep-extended-state-data>
        </ep-extended-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>In a vehicle management system of the present invention,
when vehicle information is received, details of the
received information are recognized to check whether a
diagnosis result indicating the presence of trouble is
contained. If the presence of trouble is indicated, various
kinds of data are acquired to estimate a trouble location
and decide service procedures. If the presence of trouble
is not indicated, all kinds of information including vehicle
travel information are acquired and classified to estimate
the deteriorated condition and remaining life of each part
and to analyze the vehicle travel condition, thereby
confirming the correlation between the vehicle travel
condition and the cause of a vehicle malfunction based on
the analyzed result. Various kinds of information are
notified to service factories and relevant departments and
are recorded in a database, while each user is notified of
the service timing and the analyzed result. Individual
users are therefore able to understand vehicle travel
conditions and pursue the cause of a malfunction or trouble
in each user vehicle with ease.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="141" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="97"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a vehicle management
system capable of managing health conditions of individual
user vehicles. More particularly, the present invention
relates to a vehicle management system for confirming a
travel condition of each user vehicle and pursuing the cause
of a malfunction and trouble in the vehicle with ease.</p>
    <p num="0002">A control system of a vehicle, such as an automobile,
is constructed as a complicated electronic control system,
and when there occurs an abnormal state, high levels of
expertise in knowledge and judgment are required to pursue
the cause of the abnormality. Therefore, it has been
recently proposed to provide the self-diagnosing function
for trouble diagnosis in an on-board electronic control unit.
When any abnormal state is detected by on-board diagnosis
based on the self-diagnosing function, an alarm lamp or the
like is lit up to issue an alarm to a driver, thereby
prompting the driver to take check and repair of the vehicle
in, e.g., a dealer's service factory. In the service
factory, an external device, e.g., a trouble diagnosing
device, is connected to the on-board electronic control unit 
for reading internal data, such as trouble location data and
trouble data, from the on-board electronic control unit.
Check and repair are then performed based on the read data.</p>
    <p num="0003">One example of such a trouble diagnosing device is
disclosed in</p>
    <p num="0004">JP-B- 7-15427 filed by the assignee of this
application. The disclosed trouble diagnosing device is
able to read data in an on-board electronic control unit,
i.e., detection signals of various sensors and switches,
control signals outputted to various actuators such as
injectors, within-system computation data, etc. which are
stored in the on-board electronic control unit, by utilizing
a body of the trouble diagnosing device or connecting a
computer for an external expert system to the body of the
trouble diagnosing device. As a result, it is possible to
pursue the trouble location or the cause of trouble and to
perform necessary repair or adjustment.</p>
    <p num="0005">However, malfunctions or troubles of vehicles sometimes
occur depending on a travel condition of each vehicle. For
example, when a vehicle is repeatedly subjected to a travel
condition in which the vehicle runs just a short distance in
most cases such that it starts running immediately after
starting of an engine and the engine operation is stopped
before reaching sufficient warm-up of the engine, there may
occur carbon fouling of spark plugs, oil dilution, etc., 
thus resulting in an engine malfunction. Such a trouble
caused depending on the vehicle travel condition is detected
with the self-diagnosing function only after the trouble has
occurred in fact. Even in the occurrence of an actual
trouble, pursuit of the trouble location is just possible to
achieve and a difficulty arises in pursuit of the true cause
leading to the trouble.</p>
    <p num="0006">Accordingly, it is an object of the present invention
to provide a vehicle management system capable of confirming
travel conditions of individual user vehicles and pursuing
the cause of a malfunction and trouble in each vehicle with
ease.</p>
    <p num="0007">The present invention is featured in statistically
processing travel information of individual vehicles in
respective on-board control units and transmitting the
processed information to an external database, and analyzing
travel conditions of the individual vehicles based on data
accumulated in the database, and distributing an analyzed
result to at least one of a relevant user of each vehicle
and a department having an access right to the database.</p>
    <p num="0008">With those features, travel information of individual
vehicles is statistically processed in respective on-board
control units and transmitted to an external database, and 
travel conditions of the individual vehicles are analyzed
based on data accumulated in the database. Then, an
analyzed result is distributed to at least one of a relevant
user of each vehicle and a department having an access right
to the database. Therefore, when there occurs a malfunction
or trouble in any vehicle, the cause of the malfunction or
trouble can be pursued with ease, and an advice on the
optimum driving method can be given to the user. Also,
feeding the analyzed result back to the relevant department
contributes to developing optimum control specifications and
improving system reliability.</p>
    <p num="0009">The above and other objects, features and advantages of
the invention will become more clearly understood from the
following description referring to the accompanying drawings.
<sl><li>Fig. 1 is a block diagram of an overall configuration
of a vehicle management system;</li><li>Fig. 2 is a diagram for explaining a vehicle network
system;</li><li>Fig. 3 is an overall schematic view of an engine
system;</li><li>Fig. 4 is a circuit diagram of an engine electronic
control system;</li><li>Fig. 5 is a flowchart showing an information processing 
routine on the vehicle side; and</li><li>Fig. 6 is a flowchart showing an information processing
routine on the side of central information management center.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0010">Fig. 1 shows a vehicle management system for
accumulating and managing initial values of vehicle control
information in the factory production line, managing vehicle
health conditions of individual vehicles after being
marketed and purchased by users in real time for 24 hours,
and providing each user with the latest information (health
condition) of his or her vehicle.</p>
    <p num="0011">In the vehicle management system, each vehicle 100
marketed and purchased by a user includes a wireless (radio)
communication terminal 110 as a data communication means
that is able to wirelessly communicate data, such as control
data for an on-board electronic control unit and data
regarding travel of the vehicle (i.e., vehicle information),
the latter being sampled with user's approval, to the
exterior in real time. The vehicle information transmitted
via the wireless communication terminal 110 is accumulated
and managed as a database DB in a host computer 151a that is
installed in a central information management center 151.</p>
    <p num="0012">A mobile wireless communication system via a base
station (not shown) or a satellite communication system via 
an artificial satellite (not shown), for example, can be
utilized for data communication between the vehicle 100 and
the central information management center 151. Also, the
wireless communication terminal 110 for transmitting the
vehicle information of the vehicle 100 may be constituted as
a communication terminal connected to the control unit of
the vehicle 100 through a harness. However, the wireless
communication terminal 110 is preferably constituted using a
small-sized communication terminal that is separated in the
portable form from the vehicle 100 and is employed to
perform wireless communication between itself and the on-board
control unit. This embodiment employs, as such a
portable communication terminal, a dedicated portable
telephone (cellular phone) with a built-in communication
circuit for wireless communication between the phone and the
on-board control unit. Hence, the wireless communication
terminal 110 will be described as the cellular phone 110
hereinafter. Note that, when the user has a cellular phone,
the communication terminal may be one connectable to the
user's cellular phone for data communication.</p>
    <p num="0013">In this embodiment, therefore, when a single control
unit is installed in the vehicle 100, a communication
circuit for controlling wireless communication is
incorporated in that control unit. Also, when a plurality
of control units are installed in the vehicle 100, for 
example, when a plurality of control units #n (n = 01, 02,
03, 04, 05, ...) are installed as shown in Fig. 2, the control
units #01, #02, #03, #04, #05, ... are preferably
interconnected via a network 101 so that individual pieces
of control information are unified. Then, a communication
circuit #01a for controlling wireless communication is
incorporated in a predetermined one, e.g., the control unit
#01, of the plurality of control units connected to the
network 101. Additionally, the network 101 is a vehicular
network adapted for real time control. Also, wireless
communication between the communication circuit and the on-board
control unit can be realized using, e.g., a
communication system in conformity with Bluetooth standards
for implementing short-distance wireless communication and
any other suitable standards.</p>
    <p num="0014">The communication circuit #01a provided in the control
unit of the vehicle 100 makes it possible to perform not
only wireless communication between itself and the user's
dedicated cellular phone 110, but also wireless
communication between itself and an inspection tool provided
in the factory production line at a line end thereof or a
service tool provided in, e.g., a dealer's service factory.
Further, each of the control units #01, #02, #03, #04, #05,
... installed in the vehicle 100 includes firmware capable of
rewriting control programs and various constant terms (such 
as various learned values and control constants) which are
held in the control unit even in the power-off state, in
response to commands from the inspection tool provided at
the line end or another external device.</p>
    <p num="0015">On the other hand, as shown in Fig. 1, the central
information management center 151 is connected, via a
dedicated network 150, to a plurality of departments, such
as a development headquarter 152, a software development and
environment headquarter 153, a sales and service headquarter
154, and an inspection and quality guarantee headquarter 155,
as well as to an inspection tool 156b for inspecting the
vehicle 100 on a chassis dynamometer 156a installed in the
factory production line at a line end 156 thereof. The
inspection tool 156b includes a communication adapter for
wireless communication with the communication circuit #01a
provided in the control unit of the vehicle 100. Also,
networks 160, 170, ... dedicated for, e.g., dealers in various
districts are connected to the dedicated network 150.
Further, service tools 161, 171, ..., sales tools 162, 172, ...,
and so on are connected to the corresponding networks 160,
170, ..., respectively. Thus, the data management system is
formed which enables actual diagnosis and repair of the
vehicle 100 to be performed based on the management
information collected in the central information management
center 151. In addition, the dedicated networks 150, 160, 
170, ... are connected to the Internet 180, as a network open
to the general public, so that information can be provided
via a personal computer PC of each user in addition to the
cellular phone 110.</p>
    <p num="0016">In the data management system having the configuration
described above, initial values of control information (i.e.,
initial information) of each vehicle are collected using the
inspection tool 156b at the line end 156 of the factory
production line. The vehicle is then put into the market
after analyzing accumulated initial information of the
vehicle to obtain optimum learned values, optimum control
constants, etc., and setting the obtained data in the
control unit of the vehicle. After the vehicle has been put
into the market, vehicle information obtained through user
access is also accumulated in addition to the initial
information. When the user vehicle 100 is in an operating
state, each user is able to transmit the vehicle information
to the central information management center 151 in a
wireless manner at any time regardless of whether the
vehicle is stopped or running.</p>
    <p num="0017">More specifically, when each user wants to know the
condition of his or her vehicle 100, the user can receive
information regarding the vehicle health condition, such as
the condition of maintenance and the presence or absence of
any trouble in the vehicle, by transmitting the vehicle 
information to the central information management center 151
using the cellular phone 110 dedicated for the vehicle 100.
In particular, since data can be transmitted from the
running vehicle in real time via wireless communication, it
is possible to promptly pursue the cause and take an action
even against, e.g., an abnormality appearing only in the
running state and a malfunction of the vehicle appearing
with very small reproducibility, which have been difficult
to realize the prompt pursuit of the cause in the past.</p>
    <p num="0018">For transmitting the vehicle information of the user
vehicle 100 to the central information management center 151,
the user is only required to employ the cellular phone 110
dedicated for the vehicle 100 and to depress buttons of the
cellular phone 110 to enter a preset particular number. The
entry of the preset particular number automatically brings
wireless communication between the control unit #01 of the
vehicle 100 and the central information management center
151 into a standby state, and then sets a call to the
central information management center 151. Then, upon
establishment of connection between the cellular phone 110
and the central information management center 151, data from
the individual control units collected via the network 101
in the vehicle 100 is transmitted from the communication
circuit #01a of the control unit #01 to the cellular phone
110 after being added with the vehicle body number, and is 
further transmitted to the central information management
center 151 through the cellular phone 110 after being added
with the user identification code, etc.</p>
    <p num="0019">The initial information of each vehicle and the
information of the vehicle after being marketed (i.e., the
vehicle information for each user), both accumulated in the
database DB of the central information management center 151,
are distributed via the network 150 to each of the related
departments, which are given with an access right to the
database DB, so that the vehicle health condition is managed
and various services are provided. Specifically, various
management processes, such as collection of frequency-of-usage
information of respective parts in the user vehicle,
evaluation of control algorithms, real-time diagnosis and
action to a trouble, predictive diagnosis based on
confirmation of time-dependent changes in the parts and
changes in the learned values, diagnosis of a trouble that
is difficult to reproduce, and analysis of the travel
condition of the user vehicle, are performed in the relevant
departments, whereas improvements of the control algorithms,
collection of information for novel development, etc. are
performed in the other relevant departments.</p>
    <p num="0020">Further, as a part of user services, the relevant
department performs pre-diagnosis of the user vehicle 100
before it is sent to a service factory, notifies each user 
of the time limit in sending the vehicle to the service
factory for, e.g., routine inspection, and distributes the
information to the dealer or the like for instruction of
check or diagnosis using the service tool 161 (171).
Moreover, the relevant department advises the optimum
driving based on the analyzed result of the travel condition
of the user vehicle, and provides service of rewriting a
control program of the control unit #n into specifications
in match with the usage condition of the vehicle specific to
each user, thereby presenting running environments desired
for the user. In addition, the relevant department performs
absolute quality evaluation at a part level of the vehicle
after being marketed, real-time collection of live statistic
data, relative quality evaluation for each parts maker, etc.,
and feeds the evaluation results back to the corresponding
departments.</p>
    <p num="0021">The information, such as the data analysis results and
the diagnosis results obtained for each user vehicle, is
accumulated in the central information management center 151
in a time-serial manner as history information for each user.
The accumulated information is provided to individual users
via the home page on the Internet 180 or via the cellular
phone 110 directly. Stated otherwise, each user can read
the information of the user vehicle by making access to the
corresponding home page via the Internet 180 from the 
personal computer PC or making direct access to the central
information management center 151 from the cellular phone
110, and then inputting his or her identification number,
name, password, etc. that are registered in advance. As an
alternative, the formally registered user may access a host
computer 151a of the central information management center
151 via the personal computer PC. In that case, however,
access to the host computer 151a from the users is
restricted in consideration of security such that the user
is allowed to access general information such as the
diagnosis results of the user vehicle.</p>
    <p num="0022">Management of vehicle travel information according to
the present invention will be described below in connection
with the management of the vehicle 100 by using the above-described
vehicle management system. The following
description is made of first an engine system installed in
the vehicle 100, and then an electronic control system for
controlling the engine system, information processing in an
engine control unit, and information processing in the
central information management center 151 successively.</p>
    <p num="0023">In the construction of the engine system of the vehicle
100, as shown in Fig. 3, an engine 1 mounted in the vehicle
100 is constituted as a horizontal opposed 4-cylinder engine
in this embodiment, in which a cylinder block 1a is divided
into two banks (left bank and right bank appearing 
respectively on the right side and the left side as viewed
in Fig. 3) on both sides of a crankshaft 1b at the center.
Cylinder heads 2 are provided on the left and right banks of
the cylinder block 1a of the engine 1, and an intake port 2a
and an exhaust port 2b are formed in each of the cylinder
heads 2.</p>
    <p num="0024">An intake manifold 3 is communicated with the intake
port 2a, and a throttle chamber 5 is communicated with the
intake manifold 3 through an air chamber 4 to which intake
passages of respective cylinders are collectively connected.
An air cleaner 7 is disposed upstream of the throttle
chamber 5 with an intake pipe 6 extended between them, and
is communicated with an air intake chamber 8. Also, an
exhaust manifold 9 is communicated with the exhaust port 2b.
The exhaust manifold 9 from the respective banks are joined
together and a catalyst converter 11 is interposed in a
joined portion and then communicated with a muffler 12 via
an exhaust pipe 10.</p>
    <p num="0025">A throttle valve 5a in linkage with an accelerator
pedal is provided in the throttle chamber 5, and a bypass
passage 13 is branched from the intake pipe 6 and extended
in a bypassing relation to the throttle valve 5a. An Idle
Speed Control (ISC) valve 14 is interposed in the bypass
passage 13 for adjusting the amount of air flowing through
the bypass passage 13 and controlling the idle rotational 
speed in the idle mode. Further, a fuel injector 15 is
located in the intake manifold 3 at a position just upstream
of the intake port 2a for each cylinder, and an spark plug
16 is attached to the cylinder head 2 for each cylinder such
that a discharge electrode formed at a fore end of the spark
plug 16 is exposed to a combustion chamber 1c. An igniter
18 is connected to an ignition coil 17 associated with the
spark plug 16.</p>
    <p num="0026">The fuel injector 15 is communicated with a fuel tank
20 through a fuel supply passage 19, and an in-tank type
fuel pump 21 is provided in the fuel tank 20. The fuel pump
21 supplies fuel under pressure to the injectors 15 and a
pressure regulator 23 through a fuel filter 22 interposed in
the fuel supply passage 19. The pressure regulator 23
regulates the pressure of fuel supplied to the injectors 15
to be held at a predetermined level.</p>
    <p num="0027">The pressure regulator 23 is constituted as a regulator
of the known structure that an inner space is divided by a
diaphragm provided with a pressure regulating valve into a
fuel chamber to which the fuel supplied under pressure from
the fuel pump 21 is introduced and a spring chamber in which
a spring for biasing the pressure regulating valve in the
closing direction is housed, and that the pressure in the
intake pipe is introduced to the spring chamber through a
passage communicating with the intake manifold 3. Surplus 
fuel is returned from the pressure regulating valve to the
fuel tank 20. In that way, the fuel pressure is regulated
to a constant preset level with respect to the pressure in
the intake pipe downstream of the throttle valve 5a, i.e.,
the pressure of an injection atmosphere of the fuel injector
15.</p>
    <p num="0028">At a top portion of the fuel tank 20, a fuel cut valve
24 is provided to prevent a fuel leakage if the vehicle
should be fallen down, and to prevent fuel from flowing into
an evaporating gas purge system that serves to purge a fuel
evaporating gas generated in the fuel tank 20. A first
purge passage 25 for introducing the evaporating gas purged
through the fuel cut valve 24 is extended from the fuel cut
valve 24 and then communicated with a top portion of a
canister 26 that has an adsorption region formed using
activated coal, for example. A fresh air introducing port
is formed in a bottom portion of the canister 26 for
communication with the atmosphere through an atmosphere
opening valve 27 constituted as a solenoid on/off valve. A
second purge passage 28 for introducing both fresh air from
the fresh air introducing port and the evaporating gas built
up in the adsorption region is extended from the top portion
of the canister 26 and then communicated with the intake
system (at a position just downstream of the throttle valve
5a in its fully closed state) through a canister purge 
control (CPC) valve 29 that serves to adjust the amount of
purged evaporating gas.</p>
    <p num="0029">Further, for recirculating exhaust gas from the exhaust
system to the intake system of the engine 1, an Exhaust-Gas
Recirculation (EGR) passage 30 is extended from the exhaust
manifold 9 on the side of one bank and then communicated
with the air chamber 4. An EGR valve 31 for adjusting an
EGR rate is interposed midway the EGR passage 30 so that a
part of the exhaust gas is recirculated to the intake system
depending on the position (opening degree) of the EGR valve
31.</p>
    <p num="0030">A description is now made of sensors for detecting the
engine operating condition. At a position in the intake
pipe 6 just downstream of the air cleaner 7, an intake-air
amount and intake-air temperature measuring unit 50 is
disposed which incorporates, as an integral unit, an air
flow sensor 50a for measuring the amount of intake air and
an intake air temperature sensor 50b for measuring the
temperature of intake air. Also, a throttle sensor 51
incorporating a throttle position sensor 51a and an idle
switch 51b, which is turned on upon the throttle valve 5a
coming into a fully closed state, is associated with the
throttle valve 5a disposed in the throttle chamber 5. An
intake manifold pressure sensor 52 for detecting the
pressure in the intake pipe at a position downstream of the 
throttle valve 5a is attached to the air chamber 4.</p>
    <p num="0031">Further, a knock sensor 53 is attached to the cylinder
block 1a of the engine 1, and an engine coolant temperature
sensor 54 is located in a joining passage 39 communicating
the left and right banks of the cylinder block 1a with each
other. An EGR gas temperature sensor 55 for detecting the
temperature of the EGR gas is located in the EGR passage 30.
A front Air/Fuel (A/F) sensor 56 is disposed upstream of the
catalyst converter 11, and a rear A/F sensor 57 is disposed
downstream of the catalyst converter 11.</p>
    <p num="0032">In addition, a crank angle sensor 59 is disposed to
face an outer periphery of a crank rotor 58 mounted on the
crankshaft 1b of the engine 1. A cam angle sensor 61 for
determining which cylinder is currently in the combustion
stroke, which cylinder is currently under fuel injection,
and which cylinder is currently under ignition, is disposed
to face a cam rotor 60 associated with a cam shaft 1d that
is rotated 1/2 with respect to the crankshaft 1b. On the
other hand, at the top portion of the fuel tank 20, a fuel
tank pressure sensor 62 is disposed for detecting the
pressure in the evaporating gas purge system. A fuel level
sensor 63 for detecting the fuel level and a fuel
temperature sensor 64 for detecting the fuel temperature are
provided integrally with the fuel pump 21 in the fuel tank
20. </p>
    <p num="0033">The above-described actuators and sensors provided in
the engine system are connected to an engine control unit
(ECU) 70 shown in Fig. 4. The ECU 70 corresponds to one,
e.g., #02, of the control units #01, #02, #03, #04, #05, ...
constituting the network 101 of the vehicle 100, and is
primarily constructed of a microcomputer. A CPU 71, a ROM
72, a RAM 73, a backup RAM 74, a network controller 75 for
the on-board network, a counter/timer group 76, and an I/O
(Input/Output) interface 77 are interconnected via an
internal bus 70a and also connected from the network
controller 75 to the other on-board control units via an
external bus 101a.</p>
    <p num="0034">The ROM 72 includes a mask ROM on which data is written
with a photo mask in the manufacturing stage, and an EEP
(Electrically Erasable Programmable) ROM on which data can
be electrically rewritten; e.g., a flash ROM on which data
can be erased at a time and rewritten with ease in an on-board
state. The mask ROM stores a program for
communication via the network controller 75, a program for
writing programs, constants, etc. in the EEPROM via
communication with an external device, and so on. The
EEPROM does not store any significant data in the initial
production stage. In the stage of assembling the ECU 70 in
the vehicle, engine control programs for fuel injection
control, ignition timing control, etc. and data depending on 
the model of the vehicle, such as control constants, are
written on the EEPROM through the inspection tool 156b
provided at the line end 156.</p>
    <p num="0035">The counter/timer group 76 collectively implies various
counters, such as a free run counter and a counter for
receiving and counting a cylinder determining sensor signal
(cylinder determining pulse), and various timers, such as a
fuel injection timer, an ignition timer, a periodic
interrupt timer for causing a periodic interrupt, a timer
for measuring an input interval of a crank angle sensor
signal (crank pulse), and a watchdog timer for monitoring a
system abnormality. In addition to the above examples,
various software counters and timers are also used.</p>
    <p num="0036">The ECU 70 incorporates peripheral circuits, such as a
constant-voltage circuit 78 for supplying stabilized power
to the associated sections, and a drive circuit 79 and an
A/D (Analog/Digital) converter 80 that are connected to the
I/O interface 77. The constant-voltage circuit 78 is
connected to a battery 82 through a first relay contact of a
power supply relay 81 having two-circuit relay contacts, and
is also directly connected to the battery 82. When an
ignition switch 83 is turned on and the contact of the power
supply relay 81 is closed, the power is supplied to the
associated sections in the ECU 70. On the other hand, the
backup power is supplied to the backup RAM 74 at all times 
regardless of whether the ignition switch 83 is turned on or
off. Further, the fuel pump 21 is connected to the battery
82 through a relay contact of a fuel pump relay 84. In
addition, a power supply line for supplying power to the
various actuators from the battery 82 is connected to a
second relay contact of the power supply relay 81.</p>
    <p num="0037">The ignition switch 83, the idle switch 51b, the knock
sensor 53, the crank angle sensor 59, the cam angle sensor
61, the speed sensor 65, etc. are connected to input ports
of the I/O interface 77. Further, the air flow sensor 50a,
the intake air temperature sensor 50b, the throttle position
sensor 51a, the intake manifold pressure sensor 52, the
engine coolant temperature sensor 54, the EGR gas
temperature sensor 55, the front A/F sensor 56, the rear A/F
sensor 57, the internal pressure sensor 62, the fuel level
sensor 63, the fuel temperature sensor 64, an atmospheric
pressure sensor 66 incorporated in the ECU 70, etc. are
connected to other input terminals of the I/O interface 77
through the A/D converter 80. A battery voltage VB is also
inputted to the I/O interface 77 for monitoring.</p>
    <p num="0038">On the other hand, respective relay coils of the power
supply relay 81 and the fuel pump relay 84, the ISC valve 14,
the fuel injector 15, the atmosphere opening valve 27, the
CPC valve 29, the EGR valve 31, a warning lamp 85 for
notifying the occurrence of any abnormality, etc. are 
connected to output ports of the I/O interface 77 through
the drive circuit 79. Further, the igniter 18 is connected
to another output port of the I/O interface 77.</p>
    <p num="0039">In the ECU 70, the CPU 71 executes the control program
stored in the ROM 72 to process detection signals from the
various sensors, the battery voltage VB, etc. inputted
through the I/O interface 77. The fuel injection volume,
the ignition timing, controlled variables of the actuators,
etc. are computed based on various data stored in the RAM 73,
various learned value data stored in the backup RAM 74,
fixed data stored in the ROM 72, etc., thereby performing
engine control such as Air/Fuel control (fuel injection
control), ignition timing control, idle rotational speed
control, evaporating gas purge control, EGR control, etc.</p>
    <p num="0040">Simultaneously, the ECU 70 monitors with the self-diagnosing
function whether there is no abnormality in the
engine system including the engine 1 and the peripheral
units. If any abnormality is detected, the warning lamp 85
is lit up or blinked, and trouble data is stored in the
backup RAM 74. Further, the ECU 70 samples and computes
various parameters indicating the vehicle travel condition
during a period from start to stop of the engine operation.
Then, the ECU 70 prepares frequency distributions of
respective data and stores them in the backup RAM 74. The
diagnosis information and the vehicle travel information 
stored in the backup RAM 74 are transmitted to the central
information management center 151 as a part of the vehicle
information of the vehicle 100 when the user transmits the
vehicle information using the cellular phone 110, and are
then accumulated in the database DB.</p>
    <p num="0041">Information processing executed in the ECU 70 will be
described below with reference to a flowchart of an
information processing routine shown in Fig. 5.</p>
    <p num="0042">In the information processing routine, the ECU 70 first
checks in step S50 whether the engine is stopped. If the
engine is under operation, the process flow goes to step S51
in which parameters indicating the operating condition, such
as the engine rotational speed, the cooling water
temperature, the vehicle speed, the throttle position
(accelerator position in a vehicle provided with an
electronic control throttle device), the intake air amount,
the battery voltage, the atmospheric pressure, the fuel
temperature and the fuel level, and parameters indicating
the control condition, such as the fuel injection volume,
the ignition timing, the evaporating gas purge amount and
the control level in ISC, are written and stored in the
backup RAM 74. Thereafter, the process flow goes to step
S52.</p>
    <p num="0043">In step S52, the ECU computes the time of engine
complete explosion, maximum and minimum values of the 
atmospheric pressure, the driving time, the mileage
(distance traveled), the mean specific fuel consumption,
etc., and then writes and stores data of those computed
values in the backup RAM 74 as the vehicle travel
information including the operating condition parameters and
the control condition parameters described above.
Subsequently, the process flow goes to step S53 in which if
any abnormality is detected by the self-diagnosis, the
resulting diagnosis information is written and stored in the
backup RAM 74.</p>
    <p num="0044">Then, the process flow goes from step S53 to S55 in
which it is checked whether there is a data transmission
request upon the user's manipulation on the cellular phone
110 for transmitting the vehicle information. If there is
no data transmission request, the ECU exits the routine. If
there is a data transmission request, the process flow goes
to step S56 in which the data in the backup RAM 74 is
transmitted via the vehicle network 101. Thereafter, the
ECU exits the routine. Note that the diagnosis information
in the backup RAM 74 except for trouble data is cleared to
secure a storage area for a next set of data after
transmission to the central information management center
151.</p>
    <p num="0045">Subsequently, when the engine is stopped, the process
flow goes from step S50 to S54 in which the ECU prepares 
frequency distributions of respective data of the travel
information recorded during the engine operation (or updates
the frequency distributions when they are already present),
and then writes and stores them in the backup RAM 74. Then,
the process flow goes from step S54 to S55 in which it is
checked whether there is a data transmission request. If
there is a data transmission request, the ECU transmits the
frequency distributions data in step S56 and exits the
routine.</p>
    <p num="0046">On the other hand, the central information management
center 151 executes information processing shown in Fig. 6
by the host computer 151a. In the information processing,
the host computer 151a first checks in step S100 whether the
vehicle information is received upon access from the user's
cellular phone 110. If no data is received, the host
computer exits the routine. If data is received, the
process flow goes to step S101 in which the data type of the
vehicle information and the corresponding system are
identified based on the vehicle body number, the user
identification code, the mileage (distance traveled), the
date and time of data receipt, etc. Then, the host computer
determines in step S102 whether a diagnosis determination
result indicating the presence of trouble is contained in
the vehicle information.</p>
    <p num="0047">If the vehicle information does not contain the 
determination result indicating the presence of trouble and
there is no noticeable abnormality, the process flow jumps
from step S102 to S106. If the vehicle information contains
the determination result indicating the presence of trouble,
the process flow goes from step S102 to S103 in which the
host computer acquires various data, such as the operating
condition parameters, the control condition parameters and
the diagnosis parameters corresponding to the occurrence of
trouble. Then, the process flow goes to step S104 in which
the acquired data is analyzed to estimate a trouble location,
i.e., which system or part has a trouble. After deciding
service procedures for repair and check in step S105, the
host computer proceeds to step S106.</p>
    <p num="0048">The host computer acquires all kinds of information
including the vehicle travel information in step S106, and
classifies the vehicle travel condition per district or
country in step S107. Then, it estimates the deteriorated
condition and remaining life of each part in step S108.
More specifically, time-dependent changes in the system or
the parts are confirmed based on changes in time-serially
accumulated data of the on-board control units, e.g.,
changes in learned value data, input/output data under
preset conditions, and computation data. The progress of
deterioration in the system or the parts is estimated by
comparing the vehicle initial information obtained by the 
line end inspection with the corresponding data transmitted
from the user. From the estimated progress of deterioration,
the remaining life of each part is estimated, and the part
requiring service and the timing at which the service is to
be made are computed.</p>
    <p num="0049">The process flow then goes to step S109 in which the
host computer analyzes the vehicle travel condition and
confirms the correlation between the travel condition and
the malfunction of the vehicle based on the analyzed result.
For example, in the travel condition where the driving time
and the distance traveled per driving-out on the road are in
the relatively short ranges at high frequency and the
cooling water temperature is the relatively low range at
high frequency, i.e., in the travel condition where the
vehicle runs just a short distance in most cases and repeats
the start and the stop before reaching sufficient warm-up of
the engine, it is possible to confirm the correlation
between that travel condition and a trouble, such as a
misfire due to carbon fouling of spark plug 16,
deterioration in fuel economy due to oil dilution, and a
malfunction due to carbon deposition on the EGR valve 31, or
the correlation between that travel condition and a trouble
that is expected to occur in near future.</p>
    <p num="0050">In subsequent step S110, the ECU sets control
specifications in match with the usage condition of the 
vehicle specific to each user based on the analyzed result
of the vehicle travel condition, and rewrites the current
control program and control constants depending on the
desire of the user. For example, for the user who drives
the vehicle in such a travel condition in most case that the
engine rotational speed and the opening degree of the
throttle are in the relatively high (large) ranges at low
frequency and the mean specific fuel consumption is in the
relatively small range at high frequency, i.e., that prime
importance is placed on fuel economy, the control
specifications can be modified to those ones in which the
engine output performance is slightly reduced and the fuel
economy is improved in comparison with the case employing
the standard specifications. For the user who drives the
vehicle in such a travel condition in most case that the
engine rotational speed, the intake air amount and the
opening degree of the throttle are in the relatively high
(large) ranges at high frequency, i.e., that prime
importance is placed on running performance, the control
specifications can be modified to those ones in which the
fuel consumption rate is slightly increased and the engine
output performance is improved in comparison with the case
employing the standard specifications. Further, for the
user who drives the vehicle just a short distance in most
case, the control specifications can be modified to those 
ones in which the smoldering resistance is intensified and
the engine start time is shortened.</p>
    <p num="0051">Subsequently, the process flow goes to step S111 in
which various items of information, such as the vehicle
information, notice information to the user, service
procedures, and service parts (parts to be prepared), are
notified to a dealer's service factory, for example, and the
tendency of deterioration in parts per vehicle, the
estimated results of part troubles, the time or mileage
until the occurrence of trouble, the effect upon exhaust gas
emissions, the vehicle travel condition, the modification
details of the control specifications, etc. are fed back to
the relevant departments. The process flow further goes to
step S112 in which if there is a trouble portion to be
repaired or checked or if there is a risk of the occurrence
of trouble, the user is notified of the service timing and
the correlation between the trouble and the vehicle travel
condition, and is given with an advise for the optimum
driving method as required. Then, in step S113, the above-mentioned
relevant information is recorded in the database
DB along with the history data for each vehicle based on the
vehicle body number and the user identification code. A
series of processing steps are thereby brought into an end.</p>
    <p num="0052">As a result, the correlation between a malfunction and
a travel condition of each vehicle can be confirmed, and an 
advance notice of the check timing can be given to the user
prior to the actual occurrence of trouble. It is therefore
possible not only to cut the cost and time required for
repair, but also to enable a service factory to prepare the
relevant parts in advance and to carry out the work schedule
based on the distributed diagnosis information. Further,
even when a trouble occurs due to the vehicle travel
condition, it is possible not only to merely repair a
trouble portion, but also to pursue the true cause of the
trouble and advise the more appropriate driving method to
the user.</p>
    <p num="0053">Moreover, by confirming the vehicle travel condition
per district or country and reflecting the confirmed
information on development of vehicles to be next marketed,
a vehicle having optimum specifications suitable for actual
environments of use. Additionally, running environments
desired for each user can be provided by modifying the
specification to those ones in match with the driving
conditions of individual users.</p>
    <p num="0054">Having described the preferred embodiments of the
invention referring to the accompanying drawings, it should
be understood that the present invention is not limited to
those precise embodiments and various changes and
modifications thereof could be made by one skilled in the
art without departing from the spirit or scope of the 
invention as defined in the appended claims.</p>
    <p num="0055">According to the present invention, as described above,
since vehicle travel conditions of individual users are
confirmed, the cause of a malfunction or trouble in each
vehicle can be pursued, and an advance notice of the check
timing can be given to the user prior to the occurrence of
trouble. By feeding the confirmed vehicle travel conditions
back to the relevant departments, optimum specifications in
match with actual individual environments of use can be
realized.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A vehicle management system capable of managing
vehicle travel conditions, characterized by comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>travel information of individual vehicles is
statistically processed in respective on-board control units
and transmitted to an external database; and</claim-text><claim-text>travel conditions of the individual vehicles are
analyzed based on data accumulated in said database, and an
analyzed result is distributed to at least one of a relevant
user of each vehicle and a department having an access right
to said database.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A vehicle management system according to Claim 1,
characterized in that the travel information is provided in
the form of frequency distributions of respective data
obtained during a period from start to stop of an engine and
processed in the control unit.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A vehicle management system according to Claim 1 or
2, characterized in that the control unit has changeable
control specifications and the control specifications of the
control unit are changed to those ones in match with a usage
condition of the vehicle specific to each user based on the
analyzed result of the travel condition.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A vehicle management system according to any one of
Claims 1 to 3, characterized in that each vehicle includes
data transmitting means for externally transmitting data of
the control unit mounted in the vehicle in real time via
wireless communication, and travel information transmitted
from said data transmitting means is received and
accumulated in said database.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
