<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1238892-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1238892" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="26610768" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020911">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1238892-A2" status="new" fvid="23537220">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1238892</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20020911</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02004200-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02004200</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020226</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001063338-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001063338</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010307</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001194870-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001194870</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010627</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B60R  21/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B60R  21/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B62D   6/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B62D   6/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B62D  15/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B62D  15/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B62D 111/00        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B62D 113/00        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G08G   1/14        20060101ALI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G08G   1/14        20060101CLI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B62D  15/02</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Parkhilfseinrichtung</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Parking assisting device</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Appareil d'assistance au parking</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TOYOTA JIDOSHOKKI KK</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KABUSHIKI KAISHA TOYOTA JIDOSHOKKI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Kabushiki Kaisha Toyota Jidoshokki</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>2-1, Toyoda-cho</street>
              <city>Kariya-shi, Aichi-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SHIMAZAKI KAZUNORI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YAMADA SATOSHI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SHIMAZAKI, KAZUNORI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YAMADA, SATOSHI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Shimazaki, Kazunori, c/o K.K. Toyota Jidoshokki</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>2-1, Toyoda-cho</street>
              <city>Kariya-shi, Aichi-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Yamada, Satoshi, c/o K.K. Toyota Jidoshokki</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>2-1, Toyoda-cho</street>
              <city>Kariya-shi, Aichi-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Leson, Thomas Johannes Alois</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Patentanwälte Tiedtke-Bühling-Kinne &amp;amp; Partner, Bavariaring 4</street>
              <city>80336 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A parking assisting device provides parking assisting information
consisting of a first intermittent sound of a tone (A) indicating that a vehicle is
approaching a target stop position, a continuous sound of a tone (B) indicating
that a position of a vehicle coincides with a target stop position and a second
intermittent sound of a tone (C) indicating that a vehicle has gone beyond a
target stop position. An intermittent period of the first intermittent sound
changes to be shorter as the vehicle approaches a target stop position closer
and an intermittent period of the second intermittent sound changes to be
longer as the vehicle goes beyond the target stop position farther.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="139" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="101"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <heading>1. Field of the Invention</heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a parking assisting device.</p>
    <heading>2. Description of the Related Art</heading>
    <p num="0002">Conventionally, a method of guiding a vehicle to a target parking
position according to each step shown in Figs. 14A, 14B and 14C has been
employed in a parking assisting device. That is, as step G1, the vehicle is
moved forward passing the side of a target parking position T and stopped in a
position P1 and is further moved forward with an appropriate turning track L1
to a position P2 where a turning angle is 1. Then, as step G2, the vehicle in
the position P2 is moved backward with an appropriate turning track L2 to a
position P3 where a turning angle is 2 and stopped. Lastly, as step G3, the
vehicle in the position P3 is moved backward with a turning track L3
corresponding to a maximum steering angle to the target parking position T
and the parking is completed. In this case, when the vehicle has reached the
position P2 from the position P1 or reached the position P3 from the position
P2, a driver is notified to that effect, respectively.</p>
    <p num="0003">However, conventionally, since the driver is notified that the vehicle has
reached the position P2 or the position P3 only when the position of the vehicle
coincides with the position P2 or the position P3, the driver is informed to that
effect abruptly in most cases. Therefore, in some cases, the driver may have
difficulty in stopping the vehicle in a desired position based only on the 
information.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0004">The present invention has been devised in view of the above and other
drawbacks in the prior art, and it is an object of the present invention to
provide a parking assisting device that is capable of easily stopping a vehicle in
a desired position.</p>
    <p num="0005">In order to attain the above-mentioned object, a parking assisting
device in accordance with a first aspect of the present invention comprises:
means for setting a reference of a turning position of a vehicle; means for
detecting a turning position of a vehicle based on the reference; and means for
notifying a driver of parking assisting information concerning a target guiding
position based on the detected turning position of a vehicle, wherein the
parking assisting information includes two kinds of information with forms
different from each other provided in any two states among three states
consisting of a state in which the vehicle has reached the target guiding
position and states in which the vehicle is in front of and behind the target
guiding position, the two kinds of information informing the driver of at least
two states among the three states.</p>
    <p num="0006">In the parking assisting device in accordance with a second aspect of
the present invention, the parking assisting information comprises first
information and second information provided in the states in which the
vehicle is in front of and behind the target guiding position, the first
information and the second information with forms different from each other 
informing the driver of three states consisting of the state in which the vehicle
has reached the target guiding position and the states of positions in which
the vehicle is in front of and behind the target guiding position in the parking
assisting device in accordance with the first aspect of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0007">In the parking assisting device in accordance with a third aspect of the
present invention, the parking assisting information includes third
information to be notified in the state in which the vehicle has reached the
target guiding position in the parking assisting device in accordance with the
second aspect of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0008">In the parking assisting device in accordance with a fourth aspect of the
present invention, the first information, second information and third
information indicate that the vehicle is approaching, has gone beyond and has
reached the target guiding position, respectively, in the parking assisting
device in accordance with the third aspect of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0009">In the parking assisting device in accordance with a fifth aspect of the
present invention, the first information, second information and third
information indicate that the vehicle is required to move forward, is required
to move backward and is required to stop, respectively, in the parking
assisting device in accordance with the third aspect of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0010">In the parking assisting device in accordance with a sixth aspect of the
present invention, the parking assisting information consists of sounds, and
the first information and second information have elements specifying sound
at least one of which is different between the first information and second
information and at least another one of which changes based on a vehicle 
position with respect to the target guiding position in the parking assisting
device in accordance with the second aspect of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0011">In the parking assisting device in accordance with a seventh aspect of
the present invention, the parking assisting information includes a brake
operation guiding sound provided in a first position before the vehicle reaches
the target guiding position in the parking assisting device in accordance with
the first aspect of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0012">In the parking assisting device in accordance with a eighth aspect of the
present invention, the first position is selected based on an angular speed of
the vehicle in a predetermined position before the vehicle reaches the first
position In the parking assisting device in accordance with the seventh aspect
of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0013">In the parking assisting device in accordance with a ninth aspect of the
present invention, the first position is selected based on an interrelation
between a turning position of the vehicle and an angular speed of the vehicle
in the turning position in the parking assisting device in accordance with the
seventh aspect of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0014">In the parking assisting device in accordance with a tenth aspect of the
present invention, the first position is selected by learning based on past data
in the parking assisting device in accordance with the seventh aspect of the
present invention.</p>
    <p num="0015">The parking assisting device in accordance with an eleventh aspect of
the present invention comprises: means for setting a reference of a turning
position of a vehicle; means for detecting a turning position of a vehicle based 
on the reference; and means for notifying a driver of parking assisting
information concerning a target guiding position based on the detected
turning position of a vehicle, wherein the parking assisting information
includes a brake operation guiding sound that is provided in a first position
before the vehicle reaches the target guiding position.</p>
    <p num="0016">In the parking assisting device in accordance with a twelfth aspect of
the present invention, the first position is selected based on an angular speed
of the vehicle in a predetermined position before the vehicle reaches the first
position in the parking assisting device in accordance with the eleventh aspect
of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0017">In the parking assisting device in accordance with a thirteenth aspect of
the present invention, the first position is selected based on an interrelation
between a turning position of the vehicle and an angular speed of the vehicle
in the turning position in the parking assisting device in accordance with the
eleventh aspect of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0018">In the parking assisting device in accordance with a fourteenth aspect
of the present invention, the first position is selected by learning based on past
data in the parking assisting device in accordance with the eleventh aspect of
the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0019">In the parking assisting device in accordance with fifteenth and
sixteenth aspects of the present invention, the parking assisting information
is of light instead of sound in the parking assisting device in accordance with a
thirteenth aspect of the present invention in the parking assisting device in
accordance with the sixth and eleventh aspects of the present invention. </p>
    <p num="0020">In the parking assisting device in accordance with seventeenth and
eighteenth aspects of the present invention, the parking assisting information
is of vibration instead of sound in the parking assisting device in accordance
with the sixth and eleventh aspects of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0021">With the parking assisting device in accordance with the first aspect of
the present invention, two kinds of information with forms different from each
other are provided as parking assisting information in any two states among
three states consisting of a state in which the vehicle has reached the target
guiding position and states in-which the vehicle is in front of and behind the
target guiding position. The driver recognizes that a current position of the
vehicle is in at least two states among the three states from this information.</p>
    <p num="0022">With the parking assisting device in accordance with the second aspect
of the present invention, the first information and the second information are
provided in the states in which the vehicle is in front of and behind the target
guiding position as the parking assisting information in the parking assisting
device in accordance with the first aspect of the present invention. The driver
recognizes from these pieces of information that a current state of the vehicle
is any one of the three states consisting of the state in which the vehicle has
reached the target guiding position and the states in which the vehicle is in
front of and behind the target guiding position.</p>
    <p num="0023">With the parking assisting device in accordance with the third aspect of
the present invention, the driver is notified of the state in which the vehicle
has reached the target guiding position by the third information in the parking
assisting device in accordance with the second aspect of the present invention. </p>
    <p num="0024">With the parking assisting device in accordance with the fourth aspect
of the present invention, the driver is informed that the vehicle is approaching,
has gone beyond and has reached the target guiding position by the first
information, the second information and the third information, respectively, in
the parking assisting device in accordance with the third aspect of the present
invention.</p>
    <p num="0025">With the parking assisting device in accordance with the fifth aspect of
the present invention, the driver is informed that the vehicle is required to
move forward, required to move backward and required to stop by the first
information, the second information and the third information, respectively, in
the parking assisting device in accordance with the third aspect of the present
invention.</p>
    <p num="0026">With the parking assisting device in accordance with the sixth aspect of
the present invention, the driver is informed of the first information and the
second information that have elements specifying sound, at least one of which
different between the first information and the second information and at least
another one of which changes based on a vehicle position with respect to the
target guiding position, in the vehicle assisting device in accordance with the
second aspect of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0027">With the parking assisting device in accordance with the seventh aspect
of the present invention, a brake operation guiding sound is provided in a first
position before the vehicle reaches the target guiding position in the parking
assisting device in accordance with the first aspect of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0028">With the parking assisting device in accordance with the eighth aspect 
of the present invention, the brake operation guiding sound is provided before
the vehicle reaches the target guiding position based on an angular speed of
the vehicle in a predetermined position before the vehicle reaches the first
position in the parking assisting device in accordance with the seventh aspect
of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0029">With the parking assisting device in accordance with the ninth aspect of
the present invention, the brake operation guiding sound is provided before
the vehicle reaches the target guiding position in accordance with an
interrelation between a turning position of the vehicle and an-angular speed of
the vehicle in that position in the parking assisting device in accordance with
the seventh aspect of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0030">With the parking assisting device in accordance with the tenth aspect of
the present invention, the brake operation guiding sound is provided before
the vehicle reaches the target guiding position by learning based on past data
in the parking assisting device in accordance with the seventh aspect of the
present invention.</p>
    <p num="0031">With the parking assisting device in accordance with the eleventh
aspect of the present invention, the brake operation guiding sound is provided
in the first position before the vehicle reaches the target guiding position as
parking assisting information.</p>
    <p num="0032">With the parking assisting device in accordance with the twelfth aspect
of the present invention, the brake operation guiding sound is provided before
the vehicle reaches the target guiding position based on an angular speed of
the vehicle in a predetermined position before reaching the first position in the 
parking assisting device in accordance with the eleventh aspect of the present
invention.</p>
    <p num="0033">With the parking assisting device in accordance with the thirteenth
aspect of the present invention, the brake operation guiding sound is provided
before the vehicle reaches the target guiding position in accordance with an
interrelation between a turning position of the vehicle and an angular speed of
the vehicle in that position in the parking assisting device in accordance with
the eleventh aspect of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0034">With the parking assisting device in accordance with the fourteenth
aspect of the present invention, the brake operation guiding sound is provided
before the vehicle reaches the target guiding position by learning based on
past data in the vehicle assisting device in accordance with the eleventh
aspect of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0035">With the parking assisting device in accordance with the fifteenth and
the sixteenth aspects of the present invention, parking assisting information
consisting of light instead of sound is provided in the parking assisting device
in accordance with the sixth and the eleventh aspect of the present invention,
respectively.</p>
    <p num="0036">With the parking assisting device in accordance with the seventeenth
and the eighteenth aspects of the present invention, parking assisting
information consisting of vibration instead of sound is provided in the parking
assisting device in accordance with the sixth and the eleventh aspect of the
present invention, respectively. </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0037">In the accompanying drawings:
<sl><li>Fig. 1 is a block diagram showing a configuration of a parking assisting
device in accordance with a first embodiment of the present invention;</li><li>Fig. 2 illustrates parking assisting information provided by the parking
assisting device in accordance with the first embodiment;</li><li>Fig. 3 illustrates a case in which parking assisting information is
provided for each turning angle of a target guiding position;</li><li>Fig. 4 illustrates a case in which parking assisting information is
continuously outputted throughout a series of steps of parking;</li><li>Fig. 5 illustrates parking assisting information in case of following the
steps and in case of not following the steps in accordance with the parking
assisting device of the first embodiment;</li><li>Fig. 6 illustrates parking assisting information provided by a parking
assisting device in accordance with a second embodiment;</li><li>Fig. 7 illustrates parking assisting information in case of following steps
and in case of not following the steps in accordance with the parking assisting
device of the second embodiment;</li><li>Fig. 8 illustrates parking assisting information in the case in which a
period is variable or fixed in accordance with a parking assisting device of a
third embodiment;</li><li>Fig. 9 illustrates parking assisting information provided by a parking
assisting device in accordance with a fourth embodiment;</li><li>Figs. 10A and 10B illustrate parking assisting information provided by 
a parking assisting device in accordance with a sixth embodiment;</li><li>Fig. 11 illustrates an interrelation between a current turning angle of a
vehicle and an angular speed for determining output timing of parking
assisting information in accordance with a parking assisting device of a
seventh embodiment;</li><li>Fig. 12 is a flow chart showing a learning method for correcting output
timing of parking assisting information in accordance with a parking assisting
device of an eighth embodiment;</li><li>Figs. 13A and 13B illustrate parking assisting information provided by
a parking assisting device in accordance with a ninth embodiment; and</li><li>Figs. 14A, 14B and 14C illustrate each step of parallel parking.</li></sl></p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0038">Embodiments of the case in which a parking assisting device of the
present invention is applied to parallel parking will be hereinafter described.
First Embodiment</p>
    <p num="0039">As shown in Fig. 1, a parking assisting device 11 is provided with a start
switch 12 as reference position setting means, a yaw rate sensor 13 as vehicle
turning position detecting means, a computer 14 as control means to which
the start switch 12 and the yaw rate sensor 13 are connected and a speaker 15
as parking assisting information notifying means connected to the computer
14. The start switch 12 is provided in a driving seat. When a driver actuates
the start switch 12, information of the actuation is inputted in the computer
14. Then, the computer 14 recognizes that a position of a vehicle at that 
point is a reference position for calculating a vehicle turning position. The
yaw rate sensor 13 detects an angular speed in the yaw direction of the vehicle.
The computer 14 calculates how many degrees of turning angle from the
reference position where the vehicle is currently located (vehicle turning
position) from the actuation information of the start switch 12 and a detection
result of the angular speed of the yaw rate sensor 13. Moreover, the
computer 14 determines parking assistance information to be provided at that
point from the calculated vehicle turning position. The speaker 15 outputs
parking assisting information by sound to the driver based on such a
determination of the computer 14.</p>
    <p num="0040">The parking assisting information by sound provided by the speaker 15
will be described with reference to Fig. 2. Parking assisting information 16
consists of a first intermittent sound (first information) 17 of a tone A
indicating that a vehicle is approaching a target stop position, a continuous
sound (third information) 18 of a tone B indicating that a position of the
vehicle coincides with the target stop position and a second intermittent
sound (second information) 19 of a tone C indicating that the vehicle has gone
beyond the target stop position. The tones A, B and C are different from each
other. In addition, the continuous sound 18 is provided when a turning
angle of a vehicle becomes equal to a turning angle of a target stop position
(target guiding position) within a tolerance.</p>
    <p num="0041">Next, operations of the parking assisting device of this embodiment will
be described. In this embodiment, a form in which all turning tracks L1, L2
and L3 are turning tracks by a maximum steering angle in Fig. 14 described 
above is employed. Therefore, a driver first moves forward passing the side of
a target parking position T and stops a vehicle in a position P1 where the
vehicle becomes substantially in parallel with the target parking position T.
The driver actuates the start switch 12 there. As a consequence, the position
P1 becomes a reference position for calculating a vehicle turning position, that
is, a position where a turning angle is zero degree. The driver turns a steering
wheel fully to the right from the position and starts turning and forward
movement at a maximum steering angle. A change in a turning angle
following the turning and forward movement of the vehicle is detected by the
yaw rate sensor 13 and a turning position of the vehicle is defined based on
the turning angle. The first intermittent sound 17 is outputted from the
speaker 15 while the vehicle is approaching the next target stop position P2,
that is, while the turning angle of the vehicle is smaller than 1. At this point,
an intermittent period (intermittent interval) of the first intermittent sound 17
changes to be shorter as the vehicle gets closer to the target stop position P2.
For example, the intermittent period changes such that a time period of a
silent state gets shorter in an intermittent sound in which two states
alternatively appear in such a order of "beep, (silent state), beep, (silent state),
and beep". Consequently, the driver can easily understand that the vehicle is
currently in the state of approaching the target stop position P2 and, further,
can easily recognize to which degree the vehicle has approached the target
stop position P2 from the change in the intermittent period of the first
intermittent sound 17. Then, at an instance when the turning angle becomes
1 and a position of the vehicle coincides with the target stop position P2, the 
continuous sound 18 is outputted from the speaker 15. Consequently, the
driver can recognize that the vehicle has reached the target stop position P2
and may stop the vehicle. In addition, if the driver further turned the vehicle
or moved the vehicle forward unintentionally, the second intermittent sound
19 indicating that the vehicle has gone beyond the target stop position P2 is
outputted from the speaker 15. Moreover, an intermittent period of the
second intermittent sound 19 changes to be longer as the vehicle moves
forward from the target stop position P2 farther. For example, the
intermittent period changes such that a time period of a silent state gets
longer in an intermittent sound in which two states alternatively appear in
such a order of "buzz, (silent state), buzz, (silent state), and buzz". Further, it
has been detected that the vehicle has passed the target stop position P2 from
the fact that the turning angle of the vehicle around the reference position P1
has exceeded 1. The driver can easily understand that the vehicle is
currently in the state in which it has gone beyond the target stop position P2
from such an output of the second intermittent sound 19 and, further, can
easily recognize to which extent the vehicle has gone beyond the target stop
position P2 from the change in the intermittent period of the second
intermittent sound 19. In addition, in a position x before the vehicle reaches
the target stop position P2 and a position y after the vehicle has reached the
target stop position P2, which are apart from the target stop position P2 by the
same turning angle, since the turning angles are apart from the target stop
position P2 by the same value, the intermittent periods of the first intermittent
sound 17 and the second intermittent sound 19 are the same. However, in 
this embodiment, the tone of the second intermittent sound 19 is different
from the tone of the first intermittent sound 17. Thus, even if the
intermittent periods of the first intermittent sound 17 and the second
intermittent sound 19 are the same, the driver can distinguish whether the
vehicle is approaching or has gone beyond the target position P2 from the
difference of the tones. Thereafter, the parking assisting information 16 for
informing the driver of the turning angle 2 is outputted for the target stop
position P3 as well, whereby the driver can sequentially clear predetermined
steps easily. With such parking assisting information provided, since the
driver can move the vehicle while recognizing a degree of approach to a stop
position of the vehicle in advance, the driver can stop the vehicle in a desired
position.</p>
    <p num="0042">Further, the continuous sound of the tone B is not limited to the form of
continuously sounding until the subsequent intermittent sound of the tone C
is outputted but may be a form of stopping after sounding for a predetermined
period of time (e.g., 2 to 3 seconds) (this is the same for embodiments to be
described later). Moreover, the sound of the tone B is not limited to a
continuous sound but may be a sound of other forms as long as a driver can
distinguish it from the respective sounds of the tones A and C (this is the same
for embodiments to be described later).</p>
    <heading>Second Embodiment</heading>
    <p num="0043">According to the above-mentioned first embodiment, the parking
assisting information 16 is provided for each turning angle of a target stop
position as shown in Fig. 3, whereby a driver can stop a vehicle in a desired 
position. If parking assisting information is continuously outputted
throughout a series of steps of parallel parking as shown in Fig. 4, the
following problems are likely to arise. According to meaning of each tone of
the parking assisting information 16 of the first embodiment, if a vehicle
moves without following desired steps, for example, if the vehicle has gone
beyond a position P3 on the turning track L2, since the direction of the vehicle
is slanted largely from the position P1, a turning angle around the reference
position P1 becomes larger than 2. Thus, in this case, as indicated by a
symbol f in Fig. 5, it is determined that the vehicle has gone beyond the
position P3 and the second intermittent sound 19 is provided. However, if a
steering wheel is turned in the other direction and the vehicle has moved
backward from the position P3 on the turning track L3 in accordance with the
desired steps, since the slant of the vehicle is smaller than 2, the first
intermittent sound 17 is outputted as indicated by a symbol g in Fig. 5.
Consequently, the driver hears the first intermittent sound 17 indicating that
the vehicle is approaching the target stop position while recognizing that the
vehicle is moving backward apart from the position P3. Thus, the driver is
likely to have an illusion that the vehicle is still approaching the position P3
even if it has actually passed the position P3. In the second embodiment, the
first embodiment is altered such that an unnatural state is not caused even if
parking assisting information is continuously outputted.</p>
    <p num="0044">In the second embodiment, parking assisting information of sound 21
consists of a first intermittent sound (first information) 22 of a tone A
indicating that a vehicle is required to move forward, a continuous sound 
(third information) 23 of a tone B indicating that a vehicle is required to stop
and a second intermittent sound (second information) 24 of a tone C
indicating that a vehicle is required to move backward as shown in Fig. 6.
The tones A, B and C are different from each other. In addition, the
continuous sound 23 is provided when a turning angle of a vehicle becomes
equal to a turning angle in a target stop position within a tolerance.</p>
    <p num="0045">Next, operations of the parking assisting device of the second
embodiment will be described with reference to Figs. 6 and 14. As in the first
embodiment, a form in which all turning tracks L1, L2 and L3 are turning
tracks by a maximum steering angle in Fig. 14 is employed in the second
embodiment as well. A driver first moves a vehicle forward passing the side of
the target parking position T and stops the vehicle in the position P1 where it
becomes substantially in parallel with the target parking position T. The
driver actuates the start switch 12 there. As a consequence, the position P1
becomes a position where a turning angle is zero degree. The first
intermittent sound 22 of the tone A indicating that a vehicle is required to
move forward is outputted while the driver is moving the vehicle from the
position P1 to the position P2 as a step G1. When a turning angle becomes 1,
the continuous sound 23 of the tone B indicating that a vehicle is required to
stop is outputted. If the vehicle could not stop at the turning angle 1 and
has gone beyond the position P2, that is, has moved forward excessively, since
the turning angle becomes larger than 1, the second intermittent sound 24 of
the tone C indicating that a vehicle is required to move backward is outputted.
Consequently, the driver recognizes that it is necessary to return to the 
position P2. On the other hand, while the driver stops the vehicle in the
position P2 according to the desired steps and moves the vehicle to the
position P3 as a step G2, the second intermittent sound 24 indicating that a
vehicle is required to move backward is outputted. Here, although the
second intermittent sound would indicate that the vehicle has gone beyond
the position P3 within the meaning of the first embodiment, the second
intermittent sound indicates that a vehicle is required to move backward in
the second embodiment as described above. Thus, even if parking assisting
information is outputted continuously up to the next target stop position, an
actual behavior of the vehicle and meaning of information to be informed never
become inconsistent. When the turning angle becomes 2 and the vehicle
reaches the position P3, the continuous sound 23 indicating that a vehicle is
required to stop is outputted. Moreover, a case in which the vehicle has gone
beyond the position P2 and a case in which the vehicle moves backward
according to the desired steps will be described with reference to Fig. 7
corresponding to Fig. 5 of the first embodiment. First, if the vehicle has gone
beyond the position P2, since the turning angle becomes larger than 2, the
first intermittent sound 22 is outputted as indicated by the symbol f in Fig. 7
and the driver recognizes that the vehicle is required to move forward. On the
other hand, if the vehicle has moved backward from the position P3 according
to the desired steps, since the turning angle becomes smaller than 2, the
second intermittent sound 24 is outputted. Thus, the driver can recognize
that the vehicle is required to move backward and that the driver is driving
according to the desired steps. In this way, since the driver can move the 
vehicle while recognizing a degree of approach of the vehicle to a stop position
in advance, the driver can stop the vehicle in a desired position. In addition,
even if parking assisting information is continuously outputted throughout a
series of steps, an actual behavior of the vehicle and contents of information to
be informed never become inconsistent. Further, there are advantages in
continuously outputting parking assisting information as described below. If
parking assisting information by sound is outputted for each target stop
position, a driver is likely to have an illusion that guidance by a parking
assisting device has ended when the sound stopped. However, if the sound is
continuously outputted and stops when guidance ends, the driver can
straightly recognize that guidance ends when the sound stops and the
above-mentioned illusion can be prevented. Further, as shown in Figs. 6 and
7, an intermittent interval of the respective intermittent sounds 22 and 24
changes as the vehicle approaches or moves away from a corresponding target
stop position in the same manner as in the first embodiment.
Third Embodiment</p>
    <p num="0046">Next, parking assisting device in accordance with a third embodiment
will be described with reference to Fig. 8. In this embodiment, both variable
and fixed periods of an intermittent sound are used. That is, an intermittent
sound is outputted with a period made variable in one of processes, in which a
vehicle approaches a target stop position (or in which a vehicle is required to
move forward) and in which a vehicle has gone beyond a target stop position
(or in which a vehicle is required to move backward), and with the period made
fixed in the other process. A driver can recognize that a vehicle is 
approaching a target stop position (or is required to move forward) or has gone
beyond a target stop position (or is required to move backward) by such a form
as well. Moreover, in this case, the driver can recognize whether a vehicle is
approaching a target stop position (or is required to move forward) or has gone
beyond a target stop position (or is required to move backward) by
distinguishing whether the period is variable or fixed even if tones of two
intermittent sounds before and after a continuous sound are not made
different (the intermittent sounds may be made different). Alternatively, the
period of the intermittent sound may be made variable in one of the cases in
which the vehicle is following desired steps and in which the vehicle is not
following the desired steps and may be fixed in the other. In addition, the
parking assisting information is not limited to using both variable and fixed
periods of an intermittent sound but may make degrees of variableness
different across a target stop position.
Fourth Embodiment</p>
    <p num="0047">In the parking assisting information of the above-mentioned first to
third embodiments, a form of a variable period of an intermittent sound is
such that the closer a vehicle to a target stop position, the smaller the period
becomes. In a fourth embodiment, a form of a variable period of an
intermittent sound is set as shown in Fig. 9 in the parking assisting
information of the first to the third embodiments. That is, the closer a vehicle
to a target stop position, the larger the period of the intermittent sound
becomes.</p>
    <heading>Fifth Embodiment</heading>
    <p num="0048">In the parking assisting information of the above-mentioned first to
fourth embodiments, three states, in which a vehicle is approaching a target
stop position (is required to move forward), a position of a vehicle coincides
with a target stop position (a vehicle is required to stop) and a vehicle has gone
beyond a target stop position (is required to move backward), are informed by
three sounds consisting of one continuous sound and two intermittent sounds
that are outputted before and after the continuous sound. As a fifth
embodiment, the continuous sound indicating that a position of a vehicle
coincides with a target stop position (a vehicle is required to stop) may not be
outputted in the parking assisting information of the first to the fourth
embodiments. That is, the parking assisting information of the present
invention is not limited to the above-mentioned embodiments as long as three
states consisting of a state in which a vehicle has reached a target stop
position and states of positions in front of and behind the target stop position
are indicated by two sounds with forms different from each other.</p>
    <heading>Sixth Embodiment</heading>
    <p num="0049">In a sixth embodiment, a brake operation guiding sound 25 for guiding
braking operation is further outputted in the parking assisting information of
the first to the fifth embodiments. As shown in Fig. 10A, even if a driver hears
the continuous sounds 18 and 23 indicating that the position of the vehicle
coincides with the target stop position (the vehicle is required to stop) and
operates a brake, it is likely that a position where a vehicle actually stops is
outside an initial stop tolerance. Thus, in this embodiment, sound requiring
a vehicle to stop is outputted earlier as a brake operation guiding sound as 
shown in Fig. 10B to keep an actual stop position within the initial stop
tolerance. Assuming that a turning angle indicating a target stop position is
, the brake operation guiding sound 25 for guiding braking operation is
outputted in a position before the turning angle  by an angle α (first position).
Further, a method of calculating the angle α is as follows. First, by the yaw
rate sensor 13 a yaw direction angular speed of a vehicle in a predetermined
position before the turning angle , which is known in advance as a position
where a driver wishes to stop the vehicle, by an angle β (β&gt;α) is detected.
Then, if an angular speed at that point is assumed to be ω(β), the angle α is
calculated as follows.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">ω(β) × K = α</st32:df>
That is, the higher the angular speed ω(β) of the turning angle β the larger the
angle α, and the guiding sound 25 is outputted in a position farther before the
target stop position. Further, K is a coefficient that is employed as an optimal
value by an experiment. In addition, in order to avoid confusion for a driver
due to increase of the number of sounds, the guiding sound 25 is the sound of
the tone B that is the same as the continuous sounds 18 and 23 of the first to
the fourth embodiments. In addition, in order to prevent the continuous
sounds 18 and 23 from sounding again after the guiding sound 25 sounds
once to confuse the driver, the guiding sound 25 is originally made to
continuously sound until the timing when the continuous sounds 18 and 23
sound. In addition, an output range B0 of the sound of the tone B is defined
as follows.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center"> - α &lt; B0 &lt;  + FitR</st32:df> 
Then, if the angular speed ω(β) is high, for example, when ω(β) ≥ ω(βmin), an
angular speed detected by the yaw rate sensor 13 as the angular speed ω(β) =
ω(β) is used as ω(β) without any change. Further, it is assumed that ω(βmin)
= FitR/K. On the other hand, if the angular speed ω(β) is low, for example,
when ω(β) &lt; ω(βmin), it is assumed that ω(β) = ω(βmin). In this way, by
outputting the brake operation guiding sound 25 earlier than output timing of
a continuous sound before a vehicle reaches a target stop position, it becomes
possible for the driver to stop the vehicle within the initial stop tolerance more
easily.</p>
    <heading>Seventh Embodiment</heading>
    <p num="0050">In the sixth embodiment, in order to output the brake operation guiding
sound 25 before the turning angle  by the angle α, α is determined based on
the angular speed ω(β) earlier than that. However, an angular speed of a
vehicle may significantly change after checking the angular speed ω(β). That
is, in a seventh embodiment, output timing of the brake operation guiding
sound 25 is corrected depending on change in a vehicle speed in order to
eliminate change in a stop position due to the vehicle speed. More
specifically, as shown in Fig. 11, the output timing follows an interrelation
between a current turning angle of a vehicle and an angular speed for
determining an output. In the case in which it is assumed that the vehicle is
currently in a position indicated by a turning angle Ø1 with respect to a target
stop position indicated by the turning angle , if the current angular speed of
the vehicle is ω1 as shown in Fig. 11, the brake operation guiding sound 25 is
outputted at that point. If the angular speed of the vehicle at an turning 
angle Ø1 is less than ω1, the same check is continued thereafter to output the
brake operation guiding sound 25 at an angular speed ω2 in a position of a
turning angle Ø2 and at an angular speed ω3 in a position of a turning angle
Ø3. In other words, a position where the brake operation guiding sound 25 is
outputted is selected based on an interrelation between an angular speed of a
vehicle at that point and a turning angle indicating a position of the vehicle.
In this way, an angular speed of a current position (first position) is employed
as an angular speed for determining a position (first position) where the brake
operation guiding sound 25 is outputted, whereby appropriate timing in a
current turning angle can be always calculated and the brake operation
guiding sound 25 can be outputted at optimal timing even if a vehicle speed
changes. Further, although an angular speed is used as a vehicle speed in
the sixth and the seventh embodiments, the present invention is not limited to
this but may be appropriately altered and implemented by, for example, using
a speed on a turning track.</p>
    <heading>Eighth Embodiment</heading>
    <p num="0051">In the sixth embodiment, the brake operation guiding sound 25 is
outputted before the turning angle  by the angle α. However, a position
where a vehicle actually stops after a driver hears the brake operation guiding
sound 25 and starts a braking operation varies for each driver. That is, in an
eighth embodiment, output timing of the brake operation guiding sound 25 is
corrected by learning in order to eliminate variation of a stop position due to
human factors. More specifically, a learning method as shown in Fig. 12 is
used. This learning method will be described with a form of parallel parking 
shown in Fig. 14 as an example. Further, in Fig. 14, it is assumed that
turning angles in the position P2, the position P3 and the target parking
position T, that is, a target angle 1, a target angle 2 and a final target angle are
1, 2 and 3 (3=0), respectively, and turning angles of positions where a
vehicle actually stops in association with them, that is, actual stop angle
values are stop1, stop2 and stop3, respectively. Differences between the
actual stop angle values and corresponding target angles upon guiding of
parallel parking for the n-th time are assumed to be γ1<sub>n</sub>, γ2<sub>n</sub> and γ3<sub>n</sub>,
respectively. Then, corrected values calculated when the guidance of parallel
parking is completed are assumed to be γavg1<sub>n</sub>, γavg2<sub>n</sub> and γavg3<sub>n</sub>,
respectively.</p>
    <p num="0052">As step 1 of Fig. 12, n-th parallel parking is started. As step 2, a sound
requiring to stop a vehicle is outputted in a state in which the vehicle is close
to the target angle 1. Output timing of the sound requiring to stop a vehicle
is the time when the turning angle of the vehicle is an angle [1 - α - γ1<sub>n-1</sub>], in
which γavg1<sub>n-1</sub> that is a corrected value calculated in immediately preceding
n-1-th guidance of parking is incorporated. Next, as step 3, it is determined
whether or not the vehicle stops within a range where the actual stop angle
value stop1 is 1 - FitR &lt; stop1 &lt; 1 + FitR. If it is determined that the
vehicle does not stop within the range, γ1<sub>n</sub> = stop1 - 1 is calculated and
stored as step 4. Further, if it is determined that the vehicle stops within the
range, it is assumed that γ1<sub>n</sub> = 0. Thereafter, steps 5 to 7 are performed for
the target angle 2 and steps 8 to 10 are performed for the final target angle 3
in the same manner as steps 2 to 4. Then, when the guidance of parking is 
completed by step 11, the corrected values γavg1<sub>n</sub>, γavg2<sub>n</sub> and γavg3<sub>n</sub> are
calculated as moving averages, respectively, as step 12. In this way, in this
embodiment, the sound requiring to stop a vehicle is outputted in a position of
a turning angle of -α-γ<sub>n-1</sub> that uses a corrected value by learning, whereby
guiding information of a stop position can be provided to a driver such that
variation of a stop position due to human factors is eliminated. Further, the
above-mentioned moving average as a learning method is simply an example.
There are other methods such as multiplying a calculated corrected value by
L/M (optimal values are used as L and M by an experiment). Moreover, other
learning methods may be used. In addition, it is also possible to perform the
correction of output timing of the brake operation guiding sound 25 according
to the eighth embodiment in combination with the correction of output timing
of the brake operation guiding sound 25 according to the sixth and the
seventh embodiments.</p>
    <heading>Ninth Embodiment</heading>
    <p num="0053">If the brake operation guiding sound 25 is outputted in the sixth to the
eighth embodiments, the brake operation guiding sound 25 may be outputted
such that it overlaps the first intermittent sounds 17 and 22 indicating that a
vehicle is approaching and is required to move forward without altering a form
of outputting the intermittent sounds 17 and 22 as shown in Fig. 13A. In
addition, as shown in Fig. 13B, when the brake operation guiding sound 25 is
outputted in a position before output positions of the continuous sounds 18
and 23, which indicate that the position of the vehicle coincides with the target
stop position and the vehicle is required to stop, by angles α1 and α2, the first 
intermittent sounds 17 and 22 indicating that the vehicle is approaching and
is required to move forward may also be outputted at timing for making the
output earlier by the angles α1 and α2 accordingly such that the brake
operation guiding sound 25 does not overlap the intermittent sounds 17 and
22.</p>
    <heading>Tenth Embodiment</heading>
    <p num="0054">As a tenth embodiment, intermittent sounds may not be outputted
before and after the continuous sounds 18 and 23 and a target stop position
may be informed only by a brake operation guiding sound in the above-mentioned
sixth to ninth embodiments.</p>
    <p num="0055">Moreover, as another form, a sound different from the continuous
sound of the tone B in the first to the fourth embodiments may be outputted
as the brake operation guiding sound 25 and/or the continuous sounds 18
and 23 may sound again at an interval after the guiding sound 25 sounds in
the above-mentioned sixth to ninth embodiments.</p>
    <heading>Eleventh Embodiment</heading>
    <p num="0056">In the above-mentioned first to tenth embodiments, a reference position
is set by a driver inputting it, for example, by pressing a start switch.
However, the present invention is not limited to this and a position may be
automatically detected as a reference position by detecting a certain condition
even if the driver does not set the reference position.</p>
    <p num="0057">In addition, a yaw rate sensor is employed as a sensor for detecting a
turning angle in the above-mentioned embodiments. However, the present
invention is not limited to this and other means may be used (e.g., an angular 
speed may be detected by a speed sensor and a steering angle sensor).
Moreover, a turning position is recognized as a turning angle. However, the
present invention is not limited to this and it is possible to employ other forms
of detecting and recognizing a turning position such as recognizing a turning
position as a distance of a turning track or detecting a position itself (e.g.,
detection by the GPS) to process it as a turning position.</p>
    <heading>Twelfth Embodiment</heading>
    <p num="0058">In the above-mentioned embodiments, tones are selected as elements
that are different from each other among specific elements of sound as parking
assisting information and an intermittent period is selected as an element that
indicates a form of change in an intermittent sound among specific elements
of sound. However, the present invention is not limited to this. Thus,
instead of the above-mentioned embodiments, it is also possible to
appropriately select other elements among the specific elements of sound
such as a tone, an intermittent period, a volume, a pitch, a sound pressure
and a length of one sound to form parking assisting information. Further, as
an example of difference of sound lengths, there are a long sound "beep, beep,
beep" and a short sound "bip, bip, bip".</p>
    <p num="0059">In addition, a sound may be a predetermined melody or a voice and a
type of the melody or spoken words may be specific elements of sound.
Thirteenth Embodiment</p>
    <p num="0060">In the above-mentioned embodiments, a sound is used as parking
assisting information. However, the present invention is not limited to this
and other auditory information or other information such as visual 
information and tactile information may be used. Alternatively, information
in which these pieces of information are combined with each other
simultaneously may be provided. Further, as an example of the visual
information, there is light. In the case of light, as examples of specific
elements of light, there are a color of light, a blinking period, a strength of light,
an emitting time period of light and the like. In addition, a video, a figure, a
sign or a character may be visual information. In addition, as an example of
tactile information, there is vibration. In the case of vibration, as examples of
specific elements of vibration, there are an interval of vibration, a strength of
vibration, the number of times of vibration, a rhythm of vibration and the like.</p>
    <p num="0061">Moreover, the above-mentioned embodiments concern parallel parking.
However, the present invention is not limited to this and can be applied to
other parking forms such as lateral parking.</p>
    <heading>Fourteenth Embodiment</heading>
    <p num="0062">In any of the above-mentioned first to thirteenth embodiments, parking
assisting information indicates three states, which consist of a state in which
a vehicle has reached a target stop position and states of positions in front of
and behind the target stop position, by two kinds of information that have
forms different from each other. However, the parking assisting information
of the present invention is not limited to this but may be any information as
long as it consists of two kinds of information with forms different from each
other that are provided in any two states among three states, which consist of
a state in which a vehicle has reached a target stop position and states of
positions in front of and behind the target stop position, and informs a driver 
of at least two states among the three states. Thus, for example, the parking
assisting information may be information of a first form and information of a
second form that are provided in two states in which a vehicle is approaching
a target stop position (is required to move forward) and in which a vehicle has
gone beyond a target stop position (is required to move backward), respectively,
and inform a driver of two states in which a vehicle is approaching a target
stop position (is required to move forward) and in which a vehicle has gone
beyond a target stop position (is required to move backward), two states in
which a vehicle is approaching a target stop position (is required to move
forward) and in which a position of a vehicle coincides with a target stop
position (a vehicle is required to stop) or two states in which a position of a
vehicle coincides with a target stop position (a vehicle is required to stop) and
in which a vehicle has gone beyond a target stop position (is required to move
backward). Moreover, as another example, the parking assisting information
may be information that is provided in two states in which a vehicle is
approaching a target stop position (is required to move forward) and in which
a position of a vehicle coincides with a target stop position (a vehicle is
required to stop), respectively, and informs a driver of two states in which a
vehicle is approaching a target stop position (is required to move forward) and
in which a vehicle has gone beyond a target stop position (is required to move
backward), two states in which a vehicle is approaching a target stop position
(is required to move forward) and in which a position of a vehicle coincides
with a target stop position (a vehicle is required to stop) or two states in which
a position of a vehicle coincides with a target stop position (a vehicle is 
required to stop) and in which a vehicle has gone beyond a target stop position
(is required to move backward). Similarly, the parking assisting information
may be information that is provided in two states in which a position of a
vehicle coincides with a target stop position (a vehicle is required to stop) and
in which a vehicle has gone beyond a target stop position (is required to move
backward), respectively, and informs a driver of at least two states among the
three states.</p>
    <p num="0063">As described above, according to the parking assisting device in
accordance with the first aspect of the present invention, the parking assisting
information consists of two kinds of information with forms different from
each other that are provided in any two states among three states consisting of
a state in which a vehicle has reached a target guiding position and states in
which a vehicle is in front of and behind the target guiding position. As a
result, a driver can be informed by the parking assisting information of at least
two states among the three states and can stop a vehicle at a desired position.</p>
    <p num="0064">According to the parking assisting device in accordance with the second
aspect of the present invention, first information and second information are
provided in states in which the vehicle is in front of and behind the target
guiding position, whereby a driver can be informed of three states consisting of
a state in which a vehicle has reached a target stop position and states in
which a vehicle is in front of and behind the target stop position and can stop
a vehicle in a desired position.</p>
    <p num="0065">According to the parking assisting device in accordance with the third
aspect of the present invention, third information separately from first 
information and second information is obtained, whereby a driver can
recognize more surely a state in which a vehicle has reached a target guiding
position.</p>
    <p num="0066">According to the parking assisting device in accordance with the fourth
aspect of the present invention, first information, second information and
third information are obtained, whereby a driver can recognize which state a
vehicle is in among the states in which the vehicle is approaching, has gone
beyond and has reached a target guiding position.</p>
    <p num="0067">According to the parking assisting device in accordance with the fifth
aspect of the present invention, first information, second information and
third information are obtained, whereby a driver can recognize in which state
among forward movement required, backward movement required and stop
required states a vehicle is.</p>
    <p num="0068">According to the parking assisting device in accordance with the sixth
aspect of the present invention, at least one of elements specifying sound is
obtained, whereby a driver can recognize whether contents of parking
assisting information is first or second information and change of at least
another one of the elements is detected, whereby a driver can recognize in
what kind of state a vehicle position is with respect to a target guiding
position.</p>
    <p num="0069">According to the parking assisting device in accordance with the
seventh and the eleventh aspects of the present invention, the driver hears a
brake operation guiding sound to start a braking operation in a first position
before the vehicle reaches the target guiding position, whereby a driver can 
stop a vehicle in a target guiding position more accurately.</p>
    <p num="0070">According to the parking assisting device in accordance with the eighth
and the twelfth aspects of the present invention, a brake operation guiding
sound can be outputted in an appropriate position according to a vehicle
speed.</p>
    <p num="0071">According to the parking assisting device in accordance with the ninth
and the thirteenth aspects of the present invention, since a brake operation
guiding sound can be outputted according to a current vehicle speed, a brake
operation guiding sound is outputted in an appropriate position even if a
vehicle speed is changing significantly.</p>
    <p num="0072">According to the parking assisting device in accordance with the tenth
and the fourteenth aspects of the present invention, a brake operation guiding
sound can be outputted in an appropriate position that is adapted to a habit of
each driver.</p>
    <p num="0073">According to the parking assisting device in accordance with the
fifteenth and the sixteenth aspects of the present invention, parking assisting
information can be provided using light.</p>
    <p num="0074">According to the parking assisting device in accordance with the
seventeenth and the eighteenth aspects of the present invention, parking
assisting information can be provided using vibration. </p>
    <p num="0075">A parking assisting device provides parking assisting information
consisting of a first intermittent sound of a tone (A) indicating that a vehicle is
approaching a target stop position, a continuous sound of a tone (B) indicating
that a position of a vehicle coincides with a target stop position and a second
intermittent sound of a tone (C) indicating that a vehicle has gone beyond a
target stop position. An intermittent period of the first intermittent sound
changes to be shorter as the vehicle approaches a target stop position closer
and an intermittent period of the second intermittent sound changes to be
longer as the vehicle goes beyond the target stop position farther.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A parking assisting device comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>means for setting a reference of a turning position of a vehicle;</claim-text><claim-text>means for detecting a turning position of a vehicle based on the
reference; and</claim-text><claim-text>means for notifying a driver of parking assisting information concerning
a target guiding position based on the detected turning position of a vehicle,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the parking assisting information comprises two kinds of
information with forms different from each other provided in any two states
among three states consisting of a state in which the vehicle has reached the
target guiding position and states in which the vehicle is in front of and behind
the target guiding position, the two kinds of information informing the driver
of at least two states among the three states.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A parking assisting device according to claim 1,
   wherein the parking assisting information comprises first information
and second information provided in the states in which the vehicle is in front
of and behind the target guiding position, the first information and the second
information with forms different from each other informing the driver of three
states consisting of the state in which the vehicle has reached the target
guiding position and the states of positions in which the vehicle is in front of
and behind the target guiding position.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A parking assisting device according to claim 2,
   wherein the parking assisting information includes third information to
be notified in the state in which the vehicle has reached the target guiding
position.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A parking assisting device according to claim 3,
   wherein the first information, second information and third information
indicate that the vehicle is approaching, has gone beyond and has reached the
target guiding position, respectively.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A parking assisting device according to claim 3,
   wherein the first information, second information and third information
indicate that the vehicle is required to move forward, is required to move
backward and is required to stop, respectively.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A parking assisting device according to claim 2,
   wherein the parking assisting information consists of sounds, and the
first information and second information have elements specifying sound at
least one of which is different between the first and second information and at
least another one of which changes based on a vehicle position with respect to
the target guiding position.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A parking assisting device according to claim 1,
   wherein the parking assisting information includes a brake operation
guiding sound provided in a first position before the vehicle reaches the target
guiding position.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A parking assisting device according to claim 7,
   wherein the first position is selected based on an angular speed of the
vehicle in a predetermined position before the vehicle reaches the first
position.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>A parking assisting device according to claim 7,
   wherein the first position is selected based on interrelation between a
turning position of the vehicle and an angular speed of the vehicle in the
turning position.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>A parking assisting device according to claim 7,
wherein the first position is selected by learning based on past data.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>A parking assisting device comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>means for setting a reference of a turning position of a vehicle;</claim-text><claim-text>means for detecting a turning position of a vehicle based on the
reference; and</claim-text><claim-text>means for notifying a driver of parking assisting information concerning
a target guiding position based on the detected turning position of a vehicle,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the parking assisting information includes a brake operation
guiding sound that is provided in a first position before the vehicle reaches the
target guiding position.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>A parking assisting device according to claim 11,
   wherein the first position is selected based on an angular speed of the
vehicle in a predetermined position before the vehicle reaches the first
position.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>A parking assisting device according to claim 11,
   wherein the first position is selected based on an interrelation between
a turning position of the vehicle and an angular speed of the vehicle in the
turning position.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>A parking assisting device according to claim 11,
wherein the first position is selected by learning based on past data.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>A parking assisting device according to claim 6,
wherein the parking assisting information is of light instead of sound.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>A parking assisting device according to claim 11,
wherein the parking assisting information is of light instead of sound.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>A parking assisting device according to claim 6,
   wherein the parking assisting information is of vibration instead of
sound.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="18">
      <claim-text>A parking assisting device according to claim 11,
   wherein the parking assisting information is of vibration instead of
sound.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
