<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1227628-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1227628" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="26950722" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020731">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1227628-A2" status="new" fvid="23519564">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1227628</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20020731</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02100081-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02100081</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020130</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="US-26472301-P" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>26472301</doc-number>
          <kind>P</kind>
          <date>20010130</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
      <priority-claim ucid="US-97802401-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>97802401</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20011017</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04L  12/56        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04L  12/56        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H04L  12/56D</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H04L  12/56E8</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H04L  12/56S8A</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verkehrsüberwachung von Paketübertragung in einem Dual-Speed-Hub</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Traffic policing of packet transfer in a dual speed hub</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Surveillance de trafic de transfert de paquets dans un Dual Speed Hub</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ALTIMA COMMUNICATIONS INC</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ALTIMA COMMUNICATIONS, INC.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Altima Communications, Inc.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>16215 Alton Parkway</street>
              <city>Irvine, CA 92619-7013</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GAN KUO-CHUNG CLIFF</name>
            <address>
              <country>TW</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GAN, KUO-CHUNG (CLIFF)</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>GAN, KUO-CHUNG (CLIFF)</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>3 F-2, No. 3, Lane 99 Pudding Road</street>
              <city>300, Hsin Chu</city>
              <country>TW</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Lind, Robert</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Marks &amp;amp; Clerk, 4220 Nash Court, Oxford Business Park South</street>
              <city>Oxford OX4 2RU</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A system for policing traffic of packet transfer in a hub. The system includes a
first circuit and a second circuit and a first data line connecting the first circuit to the
second circuit, wherein data is transmitted within and between the first circuit and the
second circuit across said first data line. A second data line connects the first circuit to
the second circuit, wherein data is transmitted within and between the first circuit and
the second circuit across the second data line. A monitor monitors the first data line to
determine when an amount of data being transmitted on the first data line within the first
circuit has reached a threshold. A blocking mechanism prevents data from being
transmitted on the first data line from the first circuit to the second circuit when the
amount of data being transmitted on the first data line has reached the threshold.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="139" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="99"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION:</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <heading>
      <b>Field of the Invention:</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0001">The invention relates to a method and apparatus for high performance
switching in local area communications networks such as token ring, ATM, ethernet,
fast ethernet, gigabit Ethernet and 10 gigabit Ethernet environments.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>Description of the Related Art:</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0002">As computer performance has increased in recent years, the demands on
computer networks has significantly increased; faster computer processors and higher
memory capabilities need networks with high bandwidth capabilities to enable high
speed transfer of significant amounts of data. The well known ethernet technology,
which is based upon numerous IEEE ethernet standards, is one example of computer
networking technology which has been able to be modified and improved to remain a
viable computing technology. A more complete discussion of prior art networking
systems can be found, for example, in SWITCHED AND FAST ETHERNET, by Breyer
and Riley (Ziff Davis, 1996), and numerous IEEE publications relating to IEEE 802
standards. Based upon the Open Systems Interconnect (OSI) 7 layer reference model,
network capabilities have grown through the development of repeaters, bridges, routers,
and, more recently, "switches", which operate with various types of communication
media. Thickwire, thinwire, twisted pair, and optical fiber are examples of media which 
has been used for computer networks. Switches, as they relate to computer networking
and to ethernet, are hardware based devices which control the flow of data packets or
cells based upon destination address information which is available in each packet. A
properly designed and implemented switch should be capable of receiving a packet and
switching the packet to an appropriate output port at what is referred to wirespeed or
linespeed, which is the maximum speed capability of the particular network. Basic
ethernet wirespeed is up to 10 megabits per second, Fast Ethernet is up to 100
megabits per second, and Gigabit Ethernet is capable of transmitting data over a
network at a rate of up to 1,000 megabits per second. The newest Ethernet is referred
to as 10 Gigabit Ethernet and is capable of transmitting data over a network at a rate of
up to 10,000 megabits per second. As speed has increased, design constraints and
design requirements have become more and more complex with respect to following
appropriate design and protocol rules and providing a low cost, commercially viable
solution.</p>
    <p num="0003">Referring to the OSI 7 layer reference model discussed previously, the
higher layers typically have more information. Various types of products are available
for performing switching related functions at various levels of the OSI model. Hubs or
repeaters operate at layer one, and essentially copy and "broadcast" incoming data to a
plurality of spokes of the hub. Repeaters in their most generic form have a plurality of
ports. Data received in an active receive port is repeated with signal amplitude and
timing restored on the re transmitted or repeated waveforms to all other ports except for 
the active receive port. If the repeater detects activity from two or more ports, this
constitutes a collision, and the repeater will send a jam pattern on all ports, including the
active receive ports.</p>
    <p num="0004">Dual speed hubs operate at two speeds requiring a mechanism capable of
bridging or forwarding data across two separate networks operating at different speeds.
Layer two switching related devices are typically referred to as multiport bridges, and
are capable of bridging two separate networks operating at different speeds. Bridges
can build a table of forwarding rules based upon which MAC (media access controller)
addresses exist on which ports of the bridge, and pass packets which are destined for
an address which is located on an opposite side of the bridge. Bridges typically utilize
what is known as the "spanning tree" algorithm to eliminate potential data loops; a data
loop is a situation wherein a packet endlessly loops in a network looking for a particular
address. The spanning tree algorithm defines a protocol for preventing data loops.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION:</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0005">The present invention includes a system for policing traffic of packet
transfer in a hub. The system includes a first circuit and a second circuit and a first data
line connecting the first circuit to the second circuit, wherein data is transmitted within
and between the first circuit and the second circuit across said first data line. A second
data line connects the first circuit to the second circuit, wherein data is transmitted
within and between the first circuit and the second circuit across the second data line. A
monitor monitors the first data line to determine when an amount of data being 
transmitted on the first data line within the first circuit has reached a threshold. A
blocking mechanism prevents data from being transmitted on the first data line from the
first circuit to the second circuit when the amount of data being transmitted on the first
data line has reached the threshold.</p>
    <p num="0006">In another embodiment, The invention include a method for controlling
data flow. The method includes the steps of transmitting data across a first data line
from a first circuit to a second circuit and within the first and second circuits. Data is
transmitted across a second data line from the first circuit to the second circuit and
within the first and second circuits. The first data line is monitored to determine when
an amount of data being transmitted within the first circuit on the first data line has
reached a threshold. Data is prevented from being transmitted on the first data line
from the first circuit to the second circuit when the amount of data being transmitted on
the first data line has reached the threshold.</p>
    <p num="0007">The invention in another embodiment includes a system for controlling
data flow. The system includes a means for transmitting data across a first data line
from a first circuit to a second circuit, and a means for transmitting data across a second
data line from the first circuit to the second circuit. A means is provided for monitoring
the first data line to determine when an amount of data being transmitted within the first
circuit on the first data line has reached a threshold, and a means is provided for
preventing data from being transmitted on the first data line from the first circuit to the 
second circuit when the amount of data being transmitted on the first data line has
reached said threshold.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS:</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0008">The objects and features of the invention will be more readily understood
with reference to the following description and the attached drawings, wherein:
<sl><li>Figure 1 is a block diagram of two internal state machines that can operate at
10Mbps and 100Mbps in accordance with one embodiment of the invention;</li><li>Figure 2 is a flow diagram of the process steps in accordance with one
embodiment of the invention.</li></sl></p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS:</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0009">Modern integrated circuits can have multiple ports that support different
data transfer rates for transmitting and receiving data. FIG. 1 is an illustration of a dual
speed hub of the invention having two internal state machines or dual speed hubs A
and B. State machine A can have a plurality of ports that can support data transfer
rates of 10 Mbps and 100 Mbps. Each of the ports can have a physical element (PHY)
that can be connected to a twisted pair interface using a variety of transmit and receive
protocols such as the IEEE 10/100Base T for example. In one embodiment of the
invention, each of the plurality of ports can support 10/100Base T copper media PHYs.
State machine B can also have a plurality of ports that can support 10/100Base T
copper media PHYs. Thus, the two state machines can operate at 10Mbps and
100Mbps. </p>
    <p num="0010">Stations can be connected to each of the plurality of ports in each of the
state machines A and B. As illustrated in FIG. 1, the first state machine A can have
three stations 10M A, 10M B and 10M C. Each of the stations can be connected to one
of the 10/100 PHYs. A station 100M D can also be connected to one of the 10/100
PHYs. Likewise the second state machine B can have stations 10M E, 10M F and 10M
G. Each of the stations can be connected to one of the 10/100 PHYs. A station 100M
H can also be connected to one of the 10/100 PHYs.</p>
    <p num="0011">In each of the state machines A and B, switching logic can be connected
to each of the plurality of 10/100 PHYs to perform various functions for each incoming
packet of data. The switching logic can get information from the packet in order to
transmit the packet more efficiently. For instance, the switching logic can associate
packets with a port to which the packets are destined to be sent. Associating the packet
with ports to which the packets are to be sent and storing these destinations in a table
for future use can be useful in speeding up the processing time needed to send a
packet to a particular destination. By storing the destination, a packet can be sent
directly to a destination instead of having to send the packet to every port in order to
find the correct destination. The switching logic can also be used in directing a packet
over proper data lines to a designated port.</p>
    <p num="0012">A two port bridge can be connected to the switching logic and can be used
to forward packets to a proper port. In one embodiment of the invention the two port
bridge can be used to forward a packet at either 10Mbps or 100Mbps. </p>
    <p num="0013">A repeater back plane is connected to the two port bridge and can have a
10Mbps data line and a 100Mbps data line. The back plane connects state machines A
and B using a 10M repeater back plane (10M RBP) and 100M repeater back plane
(100M RBP). The 10M RBP can be used to transmit packets between 10M stations and
the 100M RBP can be used to transmit packets between 100M stations. In FIG. 1 for
example, stations 10M A, 10M B, 10M C, 10ME, 10M F, and 10M G are 10M stations
and stations 100M D and 100M H are 100M stations.</p>
    <p num="0014">Each of the state machines have built in auto negotiation capability, which
allows each of the state machines to poll connected nodes and configure itself. State
machine A can be configured to be the master and state machine B can be configured
to be the slave. Each of the stations 10M A, 10M B, 10M C, 100M D, 10M E, 10M F,
10M G, and 100M H can be configured to communicate with each other. In one
embodiment of the invention the bridge in the master state machine A can be enabled
and the bridge in the slave state machine B can be disabled. The bridge can be
configured to process packets using functions specified in IEEE std 802.1D.</p>
    <p num="0015">One of the functions can be to keep a table that associates addresses of
packets with ports to which the packets are to be sent. This function can be referred to
as address learning. For example, if a first packet is being sent from address L on
station 10M A to address M on station 10M E, the 2 port bridge of A can be configured
to associate the first packet as being sent from the port associated with address L on
station 10M A. Since the packet is originating from station 10M A, the port associated 
with address L on station 10M A can be referred to as being the source address (SA).
A source address lookup can be performed which looks up the source address of the
packet in a table such as an address resolution lookup (ARL) table. If the source
address cannot be found in the ARL table, this will result in a source address lookup
failure (SLF). Since there is a SLF, the source address can be learned by associating
address L with the port connected to station 10M A in the ARL table.</p>
    <p num="0016">As addresses are learned, the 10M stations can share the 10M bandwidth
and the 100M stations can share the 100M bandwidth. However when a 10M station is
to communicate with a 100M station or a 100M station is to communicate with a 10M
station, both the 10M bandwidth and the 100M bandwidth can be utilized.</p>
    <p num="0017">In order to transmit a packet from a station to the a destination, a
destination address lookup can be performed by one of the state machines. The ARL
table of the state machine can be checked to determine if there is an entry in the ARL
table associating the destination address with a port of a station. If there is no entry in
the ARL table associating the destination address with a port of a station, this is referred
to as a destination lookup failure (DLF) and the packet can be broadcast or sent to all
ports. For example if the destination address M is not found in the ARL table, the
packet can be broadcast to the ports of all stations. The packet can be broadcast to
ports of stations 10M A, 10M B, 10M C, 10M F, 10M G on the 10M RBP and ports of
stations 100M D and 100M H on the 100M RBP. Thus the packet will eventually be
sent to the proper destination address M on station 10M E. </p>
    <p num="0018">If a packet were being transmitted from station 10M E from address M to
address L, an SA lookup of address M in the ARL table would result in an SLF. The
address M can be learned by associating the address M with the port associated with
station 10M E. Next a DA lookup of the ARL table can result in finding an entry in the
ARL table associating address L with the port connected to station 10M A. Thus, the
step of broadcasting the packet to all ports can be skipped and the packet can be sent
directly to the port associated with station 10M A.</p>
    <p num="0019">One problem that can be encountered is when a high volume of packets
are to be transmitted between ports within a single state machine. For example if
packets are to be transmitted between stations 10M E and 10M F within state machine
B and packets are to be transmitted between stations 10M B and 10M C within state
machine A, the amount of data being transmitted on the 10M RBP can begin to
increase. As the amount of data being transferred increases on the 10M RBP, the more
occurrences of collisions between data being transferred between stations on state
machine B (10M E and 10M F) and state machine A (10M B and 10M C). Thus, the
performance decreases because data is not being transferred efficiently.</p>
    <p num="0020">In order to alleviate the problem, when a threshold of traffic of packets
being transmitted within stations on a state machine over the 10M RBP is met, it can be
beneficial to separate all the 10M stations on state machine A from all the 10M stations
on state machine B. Separating the stations on state machine B from the stations of
state machine A, can be achieved by preventing any data from being transferred 
between stations on state machine A and stations on state machine B over the 10M
RBP. For example state machine B can be the slave with the 2 port bridge in standby
mode and can also have a traffic policing function that monitors the traffic within the
same state machine to determine if the traffic has reached a threshold. This threshold
can be preset at the factory or set by a system administrator or a user. The state
machine A can be the master having a 2 port bridge activated to forward packets on the
10M RBP and 100M RBP. When the traffic policing function determines that the traffic
on the 10M RBP has met a threshold, the bridge on the state machine can be set be in
forwarding mode.</p>
    <p num="0021">For example, if the traffic policing function on state machine B determines
that the traffic between stations 10M E and 10M F has reached a threshold, the bridge
on state machine B can be set to a forwarding mode. This will prevent any data from
being transferred over the 10M RBP to state machine A separating stations 10M A, 10M
B and 10M C on A from stations 10M E, 10M F and 10M G on state machine B. Thus,
the traffic on stations 10M A, 10M B and 10M C can be localized and the traffic on
stations 10M E, 10M F and 10M G can be localized thereby preserving the overall
performance of each state machine, especially for 10Mbps transmissions. However,
this localization will not prevent stations 10M A, 10M B and 10M C from transmitting
packets to stations 10M E, 10M F and 10M G.</p>
    <p num="0022">Transmission of packets between stations 10M A, 10M B and 10M C on
state machine A and stations 10M E, 10M F and 10M G on state machine B can be 
accomplished by using the 100M RBP. For example, traffic between station 10M A on
state machine A and 10M G on stat machine B can be transferred to the 100M RBP
bridge on state machine A to the 100M RBP bridge on state machine B. The bridge on
state machine B can then transfer the packet to the 10M RBP on state machine B to
communicate only with stations 10M E, 10M F and 10M G on state machine B. In the
case of traffic between stations 10M A and 10M D, the 100M RBP can be used to
handle the traffic between stations 10M A and 100M D without having to transmit
packets on the 10M RBP on state machine B, since the bridge of state machine B can
be configured to know that station 100M D is not located on a 10M RBP.</p>
    <p num="0023">When the traffic policing function determines that the traffic has fallen
below the threshold, the bridge of state machine B can be put into standby mode and
stations 10M A, 10M B and 10M C on state machine A and stations 10M E, 10M F and
10M G on state machine B can be combined again to share the 10M RBP. Thus, traffic
between station 10M A on state machine A and station 10M G on state machine B will
not have to utilize the 100M RBP. Instead, packets can be sent directly between
stations 10M A and 10M G over the 10M RBP. This can improve the overall
performance and latency time.</p>
    <p num="0024">FIG. 2 is a flow diagram of the method steps in one embodiment of the
invention. In step 210 data is being transmitted between a first data line station on a
first circuit and a first data line station on a second circuit across a first data line. For 
example, data can be transferred between station 10M A on state machine A and
station 10M G on state machine B over the 10M RBP.</p>
    <p num="0025">In step 220, data is transmitted between a second data line station one the
first circuit and a second data line station on the second circuit across a second data
line. For example, data can be transferred between station 100M D on state machine A
and station 100M G over the 100M RBP.</p>
    <p num="0026">In step 230 the first data line, 10M RBP, is monitored to determine if the
traffic on the 10M RBP within state machine B has reached a threshold. Once the traffic
reaches a threshold, the transmission of data is prevented instep 240 between the first
data line station 10M A on state machine A and the first data line station 10M G on state
machine B. Furthermore, stations 10M A, 10M B and 10M C on state machine A and
stations 10M E, 10M F and 10M G on state machine B can be separated so that station
10M A, 10M B and 10M C can be localized to communicate with each other on the 10M
RBP on state machine A and stations 10M E, 10M F and 10M G can be localized to
communicate with each other on the 10M RBP on state machine B. When the traffic on
the 10M RBP falls below a threshold the stations are re connected. Stations 10M A,
10M B and 10M C on state machine A and stations 10M E, 10M F and 10M G on state
machine B are not prevented from transmitting data across the 10M RBP. For example,
traffic from station 10M A on state machine A can be directly transferred to station 10M
G on state machine B over the 10M RBP. </p>
    <p num="0027">The invention as described can be used in a dual speed hub to utilize the
full bandwidth of the hub more efficiently. The invention can be particularly useful when
many stations are connected to one of the data lines, such as the 10M RBP as
described. In such a case, it is important to localize traffic within a state machine when
traffic becomes very heavy within the state machine. In one embodiment as described,
when traffic becomes heavy within a state machine on the 10M RBP, traffic is prevented
on the 10M RBP between 10M stations on state machine A and 10M stations on state
machine B. This localizes the 10M stations preventing degraded performance caused
by too many collisions on the 10M RBP. However when the traffic within a state
machine falls below the threshold, all 10M stations are reconnected between state
machines A and B so that traffic between stations on state machine A and stations on
state machine B can be directly transmitted over the 10M RBP.</p>
    <p num="0028">The above discussed configuration of the invention is, in one embodiment,
embodied on a semiconductor substrate, such as silicon, with appropriate
semiconductor manufacturing techniques and based upon a circuit layout which would,
based upon the embodiments discussed above, be apparent to those skilled in the art.
A person of skill in the art with respect to semiconductor design and manufacturing
would be able to implement the various modules, interfaces, and tables, buffers, etc. of
the present invention onto a single semiconductor substrate, based upon the
architectural description discussed above. It would also be within the scope of the
invention to implement the disclosed elements of the invention in discrete electronic 
components, and/or a corroboration of hardware and software components, thereby
taking advantage of the functional aspects of the invention without maximizing the
advantages through the use of a single semiconductor substrate.</p>
    <p num="0029">Although the invention has been described based upon these preferred
embodiments, it would be apparent to those of skilled in the art that certain
modifications, variations, and alternative constructions would be possible, while
remaining within the spirit and scope of the invention. In order to determine the metes
and bounds of the invention, therefore, reference should be made to the appended
claims.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A system for policing traffic of packet transfer in a hub, said system
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a first circuit,</claim-text><claim-text>a second circuit connected to said first circuit;</claim-text><claim-text>a first data line connecting said first circuit to said second circuit, wherein data is
transmitted within and between said first circuit and said second circuit across said first
data line;</claim-text><claim-text>a second data line connecting said first circuit to said second circuit, wherein
data is transmitted within and between said first circuit and said second circuit across
said second data line;</claim-text><claim-text>a monitor that monitors said first data line to determine when an amount of data
being transmitted on said first data line within said first circuit has reached a threshold;</claim-text><claim-text>a blocking mechanism that prevents data from being transmitted on said first
data line from said first circuit to said second circuit when the amount of data being
transmitted on said first data line has reached said threshold.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The system as recited in claim 1,
   wherein said first circuit includes first ports connected to first data line stations
and second ports connected to second data line stations, and
   wherein said second circuit includes third ports connected to first data line
stations, and fourth ports connected to second data line stations,
   wherein data is transmitted on said first data line from said first ports on said first
circuit to said third ports on said second circuit.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The system as recited in claim 1,
   wherein said monitor monitors said first data line to determine when an amount
of data being transmitted on said first data line within said second circuit has reached a
threshold, and
   wherein said blocking mechanism prevents data from being transmitted on said
first data line from said second circuit to said first circuit when the amount of data being
transmitted on said first data line has reached a threshold.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The system as recited in claim 2 further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a transmitter that transmits data across said second data line, from said first
ports on said first circuit, to said third ports on said second circuit, when the amount of
data being transmitted on said first data line has reached said threshold.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The system as recited in claim 1 further comprising:<claim-text><claim-text>a transmitter that transmits data on said first data line to first ports within said first
circuit when the amount of data being transmitted on said first data line has reached
said threshold.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The system as recited in claim 1 further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a transmitter that transmits data on said second data line from said second ports
on said first circuit to said fourth ports on said second circuit.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A method for controlling data flow, said method comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>transmitting data across a first data line from a first circuit to a second circuit and
within said first and second circuits;</claim-text><claim-text>transmitting data across a second data line from said first circuit to said second
circuit and within said first and second circuits;</claim-text><claim-text>monitoring said first data line to determine when an amount of data being
transmitted within said first circuit on said first data line has reached a threshold;</claim-text><claim-text>preventing data from being transmitted on said first data line from said first circuit
to said second circuit when the amount of data being transmitted on said first data line
has reached said threshold.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The method as recited in claim 7 further comprising the step of:<claim-text><claim-text>transmitting data across said first data line to ports within said first circuit when
the amount of data being transmitted on said first data line has reached said threshold.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>The method as recited in claim 7 further comprising the step of:
<claim-text><claim-text>transmitting data across said second data line from said first circuit to said
second circuit when the amount of data being transmitted on said first data line has
reached said threshold.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>The method as recited in claim 7 further comprising the step of:
<claim-text><claim-text>transmitting data on said first data line, from ports connected to first data line
stations on said first circuit, to ports connected to first data line stations on said second
circuit.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>The method as recited in claim 7 further comprising the step of:
<claim-text><claim-text>transmitting data on said second data line, from ports connected to second data
line stations on said first circuit, to ports connected to second data line stations on said
second circuit.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>The method as recited in claim 7 further comprising the step of:
<claim-text><claim-text>preventing data from being transmitted on said first data line, from ports
connected to first data line stations on said first circuit, to ports connected to first data
line stations on said second circuit, when the amount of data being transmitted on said
first data line has reached said threshold.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>The method as recited in claim 7 further comprising the step of:
<claim-text><claim-text>transmitting data on said second data line, from ports connected to first data line
stations on said first circuit, to ports connected to first data line stations on said second
circuit, when the amount of data being transmitted on said first data line has reached
said threshold.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>A system for controlling data flow, said system comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>first transmitting means for transmitting data across a first data line from a first
circuit to a second circuit;</claim-text><claim-text>second transmitting means for transmitting data across a second data line from
said first circuit to said second circuit;</claim-text><claim-text>monitoring means for monitoring said first data line to determine when an amount
of data being transmitted within said first circuit on said first data line has reached a
threshold;</claim-text><claim-text>first preventing means for preventing data from being transmitted on said first
data line from said first circuit to said second circuit when the amount of data being
transmitted on said first data line has reached said threshold.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>The system as recited in claim 14 further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>third transmitting means for transmitting data across ports connected to first data
line to stations within said first circuit when the amount of data being transmitted on said
first data line has reached said threshold.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>The system as recited in claim 14 further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>third transmitting means for transmitting data across said second data line from
said first circuit to said second circuit when the amount of data being transmitted on said
first data line has reached said threshold.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>The system as recited in claim 14 further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>third transmitting means for transmitting data on said first data line from ports
connected to first data line stations on said first circuit to ports connected to first data
line stations on said second circuit.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="18">
      <claim-text>The system as recited in claim 14 further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>third transmitting means for transmitting data on said second data line from ports
connected to second data line stations on said first circuit to ports connected to second
data line stations on said second circuit.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="19">
      <claim-text>The system as recited in claim 14 further comprising:<claim-text><claim-text>second preventing means for preventing data from being transmitted on said first
data line from ports connected to first data line stations on said first circuit to ports
connected to first data line stations on said second circuit when the amount of data
being transmitted on said first data line has reached said threshold.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="20">
      <claim-text>The system as recited in claim 14 further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>third transmitting means for transmitting data on said second data line from ports
connected to first data line stations on said first circuit to ports connected to first data
line stations on said second circuit when the amount of data being transmitted on said
first data line has reached said threshold.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
