<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1246140-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1246140" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="18955224" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021002">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1246140-A2" status="new" fvid="23561356">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1246140</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021002</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02006987-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02006987</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020327</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001101972-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001101972</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010330</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61J   1/14        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61J   1/14        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61J   7/00        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61J   7/00        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61M   5/00        20060101ALI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61M   5/00        20060101CLI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B65G   1/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B65G   1/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B65G   1/04        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B65G   1/04        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G07F  11/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G07F  11/42        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G07F  11/42</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61J7:00F1</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Zuführvorrichtung für Infusions- und Transfusionsflaschen</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Transfusion bottle feed apparatus</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Dispositif d'alimentation de flacons d'infusion ou de transfusion</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YUYAMA MFG CO LTD</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YUYAMA MFG. CO., LTD.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Yuyama Mfg. Co., Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>3-1, Meishinguchi 3-chome</street>
              <city>Toyonaka-shi, Osaka 561-0841</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KITAGAWA REIJI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KODAMA TSUYOSHI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YUYAMA SHOJI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KITAGAWA, REIJI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KODAMA, TSUYOSHI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YUYAMA, SHOJI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>KITAGAWA, REIJI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Yuyama Mfg. Co., Ltd., 3-1, Meishinguchi 3-chome</street>
              <city>Toyonaka-shi, Osaka 561-0841</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>KODAMA, TSUYOSHI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Yuyama Mfg. Co., Ltd., 3-1, Meishinguchi 3-chome</street>
              <city>Toyonaka-shi, Osaka 561-0841</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>YUYAMA, SHOJI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Yuyama Mfg. Co., Ltd., 3-1, Meishinguchi 3-chome</street>
              <city>Toyonaka-shi, Osaka 561-0841</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Selting, Günther, Dipl.-Ing.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Patentanwälte von Kreisler, Selting, Werner Postfach 10 22 41</street>
              <city>50462 Köln</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>The lifter 3 is moved upward until the storage shelf 2
on which the packaging box 9 that contains the transfusion
bottles 13. corresponding to the prescription is stored.
Then, the first conveyor mechanism 8 of the storage shelf 2
and the second conveyor mechanism 14 of the lifter 3 are
driven to convey the packaging box 9 of the transfusion
bottle 13 from the storage shelf 2 to the lifter 3. When
the lifter 3 is moved downward to the lowermost position,
the second conveyor mechanism 14 of the lifter 3 and the
third conveyor mechanism 16 of the receiving table 4 are
driven to convey the packaging box 9 of the transfusion
bottle 13 from the lifter 3 to the receiving table 4.
Subsequently, the grip mechanism 5 is driven to grip the
transfusion bottle 13 in the packaging box 9 on the
receiving table 4 and convey it to the collection container
20. Then, the transfusion bottle 13 is released above the
collection container 20 and contained therein. Thus, the
transfusion bottle 13 is collected with the simple
mechanism operation and rapidly fed to a patient.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="71" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="124"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a transfusion bottle
feed apparatus.</p>
    <p num="0002">Conventionally, there have been proposed various kinds
of transfusion bottle apparatuses in which a plurality of
transfusion bottles are grouped by their kinds and stored
in the apparatus body by putting the plurality of
transfusion bottles on storage shelves so that the
transfusion bottles can be collected in accordance with a
prescription data and fed to a patient.</p>
    <p num="0003">In the conventional transfusion bottle apparatuses,
the transfusion bottles having a capacity of 100 ml more or
less to be frequently used occupy the most part of storage
shelves. Thus, many kind of the transfusion bottles can
not be stored and therefore a plurality of same apparatuses
must be installed. Further, since many kinds of
transfusion bottles exist in admixture, a mechanism for
conveying each transfusion bottle to a collection container
is complicated, whereby it takes long time to collect the
transfusion bottles.</p>
    <p num="0004">Moreover, in the conventional transfusion bottle
apparatuses, since the transfusion bottle is gripped and
dropped into the collection container from a fixed height, 
when a small transfusion bottle having a capacity of 100 ml
more or less is dropped, it damages the transfusion bottles
previously collected in the collection container.</p>
    <heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0005">It is an object of the present invention to provide a
transfusion bottle feed apparatus which can rapidly collect
transfusion bottles with a simple conveying mechanism.</p>
    <p num="0006">It is an another object of the present invention to
provide a transfusion bottle feed apparatus which never
damage the transfusion bottles.</p>
    <p num="0007">In order to achieve the aforementioned objects, the
present invention provides a transfusion bottle feed
apparatuses in which a plurality of transfusion bottles are
grouped by their kinds and stored in an apparatus body so
that the transfusion bottles can be fed to a patient in
accordance with a prescription data, characterized in that:
<sl><li>a plural stages of storage shelves on which packaging
boxes with the upper surface opened are put and stored,
each of the packaging boxes contains same kind of the
transfusion bottles, the packaging boxes in which same kind
of the transfusion bottles are contained being put on the
storage shelves in an up-and-down direction;</li><li>a first conveyor mechanism provided on each of the
storage shelves for conveying the packaging box of the 
transfusion bottle stored on the storage shelves;</li><li>a lifter which can move upward and downward and can
stop at the same levels as that of the storage shelves;</li><li>a second conveyor mechanism provided on the lifter for
receiving and conveying the packaging box of the
transfusion bottle conveyed from the storage shelves by the
first conveyor mechanism;</li><li>a receiving table positioned at the same level of that
of the lifter which moved downward to the lowermost
position;</li><li>a third conveyor mechanism provided on the receiving
table for receiving and conveying the packaging box of the
transfusion bottle conveyed from the lifter by the second
conveyor mechanism; and</li><li>a grip mechanism for gripping the transfusion bottle
in the packaging box positioned on the receiving table,
conveying to a collection container, releasing the
transfusion bottle above the collection container to
contain it therein.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0008">In the present invention having above construction,
the lifter is moved upward until the storage shelf on which
the packaging box that contains the transfusion bottles
corresponding to the prescription is stored. Then, the
first conveyor mechanism of the storage shelf and the
second conveyor mechanism of the lifter are driven to 
convey the packaging box of the transfusion bottle from the
storage shelf to the lifter. When the lifter is moved
downward to the lowermost position, the second conveyor
mechanism of the lifter and the third conveyor mechanism of
the receiving table are driven to convey the packaging box
of the transfusion bottle from the lifter to the receiving
table. Subsequently, the grip mechanism is driven to grip
the transfusion bottle in the packaging box on the
receiving table and convey it to the collection container.
Then, the transfusion bottle is released above the
collection container and contained therein. Thus, the
transfusion bottle is collected with the simple mechanism
operation and rapidly fed to a patient.</p>
    <p num="0009">Preferably, the grip mechanism is provided with a
tilting mechanism for tilting the transfusion bottle
gripped by the grip mechanism; and the gripping mechanism
moves downward until the transfusion bottle tilted by the
tilting mechanism comes into contact with the bottom of the
collection container and releases the transfusion bottle to
move in the horizontal direction. Thus, the transfusion
bottle falls down with the inclined state, reducing the
impact and preventing the transfusion bottles below from
being damaged.</p>
    <p num="0010">Preferably, the receiving table is slidable toward an
opening of the apparatus body; and at the position where 
the receiving table is slid to the opening of the body
apparatus, the third conveyor mechanism discharges the
empty packaging box on the receiving table through the
opening of the apparatus body. Thus, the packaging box
with no transfusion bottle can be easily taken out. In
this case, providing a lever for kicking the rear portion
of the empty packaging box upward allows the packaging box
to be easily discharged through the opening of the
apparatus body.</p>
    <heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
    <p num="0011">Other objects and features of the present invention
will become clear from the following detail description
with reference to the accompanying drawings in which:
<sl><li>Fig. 1 is a front view showing a transfusion bottle
feed apparatus according to the present invention;</li><li>Fig. 2 is a side view of Fig. 1;</li><li>Fig. 3 is a sectional view taken along III - III line
of Fig. 1;</li><li>Fig. 4 is a sectional view taken along IV - IV line of
Fig. 1; and</li><li>Fig. 5 is a side view showing a discharge operation of
empty packaging box.</li></sl></p>
    <heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
    <p num="0012">Figs. 1 and 2 show a transfusion bottle feed apparatus
according to the present invention. In the transfusion
bottle feed apparatus, an apparatus body 1 having a
rectangular frame is provided with a plural stages of
storage shelves 2, a lifter 3, a receiving table 4 and a
grip mechanism 5.</p>
    <p num="0013">The storage shelves 2 are positioned at almost upper
part of the apparatus body 1. Behind the storage shelves 2
is provided a lifting space 6 for the lifter 3 which will
be explained hereinafter. At each storage section (three
sections are shown in the figure) of the respective storage
shelf 2, a plurality of conveyor rollers 8 (first conveyor
mechanism) which are driven to rotate by a motor 7 are
provided so that a packaging box 9 put on the plurality of
conveyor rollers 8 can be conveyed in a back-and-forth
direction of the apparatus body 1. Further, at both the
front side of the conveyor roller 8 positioned at the
foremost position and the rear side of the conveyor roller
8 positioned at the backmost position, stoppers 10, 11 are
provided in order to prevent the packaging box 9 from
dropping off. The rear stopper 11 is arranged so as to be
horizontally laid by a motor 12.</p>
    <p num="0014">On each storage shelf 2, the packaging boxes 9 in each
of which the same kind of the transfusion bottles 13 are
contained are put and stored with the upper surface opened. 
In an up-and-down direction of the storage shelves 2, the
packaging boxes 9 in which the same kind of the transfusion
bottles 13 are contained are stored. Namely, in Fig. 1,
the packaging boxes 9 in which "A" of the transfusion
bottles 13a are contained are stored in the left column;
the packaging boxes 9 in which "B" of the transfusion
bottles 13b are contained are stored in the middle column;
and the packaging boxes 9 in which "C" of the transfusion
bottles 13c are contained are stored in the right column.</p>
    <p num="0015">The lifter 3 is arranged so that it can move upward
and downward in the lifting space 6 behind the storage
shelves 2 and can stop at the same levels as that of the
storage shelves 2. On the lifter 3, as shown in Fig. 3, a
plurality of conveyor belts 14 (second conveyor mechanism)
the number of which corresponds to that of the storage
sections of each storage shelf 2 are provided. Each of the
conveyor belts 14 is driven to rotate by a motor 15 so that
the packaging box 9 put on the conveyor belt 14 can be
conveyed in the same direction as that of the conveyor
rollers 8 of the storage shelf 2.</p>
    <p num="0016">The receiving table 4, as shown in Fig. 4, is disposed
at the same level as the lifter 3 moved downward to the
lowermost position and at the front side of the liter 3.
On the receiving table 4, a plurality of conveyor belts 16
(third conveyor mechanism) are provided in the same manner 
as the conveyor belts 14 of the lifter 3. Each of the
conveyor belts 16 is driven to rotate by a motor 17 so that
the packaging box 9 put on the conveyor belt 17 can be
conveyed in the same direction as that of the conveyor
belts 14 of the lifter 3. Further, the receiving table 4,
as shown in Fig. 5, is slidably moved forward by a motor
(not shown) on guide rails 18 toward an opening formed on
the apparatus body 1. At the front portion of the
receiving table 4, there are provided levers 19 each of
which also serves as a stopper and each of which is
arranged so as to be horizontally laid by a motor not shown.</p>
    <p num="0017">At the front side of the receiving table 4, as shown
in Fig. 4, there is disposed a conveyor path 21 which
passes through the apparatus body 1 and on which a
collection container 20 is conveyed in a left-and-right
direction.</p>
    <p num="0018">The grip mechanism 5, as shown in Figs. 1 and 2,
comprises a grip arm 22 which can grip and release the
mouth portion of the transfusion bottle 13 from upward, a
tilting mechanism 23 which can tilt the grip arm 22 by
about 60 degrees, and a moving mechanism not shown which
can move the grip arm 22 upward and downward and also move
the grip arm 22 in both a back-and-forth direction and a
left-and-right direction.</p>
    <p num="0019">Operation of the transfusion bottle feed apparatus 
having aforementioned construction will be explained
hereinafter.</p>
    <p num="0020">When a prescription data is inputted to a control unit
not shown of the transfusion bottle feed apparatus, the
collection container 20 is conveyed on the conveyor path 21
and positioned in the transfusion bottle feed apparatus.
Then, the lifter 3 is moved upward to the storage shelf 2
on which the packaging boxes 9 that contain the transfusion
bottles 13 corresponding to the prescription are stored.
The conveyor rollers 8 of the storage shelf 2 and the
conveyor belts 14 of the lifter 3 are driven to convey the
packaging box 9 of the transfusion bottle 13 from the
storage shelf 2 to the lifter 3. Consequently, the lifter
3 is moved downward to the lowermost position. The
conveyor belts 14 of the lifter 3 and the conveyor belts 16
of the receiving table 4 are driven to convey the packaging
box 9 of the transfusion bottle 13 from the lifter 3 to the
receiving table 4. Then, the grip mechanism 5 is driven to
grip the transfusion bottle 13 within the packaging box 9
on the receiving table 4. The transfusion bottle 13 is
moved to the collection container 20 and released above the
collection container 20, whereby the transfusion bottle 13
is contained in the collection container 20. Thus, with
the simple operation of the mechanisms, the transfusion
bottle 13 is collected and rapidly fed. </p>
    <p num="0021">When the transfusion bottle 13 is contained in the
collection container 20, as shown in two-dots chain line in
Fig. 1, the grip arm 22 is tilted by about 60 degrees by
the tilting mechanism 23 of the grip mechanism 5 in a state
that the grip arm 22 grips the transfusion bottle 13. With
this state kept, the grip arm 22 is moved downward until
the transfusion bottle 13 comes into contact with the
bottom of the collection container 20. Then, the grip arm
22 releases the transfusion bottle 13 and retreats in a
horizontal direction. Thus, the transfusion bottle 13
falls down with the inclined state, reducing the impact and
preventing the transfusion bottles below from being damaged.</p>
    <p num="0022">When the transfusion bottle 13 in the packaging box 9
becomes shortage, as shown in Figs. 5(a) and 5(b), the
receiving table 4 is slidably moved forward on the guide
rails 18 toward the opening of the apparatus body 1, where
the lever 19 is laid and the transfer belts 16 are driven
to discharge the empty packaging box 9 on the receiving
table 4 through the opening of the apparatus body 1. At
this time, as shown in Fig. 5(c), when the lever 19 is rose
up, the rear portion of the empty packaging box 9 is kicked
upward, allowing the empty packaging box 9 to be easily
discharged through the opening.</p>
    <p num="0023">Although the present invention has been fully
described by way of the examples with reference to the 
accompanying drawing, it is to be noted that here that
various changes and modifications will be apparent to those
skilled in the art. Therefore, unless such changes and
modifications otherwise depart from the spirit and scope of
the present invention, they should be construed as being
included therein.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A transfusion bottle feed apparatuses in which a
plurality of transfusion bottles are grouped by their kinds
and stored in an apparatus body so that the transfusion
bottles can be fed to a patient in accordance with a
prescription data, characterized in that:
<claim-text><claim-text>a plural stages of storage shelves on which packaging
boxes with the upper surface opened are put and stored,
each of the packaging boxes contains same kind of the
transfusion bottles, the packaging boxes in which same kind
of the transfusion bottles are contained being put on the
storage shelves in an up-and-down direction;</claim-text><claim-text>a first conveyor mechanism provided on each of the
storage shelves for conveying the packaging box of the
transfusion bottle stored on the storage shelves;</claim-text><claim-text>a lifter which can move upward and downward and can
stop at the same levels as that of the storage shelves;</claim-text><claim-text>a second conveyor mechanism provided on the lifter for
receiving and conveying the packaging box of the
transfusion bottle conveyed from the storage shelves by the
first conveyor mechanism;</claim-text><claim-text>a receiving table positioned at the same level of that
of the lifter which moved downward to the lowermost
position;</claim-text><claim-text>a third conveyor mechanism provided on the receiving
table for receiving and conveying the packaging box of the
transfusion bottle conveyed from the lifter by the second
conveyor mechanism; and</claim-text><claim-text>a grip mechanism for gripping the transfusion bottle
in the packaging box positioned on the receiving table,
conveying to a collection container, releasing the
transfusion bottle above the collection container to
contain it therein.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The transfusion bottle feed apparatuses as in
claim 1, wherein the grip mechanism is provided with a
tilting mechanism for tilting the transfusion bottle
gripped by the grip mechanism; and the gripping mechanism
moves downward until the transfusion bottle tilted by the
tilting mechanism comes into contact with the bottom of the
collection container and releases the transfusion bottle to
move in the horizontal direction.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The transfusion bottle feed apparatuses as in
claim 1, wherein the receiving table is slidable toward an
opening of the apparatus body; and at the position where
the receiving table is slid to the opening of the body
apparatus, the third conveyor mechanism discharges the
empty packaging box on the receiving table through the
opening of the apparatus body.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The transfusion bottle feed apparatuses as in
claim 3, further comprising a lever for kicking the rear
portion of the empty packaging box upward.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
