<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1250861-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1250861" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="18971433" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021023">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1250861-A1" status="new" fvid="23591373">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1250861</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20021023</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02008734-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02008734</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020418</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001121594-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001121594</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010419</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A43B  13/14        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A43B  13/26        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A43C  15/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A43C  15/02        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A43C  15/16        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">A43C  15/16</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Stollen und Schuh mit Stollen</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Stud and shoe provided with the studs</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Crampon et chaussure avec crampons</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MINEBEA KK</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MINEBEA CO., LTD.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Minebea Co., Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>4106-73 Miyota, Miyota-machi</street>
              <city>Kitasaku-gun, Nagano-ken 3849-2100</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>AKIYAMA MOTOHARU</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HOKKIRIGAWA KAZUO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YOSHIMURA NORIYUKI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>AKIYAMA, MOTOHARU</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HOKKIRIGAWA, KAZUO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YOSHIMURA, NORIYUKI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Akiyama, Motoharu, Minebea Co., Ltd., Karuizawa</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Manufacturing Unit 4106-73 Miyota, Miyota-machi</street>
              <city>Kitasaku-gun, Nagano-ken 3849-2100</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>HOKKIRIGAWA, KAZUO</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>3-1-21, Matsugamisaki</street>
              <city>Yonezawa-shi, Yamagata-ken 992-0053</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Yoshimura, Noriyuki, Minebea Co., Ltd., Karuizawa</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Manufacturing Unit 4106-73 Miyota, Miyota-machi</street>
              <city>Kitasaku-gun, Nagano-ken 3849-2100</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Goddar, Heinz J., Dr.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>FORRESTER &amp;amp; BOEHMERT Pettenkoferstrasse 20-22</street>
              <city>80336 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>IT</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>The invention provides a stud for a shoe, light in weight, and
having a long service life and excellent abrasion resistance, and a
shoe using the same. The stud for the shoe comprises a central
protruding member (1), a seating plate (2), and peripheral binding
members (3). The seating plate (2) is formed of a metallic material,
and the central protruding member (1) or the peripheral binding
members (3) are formed of RB ceramic or CRB ceramic. The shoe is
fabricated by securely attaching the studs to an outsole (5) thereof.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="70" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="76"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a stud for a shoe, and a shoe
using the studs, and more specifically, to a stud for a shoe, light in
weight, and having not only an excellent non-skid performance or
gripping performance but also an excellent walking performance on
a hard surface of a road such as a pavement, a concrete road, and so
forth, or on a hard floor, suitable, particularly, for use in sports
shoes such as golf shoes, soccer shoes, or baseball shoes, spikes,
non-skid shoes for use in cold districts, and so forth, and a shoe
using the same.</p>
    <p num="0002">Studs for shoes, for example, spikes, especially, spikes for use
in sports shoes and non-skid shoes, are required to have excellent
gripping performance and non-skid performance, and such
performances are important from the viewpoint of providing
comfortableness in wearing and safety as well.</p>
    <p num="0003">As a constituent material of such studs, for example, spikes,
and so forth, use is made of a corrosion resistant steel such as
stainless steel and carbon steel, a metallic material such as titanium,
and so forth, and a hard resin.</p>
    <p num="0004">The metallic material is superior in strength, however, it is too
hard as the constituent material of the studs to avoid impact
resistance such as a feeling of a thrust coming up from below when
a user is walking on a hard surface of a pavement or a concrete road,
thereby aggravating discomfort of the user. In addition, there are
also problems that a steel based material used in the studs renders 
shoes heavier because of its high specific gravity while titanium is
costly. Further, there is a problem with the hard resin that it has
poor abrasion resistance and a short durability.</p>
    <p num="0005">It is an object of the invention to overcome such drawbacks
of the conventional studs as described above, and to provide a stud
for a shoe, light in weight, having a long service life and excellent
abrasion resistance, and a shoe using the same.</p>
    <p num="0006">RB ceramic for us in carrying out an embodiment of a stud
according to the invention is a carbonaceous material obtained by
utilizing rice bran, produced in quantity of 900, 000 tons a year in
Japan and in quantity of as much as 33 million tons a year
throughout the world, and has been well known by researches
carried out by Mr. Kazuo Hokkirigawa, the first inventor of the
present invention (refer to "Functional Material", May issue, 1997,
Vol. 17, No. 5, pp. 24 ∼ 28).</p>
    <p num="0007">In this literature, reference is made to a carbon material
(hereinafter referred to as RB ceramic) and the preparation thereof,
in which the carbonaceous material is obtained by mixing and
kneading defatted bran derived from rice bran with a thermosetting
resin before kneading, followed by drying a compact obtained by
pressure forming a kneaded mixture, and subsequently, baking the
dried compact as dried in an atmosphere of an inert gas.</p>
    <p num="0008">The RB ceramic and a new ceramic (CRB ceramic as described
later on) representing an improvement on the RB ceramic, for use in
an embodiment of a stud according to the invention, are ceramic
materials friendly to nature, obtained by using rice bran as raw
material, and by mixing defatted bran derived from the rice bran 
with a thermosetting resin before baking a mixture. These
materials have excellent properties as described below:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>Higher hardness</li><li>Smaller expansion coefficient</li><li>porous micro structure</li><li>good electric conductivity</li><li>small specific gravity and light weight</li><li>very small friction coefficient</li><li>excellent abrasion resistance</li><li>easy to form and easy to fabricate in a die</li><li>ceramic materials having varying characteristics can be produced
by blending with various kinds of resins</li><li>the materials being made of rice bran, they have little adverse
effect on global environment, leading to conservation of natural
resources.</li></ul></p>
    <p num="0009">The new ceramic described above is an improved material of
the RB ceramic, and is a class of ceramic (referred to as the CRB
ceramic) that is obtained by mixing defatted bran derived from rice
bran with a thermosetting resin. More particularly, the defatted
bran derived from rice bran and a thermosetting resin are mixed
and kneaded, subjecting a kneaded mixture thus obtained to a
primary baking in an inert gas at a temperature in a range of 700 to
1000°C, and pulverizing the kneaded mixture after the primary
baking into carbonized powders passing through a 100-mesh sieve.</p>
    <p num="0010">The carburized powders and the thermosetting resin are
further mixed and kneaded, pressure forming a kneaded mixture
into a compact at a pressure in a range of 20 to 30 MPa, and
subjecting the compact again to a heat treatment in an inert gas 
atmosphere at a temperature in a range of 100 to 1100°C. The
CRB ceramic differs largely from the RB ceramic in that, in contrast
with the RB ceramic having a contraction ratio of the dimensions of
the compact obtained by pressure forming to those of a finished
compact at as high as 25%, the CRB ceramic has a contraction ratio
in the order of not more than 3%, which is very small.</p>
    <p num="0011">The inventors have discovered that these ceramic materials
are light in weight and have a long service life, excellent abrasion
resistance, insusceptibilty to damage, and excellent workability, so
that the same are suitable as a constituent material of a stud, for
use in combination with a metallic material. The invention has
been developed based on such knowledge as described above.</p>
    <p num="0012">More specifically, the embodiment of the stud according to the
invention comprises a central protruding member 1, a seating plate
2, and peripheral binding members 3, wherein the central
protruding member 1 and the seating plate 2 are formed of a
metallic material, respectively, and the peripheral binding members
3 are formed of the RB ceramic or the CRB ceramic.</p>
    <p num="0013">Further, with a stud according to another embodiment of the
invention, the central protruding member 1 and the peripheral
binding members 3 may be formed of the RB ceramic or the CRB
ceramic.</p>
    <p num="0014">Furthermore, the invention provides a shoe using these studs
for a shoe.
<sl><li>Fig. 1 is a perspective view of an embodiment of a stud
according to the invention;</li><li>Fig. 2 is a cross sectional view of the stud taken on line b - b in 
Fig. 1;</li><li>Fig. 3 is a side view of the stud shown in Fig. 1;</li><li>Fig. 4 is a perspective view of a shoe with the studs securely
attached thereto; and</li><li>Fig. 5 is a side view of a shoe with the studs securely attached
thereto.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0015">RB ceramic material and CRB ceramic material for use in
carrying out an embodiment of a stud according to the invention are
made of defatted bran derived from rice bran, as a main raw
material, and a thermosetting resin.</p>
    <p num="0016">The defatted bran may be of either a local domestic origin or a
foreign origin regardless of the kind of rice.</p>
    <p num="0017">Further, for the thermosetting resin, any thermosetting resin
may be used as long as it has thermosetting property, and typical
examples thereof include phenol resin, diaryl phthalate resin,
unsaturated polyester resin, epoxy resin, polyimide resin, and
triazine resin. In particular, phenol resin is preferably used.</p>
    <p num="0018">Furthermore, a thermoplastic resin, such as a polyamide and
so forth, can be used in combination with the thermosetting resin
provided that it is used without departing from the spirit and scope
of the invention.</p>
    <p num="0019">A mixing ratio of the defatted bran to the thermosetting resin
is 50 to 90 : 50 to 10 by weight, however, the mixing ratio of 70 to
80 : 30 to 20 is preferably adopted.</p>
    <p num="0020">Next, a method of producing the CRB ceramic material is
briefly described hereinafter. The method comprises the steps of
mixing and kneading defatted bran derived from rice bran with a 
thermosetting resin before kneading, subjecting a kneaded mixture
thus obtained to a primary baking in an inert gas at a temperature
in a range of 700 to 1000°C, pulverizing the kneaded mixture after
the primary baking into carbonized powders, mixing and kneading
the carbonized powders with a thermosetting resin before kneading,
pressure forming a kneaded mixture thus obtained into a compact at
a pressure in a range of 20 to 30 MPa, and subjecting the compact
again to a heat treatment at a temperature in a range of 100 to
1100°C in an inert gas atmosphere.</p>
    <p num="0021">A thermosetting resin in a liquid state, having a relatively
small molecular weight, is desirable as the thermosetting resin for
use in the primary baking.</p>
    <p num="0022">A rotary kiln is normally used in carrying out the primary
baking, and baking time is in a range of 40 to 120 min. A mixing
ratio of the carbonized powders obtained by the primary baking to
the thermosetting resin is 50 to 90 : 50 to 10 by weight, however, the
mixing ratio of 70 to 80 : 30 to 20 is preferably adopted.</p>
    <p num="0023">The kneaded mixture of the carbonized powders and the
thermosetting resin is pressure formed into the compact at a
pressure in a range of 20 to 30 MPa, preferably, in a range of 21 to
25 MPa. A die for use is preferably at a temperature of about
150°C.</p>
    <p num="0024">For the heat treatment, a well controlled electric furnace is
normally employed, and heat treatment time is in a range of about
60 to 360 min.</p>
    <p num="0025">A heat treatment temperature is preferably in a range of 100
to 1100 °C, and a warming rate up to heat treatment temperature is
required to be relatively moderate up to 500 °C. In terms of more 
specific-values, the warming rate is in a range of 0. 5 to 2 °C /min,
and is preferably about 1 °C.</p>
    <p num="0026">Further, in lowering the temperature of the compact after
baked by the heat treatment in this manner, a cooling rate is
required to be relatively moderate until reaching 500°C. Upon the
temperature dropping below 500°C, the compact is left to cool by
itself.</p>
    <p num="0027">In terms of more specific values, the cooling rate is in a range
of 0.5 to 4°C / min, and is preferably about 1°C / min.</p>
    <p num="0028">Further, the inert gas used at the time of the primary baking
as well as the secondary heat treatment may be any gas selected
from the group consisting of helium, argon, neon, and nitrogen gas,
however, nitrogen gas is preferably used.</p>
    <p num="0029">The stud according to the embodiment of the invention can be
used as appropriate in combination with a conventional metal based
stud, a hard resin based stud, a stud made of other synthetic resins,
or a stud made of an elastic or a soft material, such as natural
rubber, synthetic rubber, and other elastomers.</p>
    <p num="0030">Further, for an outsole of a shoe, use is preferably made of a
synthetic resin, a synthetic rubber, natural rubber, or a synthetic
elastomer, in common use as a conventional material for the outsole.</p>
    <p num="0031">The synthetic resin may be any synthetic resin, if hard and
strong to a degree, selected from the group consisting of hard
polyethylene, polyolefin such as polypropylene, polyamide such as
nylon 66, polycarbonate, and so forth.</p>
    <p num="0032">Further, examples of the synthetic rubber include butadiene
rubber, styrene-butadiene rubber, acrylonitrile- butadiene rubber,
isoprene rubber, chloroprene rubber, butyl rubber, ethylene-polypropylene-diene 
rubber, acrylic rubber, urethane rubber, and
so forth.</p>
    <p num="0033">With the stud according to the embodiment of the invention,
protruded parts thereof are preferably made up of a main
protruding member 1 disposed at the center, and protrusions of
peripheral binding members 3 disposed around the main protruding
member 1, as shown in Figs. 1 to 3, from the viewpoint of avoiding
concentration of force on the main protruding member 1 at the
center when shoes are worn by a user. Further, the main
protruding member 1 can be formed in the shape of a pointed
conical protrusion although not shown in the figures.</p>
    <p num="0034">According to the invention, the central protruding member 1
and a seating plate 2 can be formed of a metallic material, and the
peripheral binding members 3 can be formed of the RB ceramic or
the CRB ceramic, or the central protruding member 1 and the
peripheral binding members 3 can be formed of the RB ceramic or
the CRB ceramic.</p>
    <p num="0035">Otherwise, the central protruding member 1 and the seating
plate 2 can be formed of a metallic material, and integrally with
each other, for use in combination with the peripheral binding
members 3 formed of the RB ceramic or the CRB ceramic.</p>
    <p num="0036">Further, the seating plate 2 can be formed of a metallic
material, and the central protruding member 1 and the peripheral
binding members 3 can be formed of the RB ceramic or the CRB
ceramic, and integrally with each other in such a way as to wrap up
the seating plate 2. In this case, the central protruding member 1
may be changed in shape depending on stress to which the same is
subjected. For example, an angularity of the conical protrusion 
thereof can be changed in a range of an acute angle to an obtuse
angle to prevent the central protruding member 1 from being
excessively loaded. Furthermore, it is also possible to render the
apex of the conical protrusion flat so as to cause a load imposed
thereon to be dispersed or to form the apex thereof in the shape of a
plurality of conical protrusions as ranged.</p>
    <p num="0037">Further, the RB ceramic or the CRB ceramic for use in
carrying out the embodiment of the stud according to the invention
is light in weight, and has a characteristic of excellent abrasion
resistance, however, one subjected to the secondary heat treatment
at a high temperature has susceptibility to buckling when a large
load is imposed thereon because it is slightly lower in mechanical
strength. With the present invention, it is therefore preferable to
form the seating plate from a metallic material having high
mechanical strength for use in combination with the central
protruding member and the peripheral binding members, formed
from a metallic material or hard resin other than the metallic
material.</p>
    <p num="0038">In the case of using the CRB ceramic in carrying out the
embodiment of the stud according to the invention, the CRB ceramic
obtained by baking at a low temperature lower than about 500°C
generally has characteristics such as toughness and excellent
mechanical property while the same obtained by baking at a high
temperature not lower than 600°C generally has characteristics
such as high porosity, high hardness, and light weight, so that it is
possible to make selective use thereof depending on required
properties of a given stud.</p>
    <p num="0039">The embodiments of the invention are summed up as follows: <sl><li>(1) A stud for a shoe, comprising a central protruding member, a
seating plate, and peripheral binding members, wherein the seating
plate is formed of a metallic material, and the central protruding
member or the peripheral binding members are formed of RB
ceramic or CRB ceramic.</li><li>(2) A stud for a shoe as set forth in item (1) above, wherein the
seating plate and the central protruding member are formed of the
RB ceramic or the CRB ceramic, integrally with each other.</li><li>(3) A stud for a shoe as set forth in item (1) above, wherein the
seating plate, the central protruding member, and the peripheral
binding members are formed of the RB ceramic or the CRB ceramic,
integrally with each other.</li><li>(4) A stud for a shoe as set forth in any one of items (1) to (3) above,

wherein the CRB ceramic is obtained by a secondary heat treatment
applied at a temperature in a range of 200 to 1000°C.</li><li>(5) A stud for a shoe as set forth in any one of items (1) to (4) above,

wherein the peripheral binding members are each provided with a
peripheral protrusion lower in profile than a protrusion of the
central protruding member.</li><li>(6) A stud for a shoe as set forth in any one of items (1) to (5) above,

wherein the protrusion of the central protruding member has an
angularity of an optional angle in a range of an acute angle to an
obtuse angle</li><li>(7) A stud for a shoe as set forth in any one of items (1) to (6) above,

wherein the protrusion of the central protruding member is in any
one shape selected from the group of a shape having one apex of the
protrusion and a shape having a plurality of apexes thereof.</li><li>(8) A shoe provided with a plurality of studs each comprising a 
central protruding member made of metal, disposed on parts of an
outsole thereof, and a plurality of the studs as set forth in any one of
items (1) to (7) above, disposed on other parts of the outsole, each
comprising the central protruding member made of the RB ceramic
or the CRB ceramic, and lower in profile than the studs comprising
the central protruding member made of metal.</li><li>(9) A shoe as set forth in item (8) above, for use in golf, soccer,
baseball or track.</li></sl></p>
    <heading>Embodiments</heading>
    <heading>(production of a precursor of the CRB ceramic)</heading>
    <p num="0040">The precursor of the CRB ceramic for use in fabrication of a
constituent member making up a main protruded part of a stud for a
shoe was produced as follows:

75 kg of defatted bran derived from rice bran was mixed and
kneaded with 25 kg of phenol resin (resol) in liquid state while
heating both to 50 to 60°C. A plastic and homogeneous mixture
was obtained.</p>
    <p num="0041">The mixture was subjected to a primary baking at 900°C in a
nitrogen atmosphere in a rotary kiln for 60 minutes. Subsequently,
a baked product thus obtained was screened through a 100-mesh
sieve, thereby obtaining carbonized powders 50 to 250 mm in
particle diameter.</p>
    <p num="0042">75kg of thus obtained carbonized powder was mixed and
kneaded with 25kig of phenol resin (resol) in solid state while
heating both to 100 to 150°C, thereby obtaining the precursor of the
CRB ceramic, composed of a plastic homogeneous mixture.</p>
    <p num="0043">The embodiments of the invention are described hereinafter
with reference to the accompanying drawings </p>
    <heading>Embodiment 1</heading>
    <p num="0044">There is shown an example of fabricating a stud(wherein a
central protruding member 1 and a seating plate 2 are made of
stainless steel, and peripheral binding members 3 are made of the
CRB ceramic) according to an embodiment 1 of the invention.</p>
    <p num="0045">The stud comprises a central protruding member 1 and a
seating plate 2, both made of stainless steel, and peripheral binding
members 3 made of the CRB ceramic. The central protruding
member 1 is comprised of a stud protrusion 11 substantially in the
shape of a hexagonal prism, and a flange 12 circular in shape,
provided integrally therewith, around the periphery of the lower
end thereof. The flange 12 is provided with a plurality of holes 13
defined therein, and the stud protrusion 11 is provided with slender
grooves 14, defined in the bottom face thereof, for fitting onto small
protrusions 22 of the seating plate 2.</p>
    <p num="0046">The seating plate 2 comprises a disk 21, a plurality of the
small protrusions 22 protruding from the upper face of the disk 21,
and a threaded part 23 for fixedly attaching the stud to an outsole
of the shoe, provided on the underside of the disk 21 in such a way
as to hang therefrom. The small protrusions 22 are inserted into
the slender grooves 14 of the stud protrusion 11, respectively. The
disk 21 is provided with a plurality of holes defined at positions
thereon, corresponding to respective positions of the plurality of the
holes 13 of the flange 12.</p>
    <p num="0047">The central protruding member 1 and the seating plate 2 are
linked together with the peripheral binding members 3 in the
following manner. First, the seating plate 2 is covered directly by
the central protruding member 1, and the stud protrusion 11 is 
brought into intimate contact with the disk 21. Since a height of
the small protrusions 22 of the seating plate 2 is substantially
equivalent to a depth of the slender grooves 14 of the stud
protrusion 11, both parts come into intimate contact with each other.</p>
    <p num="0048">Subsequently, the central protruding member 1 integrated
with the seating plate 2 excluding the threaded part 23 is placed
inside a die in the shape of the central protruding member 1 and the
seating plate 2 excluding the threaded part 23, and the precursor of
the CRB ceramic is injected therein to be pressure formed into a
compact in the shape shown in Figs. 1 and 2 at a pressure of 22 MPa.
The die for use is at a temperature of about 150°C. The compact is
taken out of the die, and is subjected to a heat treatment in a
nitrogen atmosphere whereby the compact is heated at a warming
rate of 1°C / min up to 500°C, held at 500°C for 60 min, heat treated
at 800°C for about 120 min before lowering the temperature of the
compact at a cooling rate in a range of 2 to 3°C / min until reaching
500°C and upon the temperature dropping below 500°C, the
compact is left to cool by itself. The thickness of the peripheral
binding members 3, on the side of the seating plate 2, is rendered
thicker on the peripheral side of the disk 21, and thinner on the
center side thereof.</p>
    <p num="0049">A protrusion of the respective peripheral binding members 3
is made up of a protrusion in the shape of an elliptical hemisphere,
and a protrusion in the shape of a truncated cone, disposed at the
center of the apex of the former, and is as shown in Fig.1 to Fig.3,
arranged so as to surround the stud protrusion 11 which is the
protruded part of the central protruding member 1, and so as to be
lower in profile than the protruded part described. </p>
    <p num="0050">The central protruding member 1 is securely bonded to the
seating plate 2 with the peripheral binding members 3, and in
addition, concentration of force towards the central protruding
member 1 is prevented by the protrusion of the respective peripheral
binding members 3. Furthermore, the binding members 3 can
fulfill a function similar to that of a packing upon attaching the stud
to the outsole of a shoe by rendering the thickness thereof, on the
side of the seating plate 2, thicker on the peripheral side of the disk
21, and thinner on the center side thereof.</p>
    <heading>Embodiment 2</heading>
    <heading>(a central protruding member and a seating plate are formed of
metal, and integrally with each other)</heading>
    <p num="0051">A stud is fabricated in a manner similar to that for the stud
according to the embodiment 1 of the invention except that use is
made of a stainless steel structure fabricated by forming the central
protruding member integrally with the seating plate in the die.</p>
    <heading>Embodiment 3</heading>
    <heading>(an embodiment wherein a central protruding member and
peripheral binding members are formed of the CRB ceramic,
integrally with each other)</heading>
    <p num="0052">A seating plate 2 is prepared, and is placed in a die
corresponding to the shape of a central protruding member 1 and
peripheral binding members 3 (a threaded part 23 is not placed in
the die).</p>
    <p num="0053">Subsequently, the same precursor of the CRB ceramic as
produced according to the embodiment 1 is pressure formed into a
compact at a pressure of 25 MPa. The die for use is at a
temperature of about 150°C. </p>
    <p num="0054">The compact is taken out of the die, and is subjected to a heat
treatment in a nitrogen atmosphere whereby the compact is heated
at a warming rate of 1°C / min up to 500°C, held at 500°C for 60
min, heat treated at 900°C for about 120 min. Thereafter, the
temperature of the compact is lowered at a cooling rate in a range of
2 to 3°C / min until reaching 500°C and upon the temperature
dropping below 500°C, the compact is left to cool by itself.</p>
    <p num="0055">A stud is obtained wherein the seating plate 2 made of metal
is formed integrally with the central protruding member 1 and the
peripheral binding members 3, both made of the CRB ceramic.</p>
    <heading>Embodiment 4</heading>
    <heading>(fabrication of golf shoes)</heading>
    <p num="0056">As shown in Fig. 4, the stud fabricated according to the
embodiment 1 or 2 is screwed into a female thread 41 of a fixture
mount 4 of an outsole 5 of a shoe . The constituent material of the
outsole 5 is hard rubber. Golf shoes comfortable to wear, having
excellent gripping performance and non-skid performance are
obtained. In the figure, a central protruding member 1 is not
shown.</p>
    <heading>Embodiment 5</heading>
    <heading>(fabrication of golf shoes using studs made of the CRB ceramic in
combination with studs made of metal)</heading>
    <p num="0057">As shown in Fig. 5, with a golf shoes according to an
embodiment 5, spikes P made of stainless steel, taller than studs
made of the CRB ceramic, are disposed in parts of an outsole 5, on
which the weight of a user rests while studs S, as other studs,
comprising the central protruding member formed of the CRB
ceramic, according to the embodiment 3, are disposed. </p>
    <p num="0058">Golf shoes, light in weight and comfortable to wear, are
obtained wherein a good gripping effect of the spikes made of
stainless steel is exhibited when a user is walking on a concrete or
cart road, and an excellent non-skid performance effected by
gripping of the grass with the studs made of the CRB ceramic is
exhibited when the user is walking on the grass.</p>
    <p num="0059">Thus, the stud and shoes using the studs according the
embodiments of the invention are able to provide shoes light in
weight and comfortable to wear, having a long service life, an
excellent abrasion resistance, excellent gripping performance, and
excellent non-skid performance.</p>
    <p num="0060">The features disclosed in the foregoing description, in the
claims and/or in the accompanying drawings may, both separately
and in any combination thereof, be material for realising the
invention in diverse forms thereof.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A stud for a shoe, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a central protruding member (1);</claim-text><claim-text>a seating plate (2); and</claim-text><claim-text>peripheral binding members (3); wherein the seating plate (2)
is formed of a metallic material, and the central protruding member
(1) or the peripheral binding members (3) are formed of RB ceramic
or CRB ceramic.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A stud for a shoe according to Claim 1, wherein the seating
plate (2) and the central protruding member (1) are formed of the
RB ceramic or the CRB ceramic, and integrally with each other.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A stud for a shoe according to Claim 1, wherein the seating
plate (2), the central protruding member (1), and the peripheral
binding members (3) are formed of the RB ceramic or the CRB
ceramic, and integrally with each other.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A stud for a shoe according to any one of Claims 1 to 3,
wherein the CRB ceramic is obtained by a secondary heat treatment
applied at a temperature in a range of 200 to 1000°C.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A stud for a shoe according to any one of Claims 1 to 4,
wherein the peripheral binding members (3) are each provided with
a peripheral protrusion lower in profile than a protrusion (11) of the
central protruding member (1).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A stud for a shoe according to any one of Claims 1 to 5,
wherein the protrusion (11) of the central protruding member (1)
has an angularity of an optional angle in a range of an acute angle
to an obtuse angle.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A stud for a shoe according to any one of Claims 1 to 6,
wherein the protrusion (11) of the central protruding member (1) is
in any one shape selected from the group of a shape having one
apex of the protrusion (11) and a shape having a plurality of apexes
thereof.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A shoe provided with a plurality of studs each comprising a
central protruding member (1) made of metal, disposed on parts of
an outsole (5) thereof, and a plurality of the studs according to any
one of Claims 1 to 7, disposed on other parts of the outsole (5), each
comprising the central protruding member (1) made of the RB
ceramic or the CRB ceramic, and lower in profile than the studs
comprising the central protruding member (1) made of metal.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>A shoe according to Claim 8, for use in golf, soccer, baseball
or track.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
