<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1223211-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1223211" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="18875627" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020717">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1223211-A1" status="new" fvid="23490776">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1223211</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20020717</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02000595-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02000595</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020110</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001007956-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001007956</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010116</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B32B   7/02        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B32B   7/02        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C09K  19/38        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C09K  19/38        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G02B   5/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G02B   5/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G02B   5/30        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G02B   5/30        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G02F   1/13        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G02F   1/1335      20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G09F   9/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G09F   9/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K  19/38B4B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G02B   5/02</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G02F   1/1335P</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Optische Streuscheibe, optisches Element und Flüssigkristallanzeige</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Optical diffusing plate, optical element and liquid crystal display</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Plaque diffusant la lumière, élément optique et écran à cristaux liquides</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NITTO DENKO CORP</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NITTO DENKO CORPORATION</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Nitto Denko Corporation</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1-1-2, Shimohozumi</street>
              <city>Ibaraki-shi, Osaka 567-8680</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MIYATAKE MINORU</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MOCHIZUKI AMANE</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NAKANISHI SADAHIRO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NAKANO SHUSAKU</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MIYATAKE, MINORU</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MOCHIZUKI, AMANE</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NAKANISHI, SADAHIRO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NAKANO, SHUSAKU</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>MIYATAKE, MINORU</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>c/o Nitto Denko Corporation, 1-1-2, Shimohozumi</street>
              <city>Ibaraki-shi, Osaka 567-8680</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>MOCHIZUKI, AMANE</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>c/o Nitto Denko Corporation, 1-1-2, Shimohozumi</street>
              <city>Ibaraki-shi, Osaka 567-8680</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>NAKANISHI, SADAHIRO</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>c/o Nitto Denko Corporation, 1-1-2, Shimohozumi</street>
              <city>Ibaraki-shi, Osaka 567-8680</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>NAKANO, SHUSAKU</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>c/o Nitto Denko Corporation, 1-1-2, Shimohozumi</street>
              <city>Ibaraki-shi, Osaka 567-8680</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Sajda, Wolf E., Dipl.-Phys.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>MEISSNER, BOLTE &amp;amp; PARTNER Widenmayerstrasse 48</street>
              <city>80538 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>NL</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>An optical diffusing plate is disclosed that gives an
anisotropic scattering of a linearly polarized light and has
an excellent diffusion property in a scattering direction,
and that is suitable for improving visibility and brightness
of a liquid crystal display. The optical diffusing plate
comprises a birefringent film (1) and minute domains (e)
with birefringence characteristics different from those of the
birefringent film (1) in a dispersed state in the
birefringent film (1),

wherein the minute domains (e) comprise a side chain type
liquid crystal polymer comprising a monomer unit
containing a liquid crystalline fragment side chain and another
monomer unit containing a non-liquid crystalline fragment
side chain, and

wherein a first refractive index difference (Δn1), between
the birefringent film (1) and the minute domains (e) in a
direction orthogonal to the axial direction which gives
maximum transmittance of linearly polarized light is 0.03 or
more, and a second refractive index difference (Δn2), in the
axial direction which gives maximum transmittance is 80 % or
less of the first refractive index difference (Δn1).
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="128" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="36"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Field of the Invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to an optical diffusing
plate that gives an anisotropic scattering of a linearly
polarized light and has an excellent diffusion property in
a scattering direction, and that is suitable for improving
visibility, brightness etc. of a liquid crystal display etc.
Moreover, the present invention relates to an optical element
using the optical diffusing plate concerned.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Description of the Prior Art</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0002">Conventionally, an optical diffusing plate designed so
that anisotropic scattering might be given to a linearly
polarized light by making a domain with a refractive index
anisotropy contained in a dispersed state in a base material
has been known. As the optical diffusing plate concerned;
an optical diffusing plate that comprises a combination of
a thermoplastic resin anda low molecular weight liquid crystal,
that comprises a combination of a low molecular weight liquid
crystal and a photo-curable low molecular weight liquid crystal
and that comprises a combination of a polyvinyl alcohol and 
a low molecule liquid crystal, have been known (USP No. 2123902
specification, WO 87/01822 official gazette, JP-A 9-274108).</p>
    <p num="0003">What is expected in the above-mentioned optical
diffusing plate is that supplying a linearly polarized light
in a state difficult to be absorbed by a polarizing plate reduces
an absorption loss, and consequently the brightness of a liquid
crystal display is improved. It is expected using this method
that the following conventional problems may be solved; a
problem based on a large wavelength dependability of a
cholesteric liquid crystal in the conventional absorption loss
reduction systems in which a cholesteric liquid crystal layer
and a quarter wavelength plate are used, and especially,
problems that transmitted light is chromatic from oblique
direction and that these cannot be applied to a reflected type
liquid crystal display etc. However, in the above-mentioned
conventional optical diffusing plate, there were problems of
a difficulty in manufacturing, and of a practical usability
in difficult handling with a poor functional stability, when
applied in a liquid crystal display, etc.</p>
    <p num="0004">As an optical diffusing plate in which the
above-mentioned problem was solved, an optical diffusing plate
using a birefringent film that contains minute domains with
different birefringent characteristics in a dispersed state
is proposed (JP-A 2000-187105). Although the above-mentioned
problem is solved and excellent polarization characteristics 
are developed using this optical diffusion plate, the further
improvement is desired about polarization characteristics.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0005">An object of the present invention is to provide an optical
diffusing plate that is easily manufactured and has outstanding
thermal and chemical stability and is excellent in practical
use or is excelled in polarization characteristics, and in which
while brightness is increased as a result of supplying linearly
polarized light with reduced absorption loss by polarizing plate,
chromatic problem is rarely induced, and that is applicable to
reflected type liquid crystal display etc. And another object
of the present invention is to provide an optical element and
further a liquid crystal display using the above-mentioned
optical diffusing plate.</p>
    <p num="0006">As a result of repeated examinations carried out
wholeheartedly by the present inventors to solve the
above-mentioned problems, it was found out, as is shown below,
that the above-mentioned object was attained and the present
invention was completed using an optical diffusing plate in which
a side chain type liquid crystal copolymer is used as a minute
domain contained in dispersed state in a birefringent film.</p>
    <p num="0007">Namely, the present invention relates to an optical
diffusing plate comprising a birefringent film and a minute
domain with a birefringent characteristic different from the 
birefringent film in a dispersed state in the birefringent
film,

   the minute domain comprising a side chain type liquid
crystal polymer comprising a monomer unit (a) containing a liquid
crystalline fragment side chain and a monomer unit (b) containing
a non-liquid crystalline fragment side chain, and

   a refractive index difference (Δn1) between the
birefringent film and the minute domain in a direction orthogonal
to a direction of axis that gives a maximum transmittance of
linearly polarized light being 0.03 or more, and a refractive
index difference (Δn2) in a direction of axis that gives a maximum
transmittance being 80 % or less of the Δn1.</p>
    <p num="0008">Since the minute domain and the birefringent film that
contains the dispersed minute domain is formed by a polymer
materials and a forming material has an excellent handling
property, the birefringent film is easily manufactured using
an optical diffusing plate of the present invention. Since the
forming material has a thermal and chemical stability, it
develops stable optical function and excels in practicality.
Moreover, a linearly polarized light transmits in the direction
of the axis (Δn2 direction) that gives a maximum transmitance
of the linearly polarized light, while maintaining an excellent
polarization state, and the linearly polarized light is scattered
in the direction (Δn1 direction) orthogonal to the
above-mentioned Δn2 direction based on a refractive index 
difference Δn1 between a birefringent film and a minute domain,
and as a result the polarization state is relaxed or canceled.</p>
    <p num="0009">And moreover since a side chain type liquid crystal
copolymer contains a monomer unit (b), it becomes possible to
provide a birefringent characteristic smaller than the one
obtained using only a side chain type liquid crystal polymer
consisting of a monomer unit (a) independently. Consequently,
since the birefringent characteristic of a side chain type liquid
crystal copolymer may be controlled to a desired value of
birefringence, it becomes possible to manufacture an optical
diffusing plate with outstanding polarization characteristic.</p>
    <p num="0010">In the above-mentioned optical diffusing plate, it is
preferable that a minute domain is distributed in a dispersed
and state caused by phase separation, and that a length in Δ
n1 direction of the minute domain (direction orthogonal to the
above-mentioned axial direction) is from 0.05 to 500 µm.</p>
    <p num="0011">The above-mentioned optical diffusing plate may be used
as one layer, two or more layers may be used in laminated state
so that the Δn1 direction of an upper layer and a lower layer
may have a mutually parallel relationship in order to increase
polarization characteristics.</p>
    <p num="0012">Moreover, the present invention relates to an optical
element comprising a laminated layer of at least one kind
selecting from a polarizing plate and a retardation plate, and
the above mentioned optical diffusing plate. </p>
    <p num="0013">In the above-mentioned optical element, it is desirable
that transmission axis of the polarizing plate and the Δn2
direction of the optical diffusing plate (the above-mentioned
axial direction) have a mutually parallel relationship.</p>
    <p num="0014">When a polarizing plate is configured to an optical
diffusing plate so that the transmission axis may have a
relationship parallel to the above-mentioned Δn2 direction,
a linearly polarized light that has transmittance in the Δ
n2 direction transmits polarizing plate efficiently and a
linearly polarized light that has transmittance in the
above-mentioned Δn1 direction is scattered, and the
polarization direction is transformed. Consequently since the
linearly polarized light becomes to contain a linearly polarized
light component that has a transmittance in the Δn2 direction,
the component light is transmitted through the polarizing
plate.</p>
    <p num="0015">Furthermore, the present invention relates to a liquid
crystal display comprising the above-mentioned optical
diffusing plate or the above-mentioned optical element on one
side or both sides of liquid crystal cells.</p>
    <p num="0016">When the above-mentioned polarizing plate is used, an
amount of the transmitted linearly polarized light is increased
and an absorption loss is reduced simultaneously, the brightness
of a transmitted type liquid crystal display etc. can be raised.
Moreover, a possible chromatic problem based on high wavelength 
dependability as in cholesteric liquid crystal becomes rarely
to be induced. Furthermore, the above-mentioned polarizing
plate is easily applicable also in a reflected type liquid crystal
display etc., and a liquid crystal display with outstanding
brightness and visibility may be stably obtained.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0017">
      <sl>
        <li>Fig. 1 is a sectional view of an example of an optical
diffusing plate;</li>
        <li>Fig. 2 is a sectional view of an example of a laminated
optical diffusing plate;</li>
        <li>Fig. 3 is a sectional view of an example of an optical
element;</li>
        <li>Fig. 4 is a sectional view of an example of a liquid crystal
display; and</li>
        <li>Fig. 5 is a sectional view of an example of other liquid
crystal display.</li>
      </sl>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0018">An optical diffusing plate of the present invention
comprises a minute domain contained in dispersed state in a
birefringent film having different birefringent
characteristics from the birefringent film, the minute domain
comprises a side chain type liquid crystal polymer comprising
a monomer unit (a) containing a liquid crystalline fragment side 
chain, and a monomer unit (b) containing a non-liquid crystalline
fragment side chain, and a refractive index difference (Δn1)
between the above-mentioned birefringent film and the minute
domain in a direction orthogonal to a direction of axis that
gives a maximum transmittance of linearly polarized light is
0.03 or more, and a refractive index difference (Δn2) in a
direction of axis that gives a maximum transmittance is 80 %
or less of the above-mentioned Δn1.</p>
    <p num="0019">Examples of optical diffusing plates of the present
invention are shown in Fig. 1 and Fig. 2. Notation 1 shows
an optical diffusing plate and 10 shows a laminated optical
diffusing plate in which the optical diffusing plates 1 are
laminated together. Each optical diffusing plate is a
birefringent film that contains minute domains e in a dispersed
state having different birefringent characteristics from each
other. In addition, notation 2b shows an adhesive layer
between laminated optical diffusing plates, 2a an adhesive
layer that comprises an adhesive layer for an adherend, and
21 a separator that covers adhesive layer temporarily.</p>
    <p num="0020">The optical diffusing plate of the present invention
is manufactured by a suitable method, for example, as follows:
a film is formed from a mixture of one kind or two kinds or
more of base material polymers used as a base material of a
birefringent film and one kind or two kinds or more of the 
above-mentioned positive uniaxial liquid crystal polymers
used as a minute domain, and subsequently this film is aligned
through stretching processing to obtain a minute domain of
the liquid crystal polymer formed in the birefringent film
having different birefringent characteristics from the
birefringent film.</p>
    <p num="0021">Suitable transparent polymer may be used as the
above-mentioned base material polymer, and there is especially
no limitation. As examples of the polymer, for example;
polyester series polymers such as polyethylene terephthalate
or polyethylene naphthalate; styrene series polymers such as
polystyrene or acrylonitrile styrene copolymer (AS resin);
olefin series polymers such as poly olefin which include
polyethylene, polypropylene, cyclo- series, or norbornene
structure, or ethylene propylene copolymers; carbonate series
polymers; acrylics series polymers such as poly
methylmethacrylate; vinyl chloride series polymers; cellulose
series polymer such as cellulose diacetate or cellulose
triacetate; amide series polymers such as nylon or aromatic
polyamide; imide series polymers; sulfone series polymers;
polyether sulfone series polymers; polyether ether ketone
series polymers; poly phenylene sulfide series polymer; vinyl
alcohol series polymer; vinylidene chloride series polymer;
vinyl butyral series polymers; allylate series polymers; and
poly oxy methylene series polymers; or blended mixtures of 
the above described polymers may be mentioned. Polymers,
above all, comprising hydrocarbon without any polar group as
ester group, ether group and carbonate group are preferable.</p>
    <p num="0022">On the other hand, as a positive uniaxial liquid crystal
polymer, for example, a side chain type liquid crystal copolymer
comprising a monomer unit (a) containing liquid crystalline
fragment side chain and a monomer unit (b) containing non-liquid
crystalline fragment side chain may be mentioned.</p>
    <p num="0023">As a fragment side chain in the above-mentioned monomer
unit (a), for example, a side chain that has side chain part
represented by a general formula (1) : -Y-Z-A (where, Y
represents a poly methylene chain or poly oxy methylene chain
branched from main chain, and Z represents para-substituted
cyclic compounds), may be mentioned.</p>
    <p num="0024">In the above-mentioned general formula (1), Y represents
a spacer group that gives flexibility, and comprises poly
methylene chain -(CH<sub>2</sub>) <sub>p</sub>- or poly oxy methylene chain
- (CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>q</sub>-. The numbers p and q of repetitions are suitably
determined by chemical structure of mesogenic group Z bonded
with it etc., and, generally p is an integer of 0 to 20, preferably
2 to 12, and q is an integer of 0 to 10, preferably 1 to 4.</p>
    <p num="0025">As a preferable spacer group Y to form a birefringent
film for controlling refractive index, for example, ethylene,
propylene, butylene, pentylene, hexylene, octylene, decylene,
undecylene, dodecylene, octadecylene, ethoxy ethylene, and 
methoxy butylene, etc. may be mentioned.</p>
    <p num="0026">Z is para-substituted cyclic compound serving as
mesogenic group that gives liquid crystal alignment ,as
examples of para-substituted aromatic unit and
para-sustituted cyclohexyl ring unit, such as types of
compounds; azomethyne type ,azo type, azoxy type, ester type,
tolane type,phenyl type, biphenyl type, phenyl cyclo hexyl
type and bicylcohexyl type may be mentioned.</p>
    <p num="0027">As a preferable para-substituted cyclic compound Z to
form a birefringent film for controlling refractive index,
compounds represented by following [Formula 1] may be
mentioned. <img id="img-00120001" orientation="unknown" wi="140" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00120001.tif" inline="no" he="209"/>
(Where m is 1 or 2.) In the above formulas, a spacer group
Y and a mesogenic group Z may be bonded through ether linkage,
i.e., -O-. Moreover, one or two hydrogen of phenyl group that 
forms para-substituted cyclic compound may be substituted by
halogen, and in this case as a halogen chlorine or fluorine
is preferable.</p>
    <p num="0028">Moreover, terminal substituent group A in para-position
of para-substituted cyclic compound Z may be suitable group,
and for example; cyano group ,alkyl group ,alkenyl group ,alkoxy
group ,oxa alkyl group ,halogen group and haloalkyl group,
haloalkoxy group, and haloalkenyl group with which one or more
of hydrogen are substituted by fluorine or chlorine may be
mentioned.</p>
    <p num="0029">Therefore, the above-mentioned side chain type liquid
crystal copolymer may be a copolymer that shows
thermoplasticity and proper alignment, such as nematic phase
and smectic phase, at room temperature or higher temperature.</p>
    <p num="0030">In the fragment side chain in the above-mentioned monomer
unit (a), it is preferable that at least one substituent
selected from a group of alkoxy group, cyano group, fluoro
group, and alkyl group is contained in a parallel direction
(symmetrically) to a molecule length axis of the fragment side
chain.</p>
    <p num="0031">As the above-mentioned monomer unit (a), a monomer unit
represented by the general formula (a) : [Formula 2] , for example,
is mentioned as a preferable example. <img id="img-00140001" orientation="unknown" wi="104" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00140001.tif" inline="no" he="36"/>
(Where, R<sup>1</sup> represents hydrogen atom or methyl group; a
represents a positive integer of 1 to 6; X<sup>1</sup> represents -CO<sub>2</sub>-group
or -OCO-group; R<sup>2</sup> represents cyano group, alkoxy group with
1 to 6 of carbon, fluoro group, or alkyl group with 1 to 6
of carbon; and b and c represents integer of 1 or 2, respectively.</p>
    <p num="0032">Moreover, the fragment side chain in the above-mentioned
monomer unit (b) preferably has at least one substituent
selected from a group of alkyl group, fluoro alkyl group, and
alkoxy group. Control of refractive index characteristics
and birefringent characteristics becomes possible using the
monomer unit that has the fragment side chain with such a
substituent.</p>
    <p num="0033">As the above-mentioned monomer unit (b) , a monomer unit
represented by a general formula (b) : [Formula 3], for example,
may be mentioned.
<img id="img-00140002" orientation="unknown" wi="47" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00140002.tif" inline="no" he="36"/>
(Where, R<sup>3</sup> represents hydrogen atom or methyl group, R<sup>4</sup>
represents alkyl group with 1 to 22 of carbon, fluoro alkyl
group with 1 to 22 of carbon, or a substituent represented 
by a general formula (c): [Formula 4]).
<img id="img-00150001" orientation="unknown" wi="56" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00150001.tif" inline="no" he="26"/>
(Where, d represents a positive integer of 1 to 6 and R<sup>5</sup>
represents alkyl group with 1 to 6 of carbon.) A monomer unit
that has such a linear side chain and is represented by a general
formula (b) is preferable in controlling refractive index
characteristics and birefringent characteristics. An
ordinary ray refractive index may be decreased, and at the
same time birefringence may be decreased by increasing a
percentage of monomer unit represented by the general formula
(b).</p>
    <p num="0034">A percentage of the monomer unit (a) and the monomer
unit (b) is not especially limited. The percentage should
be varied depending on a kind of the monomer unit, the preferable
percentages of the monomer unit are (b) / {(a)+(b)} = 0.01
to 0.8 (molar ratio) , since increase in the percentage of the
monomer unit (b) impairs development of birefringent
characteristics of a side chain type liquid crystal copolymer.
Moreover, it is preferable that a weight average molecular
weight of a side chain type liquid crystal polymer is 2000
to 100000. In addition, a side chain type liquid crystal
copolymer comprising the monomer units represented by the above
described formulas [Formula 2] and [Formula 3] as a monomer 
unit (a) and a monomer unit (b) may be prepared by copolymerizing
an acrylics series monomer or a methacryl series monomer
corresponding to the monomer units of the above-mentioned
illustration.</p>
    <p num="0035">A case of poly acrylate or poly methacrylate was
illustrated for a side chain type liquid crystal copolymer
in the above-mentioned description as a frame structure that
forms main chain, a main chain of the present invention may
be formed with proper combination of chains, such as linear,
branched, or cyclic. As examples; poly
alpha-haloacrylates ,poly alpha-cyano acrylates, poly
acrylamides, polyacrylonitriles, poly
methacrylonitriles ,polyamides ,polyesters ,polyurethanes;
polyethers, polyimides, and polysiloxanes may be mentioned.</p>
    <p num="0036">In the above method, a base material polymer and the
side chain type liquid crystal polymer preferably are used
in combination wherein a phase separation is induced, in order
that a minute domain formed in the optical diffusing plate
obtained may develop excellent dispersibility and
distribution property. Thus the dispersibility and
distribution property may be controlled by a combination of
those compatibilities. Phaseseparation may be obtained using
suitable methods , for example, by making materials with mutual
non-compatibility into a solution state in a suitable solvent,
and by mixing the materials under heated and melted phase. </p>
    <p num="0037">In addition, in the above-mentioned stretching alignment
processing method, when forming a birefringent film that
contains the above-mentioned minute domain in a dispersed state,
a target birefringent stretched film may be formed at arbitrary
stretching temperature and at stretching ratio. Moreover the
above-mentioned base material polymer has anisotropic
polymers classified into positive and negative based on a
characteristics of refractive index variation by the
stretching direction, and both of the positive and negative
anisotropic polymers may be used in the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0038">Target films to which alignment processing is given may
be prepared using proper methods, such as a casting method,
an extrusion molding method, an injection molding method, and
a roll forming method, the flow casting molding method.
Moreover, a method may be used in which a developed monomer
is polymerized with heat-treatment or radiation processing
of ultraviolet radiation etc. to obtain a film.</p>
    <p num="0039">A method in which a mixed solution of a base polymer
and the liquid crystal polymer is prepared in some suitable
solvent and subsequently the mixed solution is made into a
film using a casting method or a flow casting molding method
is preferable, because in the method a minute domain contained
in a dispersed state in a birefringent film may have an advanced
uniform distributed state. When this method is applied, the
size and distributed state etc. of the minute domain may be 
controlled by the factors , such as a kind of solvent, a viscosity
of the mixed solution, and a rate of drying of a mixed
solution-developing layer. A method of lowering viscosity
of mixed solution and a method of increasing the rate of drying
of the mixed solution-developing layer etc. are advantageous
to make a size of a minute domain considerably small.</p>
    <p num="0040">Thickness of a film for alignment processing may be
suitably determined, and, generally the thickness is 1 µm to
3 mm, preferably 5 µm to 1 mm and still more preferably 10
to 500 µm taking the easiness of alignment processing etc.
into consideration. In addition, when the film is formed,
proper additives , such as a dispersant, a surface active agent,
a UV absorbent, a color tone modifier, a flame retarder, a
mold lubricant, and an antioxidant may be blended therein.</p>
    <p num="0041">Alignment processing may be carried out using one or more
of the following suitable methods that may control a refractive
index by alignment: a method of stretching processing and rolling
processing in uniaxial or biaxial and sequential biaxial or
Z-axial direction; a method in which a material is impressed
with electric field or magnetic field at a temperature equal
to or more of glass transition temperature or of liquid crystal
transition temperature followed by immediate cooling to fix
alignment; a method in which a material is flowed and aligned
at the time of film formation; and a method in which a side chain
type liquid crystal copolymer is self-aligned based on a small 
degree of alignment of an isotropic polymer. Therefore, a
birefringent film in containing a minute domain is contained
in dispersed state may be a stretched film or an unstretched
film. In addition, although in the case of a stretching film
a brittle polymer may be used as a base material polymer,
especially a polymer that is excellent in stretchability is
desirable.</p>
    <p num="0042">An optical diffusing plate of the present invention
comprises a birefringent film containing the above-mentioned
minute domain in dispersed state, and a refractive index
difference (Δn1) between a birefringent film portion that has
a base material polymer of the above-mentioned optical diffusing
plate as composition element and a minute domain that has a side
chain type liquid crystal copolymer as composition element is
0.03 or more in a direction orthogonal to the direction of axis
that gives a maximum transmittance of a linearly polarized light,
and moreover a refractive index difference (Δn2) in the direction
of axis that gives a maximum transmittance is controlled to 80%
or less of the above-mentioned Δn1. By being given such a
difference of the refractive index, maintenance of outstanding
scattered state in Δn1 direction (direction orthogonal to the
above-mentioned direction of axis), and outstanding
polarization state in Δn2 direction (the above-mentioned axial
direction) is realized.</p>
    <p num="0043">When taking into consideration transformation or 
cancellation of a polarization state based on scattering, a
refractive index difference (Δn1) in the Δn1 direction
preferably has a moderately large value of 0.04 to 1 and especially
of 0.045 to 0.5. On the other hand, in order to maintain
polarization state, a refractive index difference (Δn2) in the
Δn2 direction has preferably small value, and it is preferably
0.03 or less, more preferably 0.02 or less and still preferably
0.01 or less.</p>
    <p num="0044">Therefore, the above-mentioned alignment processing may
also be defined as the operation that increases a refractive
index difference between the above-mentioned birefringent film
portion and the minute domain in Δn1 direction, as the operation
that decreases in Δn2 direction, or as the operation of attaining
the both.</p>
    <p num="0045">In order to realize the above-mentioned uniform scattering
effect etc., the minute domain in the above-mentioned optical
diffusing plate may be dispersed and distributed in birefringent
film as uniformly as possible. Since a size of minute domain,
especially a length in the Δn1 direction, the scattering
direction, is associated with a backscattering (reflection) or
a wavelength dependability, a length of the minute domain in
the Δn1 direction is preferably as small as possible, and it
is preferably in the order of several micrometer taking
controlling of the backscattering into consideration.</p>
    <p num="0046">Taking into consideration having backscattering induced 
and increased, on the other hand, it is desirable that a diameter
of the minute domain in the Δn1 direction may have a size in
which Rayleigh scattering is induced. In order to induce
Rayleigh scattering, it is desirable that the diameter of the
minute domain is small enough to a wavelength of light. On the
other hand, from a point of controlling the wavelength
dependability of a scattering light, it is preferable that size
of minute domain in the Δn1 direction is as large as possible,
therefore it has an antagonistic relationship to the method of
controlling the above-mentioned backscattering.</p>
    <p num="0047">On the assumption of the above-mentioned backscattering
and the wavelength dependability, etc. in order to solve various
problems of, such as; increasing optical use efficiency,
preventing chromaticity caused by wavelength dependability,
preventing inhibition of clear display by viewing of the minute
domain and further increasing film productivity and film strength,
a preferable size of the minute domain, especially a length in
the Δn1 direction is 0.05 to 500 µm, more preferably 0.1 to
250 µm and still more preferably 1 to 100 µm. In addition,
although a minute domain usually exists in a birefringent film
in a state of domain, there is especially no limitation for a
length in the Δn2 direction.</p>
    <p num="0048">As is described above, an optical diffusing plate of the
present invention is given anisotropy in birefringence
characteristics in the Δn1 direction and the Δn2 direction, 
and a linearly polarized light is controlled by difference of
the oscillating plane. A percentage occupied by the minute
domain in the optical diffusing plate may properly be determined
based on the scattering nature in the Δn1 direction etc., it
is 0.1 to 70 weight %, preferably 0.5 to 50 weight 5 and more
preferably 1 to 30 weight %.</p>
    <p num="0049">An optical diffusing plate of the present invention may
comprise a single layer of birefringent film containing minute
domains in a dispersed state having different birefringent
characteristics as is shown in Fig. 1, and may comprise a
laminated multi-layer of the optical diffusing plate 1 as is
show in Fig. 2. A cumulative scattering effect beyond increase
in thickness is demonstrated using such laminating method,
and when combined with a polarizing plate, a larger amount
of transmitted light through polarizing plate than reflection
loss may be advantageously obtained.</p>
    <p num="0050">Although laminated body may be configured by optical
diffusing plates laminated at arbitrary aligning angles in Δ
n1 direction or Δn2 direction, when an increase of scattering
effect is desired, the upper and lower layers may be preferably
laminated so that their Δn1 direction may have mutually parallel
relationship. The number of laminating of the optical diffusing
plates may be properly determined as two or more.</p>
    <p num="0051">Moreover, Δn1 and Δn2 of each optical diffusing plate
to be laminated may be equal or different from each other. In 
addition, the relationship between upper and lower layers in
Δn1 direction etc. is preferably as parallel as possible, a
gap by work error etc. is permitted. Moreover, when Δn1
direction etc. has variation, the average direction is adopted.</p>
    <p num="0052">Each optical diffusing plate in laminated multi-layer
may only be piled up without any treatment, but preferably
may be adhered through an adhesive layer etc. in order to prevent
Δn1 direction etc. might shift or any foreign matter etc.
might enter into each interface. Proper adhesives, such as,
for example, hot melt type and pressure sensitive adhesion
type, may be used for adhesion. In order to reduce reflective
loss, adhesive layer that has as small as refractive index
difference with optical diffusing plate is preferable, and
adhesion may also be carried out using the base material polymer
itself or the side chain type liquid crystal polymer that forms
the minute domain.</p>
    <p num="0053">An optical diffusing plate of the present invention,
making efficient use of the characteristics showing
transmittance and scattering properties of linearly polarized
light, may be used, for example, in various kinds of uses,
such as a polarization amplification plate, color controlling
panel, polarized light separation plate, display
characteristics control plate, and liquid crystal display
screen, and polarized light auxiliary plate.</p>
    <p num="0054">In the above-mentioned polarization amplification plate, 
an optical diffusing plate that has a small backscattering and
a strong light scattering property is configured in the incident
light side of polarizing plate, and the scattering property (Δ
n1 direction) is utilized to transform the polarization direction.
Consequently, an amount of linearly polarized light which has
transmittance in Δn2 direction is increased, and a polarization
degree and an optical use efficiency are expected to be enhanced.
Moreover, a color control panel amplifies the polarization of
blue region and aims at adjustment of color balance while
preventing yellowing of a display by configuring an optical
diffusing plate with a high wavelength dependability on the
surface of a reflected type liquid crystal display with low blue
transmittance.</p>
    <p num="0055">In polarization separation plate, an optical diffusing
plate that shows a scattering near Rayleigh scattering is
configured between a light leading plate and a polarizing plate,
and after canceling a polarization of backscattering light
thereby, the light is introduced again into the polarizing plate
through the reflective layer at the bottom of light leading plate
etc. Using the above-mentioned configuration it is expected
that the amount of the linearly polarized light with
transmittance in the Δn2 direction is increased and the degree
of polarization or in optical use efficiency is improved.</p>
    <p num="0056">A display characteristics control plate is used for the 
purpose that white display is scattered and black display is
transmitted to make contrast and clarity of picture improved,
by configuring an optical diffusing plate which has a few
backscattering and a high haze anisotropy between a liquid
crystal cell and a polarizing plate in the viewing side. A
liquid crystal display screen aims at improvement in contrast,
using an optical diffusing plate as a screen transmitting
selectively a specified linearly polarized light in incident
light. A polarized light auxiliary plate is used for the
purpose of controlling absorption of incident light by a
polarizing plate and preventing temperature rise of the
polarizing plate by configuring an optical diffusing plate
having a high haze anisotropy between the polarizing plate
and light sources inside of a display.</p>
    <p num="0057">Therefore, in practical use, an optical diffusing plate
of the present invention may also be used as an optical element
that comprises a laminated material in which an optical
diffusing plate is configured at one side or both sides of
suitable optical parts, such as a polarizing plate and/or a
retardation plate. An example is shown in Fig. 3. Notation
3 is an optical part. This laminated layer may only be piled
up without any treatment, and may also be adhered through an
adhesive layer etc. As an adhesive layer, the adhesive layer
used in laminating of each above-mentioned optical diffusing
plate may be used. </p>
    <p num="0058">There is especially no limitation in optical parts used
for the above-mentioned lamination and, for example, proper
parts, such as a polarizing plate, a retardation plate, a
backlight such as a light leading plate, a reflective plate,
a polarized light separation plate that comprises multilayer
film, etc., and a liquid crystal cell, may be used. Moreover,
optical parts , such as a polarizing plate and retardation plate,
may be of various kinds of types.</p>
    <p num="0059">That is, as a polarizing plate, various kinds of types,
such as an absorbing type, a reflecting type, and a scattering
type, may be used; and as a retardation plate, various kinds
of types, such as a quarter wavelength plate, a half wavelength
plate, an uniaxial and biaxial stretched film type, and an
oblique alignment film type aligned further in thickness
direction, a liquid crystal polymer type and a type in which
the above-mentioned types are laminated may be used in the
present invention.</p>
    <p num="0060">As examples of the polarizing plate described above,
a polyvinyl alcohol series film; a partially formalized
polyvinyl alcohol series film; an absorbed type polarizing
plate in which dichroism substances, such as iodine and a
dichroism dye, domainbsorbed in a hydrophilic polymer film
like a partially saponified film of ethylene/vinyl acetate
copolymer series polymer and subsequently stretched; a
poly-ene aligned film such as a dehydrated compound of polyvinyl 
alcohol; or a dehydrochlorinated compound of polyvinyl
chloride etc. may be mentioned.</p>
    <p num="0061">Moreover, a polarizing plate on which a transparent
protective layer comprising a coated layer of plastics and
a laminated layer of a film etc. are prepared in order to retain
water resistance on one side or both sides of the
above-mentioned polarizing film. Furthermore, a polarizing
plate with a fine concavo-convex structure on the surface may
be mentioned in which transparent fine-grains having an average
grain size of 0.5 to 20 µm, such as inorganic fine-grain, which
may have conductivity, of silica, alumina, titania, zirconia,
tin oxide, indium oxide, cadmium oxide, antimony oxide, etc.,
and organic fine-grain of cross-linked or non cross-linked
polymer, in the transparent protection layer are contained.</p>
    <p num="0062">On the other hand, as examples of a retardation plate,
a stretched film comprising base material polymer shown in
the example of the above-mentioned birefringent film, a liquid
crystal polymer, and most of all a retardation plate comprising
a twist alignment liquid crystal polymer etc. may be mentioned.
Furthermore, as an example of a light leading plate, a light
leading plate may be mentioned wherein light sources, such
as a linear light source as a cathode-ray tube (cold or hot
type), a light emitting diode and EL, are configured on the
side of a transparent resin plate, and a constitution in which
the light transmitted inside of a plate is emitted from one 
side of the resin plate by the action of diffusion, reflection,
diffraction, interference, etc. is adopted.</p>
    <p num="0063">When an optical element containing a light leading plate
is assembled, one or more auxiliary means, such as a prism
array layer comprising a prism sheet for controlling the
emitting direction of light etc., a diffusing plate for
obtaining uniform light emission, and a linear light-source
holder for leading the emitted light from a light source to
the side of a light leading plate, are configured in
predetermined positions, such as in upper or lower side and
in lateral side, of a light leading plate if necessary to obtain
a suitable assembled body.</p>
    <p num="0064">The laminated layer that forms the optical element of
the present invention may be a laminated layer comprising one
kind of optical parts, and may be a laminated layer comprising
two or more kinds of optical parts. Moreover, for example,
in the laminated layer of the present invention, two or more
layers of the same kinds of optical parts , such as a retardation
plate, may be laminated together, and in this case, the optical
parts as a retardation plate etc. may have the same or different
characteristics. As for the optical diffusing plate used into
the optical element, one or more of plates may be configured
on one or both of outer the surface of a laminated layer, or
in the proper position outside or inside of laminated layers,
such as on one side or both sides, of the optical parts 
configuring the laminated layer.</p>
    <p num="0065">When an optical element contains a polarizing plate, in
order to utilize effectively transmission and scattering
characteristics of an optical diffusing plate, the optical
diffusing plate is preferably configured so that the Δn2
direction may have a parallel relationship with a transmission
axis of the polarizing plate. The parallel relationship may
be applied correspondingly for the case of laminating the
above-mentioned birefringent film. In the optical element with
this configuration, a linearly polarized light absorbed by the
polarizing plate will be scattered through the Δn1 direction
of optical diffusing plate. Therefore, such an optical element
can be preferably used for a polarization amplification plate,
a polarization separation plate, the above-mentioned liquid
crystal display screen and the above-mentioned polarization
auxiliary plate, etc.</p>
    <p num="0066">In addition, as a polarizing plate for configuring an
optical element, in order to improve brightness or contrast,
a polarizing plate with high polarizing degree such as an
absorbed type polarizing plate containing the above-mentioned
dichroism substance etc., especially a polarizing plate with
40 % or more of light transmittance, and with 95.0 % or more,
preferably 99 % or more of polarizing degree is used.</p>
    <p num="0067">Since the optical diffusing plate and optical element
of the present invention have the above-mentioned feature, 
they may be preferably used for formation of a liquid crystal
display. An example of a liquid crystal display is shown in
Fig. 4 and Fig. 5. Notation 4 shows a polarizing plate, 5
a liquid crystal cell, 6 a diffuse-reflection plate, 7 a light
leading plate, 71 a reflective layer, 72 a light source and
8 shows an optical diffusing plate for diffusing viewing light.</p>
    <p num="0068">The above-mentioned Fig. 4 shows a reflected type liquid
crystal display. The optical diffusing plate 1 is configured
so that Δn2 direction may have a parallel relationship to the
transmission axis of the polarizing plate on the outside of the
polarizing plate 4 in a viewing side. On the other hand, Fig.
5 shows a transmitted type liquid crystal display. The optical
diffusing plate 1 is configured so that Δn2 direction may have
a parallel relationship to the transmission axis of the
polarizing plate, between the light leading plate 7 forming a
backlight and the polarizing plate 4 on the back side in a viewing
side.</p>
    <p num="0069">Generally several composition parts, such as a
polarizing plate, a liquid crystal cell, a reflective plate
or a backlight, and if necessary other optical parts, such
as optical parts, are suitably assembled with a drive circuit
incorporated to obtain a liquid crystal display. In the
present invention, there is especially no limitation except
for the point of using the above-mentioned optical diffusing
plate or optical elements, and a liquid crystal display of 
the present invention may be assembled using conventional
method. Therefore, when a liquid crystal display is assembled,
suitable optical parts, such as an optical diffusing plate
laid on the polarizing plate in the viewing side, an anti-glare
layer, anantireflection film, a protection layer, aprotection
plate, and the compensation plate laid between a liquid crystal
cell and polarizing plates in the viewing side, may suitably
be configured.</p>
    <p num="0070">As described above, the above-mentioned compensation
plate is used in order to compensate birefringent wavelength
dependability etc. and to improve visibility, and is configured
between a polarizing plate in the viewing side and/or in the
side of a backlight and a liquid crystal cell etc. In addition,
as a compensation plate, suitable parts, such as the
above-mentioned retardation plate, may be used based on a
wavelength region etc. Moreover, the compensation plate may
comprise two or more layer of retardation layers.</p>
    <p num="0071">In the above case, one layer or two or more layers of
optical diffusing plate or an optical element, being considered
as one unit, may be configured in the suitable position on
one side or both sides of a liquid crystal cell. In a liquid
crystal display configured so that the Δn2 direction of optical
diffusing plate and the transmission axis of polarizing plate
may have a parallel relationship, one layer or two layers or
more of optical diffusing plate may be configured, for example, 
in a reflected type liquid crystal display in incident light
side of the polarizing plate especially of the polarizing plate
in viewing side, or in a transmitted type liquid crystal display
in a suitable position between the polarizing plate on the back
side of viewing side and the backlight. In addition, the suitable
position here means a suitable position where it is desired that
a polarization of the linearly polarized light absorbed by the
polarizing plate is transformed by scattering.</p>
    <p num="0072">In addition, when the above-mentioned optical diffusing
plate is configured, the optical diffusing plate may be used,
as mentioned above, as an optical element laminated and combined
with adjacent optical parts etc. Moreover, in a liquid crystal
display, each composition element may preferably be adhered
and combined through adhesive layers as in the case of the
above-mentioned optical diffusing plate of the present
invention.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLE</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0073">The present invention is explained below referring to
examples below; the present invention is not limited to these
examples. In addition, a part in each example represents weight
part.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Example 1</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0074">A 20 weight % solution in dichloro-methane containing a 
norbornene series resin (product by JSR Corporation, brand name
ARTON) 100 parts as base material polymer of birefringent film
and 6 parts of a side chain type liquid crystal polymer represented
by the [Formula 5] (where n= 35, represents molar % of monomer
unit, and shown in block for convenience. Weight average
molecular weight: 10500) are mixed together. The mixture was
cast to form a film with a thickness of 100 µm by a cast method.
The film obtained was stretched at a stretching ratio of two
at 175°C to obtain an optical diffusing plate comprising a
birefringent film that contains a minute domain of the
above-mentioned a side chain type liquid crystal polymer in
dispersed state.
<img id="img-00330001" orientation="unknown" wi="120" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00330001.tif" inline="no" he="58"/></p>
    <p num="0075">In the above-mentioned birefringent stretched film, a
norbornene series resin forms a film, in which a side chain
type liquid crystal polymer is dispersed having a shape of
a domain in the form with a long axis in the stretching direction
to form a minute domain. Using a method of observing
chromaticity caused by a difference in phase difference resulting 
from a minute alignment turbulence in a liquid crystal polymer
within a domain, a measuring was carried out using a polarization
microscope to obtain an average diameter of the domain. The
average diameter obtained showed about 6 µm in length in the
Δn1 direction.</p>
    <p num="0076">The refractive index difference (Δn1) of the optical
diffusing plate gave 0.108, and the refractive index difference
(Δn2) gave 0.010.</p>
    <p num="0077">In addition, the refractive index in the Δn1 direction
of the film obtained by being stretched at a stretching ratio
of two in the above-mentioned norbornene series resin gave 1.512,
and the refractive index in the Δn2 direction gave 1.510.
Moreover, the refractive index (extraordinary ray refractive
index) in the Δn1 direction of the side chain type liquid crystal
polymer gave 1.620, and the refractive index (ordinary ray
refractive index) in the Δn2 direction gave 1.520.</p>
    <p num="0078">Measurement of refractive index was performed for each
of the single film using Abbe refractometer 1T type made by Atago
Co., Ltd. respectively. Norbornene series resin film was
measured without any pre-treatment. After 20 % solution of a
polyimide in N-methyl pyrolidone was spin-coated on a glass
substrate containing lead under a condition of 2000 rpm and for
10 seconds and was heated at 300°C for 1 hour, a rubbing treatment
was carried out to the coated substrate to obtain an alignment
film. Thus, after a solution of a side chain type liquid crystal 
polymer in cyclohexanone (26 weight %) was spin-coated on the
above-mentioned alignment layer, the coated substrate was heated
at 160°C to obtain an aligned side chain type liquid crystal
polymer for measuring.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Example 2</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0079">Two birefringent films manufactured according to Example
1 were laminated and adhered together through acrylics series
adhesive layer with thickness of 20 µm so that the Δn2 directions
of the films correspond to obtain an optical diffusing plate.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Example 3</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0080">The optical diffusing plate obtained in Example 1, and
a commercially available polarizing plate that has 41 % of a
total light transmittance and 99 % of a polarization degree of
transmission light was adhered together through an acrylics
series adhesive layer so that the Δn2 direction corresponds
with the transmission axis to obtain an optical element.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Example 4</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0081">On a diffuse reflection plate, a polarizing plate, a TN
liquid crystal cell, and the optical element obtained in Example
3 were adhered one by one through an acrylics series adhesive
layer so that the polarizing plate is configured at cell side
to obtain a reflected type liquid crystal display as in Fig. 
4. In addition, the polarizing plate was configured so that
the direction of the transmission axis may correspond with each
rubbing direction that meets liquid crystal cell.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Comparative Example 1</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0082">An optical diffusing plate comprising a birefringent film
with a refractive index difference (Δn1) of 0.333 and a
refractive index difference (Δn2) of 0.035 was obtained
following the same method as in Example 1 except that a side
chain type liquid crystal polymer represented by the [Formula
6] below (weight average molecular weight : 8900) was used.
<img id="img-00360001" orientation="unknown" wi="115" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00360001.tif" inline="no" he="34"/>
In addition, a refractive index (extraordinary ray refractive
index) of the Δn1 direction of the above-mentioned side chain
type liquid crystal polymer gave 1.845, and a refractive index
(ordinary ray refractive index) of the Δn2 direction gave 1.545.
In the above-mentioned birefringent film, a norbornene series
resin serves as a base film wherein a side chain type liquid
crystal polymer is dispersed to form a minute domain in domain
form in a shape with a major axis in the stretching direction.
The average diameter obtained showed about 6 µm in length in
the Δn1 direction. </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Comparative Example 2</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0083">In Example 3, the same method was followed except that
an optical diffusing plate obtained in Comparative Example 1
was used as an optical diffusing plate to obtain an optical
element.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Evaluation Test 1</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0084">A total light transmittance, a diffusion transmittance,
and a haze were measured for the optical diffusing plates and
optical elements obtained in Examples and Comparative Examples
using Poick integrating sphere type haze meter based on ASTM-D
1003-61. Moreover, the degree of polarization of all
transmitted light was also investigated, and the resultwas shown
in Table 1. In addition, as for an optical element, the incident
light had to enter from a polarizing plate and an optical diffusing
plate side, and a value in case from the optical diffusing plate
side was shown in parentheses.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Total light transmittance (%)</entry><entry align="center">Polarization degree (%)</entry><entry align="center">Diffusion transmittance (%)</entry><entry align="center">Haze (%)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 1</entry><entry align="center">87</entry><entry align="center">48</entry><entry align="center">34</entry><entry align="center">39</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 2</entry><entry align="center">83</entry><entry align="center">58</entry><entry align="center">46</entry><entry align="center">55</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 3</entry><entry align="center">41(55)</entry><entry align="center">99</entry><entry align="center">3(12)</entry><entry align="center">8(22)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 1</entry><entry align="center">91</entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">55</entry><entry align="center">60</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 2</entry><entry align="center">41(51)</entry><entry align="center">99</entry><entry align="center">4(14)</entry><entry align="center">10(27)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0085">Results of Table 1 show that optical diffusing plates with
polarizing function are obtained (Examples 1 and 2). And also
they show that although the birefringent films are laminated
up and therefore a total light transmittance is decreased by
reflective loss (Examples 1 and 2) , an increase in quantity of
total light transmittance of more than reflective loss was
obtained in case of combined with polarizing plate, and the
linearly polarized light transmitting through the polarizing
plate was improved by leaps and bounds by scattering of the
linearly polarized light absorbed by the polarizing plate
(Example 3). From the result of comparison in Example 3 wherein
the direction of incident light was changed, the total light
transmittance was improved by entering the light from optical
diffusing plate side as compared with the case of using only
polarizing plate (41%).</p>
    <p num="0086">Furthermore, the degree of improvement in the total light
transmittance is more effective in the case where a side chain
type liquid crystal copolymer is used (Example 1) than in the
case where a side chain type liquid crystal polymer consisting
of a single monomer unit is used (Comparative Example 1. This
result shows that the polarization characteristics is improved
using a side chain type liquid crystal copolymer of the present
invention as a liquid crystal polymer that constitutes an optical
diffusing plate with polarization function. </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Evaluation Test 2</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0087">When a brightness of the liquid crystal display obtained
in Example 4 was measured in displaying state using a brightness
meter, a significant improvement in brightness was confirmed
compared with the case where only polarizing plate is used.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>An optical diffusing plate, comprising
   a birefringent film (1) and a minute domain (e) with a
birefringent characteristic different from the
birefringent film (1) in a dispersed state in the
birefringent film (1),
   wherein the minute domain (e) comprises a side chain
type liquid crystal polymer comprising a monomer unit
(a) containing a liquid crystalline fragment side chain
and a monomer unit (b) containing a non-liquid
crystalline fragment side chain, and
   wherein a first refractive index difference (Δn1)
between the birefringent film (1) and the minute domain
(e) in a direction orthogonal to an axial direction that
gives a maximum transmittance of linearly polarized
light is 0.03 or more, and a second refractive index
difference (Δn2) in an axial direction that gives a
maximum transmittance is 80 % or less of the first
refractive index difference (Δn1).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The optical diffusing plate according to claim 1,
wherein the minute domain (e) is distributed in a
dispersed state caused by phase separation, and the
length in the direction of the first refractive index
(Δn1) of the minute domain (e) (direction orthogonal to
the axial direction) is from 0.05 µm to 500 µm.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>An optical diffusing plate,
wherein two or more of the optical diffusing plates
according to claim 1 or 2 are laminated so that the
direction of the first refractive index difference (Δn1)
of an upper layer and a lower layer have a mutually
parallel relationship.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>An optical element comprising a laminated layer of at
least one kind selected from a polarizing plate (4) and
a retardation plate, and the optical diffusing plate
according to any of claims 1 to 3.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The optical element according to claim 4,
wherein a transmission axis of a polarizing plate (4)
and the direction of the second refractive index
difference ((Δn2) of an optical diffusing plate (the
axial direction) have a mutually parallel relationship.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A liquid crystal display comprising the optical
diffusing plate according to any of claims 1 to 3 or the
optical element according to claim 4 or claim 5 on one
side or both sides of liquid crystal cells.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
