<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1244099-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1244099" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="18937306" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020925">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1244099-A2" status="new" fvid="23565139">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1244099</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20020925</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02251986-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02251986</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020320</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001081152-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001081152</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010321</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B   7/00        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B   7/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B   7/005       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B   7/007       20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B   7/007       20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B  20/10        20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B  20/10        20060101C I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B  27/19        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B  27/19        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B  27/24        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G11B  20/10A</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G11B  27/24</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G11B   7/005</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">S11B7:007G</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">S11B7:00S2</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Wobbelerfassungsschaltung und optische Plattenvorrichtung</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Wobble detection circuit and optical disk apparatus</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Circuit de détection d'oscillation et appareil de disque optique</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>RICOH KK</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>RICOH COMPANY, LTD.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Ricoh Company</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>3-6, Nakamagome 1-chome, Ohta-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo 143-8555</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MAEGAWA HIROSHI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MAEGAWA, HIROSHI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>MAEGAWA, HIROSHI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1996-B205, Shinyoshidacho, Kohoku-ku</street>
              <city>Yokohama-shi, Kanagawa</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Lamb, Martin John Carstairs</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>MARKS &amp;amp; CLERK, 57-60 Lincoln's Inn Fields</street>
              <city>London WC2A 3LS</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>NL</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A wobble detection circuit detects a signal by
a common photodetector (light receiving) element from
several kinds of media having different pre-formats.
Further, the wobble detection circuit changes a gain for
amplifying the signal in a wobble signal detection
process depending on the pre-format of a reproducing or
recording medium to obtain a wobble signal.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="162" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="94"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <heading>1. Field of the Invention</heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a circuit for
detecting a wobble signal from various kinds of media
having different pre-formats.</p>
    <heading>2. Description of the Related Art</heading>
    <p num="0002">A general recording medium employs a pre-format
in which a wobble signal frequency detectable
from deviation of tracks formed on the medium becomes
constant when constant linear velocity (CLV) rotation
control is performed in order to detect a linear
velocity at a radial position accurately. A detailed
description of the wobble signal will be given later.</p>
    <p num="0003">The wobble signal frequency differs depending
on the pre-format. For example, CD, DVD-RAM, and DVD-R
have different wobble signal frequencies. Additionally,
physical address information is also necessary so as to
identify an approximate position in an unrecorded area.
However, the physical address information is obtained by
different method depending on the pre-format. For
example, the physical address information is obtained by
performing frequency modulation to the wobble signals in
a CD, by prepits in a DVD-RAM, and by land prepits
formed between tracks in a DVD-R.</p>
    <p num="0004">A simple method to cope with a plurality of 
media having different pre-formats is to carry detection
circuits exclusive for respective pre-formats in
parallel and to select the detection circuit depending
on the pre-format of the medium to be accessed.</p>
    <p num="0005">In Japanese Laid-Open Patent Application No.
2000-207745 "Wobble Clock Generating Circuit and Optical
Disc Apparatus Using the Same", two or more filter
circuits are provided so as to select the filter
suitable for the wobble signal that changes frequency
according to rotational errors of a spindle motor.</p>
    <p num="0006">As in the case of the above-mentioned
publication, there is a case where a plurality of the
filter circuits are carried in parallel even for one
formatted medium and the suitable filter circuit is
selected and used. A structure in the above-mentioned
case is for preventing performance of the wobble signal
detection from deteriorating due to change of rotational
velocity of the medium.</p>
    <p num="0007">Thus, in an apparatus which records on and
reproduces a plurality of the media having various pre-formats,
when the wobble detection circuits exclusive
for respective pre-formats are provided or when, as in
the above publication, a plurality of filter circuits
are carried in parallel for one pre-format medium, the
circuit size becomes very large. Accordingly, power 
consumption increases and it becomes difficult to reduce
the circuit size.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0008">It is a general object of the present
invention to provide an improved and useful circuit
structure in which the above-mentioned problems are
eliminated.</p>
    <p num="0009">The object described above is achieved,
according to one aspect of the present invention, by a
wobble detection circuit, wherein: a signal is detected
by a common photodetector (light receiving) element from
several kinds of media having different pre-formats; and
a gain for amplifying the signal in a wobble signal
detection process is changed depending on the pre-format
of a reproducing or recording media to obtain a wobble
signal. Thus, a wobble signal of good quality can be
detected since signal processing can be performed while
maintaining suitable signal strength with regard to
signals obtained by a plurality of media having
different pre-formats and signal strength as well as
different frequencies of signals.</p>
    <p num="0010">The object described above is also achieved,
according to another aspect of the present invention, by
a wobble detection circuit, wherein a plurality of 
divided photodetector (light receiving) elements are
provided, each of the photodetector elements receives
reflectional light from each corresponding medium among
several kinds of media having different pre-formats, and
a pair of outputs of the photodetector element are
selected so as to share a rear processing circuit. Thus,
many parts of the wobble detection circuit can be used
in common irrespective of the pre-formats of the media,
and power consumption can be reduced since the size of
the wobble detection circuit is reduced. Additionally,
the above-mentioned wobble detection circuit can be
applied to an optical system having a divided structure
for each photodetector element.</p>
    <p num="0011">The object described above is also achieved,
according to another aspect of the present invention, by
a wobble detection circuit, wherein a plurality of
divided photodetector (light receiving) elements are
provided, each of the photodetector elements receives
reflectional light from each corresponding medium among
several kinds of media having different pre-formats, and
after obtaining push-pull signals from outputs of the
photodetector elements, one of the push-pull signals is
selected so as to use the rear processing circuit in
common. Thus, a part of the wobble detection circuit
can be used in common irrespective of the pre-formats of 
the media, and the power consumption can be reduced
since the size of the circuit is reduced. Additionally,
it is possible to obtain the wobble signals of good
quality since the process up to the generation of a
push-pull signal is performed before a selector, and
homologous noise components superimposed on two signals
input to a subtracting amplifier can be eliminated
effectively.</p>
    <p num="0012">The object described above is also achieved,
according to another aspect of the present invention, by
the wobble detection circuit, wherein wobble signals of
good quality can be obtained since a gain for amplifying
the signal in a wobble signal detection process is
changed depending on the pre-format so that signal
processing is possible while maintaining suitable signal
strength for the signals obtained by the plurality of
media having different pre-formats as well as
frequencies of the wobble signals.</p>
    <p num="0013">The object described above is also achieved,
according to another aspect of the present invention, by
the wobble detection circuit, wherein a plurality of
filter circuits having variable frequency
characteristics are provided, and the filter circuit is
selected according to the wobble frequency to be
detected. Thus, it is possible to obtain the wobble 
signals of good quality by providing an exclusive
circuit for each wobble frequency with regard to an
important part relating to performance of signal
detection, while using a part of the circuit in common
irrespective of the pre-formats of the media.</p>
    <p num="0014">The object described above is also achieved,
according to another aspect of the present invention, by
the wobble detection circuit, wherein the frequency
characteristic of the filter circuit is changed
according to the frequency to be detected. Thus, it is
possible to detect a wobble signal with the single
filter circuit from a multitude of media having
different pre-formats. Additionally, the single filter
circuit can be used in a CAV (constant angular velocity)
access in which the wobble frequency is changed
continuously.</p>
    <p num="0015">The object described above is also achieved,
according to another aspect of the present invention, by
the wobble detection circuit that can be used for pre-formats
of various frequencies merely by setting a
dividing ratio calculated by relationship between a
channel clock signal and a wobble signal to a divider
circuit, since a signal obtained by dividing the channel
clock of reproducing or recording data by a variable
divider circuit is used for a reference signal 
determining the frequency characteristic of the filter
circuit.</p>
    <p num="0016">The object described above is also achieved,
according to another aspect of the present invention, by
the wobble detection circuit, wherein the polarity of
the wobble signal is inverted depending on the pre-format
of the media. Thus, it is possible to generate a
binary wobble signal with a desired polarity
irrespective of the given polarity of the wobble signal
of each pre-format.</p>
    <p num="0017">The object described above is also achieved,
according to another aspect of the present invention, by
the wobble detection circuit, wherein characteristics of
the wobble detection circuit are changed and a selection
of a physical address detection circuit is made based on
a selected signal depending on the pre-format. Thus, an
operation of an unused address detection circuit can be
stopped. At the same time, an output terminal of the
address signal as well as a terminal of the wobble
signal can be used in common when the wobble detection
circuit is carried on such as an LSI, so that the size
of a package can be reduced.</p>
    <p num="0018">The object described above is also achieved,
according to another aspect of the present invention, by
an optical disk apparatus that carries the wobble 
detection circuit and can record on or reproduce several
kinds of the media having different pre-formats. Thus,
it is possible to realize a small and power-saving
optical disk apparatus having effective and high-performance
circuit structure.</p>
    <p num="0019">Other objects, features and advantages of the
present invention will become more apparent from the
following detailed description when read in conjunction
with the following drawings.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0020">
      <sl>
        <li>FIG. 1 is a block diagram showing a general
structure of an optical disk apparatus;</li>
        <li>FIG. 2 is an enlarged view of a part of a
medium;</li>
        <li>FIGS. 3A is an illustrative drawing showing a
divided-by-two photodetector (light receiving) element;</li>
        <li>FIG. 3B is an illustrative drawing showing a
subtracting amplifier producing a push-pull signal;</li>
        <li>FIG. 4A is an illustrative drawing showing a
divided-by-four photodetector (light receiving) element;</li>
        <li>FIG. 4B is an illustrative drawing showing
adding amplifiers and a subtracting amplifier producing
a push-pull signal;</li>
        <li>FIG. 5 is a block diagram showing a first 
embodiment of the present invention;</li>
        <li>FIG. 6 is a block diagram showing a second
embodiment of the present invention;</li>
        <li>FIG. 7 is a block diagram showing a second
embodiment of the present invention;</li>
        <li>FIG. 8 is a block diagram showing a third
embodiment of the present invention;</li>
        <li>FIG. 9 is a block diagram showing a fourth
embodiment of the present invention;</li>
        <li>FIG. 10 is a block diagram showing a fifth
embodiment of the present invention;</li>
        <li>FIG. 11 is a block diagram showing a sixth
embodiment of the present invention; and</li>
        <li>FIG. 12 is a block diagram showing a seventh
embodiment of the present invention.</li>
      </sl>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0021">FIG. 1 is a schematic diagram showing an
optical disk apparatus. A spot of laser light is
emitted on a medium 1, and reflection light is detected
by a pickup 2. The reproducing signal detected is
processed at a reproducing circuit 3. The data format
of a user data component generated by the reproducing
circuit 3 is converted by a decoder 4. The converted
user data is delivered to an external host (illustration 
thereof is omitted) via a CPU 5.</p>
    <p num="0022">Additionally, information to be recorded is
delivered from the external host to an encoder 6 via the
CPU 5. The data format of the information is converted
by the encoder 6. Then, the information is written on
the medium 1 such that a laser controlling circuit 7
controls emission of the laser carried on the pickup 2
according to information bit.</p>
    <p num="0023">On the other hand, a push-pull signal (a kind
of track error signal) detected by the pickup 2 is sent
to a wobble detection circuit 8. A wobble signal
extracted is sent to a servo circuit 9 or a clock
generation circuit 10. The servo circuit 9 controls
rotation of a motor 11 carrying the medium 1. The clock
generation circuit 10 generates an accurate clock
following rotation of the medium 1.</p>
    <p num="0024">Additionally, the push-pull signal including
the physical address is sent to an address detection
circuit 12. Then, the push-pull signal is converted
into address information by an address decoder 13. The
address decoder 13 decodes the address information of
accessing position. The pickup 2 carries an objective
lens that focuses the laser light and a photodetector
(light receiving) element that receives the reflection
light from the medium 1. </p>
    <p num="0025">The simplest example of a generation method of
the wobble signal used in the present invention is to
detect the wobble signal from the push-pull signal. FIG.
2 shows an enlarged view of a part of the medium, and
tracks T and a spot S are shown. The push-pull signal
is obtained by a difference between the reflection light
in the right side and the reflection light in the left
side with respect to a dividing line in a direction
tangential to the track. FIG. 3A shows a divided-by-two
photodectector (light receiving) element 100, which is
divided into two photodetector parts A and B by a
dividing line L1. The dividing line L1 is in a
tangential direction to the track. Output signals of
the photodetector parts A and B will respectively be
denoted by A and B. FIG. 3B shows a subtracting
amplifier reproducing the push-pull signal PPS. When
the divided-by-two photodetector element is used, the
push-pull signal PPS can be obtained by subtracting B
from A using the subtracting amplifier shown in FIG. 3B.</p>
    <p num="0026">FIG. 4A shows a divided-by-four photodetector
(light receiving) element 101 divided into four
photodetector parts A, B, C and D by the dividing line
L1 and a dividing line L2. The dividing line L2 is
orthogonal to the track. The output signals of the
photodetector parts A, B, C and D will respectively be 
denoted by A, B, C and D. FIG. 4B shows two adding
amplifiers and a subtracting amplifier. When the
divided-by-four photodetector element is used, the push-pull
signal PPS can be obtained as follows: the adding
amplifiers add A and B to D and C, respectively. Then,
the subtracting amplifier calculates a difference
between the two calculated results, that is, (A + D) -
(B + C). Accordingly, the wobble signals can be
obtained from predetermined components included in the
push-pull signals obtained as described above.</p>
    <p num="0027">A description will be given of the wobble
detection circuit of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0028">FIG. 5 is a schematic diagram showing a first
embodiment (corresponding to claim 1) of the present
invention. In this embodiment, a photodetector (light
receiving) element is used in common for receiving the
reflection light from the medium irrespective of the
pre-format.</p>
    <p num="0029">It is assumed that a photodetector (light
receiving) element 14 is the divided-by-four
photodetector (light receiving) element. A and D, and B
and C are symmetric with respect to the dividing line
that is orthogonal to the track. Two adding amplifiers
15 add A and B to D and C, respectively, so as to
generate two signals A + D and B + C. The two signals 
are divided by the dividing line in the tangential
direction to the track. Needless to say, the
photodetector (light receiving) element 14 may be the
divided-by-two photodetector (light receiving) element
or a structure of more parts as long as the two signals
divided by the dividing line in the tangential direction
to the track are generated.</p>
    <p num="0030">The push-pull signals are generated by
calculating the difference between the two signals by a
subtracting amplifier 16. Then, by digitalizing the
push-pull signals by a binary circuit 17, binary wobble
signals BWS are produced. Any one of the amplifiers in
the process described above or an amplifier 18 inserted
between the subtracting amplifier 16 and the binary
circuit 17 may have a gain switching function so as to
set an appropriate gain in accordance with the pre-format.</p>
    <p num="0031">The amplifier 18 is surrounded by a broken
line so as to indicate that the adding amplifier 15 or
the subtracting amplifier 16 may include the function of
the amplifier 18. For, since the wobble signal strength
standardized at the reproducing signal level differs
depending on the pre-format, the appropriate gain for
obtaining the binary wobble signals BWS of high quality
differs depending on the pre-format. </p>
    <p num="0032">FIG. 6 is a schematic diagram showing a second
embodiment (corresponding to claims 2 and 4) of the
present invention. This embodiment shows the structure
of the wobble signal detection circuit when the divided
photodetector element receiving the reflection light
from the medium differs depending on the pre-format.
Further, in FIGS. 6 through 12, those elements that are
the same as those corresponding elements in FIG. 5 are
designated by the same reference numerals.</p>
    <p num="0033">In FIGS. 6 through 8, two types of the pre-formats,
a type A and a type B, are shown as examples.
Additionally, in FIG. 6, it is assumed that a
photodetector (light receiving) element 21 of the type A
is a divided-by-four photodetector element, and a
photodetector (light receiving) element 22 of the type B
is a divided-by-two photodetector element. Thus, in
order to make the circuit after the subtracting
amplifier 16 the same as the circuit shown in FIG. 5, it
is preferable to select signals before the subtracting
amplifier 16.</p>
    <p num="0034">That is, a signal processing of the type A
pre-format is as follows: with regard to outputs of the
photodetector element 21, each addition amplifier 23
adds a pair of the signals that are symmetric with
respect to the dividing line; the dividing line is 
orthogonal to the track; two signals generated are
divided by the dividing line in the tangential direction
to the track. The outputs of the photodetector element
22 of the type B are directly input to a selector 24
since the photodetector element 22 is the divided-by-two
photodetector element. Needless to say, the
photodetector elements may alternately be structures
with more blocks instead of the divided-by-two
photodetector element or the divided-by-four
photodetector element, as long as two signals divided by
the dividing line in the tangential direction to the
track are produced before the signals are sent to the
selector 24. The pairs of signals obtained from a
plurality of media having different pre-formats are
input to the selector 24, and a pair of signals are
selected by the pre-format selection signal SEL. The
process thereafter is the same as the process of the
circuit in FIG. 5.</p>
    <p num="0035">FIG. 7 shows a case where a plurality of
photodetector (light receiving) elements 26 and 27 have
parts of the same number. In this case, outputs of
these photodetector elements 26 and 27 may directly be
input to a selector 28. Then, the signals selected by
the selector 28 may be added up by an adding amplifier
29. </p>
    <p num="0036">FIG. 8 shows a third embodiment (corresponding
to claims 3 and 4) of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0037">As shown by a type A wobble detection circuit
W1 and a type B wobble detection circuit W2, a plurality
of circuits are provided in parallel as many as the
number of the photodetector elements. The circuits
have the same structure as the circuit shown in FIG. 5
with regard to a part from the divided photodetector
element 14 to the subtracting amplifier 16. A selector
30 selects an output from the outputs of the wobble
detection circuits W1 and W2. The binary wobble signal
is obtained by the binary circuit 17. Needless to say,
it may be possible to provide a plurality of circuits
including the structure from the detection circuit to
the binary circuit 17 in parallel. However, it is
preferable that the output is selected before the output
is input to an output terminal so as not to increase the
number of the output terminals when the circuit is
incorporated in an LSI.</p>
    <p num="0038">The same as the amplifier shown in FIG. 5, the
amplifiers 18 in FIGS. 6 through 8 surrounded by the
broken lines have the gain switching function so as to
set the gain suitable for the pre-formats (corresponding
to claim 4). Needless to say, the adding amplifier or
the subtracting amplifier may have the function 
mentioned above. Especially, the gain switching
function is necessary for the amplifiers 18 in FIGS. 6
and 7 since the amplifiers 18 are provided between a
plurality of detection circuits and a single binary
circuit 17. On the other hand, when the amplifier 18 is
provided for each detection circuit, the amplifier 18
may have a fixed amplification function suitable for a
pre-format.</p>
    <p num="0039">FIG. 9 shows a fourth embodiment
(corresponding to claim 5) of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0040">The part before the subtracting amplifier 16
is the same as the corresponding part of the circuit
mentioned above. The output of the subtracting
amplifier 16, a push-pull signal, passes through a
filter circuit 19 for extracting the wobble signal
component by eliminating a noise component. Then, the
push-pull signal is amplified to proper amplitude by an
amplifier 20, and converted into a digital signal by the
binary circuit 17. Sets of the filter circuit 19 and
the amplifier 20 exclusive for corresponding pre-formats
are provided in parallel as many as the number of the
pre-formats, or sets of the filter circuit 19 and the
amplifier 20 that serve for a plurality of pre-formats
of the wobble signal frequencies that are approximately
the same may also be provided. When the set of the 
filter circuit 19 and the amplifier 20 serves for a
plurality of pre-formats, the number of the
photodetector elements and the number of the filters may
be different.</p>
    <p num="0041">Outputs of the amplifiers 20 are sent to the
selector 30. One of the outputs is selected by the
selecting signal SEL corresponding to the pre-format.
The selected output is input to the binary circuit 17.
The above explanation is given on the assumption that
the subtracting amplifier 16 receives outputs from a
plurality of adding amplifiers. Needless to say, it may
be possible to employ a structure in which the filter
circuit is provided after the selector 30. In this
structure, the selector 30 selects one of the outputs of
the plurality of subtracting amplifiers. Then, the
selected output is sent to the filter circuit.</p>
    <p num="0042">FIG. 10 shows a fifth embodiment
(corresponding to claims 6 and 7) of the present
invention.</p>
    <p num="0043">A filter circuit 21 extracts a wobble signal
component from the push-pull signal output by the
subtracting amplifier 16 by eliminating the noise
component. The filter circuit 21 is a variable
frequency characteristic filter that can be used in
common for the pre-formats of different wobble signal 
frequencies. The variable frequency characteristic is
such that a cut-off frequency of the filter changes
according to a signal provided from outside of the
circuit, a data channel clock signal, for example, or a
frequency of a reference signal obtained by dividing a
data channel clock signal by a 1/X frequency divider
circuit 22.</p>
    <p num="0044">As a general circuit, there are a SCF
(switched capacitor filter) and a phase comparison
filter. These filters can change the frequency
characteristics almost continuously. Thus, providing
the filter circuit 21 is equivalent to providing a
plurality of filters that have different fixed frequency
characteristics. Accordingly, providing the filter
circuit 21 has the advantages of size and
characteristics. For example, the wobble signal
frequency changes continuously depending on radius when
rotating a medium at CAV (constant angular velocity)
when the wobble is formed on the medium so as to realize
the CLV (constant linear velocity). The wobble signal
frequency becomes low at the inner diameter and high at
the outer diameter. Accordingly, it is necessary to
provide a multitude of filters, each of which has
different fixed frequency characteristics, when
accessing the medium of CLV format at CAV. However, it 
is preferable to use the filter of variable frequency
characteristics since better continuity is secured.</p>
    <p num="0045">FIG. 11 shows a sixth embodiment
(corresponding to claim 8) of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0046">In an example shown in FIG. 11, the circuit
ahead of the binary circuit 17 is the same structure as
the circuit mentioned above. The binary wobble signal
BWS digitized by the binary circuit 17 passes through
both an inversion buffer 40 that reverses the polarity
and an noninversion buffer 41 that does not change the
polarity. Then, the selector 30 selects one of outputs
of the inversion buffer 40 and the noninversion buffer
41. The selector 30 makes a selection based on a
polarity selection signal POL as a connection-switching
signal. A structure may also be possible in which the
polarity of the signal output by the subtraction
amplifier is reversed though the illustration thereof is
omitted.</p>
    <p num="0047">FIG. 12 shows a seventh embodiment
(corresponding to claim 9) of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0048">A physical address is formed on a medium for
recording so that an approximate position can be
identified though in an unrecorded area. For example,
the physical address can be identified by frequency
modulation to the wobble signals in CD, by prepits 
between tracks in DVD-RAM, and by LPP (land prepits)
between tracks in DVD-R. When the pre-format differs in
this way, a physical address detection circuit as well
as the wobble signal frequency differ. Thus, by using
selection signal SEL that selects the wobble detection
circuit 32 depending on the pre-format, the selector 30
switches address detection circuits (for example, an
address detection circuit 33A for the type A pre-format
and an address detection circuit 33B for the type B pre-format
as shown in FIG. 12) so as to obtain an address
signal ADS.</p>
    <p num="0049">As mentioned above, when a plurality of media
with different pre-formats use the same detection
circuits of the wobble signal and the address signal in
common, not only the size of the circuit can be reduced
but also an output terminal can be used in common so as
to use a small size package.</p>
    <p num="0050">The present invention is not limited to the
specifically disclosed embodiments, and variations and
modifications may be made without departing from the
scope of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0051">The present application is based on Japanese
priority application No. 2001-081152 filed on March 21,
2001, the entire contents of which are hereby
incorporated by reference.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A wobble detection circuit, wherein:
<claim-text><claim-text>a signal is detected by a common photodetector
(light receiving) element from several kinds of media
having different pre-formats; and</claim-text><claim-text>a gain for amplifying the signal in a wobble
signal detection process is changed depending on the
pre-format of a reproducing or recording medium to
obtain a wobble signal.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A wobble detection circuit, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>an optical system having a plurality of
photodetector (light receiving) elements corresponding
to several kinds of media having different pre-formats,
the optical system receiving reflectional light from a
medium at a corresponding photodetector element, each of
the photodetector elements being divided at least into
two parts by a line tangential to a track formed on the
medium;</claim-text><claim-text>a selector selecting a pair of outputs to be
used from the plurality of divided-by-two photodetector
elements;</claim-text><claim-text>a subtracting amplifier obtaining a difference
signal between the pair of outputs selected by the
selector; and</claim-text><claim-text>a binary circuit converting an output of the
subtracting amplifier into a digital signal;</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the selection of a pair of outputs
from the plurality of divided photodetector elements
depends on the pre-format of a reproducing or recording
medium.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A wobble detection circuit, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>an optical system having a plurality of
photodetector (light receiving) elements corresponding
to several kinds of media having different pre-formats,
the optical system receiving reflectional light from a
medium at a corresponding photodetector element, each of
the photodetector elements being divided at least into
two parts by a line tangential to a track formed on the
medium;</claim-text><claim-text>a plurality of subtracting amplifiers, each
subtracting amplifier obtaining a difference between a
pair of outputs of the corresponding divided-by-two
photodetector element; and</claim-text><claim-text>a selector selecting an output from outputs of
the plurality of the subtracting amplifiers;</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the selection of output from the
outputs of the plurality of the subtracting amplifiers
depends on the pre-format of a reproducing or recording
medium.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The wobble detection circuit as claimed in
claim 2 or 3, wherein a gain for amplifying a signal in
a wobble signal detection process is changed depending
on the pre-format of the reproducing or recording medium.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The wobble detection circuit as claimed in
claim 1, wherein a plurality of filter circuits having
different characteristics are provided, and the filter
circuit to be used is selected depending on wobble
frequency to be detected.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The wobble detection circuit as claimed in
claim 1, wherein a filter circuit having variable
frequency characteristic is provided, and the frequency
characteristic of the filter circuit is changed
depending on wobble frequency to be detected.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A wobble detection circuit as claimed in
claim 6, the filter circuit having:
<claim-text><claim-text>the frequency characteristic determined
according to a frequency of a provided reference signal;
and</claim-text><claim-text>a divider circuit dividing a channel clock
signal to obtain a reference signal for reproducing or
recording data,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein an output of the divider circuit is
regarded as the reference signal of the filter circuit,
and the frequency characteristic of the filter circuit
is changed by changing a dividing ratio.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The wobble detection circuit as claimed
in claim 1, wherein an inversion circuit inverting
polarity of the wobble signal and a selector selecting
noninversion or inversion are provided, and the polarity
is selected depending on the pre-format of the
reproducing or recording medium.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>The wobble detection circuit as claimed
in claim 8, comprising a plurality of physical address
detection circuits corresponding to the pre-formats and
a selector selecting a physical address detection
circuit, wherein characteristics of the wobble detection
circuit are changed and selection of the physical
address detection circuit is made based on a selecting
signal that depends on the pre-format of the reproducing
or recording medium.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>An optical disk apparatus, wherein the
wobble detection circuit claimed in claim 1 is mounted,
and recording or reproducing is performed with regard to
several kinds of media having different pre-formats.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
