<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1244208-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1244208" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="18937023" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020925">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1244208-A1" status="new" fvid="23564784">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1244208</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20020925</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02251947-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02251947</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020320</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001080812-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001080812</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010321</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H03F   1/52        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H03F   1/52        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H03F   3/20        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H03F   3/217       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H03F   1/52B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H03F   3/217B</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Leistungsverstärker</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Power amplifying device</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Amplificateur de puissance</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>PIONEER CORP</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>PIONEER CORPORATION</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Pioneer Corporation</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>4-1 Meguro 1-chome</street>
              <city>Meguro-ku, Tokyo</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HONDA JUN</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HONDA, JUN</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Honda, Jun c/o Pioneer Tokorozawa Plant</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>2610 Hanazono 4-chome</street>
              <city>Tokorozawa-City, Saitama</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Luckhurst, Anthony Henry William</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>MARKS &amp;amp; CLERK, 57-60 Lincoln's Inn Fields</street>
              <city>London WC2A 3LS</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A power amplifying device promptly detects an abnormal
condition of a load and permits protection of an output
without causing power loss. A test signal having a
predetermined frequency and signal level is supplied to an
amplifier, and the output level is measured. The measured
level is compared with the output level that is projected
when the test signal is supplied with an appropriate load
connected to the amplifier so as to detect a load condition.
If a determination result indicates that the load is shortcircuited
or released, then the operation of the amplifier
is promptly interrupted.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="98" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="113"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">1. Field of the Invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a power amplifying
device.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">2. Description of the Related Art</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0002">An amplifier used for amplifying electrical power
supplies a high electrical power to a load at a relatively
low output impedance. Hence, it is necessary to ensure that
the impedance of the load to which the amplifier is
connected is within a specified range. If the load is
short-circuited, the impedance of the load is reduced to
zero, and a large current flows into a power amplifying
element during an amplifier output stage, leading to a
failure of the power amplifying element used in the
amplifier output stage. For this reason, when an amplifier
is used to amplify electrical power, there is a required to
always check the condition of the load connected to the
amplifier, and to immediately interrupt the amplifying
operation of the amplifier to protect an amplifier output
stage circuit, if the impedance value of the load deviates
frog a predetermined range.</p>
    <p num="0003">A conventional amplifier for amplifying electric power
detects a load condition as described below. First, a
detection resistor having a small resistance value is
connected in series with the load to measure a voltage drop 
observed on the detection resistor due to load current.
Thus, changes in the load current are detected so as to
detect load conditions from the changes.</p>
    <p num="0004">In other words, the load conditions cannot be detected
unless the load current passes through the detection
resistor. More specifically, an abnormal load condition
cannot be detected unless an amplifying operation is
actually performed under an abnormal load condition.
Furthermore, since the detection resistor is connected in
series with a load, a power loss inevitably results by the
load current passing through the detection resistor. In
addition, a large resistance element must be used as the
detection resistor because of a heat generation problem
caused by such power loss. This adversely affects efforts
to provide smaller amplifiers.</p>
    <p num="0005">Recently, in response to the demands for reduced sizes
and higher efficiency of amplifiers, amplifiers using the
"class D amplifying method" are becoming more popular.</p>
    <p num="0006">According to the class D amplifying method, a input
analog signal is first subjected to processing for
modulation, such as pulse width modulation (PWM) or the
pulse density modulation (PDM). Then, a signal that has
been converted into a digital signal by the modulation is
amplified. Thereafter, the amplified signal is passed
through a low-pass filter to convert it back into an analog
signal. A class D amplifier is able to amplify an analog
signal simply by amplifying a digital signal (signal ON/OFF 
processing). Theoretically, therefore, 100% power
efficiency can be obtained. This makes it possible to
reduce the size of the amplifier by taking full advantage of
the high efficiency.</p>
    <p num="0007">Thus, the power loss attributable to the detection
resistor mentioned above and the need for using large
components because of the heat generation problem conflict
with the advantages obtained by class D amplifiers. There
is also a problem with the conventional method for detecting
a load condition since an abnormal load current cannot be
detected unless the load actually develops an anomaly.</p>
    <p num="0008">A class D amplifier has a low-pass filter in its output
section. When the amplifier is not under a load, a signal
current will only pass the low-pass filter of the output
section. In general, a filter of the output section is
constituted by an LC low-pass filter, and therefore has a
predetermined resonance frequency. For this reason, if a
signal input to the class D amplifier includes such a
resonance frequency, a resonance phenomenon occurs when the
amplifier is not under a load. This causes a significant
drop in the impedance of the output section of the class D
amplifier, allowing a large current to flow, which may
possibly lead to a failure of the class D amplifier. There
has been a problem with the conventional method for
detecting a load condition by using a detection resistor in
that it is difficult to detect a no-load condition of the
amplifier. </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">OBJECTS AND SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0009">Accordingly, the present invention was developed with a
view toward solving the problems described above. It is an
object of the present invention to provide a power
amplifying device that permits an abnormal load condition to
be quickly detected so as to protect an amplifier output,
and minimize power loss.</p>
    <p num="0010">To this end, according to one aspect of the present
invention, there is provided a power amplifying device which
includes a power amplifying circuit and to which a load
having a predetermined impedance is connected, including a
test signal generating part that generates a test signal
having a predetermined frequency, a signal level measuring
part that measures a signal level of the test signal that
has passed through a filtering circuit provided in an output
part of the electric power amplifying device, a signal level
comparing part that compares a measurement result supplied
by the signal level measuring part with a predetermined
reference signal level, and a control part that detects a
condition of the load connected to the power amplifying
device on the basis of a comparison result supplied by the
signal level comparing part, and provides protective
measures for the power amplifying device according to a
result of the detection.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BRIEF EXPLANATION OF THE DRAWINGS</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0011">
      <sl>
        <li>Fig. 1 is a block diagram showing a configuration of a
class D amplifier provided with a protective function that 
is an embodiment of the present invention;</li>
        <li>Fig. 2 is an explanatory diagram showing changes in the
frequency characteristic observed when the value of the load
impedance is changed in the device shown in Fig. 1;</li>
        <li>Fig. 3 is a flowchart showing the processing for
detecting a load condition and the processing for protecting
an amplifier in the device shown in Fig. 1;</li>
        <li>Fig. 4 is a block diagram showing the configuration of
a class D amplifier equipped with a protective function in
accordance with a second embodiment of the present
invention;</li>
        <li>Fig. 5 is a block diagram showing the configuration of
a class D amplifier equipped with a protective function in
accordance with a third embodiment of the present invention;
and</li>
        <li>Fig. 6 is a block diagram showing the configuration of
a class D amplifier equipped with a protective function in
accordance with a fourth embodiment of the present invention.</li>
      </sl>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0012">Fig. 1 is a block diagram showing the configuration of
a class D amplifier in accordance with the present invention.
Normally, a speaker 16 is connected to the class D amplifier
as a load.</p>
    <p num="0013">Referring to Fig. 1, a signal switching circuit 11
comprises an analog switch using, for example, an FET, a
transistor, or a mercury relay. The signal switching
circuit 11 switches between an input signal and a test 
signal in response to an input switching signal received
from a control circuit 20, and connects the selected signal
to an input section of a class D amplifier IC 14, comprising
a power amplifier circuit. The input signal is received
from audio equipment, such as a tuner or a CD player,
through a signal input terminal 10. The test signal is
supplied from a test signal generating circuit 12.</p>
    <p num="0014">The test signal generating circuit 12 is an oscillating
circuit that generates test signals used to detect load
conditions of the class D amplifier. The circuit comprises
a PLL synthesizer having, for example, a quartz resonator or
a ceramic resonator as an oscillating source, and is capable
of generating arbitrary frequencies. The frequencies to be
generated may be controlled by control signals supplied from
the control circuit 20.</p>
    <p num="0015">The class D amplifier IC 14 primarily includes a
comparator circuit 141, a triangular wave oscillation
circuit 142, an output-stage driver circuit 143, and an
output-stage circuit 144.</p>
    <p num="0016">The comparator circuit 141 compares a signal received
through the intermediary of the signal switching circuit 11
with a triangle wave from the triangle wave oscillation
circuit 142, converts the magnitude relationship between the
two signals into a binary signal, and outputs the binary
signal. Thus, the amplitude information regarding input
signals is converted into a change in the pulse width of a
binary signal. In other words, such processing generates a 
signal by subjecting input signals to PWM modulation.</p>
    <p num="0017">The output-stage driver circuit 143 converts the PWM
signal into two signals having phases that are inverted from
each other. These two signals are used to drive the gate of
the output-stage circuit 144. The output-stage circuit 144
comprises a power switching circuit formed by, for example,
a MOS-FET.</p>
    <p num="0018">A low-pass filter 15 suppresses harmonic components
contained in an output signal of the class D amplifier IC 14
to extract and reproduce a frequency component and an
amplitude component of the input signal. As mentioned above,
such a filter is generally includes an LC filter having a
small power loss.</p>
    <p num="0019">The speaker 16 converts electrical signals from the
low-pass filter 15 into acoustic signals and outputs the
acoustic signals.</p>
    <p num="0020">A test signal measuring circuit 17 comprises, for
example, a buffer amplifier having a high input impedance
and an A/D converter. The test signal measuring circuit 17
extracts an output signal from the low-pass filter 15
without influencing output of the filter, and measures the
signal level of the output signal.</p>
    <p num="0021">A reference signal level setting circuit 18 stores a
predetermined reference signal level. A signal level
comparator circuit 19 compares a signal level measured value
from the test signal measuring circuit 17 with a reference
signal level of the reference signal level setting circuit 
18. The signal level comparator circuit 19 supplies a
result of the comparison to the control circuit 20.</p>
    <p num="0022">The control circuit 20 is primarily a microcomputer
(hereinafter referred to as "the µCPU") that controls the
operation of the entire class D amplifier circuit shown in
Fig. 1. The control circuit 20 includes memory devices,
such as a read only memory (ROM) and a random access memory
(RAM). The ROM stores a main program and various types of
subroutine programs for the operation of the circuit. The
µCPU executes the programs in synchronization with built-in
clocks. The RAM temporarily saves diverse types of
processing results during the operation of the circuit and a
variety of types of flag registers providing guidelines for
making decisions in processing.</p>
    <p num="0023">An alarm display circuit 21 notifies a user of an
anomaly of a load connected to the low-pass filter 15. Such
anomaly may be a short circuit, release, etc. of the load.
The alarm display circuit 21 may comprise, for example, an
LED or a liquid crystal display device and a driving circuit
therefor.</p>
    <p num="0024">An operation input circuit 22 operates the class D
amplifier shown in Fig. 1. The operation input circuit 22
has a console panel including a ten-digit keypad and various
function keys, and a circuit for interfacing with the
control circuit 20. When a user wishes to detect the
condition of a load connected to the class D amplifier, the
user enters predetermined commands to the circuit to carry 
out the processing for the detection.</p>
    <p num="0025">Generally, the frequency characteristic of an LC low-pass
filter, in the region of a cutoff frequency fc is
disturbed unless the input/output impedances are matched.
The frequency characteristic, therefore, will be as shown in
Fig. 2 when the impedance of the load connected to the low-pass
filter 15 changes.</p>
    <p num="0026">As is obvious from Fig. 2, in the region of the cutoff
frequency fc of the filter, as the impedance of the load
increases over a design value, that is, as the load
approaches a released condition, the gain in the frequency
characteristic increases. Conversely, as the impedance of
the load decreases, that is, as the load approaches a short-circuited
condition, the gain in the frequency
characteristic decreases. In this embodiment, the class D
amplifier is protected by making use of the changes in the
frequency characteristic caused by the variations in the
load impedance.</p>
    <p num="0027">The function for detecting load conditions and the
function for protecting the amplifier in the circuit of Fig.
1 will now be described with reference to the processing
flowchart shown in Fig. 3.</p>
    <p num="0028">The processing illustrated by the flowchart of Fig. 3
may be arranged so that it is started at an "initial setting
operation" time at which the power of the class D amplifier
shown in Fig. 1 is turned ON. Alternatively, the processing
may be arranged so that it is manually started by a user at 
any time through the operation input circuit 22.</p>
    <p num="0029">When the processing shown in Fig. 3 is started, the
control circuit 20 first supplies an input switching signal
to the signal switching circuit 11 to switch the input of
the class D amplifier IC 14 to the test signal generating
circuit 12 (step 10). Then, the control circuit 20 supplies
a predetermined control signal to the test signal generating
circuit 12. Based on the received control signal, the test
signal generating circuit 12 generates a test signal that
has a predetermined frequency and a predetermined signal
level (step 11). The test signal is applied to the input
part of the class D amplifier IC 14 through the intermediary
of the signal switching circuit 11. The test signal is then
converted into a PWM signal in the class D amplifier IC 14
to undergo power amplification in a pulse waveform. An
output signal from the class D amplifier IC 14 passes
through the low-pass filter 15 so as to remove higher
harmonics superimposed on the signal, before the output
signal is supplied to the speaker 16, which is the load of
the low-pass filter 15.</p>
    <p num="0030">Setting the signal level of the test signal supplied to
the class D amplifier IC 14 at an extremely low signal level
will hold the signal level at the output end of the
amplifier IC 14 at a low value. This will prevent abnormal
current from passing the output stage of the class D
amplifier IC 14 even if the load is in an abnormal condition
when the test signal is supplied. </p>
    <p num="0031">In the embodiment shown in Fig. 1, a frequency in the
region of 44 kHz, which is the cutoff frequency of the low-pass
filter 15, is used as the frequency of the test signal.
As mentioned above, in the LC low-pass filter, the greatest
change in the frequency characteristic is caused by a change
in a load impedance at a frequency near the cutoff frequency.
At frequencies other than the frequencies around the cutoff
frequency, there is less disturbance in the frequency
characteristic attributable to a change in the impedance.
For this reason, the test signal of the frequency mentioned
above (in the region of 44 kHz) is used in this embodiment.</p>
    <p num="0032">The upper limit of human audible frequency is generally
known to be in the vicinity of 20 kHz. Hence, it is
unlikely that the test signal output as an acoustic signal
from the speaker 16 will be audible to users.</p>
    <p num="0033">If a low-pass filter having a cutoff frequency that is
lower than the aforesaid frequency (in the region of 44 kHz)
is used for the output of a class D amplifier, then it is
necessary to use a frequency in an audible range as the test
signal frequency. In this case, the test signal will be
leaked out as an audible sound from the speaker 16. However,
the processing shown in Fig. 3 is carried out when the power
is turned ON or a user decides to conduct a test for
detecting a load condition. This means that processing
based on the test signal is started while no signal is being
supplied from audio equipment to the class D amplifier.
Hence, the operation will not provoke any remarkable 
uncomfortableness of a user.</p>
    <p num="0034">The control circuit 20 drives the test signal
generating circuit 12 in step 11 to generate the test signal
and to actuate the test signal measuring circuit 17 in
synchronization with the test signal. Then, the test signal
measuring circuit 17 measures the output level of the test
signal supplied from the low-pass filter 15 to the speaker
16 (step 12). The measured value of the test signal level
is compared by the signal level comparator circuit 19 with
diverse reference signal levels set in the reference signal
level setting circuit 18 (steps 13 through 17).</p>
    <p num="0035">In step 13, it is first determined whether the measured
level of the test signal lies within a permissible range
with respect to the reference signal level. The reference
signal level here refers to the signal level appearing at
the output end of the low-pass filter 15 when a rated load
impedance is connected to the low-pass filter 15. The rated
load impedance in this case refers to a designed load
impedance. For the reference signal level, a value
determined by computation may be stored beforehand in the
ROM of the control circuit 20, and the stored value may be
loaded into the reference signal level setting circuit 18,
when the comparing operation is performed by the signal
level comparator circuit 19.</p>
    <p num="0036">It is assumed that the input level of the test signal
supplied to the class D amplifier IC 14, and the
amplification factor of the class D amplifier IC 14 are 
fixed. Then, it is also assumed that the impedance of the
load connected to the output end of the low-pass filter 15
is greater than a design value. As is obvious from Fig. 2,
in the vicinity of the cutoff frequency fc at this time, the
signal level appearing at the output end of the low-pass
filter 15 is higher than when the rated load is connected
thereto.</p>
    <p num="0037">Conversely, as the value of the load impedance
decreases to less than the design value, the signal level
around fc decreases, as shown in Fig. 2 mentioned above.</p>
    <p num="0038">More specifically, the condition of the load can be
detected by measuring the level of the test signal at the
output end of the low-pass filter 15, and comparing the
measured level with the signal level obtained when an
appropriate load is connected thereto.</p>
    <p num="0039">If it is determined in step 13 that the measured level
of the test signal is within the permissible range of the
reference signal level, then it is presumed that a load of
an appropriate impedance has been connected to the output
end of the low-pass filter 15. The control circuit 20
proceeds to step 20 to carry out the processing applied to a
case where the load is normal. Then, the control circuit 20
stops the operations of the test signal measuring circuit 17
and the test signal generating circuit 12. The control
circuit 20 also switches the signal switching circuit 11 to
the input terminal 10, then causes the class D amplifier IC
14 to start a normal amplifying operation. This terminates 
the processing illustrated by the flowchart shown in Fig. 3
(step 21).</p>
    <p num="0040">If it is determined in step 13 that the measured level
is not within the permissible range of the reference signal
level, then the signal level comparator circuit 19
determines whether the measured level has reached an upper
limit range of the signal level (step 14). The upper limit
range in this case refers to the level range within which an
output level may rise if a load is released or in a
condition close to release of the load. If an output level
increases to the upper limit range, then the signal level
comparator circuit 19 decides that the load has been
released or is in a condition close to release, and notifies
the control circuit 20 to that effect. Upon receipt of the
notification, the control circuit 20 issues an instruction
for displaying the release of the load to the alarm display
circuit 21 (step 15). Then, the control circuit 20 promptly
stops the operation of the class D amplifier IC 14 (step 16)
and terminates the processing shown in Fig. 3.</p>
    <p num="0041">If it is determined in step 14 that the measured level
has not reached the upper limit range, then the signal level
comparator circuit 19 determines whether the measured level
has decreased to a lower limit range of the signal level
(step 17). The lower limit range in this case refers to the
level range within which an output level may decreases if a
load is short-circuited or in a condition close to a short
circuit. If a measurement level decreases to the lower 
limit range, then the signal level comparator circuit 19
decides that the load has been short-circuited or in a
condition close to a short circuit, and notifies the control
circuit 20 to that effect. Upon receipt of the notification,
the control circuit 20 issues an instruction for displaying
the short circuit of the load to the alarm display circuit
21 (step 18). Then, the control circuit 20 promptly stops
the operation of the class D amplifier IC 14 according to
the processing of step 16 mentioned above and terminates the
processing shown by the flowchart of Fig. 3.</p>
    <p num="0042">If it is determined in step 17 that the measured level
has not decreased to the lower limit range, this condition
means following. The measured level of the test signal is
not within the permissible range, meaning that an
appropriate load impedance has not been connected, but the
output end of the low-pass filter 15 has not yet reached a
condition at which the load has been released or short-circuited.
In this case, the control circuit 20 carries out
processing as shown in the flowchart of Fig. 3 so as to
leave an action to be taken up to a decision made by a user.
Upon receipt of such a determination result from the signal
level comparator circuit 19, the control circuit 20 issues,
in step 19, an instruction to indicate a load anomaly to the
alarm display circuit 21. Thereafter, the control circuit
20 implements the processing from step 20 and step 21
mentioned above to start the normal amplifying operation of
the class D amplifier IC 14. </p>
    <p num="0043">To improve reliability, the processing for measuring
the signal level and the processing for determining a
measured value shown in Fig. 3 may be repeatedly carried out
for a predetermined number of times at short time intervals.
In this case, an arrangement may be made so that if any load
anomalies should be detected while the detection processing
is being repeatedly implemented, then it is decided that the
load has developed an abnormal condition, and the user is
alerted to stop the amplifying operation. Alternatively, it
may be arranged so that, if an anomaly is detected only once,
then only an alarm is displayed, and the amplifying
operation is not interrupted until the anomaly is detected
for at least a predetermined number of times.</p>
    <p num="0044">The class D amplifier with a protective function in
accordance with the present invention may have the
configuration shown by the block diagram of Fig. 4. The
block diagram of Fig. 4 shows a digital signal processing
circuit 13 that uses a digital signal processor (hereinafter
referred to simply as the "DSP") in the front stage of the
class D amplifier IC 14. The digital signal processing
circuit 13 directly receives digital signals from digital
audio equipment, such as an MD player or a digital tuner,
connected to the front stage of the amplifier.</p>
    <p num="0045">Accordingly, in the embodiment shown in Fig. 4, a test
signal from the test signal generating circuit 12 is
supplied as a digital signal to the signal switching circuit
11. Furthermore, adopting the configuration shown in Fig. 4 
makes it possible to receive control signals for the music
to be played, which are input signals, from the digital
audio equipment connected to the front stage. The control
signals in this case refer to the signals of information
regarding the start, end, intervals, etc. of the music to be
played. The control signals enable the control circuit 20
to detect a timing at which no such input signals of music
or the like are applied to the class D amplifier. At this
timing, the control circuit 20 may start the processing
shown in Fig. 3 to detect the condition of a load connected
to the class D amplifier.</p>
    <p num="0046">The digital signal processing circuit 13 includes a D/A
converter at its output end because the signals to be
supplied to the class D amplifier IC 14 must be turned into
analog signals. Forming the outputs from the digital signal
processing circuit 13 into PWM signals makes it possible to
directly drive the output-stage driver circuit 143 by using
the PWM output signals.</p>
    <p num="0047">The block diagram of Fig. 5 illustrates a class D
amplifier equipped with a protective function according to
another embodiment of the present invention. The class D
amplifier shown in Fig. 5 uses a signal superimposing
circuit 23 in place of the signal switching circuit 11 shown
in Fig. 1. The signal superimposing circuit 23 in this
embodiment comprises, for example, an adding circuit and a
signal hybrid circuit. In the embodiment shown in Fig. 5, a
test signal from a test signal generating circuit 12 is 
superimposed on an input signal from an input terminal 10,
and the resulting signal is supplied to the input part of a
class D amplifier IC 14. The embodiment is configured such
that only a test signal is extracted through a band pass
filter 24 for extracting a test signal, that is located at
the output end of a low-pass filter 15, and the extracted
test signal is supplied to a test signal measuring circuit
17.</p>
    <p num="0048">The test signal extracting filter 24 may be constructed
of an active filter having a high input impedance so as to
minimize the influences of the low-pass filter 15 on outputs.
Alternatively, the test signal extracting filter 24 may be
constructed of a DSP having a high input impedance. In this
case, the filtering for extracting the test signal will be
digitally effected and measured values input to the test
signal measuring circuit 17 is also supplied in the form of
digital signals.</p>
    <p num="0049">In the embodiment shown in Fig. 5, it is required to
securely separate the test signal from input signals of
music or the like by using the test signal extracting filter
24 when taking out the test signal. For this purpose, it is
necessary to set the cutoff frequency of the low-pass filter
15 at a level higher than that in a band wherein the input
signals for music or the like exist. It is preferred to set
the frequency of a test signal at the cutoff frequency of
the low-pass filter 15 or at a frequency in the vicinity
thereof. This setting causes the test signal to have a 
frequency that is higher than the band wherein the input
signals of music or the like are present, that is, higher
than a human audible frequency band. Thus, it is possible
to constantly check a load condition without causing a user
to notice a test signal sound leaking out of a speaker 16.
This leads to dramatically improved reliability of the
amplifier.</p>
    <p num="0050">As shown in Fig. 6, the input part of the class D
amplifier of Fig. 5 may be formed of a digital signal
processing circuit 13 using the DSP shown in Fig. 4. This
makes it possible to start the operation for checking a load
by using control signals from digital audio equipment
connected to the front stage of the class D amplifier, as
explained in conjunction with Fig. 4.</p>
    <p num="0051">When the configuration shown in Fig. 6 is adopted, the
same interface as explained in conjunction with Fig. 4 will
be used for the interface between the digital signal
processing circuit 13 and the class D amplifier IC 14.</p>
    <p num="0052">A band width of the input signals after conversion is
restricted to within a band width that is half a sampling
frequency or less regardless of whether the A/D conversion
on the input signals of music or the like is effected inside
or outside the class D amplifier, as is obvious from the
sampling theorem.</p>
    <p num="0053">Accordingly, as shown in Fig. 5 or Fig. 6, when a test
signal is superimposed on the input signals of music or the
like, the cutoff frequency of the low-pass filter 15 is set 
at a frequency higher than the frequency that is half the
sampling frequency of the input signals, and the frequency
of the test signal is set at or near the cutoff frequency.
Under this setting condition, only the test signal can be
securely extracted without being influenced by the input
signals. Moreover, the condition of a load can be
constantly monitored, permitting further reliable protection
of an amplifier.</p>
    <p num="0054">The present invention is not limited to the embodiments
described above. The present invention may alternatively be
embodied by a one-chip LSI that includes such constituents
as the control circuit 20, the signal level comparator
circuit 19, and the digital signal processing circuit 13.
In this case, a µCPU included in the LSI may carry out the
operation processing explained above merely by using
software according to programs also included in the LSI.</p>
    <p num="0055">In the embodiments set forth above, the class D
amplifier has only a single channel; however, the present
invention is not limited thereto. For instance, the
embodiments may alternatively use a class D amplifier having
a stereo channel or more multiple channels for signal
amplification.</p>
    <p num="0056">Furthermore, as shown in Fig. 4 or Fig. 6, providing
the input part of the class D amplifier IC 14 with the
digital signal processing circuit 13 makes it possible to
carry out various types of digital signal processing on the
input signals. For example, an arrangement may be made such 
that digital filtering for suppressing only a particular
frequency component (e.g., a resonance frequency component
of the low-pass filter 15) contained in the input signals
may be carried out on the input signals, when the release of
a load is detected. This allows the class D amplifier IC 14
to be protected when the load is released.</p>
    <p num="0057">The interruption of the operation of the class D
amplifier IC 14 that is effected when an abnormal condition
of a load is detected, as described in the above embodiments,
is not limited to a forcible interruption of the amplifying
operation of the class D amplifier IC 14. The interruption
of the operation includes, for example, the processing for
restricting the supply of input signals to the class D
amplifier IC 14. In other words, the term "the interruption
of the operation" generically refers to any processing that
restrains the supply of current to an output stage of the
class D amplifier IC 14.</p>
    <p num="0058">Substantially as described above, the present invention
provides a configuration that permits the load condition of
an amplifier to be detected by measuring the output level of
a class D amplifier by using a low-level test signal. With
this arrangement, it is possible to protect the amplifier
against overcurrent caused by an abnormal load condition.</p>
    <p num="0059">Moreover, the present invention obviates the need for a
large power resistance element for measuring load current.
This prevents wasteful power loss and accordingly prevents
heat generation resulting from the power loss, thus 
contributing to a reduction in size and increased
integration scale of an amplifier.</p>
    <p num="0060">It is understood that the foregoing description and
accompanying drawings set forth the preferred embodiments of
the invention at the present time. Various modifications,
additions and alternative designs will, of source, become
apparent to those skilled in the art in light of the
foregoing teachings without departing from the spirit and
scope of the disclosed invention. Thus, it should be
appreciated that the invention is not limited to the
disclosed embodiments but may be practiced within the full
scope of the appended claims.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A power amplifying device to which a load having a
predetermined impedance is connected, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a power amplifying circuit;</claim-text><claim-text>a test signal generating part that generates a test
signal having a predetermined frequency;</claim-text><claim-text>a signal level measuring part that measures a signal
level of the test signal that has passed through a filtering
circuit provided in an output part of the power amplifying
device;</claim-text><claim-text>a signal level comparing part that compares a
measurement result supplied by the signal level measuring
part with a predetermined reference signal level; and</claim-text><claim-text>a control part that detects a condition of the load
connected to the electric power amplifying device on the
basis of a comparison result supplied by the signal level
comparing part, and effects protection of the electric power
amplifying device in accordance with a detection result of
the control part.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The power amplifying device according to Claim 1,
wherein the power amplifying circuit is a power amplifying
circuit that effects class D power amplification.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The power amplifying device according to Claim 1,
wherein the frequency of the test signal generated by the
test signal generating part includes a cutoff frequency of
the filtering circuit.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A power amplifying device to which a load having a
predetermined impedance is connected, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a power amplifying circuit;</claim-text><claim-text>a test signal generating part that generates a test
signal having a predetermined frequency;</claim-text><claim-text>a signal level measuring part that measures a signal
level of the test signal that has passed through an LC
filtering circuit provided in an output part of the power
amplifying device;</claim-text><claim-text>a signal level comparing part that compares a
measurement result supplied by the signal level measuring
part with a predetermined reference signal level; and</claim-text><claim-text>a control part that detects a condition of the load
connected to the electric power amplifying device on the
basis of a comparison result supplied by the signal level
comparing part, and effects control to suppress a frequency
component in an input signal supplied to the LC filtering
circuit at which the LC filtering circuit resonates in
accordance with a detection result of the control part.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The power amplifying device according to Claim 4,
wherein the power amplifying circuit is a power amplifying
circuit that effects class D power amplification.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The power amplifying device according to Claim 4,
wherein the frequency of the test signal generated by the
test signal generating part includes a cutoff frequency of
the LC filtering circuit.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
