<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1262748-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1262748" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="27383135" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021204">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1262748-A2" status="new" fvid="23607268">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1262748</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021204</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02011926-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02011926</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020529</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="US-12466702-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>12466702</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20020416</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
      <priority-claim ucid="US-29492501-P" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>29492501</doc-number>
          <kind>P</kind>
          <date>20010530</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
      <priority-claim ucid="US-31694501-P" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>31694501</doc-number>
          <kind>P</kind>
          <date>20010831</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04N   1/60        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04N   1/60        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H04N   1/60F2</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Vorrichtung und Verfahren zur Rechnergestützten Fernprüfung von Farben</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">A remote proofing computer system and method</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé et dispositif informatisés d'épreuve de couleurs à distance</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HEWLETT PACKARD CO</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HEWLETT PACKARD COMPANY, A DELAWARE CORPORATION</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Hewlett Packard Company, a Delaware Corporation</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>3000 Hanover Street</street>
              <city>Palo Alto, CA 94304</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GONZALEZ ANDRES</name>
            <address>
              <country>ES</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MACKENZIE ANDREW</name>
            <address>
              <country>ES</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SUCH ALBERT</name>
            <address>
              <country>ES</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GONZALEZ, ANDRES</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MACKENZIE, ANDREW</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SUCH, ALBERT</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>GONZALEZ, ANDRES</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>C/ Virgen del Pilar 82 A</street>
              <city>08291 Cerdanyola del Valles</city>
              <country>ES</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>MACKENZIE, ANDREW</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Rosellon 157-159</street>
              <city>08036 Barcelona</city>
              <country>ES</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>SUCH, ALBERT</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Muntaner, 147 Principal 1a</street>
              <city>08036 Barcelona</city>
              <country>ES</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Yennadhiou, Peter</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Hewlett Packard Espanola, Legal Department Avda. Graells, 501</street>
              <city>08190 Sant Cugat del Vallès, Barcelona</city>
              <country>ES</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>NL</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>Conventional obstacles to entry and survival of small
graphic-arts service providers are softened ― particularly
for those businesses that operate as computerized "ASP"
enterprises (21-25) involving wide-area networks ― by
encouraging small operators to coexist effectively in use
of a pivotal network-based service. One key mechanism
promoting this capability is a system of optionally mutual
links (Figs. 13-15; lower half of Figs. 2, 7, 12 and 16-27)
between the pivotal service (11) and the ASPs. The
service also counteracts a tendency in the industry to
favor wastefully redundant vertical integration. On the
other hand, the system also implements the prerogatives of
an enterprise (such as a printing-broker ASP, 24) that has
an established customer, to closely channel the attention
of that customer ― but subject, importantly, to being
overruled by the customer. Ideally the system is
carefully tuned to enable such customer action without
unduly pressing the option upon the customer.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="115" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="85"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <u style="single">RELATED PATENT DOCUMENTS</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0001">Closely related documents are other, coowned U. S.
utility-patent applications filed in the U. S. Patent and
Trademark Office ― and hereby incorporated by reference
in their entirety into this document. Two are copending
U. S. provisional applications of Such <u style="single">et al.</u>, serials
60/294,925 and 60/316,945, whose priority benefit is hereby
claimed. A third is in the names of Jodra <u style="single">et al.</u>, serial
09/832,638, later issued as U. S. Patent 6,<u style="single">      </u>,<u style="single">      </u>.
A fourth is in the names of Vilanova <u style="single">et al.</u>, 09/945,492,
later U. S. 6,<u style="single">      </u>,<u style="single">      </u>. A fifth is in the names of Soler
<u style="single">et al.</u>, serial 09/919,260, later U. S. 6,<u style="single">      </u>,<u style="single">      </u> ― together
with references cited therein. A sixth is in the
names of Subirada <u style="single">et al.</u>, serial 09/919,207, later U. S.
6,<u style="single">      </u>,<u style="single">      </u>. A seventh is attorney docket 60013597Z152 in
names of Gonzalez <u style="single">et al.</u>, titled "REMOTE HARDCOPY PROOFING
SERVICE ADAPTIVELY ISOLATED FROM THE INTERNET", in preparation
concurrently herewith, and later U. S. 6,<u style="single">      </u>,<u style="single">      </u>.
Also potentially of interest and wholly incorporated herein
are U. S. 6,043,909 and 6,157,735 of Richard A. Holub.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0002">This invention relates generally to remote hardcopy
proofing; and more particularly to integration of business
systems and procedures for remote hardcopy proofing of
printing jobs including color images. Preferred embodiments 
include integrated features for incorporating the
efficiencies and consumer benefits of electronic commerce
and advanced technology into buying, soft proofing and data
transfer for such printing jobs. Preferred embodiments
are especially effective in association with closed-loop-color
proofing.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0003">
      <sl>
        <li>(a) <u style="single">Classical relationships in the industry</u> ― Classical
participants in the printing or so-called "graphic
arts" industry generally fell into these categories:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>a primary customer or client ― <u style="single">i. e.</u>, a publisher or
other entity that wished to have printed goods for
its own purposes, ranging from advertising to fiction,
technical data or poetry;</li><li>a printing house, which physically produced the final
printed goods ― and which could vary from a neighborhood
family "instant printer" business to a giant
international producer of fine-quality books and
magazines;</li><li>a prepress entity, which could be a free-standing
business serving small printing houses or could be a
department or makeready room within a large printing
house ― and whose function was to receive camera-ready
copy and sometimes raw text copy (manuscript)
to be typeset, and from these materials to generate 
printing negatives and plates for use in actual
printing production;</li><li>a graphic artist or advertising agency, which could
be a free-standing business or could be associated
with either the primary customer or the prepress
entity ― and whose function was to generate, from a
customer's instructions and other inputs, the camera-ready
copy which would then become the prepress entity's
input materials;</li><li>a customer-service representative, ordinarily an
individual associated with the printing or prepress
house (often the proprietor or manager of that entity),
who typically met at that entity's makeready
room, or conference room, with the artist's or customer's
representative to "show proof" ― <u style="single">i. e.</u>, personally
take from the makeready-room job bins and hand
to that representative, for discussion, a preproduction
specimen of the job, based on negatives (or
plates) that had been readied for production of the
finished piece;</li><li>a courier, who simply carried the specimen physically
from the prepress or printing house to the artist's
or customer's representative in event the latter did
not wish to travel to the prepress or printing facilities;
and</li><li>a buyer, who once again could be either a free-standing
business (sometimes denominated a "printing broker"),
or who could be associated with the primary
customer or with the graphic artist or ad agency ― 
and whose function was to select and negotiate with,
most commonly on behalf of the primary customer,
suitable printing and prepress institutions for the
kind and scope of job to be printed.</li></ul></li>
      </sl>
    </p>
    <p num="0004">Most of these classical categories of participants
survive to the present day. Sea changes, however, have
arrived with the electronic age ― more specifically with
its character as a so-called "information age", and especially
with the advent of wide-area networks in general
and the Internet in particular, and the Worldwide Web, and
the now-familiar concept of a "website".
<sl><li>(b) <u style="single">Websites, and other FTP sites</u> ― As is well
known in this field, the acronym "FTP" means "file transfer
protocol". FTP is a standard procedure for operation
of two computers, commonly but not necessarily remote from
each other, to copy a computer file from one of the machines
to the other.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0005">The data may pass through the Internet, or through
another type of network such as but not necessarily a private
network. Alternatively FTP data may pass through a
peer-to-peer telephone connection ― or even simply a direct
cable ― between the two computers.</p>
    <p num="0006">People skilled in this field will understand that an
FTP site or in particular a website enables a user in control
of the connection to copy data in one direction or
the other, or possibly in both directions. A website is
in essence a special case of an FTP site, namely one to
which connection is made through the Internet, using its
Worldwide Web capabilities.</p>
    <p num="0007">A website or other FTP site ordinarily encompasses
some sort of user interface, but this may be of a very 
primitive type ― for example, responding only to simple
typed-in FTP syntax as through a DOS or Unix console application.
Thus for purposes of the present document such
a site does not necessarily provide GUI interactions, or
even full-screen DOS or Unix data-reading and data-entry
functions, although modernly a GUI format is extremely
common and popular.</p>
    <p num="0008">FTP sites are usually automatic ― that is, in normal
operation largely free from human intervention. For present
purposes, however, most such sites require some level
of security, authentication etc. All of that, if present,
is considered part of the well-known infrastructure of the
FTP site and associated network connections.
<sl><li>(c) <u style="single">The printing-broker ASP</u> ― One way in which the
electronic age naturally modified the classical system was
to undermine the position of the buyer or broker. The
broker's major role was as a purveyor of accumulated information
and wisdom about printing and prepress ― in
other words, as a guide and shepherd who conducted primary
customers, in relative safety and surefootedness, to suitable
production people.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0009">The guide, however, extracted a relatively sizable
toll (commission) for the guidance, which was a mixture of
interpersonal skills with <u style="single">basic information</u> about the industry.
In an information age it has been natural for
money to seek an alternative route.</p>
    <p num="0010">Thus some computer-wise buyers or brokers undertook
to gain an economic advantage over other buyers and brokers
by automating the process. The familiar introductions,
questions, answers and contractual arrangements
were easy to convert into text, checkboxes and "FAQS"
(frequently asked question-and-answer lists) in websites, 
and through use of this mechanism a single industry-experienced
broker could easily service perhaps an order of
magnitude greater clientele, at far lower cost to each
customer.</p>
    <p num="0011">Great variation in skill, communication, pricing and
overall effectiveness is inevitable in such efforts, and
many brokers and agents doubtless continue to operate in
the classical manner. Their function has given way, however,
to a new niche in the industry: a broker/agent "application
service provider" or "ASP". (The acronym and
therefore the terminology are likely derived, in that order,
by analogy to the better-known "ISP", or Internet
service provider ― who simply receives telephone calls
and automatically connects the callers to high-speed
optic-fiber or cable Internet ports.)</p>
    <p num="0012">This printing-broker ASP, or <u style="single">transactional ASP</u>, or by
abbreviation <u style="single">transASP</u> serves a function very much akin to
the traditional broker/agent function ― but does so by
inviting customers and printshops alike to come on-line
electronically. While on-line they meet, negotiate, and
do business with one another through a website intermediary
and user interface (<u style="single">e. g.</u>, a graphical user interface,
"GUI") protocol rather than through personally guided introductions
and personally conducted negotiations.
<sl><li>(d) <u style="single">The proofer ASP</u> ― Another natural modification
of the classical scheme arose from the classical industry
custom called "showing proofs" (preproduction approximate
samples of print jobs) ― and the viewing and approving of
those proofs. The earlier-mentioned Jodra patent document
discusses this function at length, pointing out in particular
that it is a central function related to the economics
of allocating costs of error or disagreement.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0013">At the same time, however, classically the viewing of
hardcopy proofs itself generated very substantial costs ―
in travel by people whose time was expensive, and in delay,
and even in additional disagreements. This process
of showing proofs accordingly became another sensitive
high-pressure point in the flow of money and other resources
through the graphic-arts industry.</p>
    <p num="0014">Various computerized proof-related workflow models
have rapidly evolved in the natural seeking of lower impedances
to the flow of work, time and cash. Since it is
now common for customers to supply original artwork in the
form of a computer data file, it is natural for a graphic
artist, prepress or printing house to want to send back
some kind of picture of how the finished job will appear.</p>
    <p num="0015">The easiest way to do this is in the form of a set of
image data files that can be displayed on a computer
screen or monitor, showing with varying degrees of roughness
how the makeready work has progressed. Such a file
in many cases can be simply sent by e-mail to the customer
or agent.</p>
    <p num="0016">An incidental benefit has been to reduce the need for
commitment of time and talent by the classical customer-service
representative mentioned above. Much of what that
individual typically did can now be reduced, once again,
to carefully drafted text and checkboxes in a website.
With care, a personal touch can be maintained at this
critical point, while both the enterprise and its customer
enjoy improved efficiency and economics ― without adverse
effects on quality or competition, or survival of the
small business entity.</p>
    <p num="0017">Already a great deal of convention has grown up
around this approach, in the nature of somewhat standardized
image-presentation formats (<u style="single">e. g.</u> the "portable document 
file" or "PDF" introduced by the Adobe company), and
likewise somewhat standardized transaction summary formats
(<u style="single">e. g.</u> the "job definition file" or "JDF"). Printing out
a PDF image on a computer printer is quite commonplace,
but introduces myriad complications and still further
sources of disagreement ― and therefore many operators
have focused on the far more straightforward process of
showing proof on a computer monitor.</p>
    <p num="0018">Since no hardcopy proof is involved, this type of
proof is called a "soft proof" or sometimes even a "virtual
proof". It is understood that in many ways what appears
on the monitor is intrinsically different from what
will appear eventually on some printing medium (such as
paper), but such are the pressures of the industry that
many participants are glad to accept such variations as a
sufficient approximation.</p>
    <p num="0019">In fact it is possible that the intrinsic differences
are so obvious and striking that they actually defuse a
large part of the complication that can arise in showing
proofs. For example, the customer may perhaps be warned
that "of course" colors and even proportions may appear
"very" different from the finished product, and the proof
is being shown only to give the customer a "rough" idea
that the job is being assembled correctly.</p>
    <p num="0020">Because of the very plain intrinsic differences of
the self-luminous screen display with its vivid additive
primaries and the purely reflective printed matter, rendered
in subtractive primaries, customers and artists undoubtedly
tend to discount and overlook relatively major
differences. In this way, interestingly, many of the most
difficult confrontations between printer/prepress and artist/customer
may be simply sidestepped. Also interestingly, 
for many customers and even many artists this is
sufficient.</p>
    <p num="0021">Soft proofing is particularly useful and adequate at
an earlier stage of project development when an artist or
advertising agency is showing a <u style="single">concept</u> proof to a customer
or buyer. Here it is understood that the final colors,
proportions, papers etc. are all only a matter of
fine detail; and what is being shown is an original creative
idea, fresh from the artistic mind and just first
reduced to a tentative wording and layout. It is also
usually understood that the final product will be subject
to showing of a hardcopy proof.</p>
    <p num="0022">In any event the preparation of even a virtual or
soft proof is not without its hazards, and this stage of
work has engendered another kind of application service
provider: the proofing ASP. Such an entity is likely to
start off in business with preparation and transmission of
soft proofs, and negotiations over them ― but perhaps in
the nature of the business a proofing ASP tends to gravitate
into preparation of hardcopy proofs as well, as customers
inquire whether the ASP cannot provide something
more permanent and more satisfying.</p>
    <p num="0023">The proofing ASP typically enjoys an advantage of
having a business outlet with geographical proximity to
the primary customer or artist, and by dint of experience
and professionalism can do a reasonably creditable job of
making a hardcopy proof look generally similar to the anticipated
eventual production piece. At this point, however,
what is being shown is a printed item on a piece of
printing medium that can be held in the hand ― and not
incidentally can be kept for comparison with what is later
delivered. </p>
    <p num="0024">Accordingly the customer and artist are much less
willing to accept significant variations. The greater
capability actually ups the ante as to what is demanded.
<sl><li>(e) <u style="single">The e-transport ASP</u> ― The Internet, although
initially it may have sparked much of the computer revolution
in the graphic-arts industry, was neither the first
nor the last computer network. Furthermore it was neither
the first nor last service operated by most of its primary
users over telephone connections ― examples of particularly
successful such services being in the field of legal
caselaw research.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0025">It is also natural that many users have found the Internet
unsatisfactory for industrial purposes. The medium
was almost pristine in its academic atmosphere as recently
as fifteen years ago, but since its invasion by the Windows-driven
general public the Internet has now become
susceptible to excessive congestion and dropped connections.
Particularly for relatively unsophisticated computer
users in small businesses, the Internet is also now
susceptible to massive proliferation of advertising, junk
mail and other distractions from a businesslike procedure.
Fast lines (digital service lines or cable) are not available
everywhere.</p>
    <p num="0026">Offering an escape from all such annoyances ― and
also offering ancillary services such as large-volume
website storage, software escrow, and delivery follow-up
― is the <u style="single">private-network</u> ASP. This type of business focuses
primarily upon maintaining and operating a reliable
fast optic-fiber/coax-cable backbone between major hubs.</p>
    <p num="0027">These capabilities are rapidly replacing the classical
courier service. The trend is natural since what is
to be moved from one place to another is already information 
in digital form; and the transportation of physical
mass (<u style="single">e. g.</u> paper) is fundamentally irrelevant to the
transport of image information.</p>
    <p num="0028">Some such businesses offer ample dial-up telephone
numbers, as do the familiar ISPs. Some offer a customer
an on-site termination directly, or almost directly, to
the backbone.</p>
    <p num="0029">Through various migrations some private-net ASPs have
become associated with one or another industry. The
graphic-arts industry is one natural magnet for such association,
since it supports a very large and steady flow
of very large (megabyte and even gigabyte) files.
<sl><li>(f) <u style="single">ASP hybridization</u> ― Some ASPs in and servicing
the graphic-arts industry have tended to acquire complementary
ASP activities. For example, a private-network
ASP may begin to offer specific soft-proofing support
services ― perhaps because of a bad experience with a
graphic-arts customer who went down the street to visit a
broker or soft proofer one day, discovered that the broker
or proofer had a good deal with another network, and never
came back.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0030">Similarly a printing-industry transASP (e-broker) may
begin to offer some limited form of proofing for its customers.
The quieter reason may be to keep its customers
from straying out of the fold to local graphic artists or
local prepress shops that may have convenient proofing capabilities
― but who may also want to divert the middleman
function to their own channels.</p>
    <p num="0031">Analogously a virtual-proofing ASP may begin to offer
the so-called "digital asset management" more naturally
expected of the private-net ASP. Once again the underlying
motivation may be to offer the most comprehensive 
service possible, with an eye to minimizing a customer's
motivation to wander out into the digital-asset-management
marketplace and perhaps inadvertently stumble into a cheaper
virtual-proof ASP.</p>
    <p num="0032">Of course it is not intended to suggest that all ASP
hybrids have developed from such protective instincts or
specific negative experiences. Some are simply a matter
of natural business expansion ― into areas, for example,
of inquiry from existing customers.</p>
    <p num="0033">Nevertheless the phenomenon of vertical expansion
among these ASP functions is surely driven in significant
part by wariness. Time, talent and even money devoted to
cultivating a good customer can evaporate quickly and devastatingly
in the maximally competitive, extremely volatile
and minimally loyal printing industry.</p>
    <p num="0034">One may question, however, the overall efficiency and
the primary-customer benefits of such integration. A
first impact of this trend appears to be greater redundancy
for each of the functions involved ― and then an
even-more-heightened competitiveness, in an industry already
marked by low margins and a frenetic work ethic. In
the end a resulting trend is to squeeze out small operators,
who have traditionally tended to preserve the primary
customer's options for diversity, enduring economy,
and personal service.</p>
    <p num="0035">Although a certain amount of copartnering is seen
among some successful graphic-arts ASP enterprises, the
cautionary character of the printing-business mind tends
to deter full and fruitful exploitation of this healthy
alternative to vertical expansion. This limited degree of
copartnering may be seen as a significant problem in the
printing industry. </p>
    <p num="0036">Another deterrent, adding to the same problem in the
industry, is a lack of full interoperability between different
service ASPs. A certain degree of effort to build
standards for linking various printing ASPs has been proposed
in the trade, as for example in the PrintTalk Consortium,
but this thrust has not been successful ― at
least not yet.</p>
    <p num="0037">Furthermore it appears to focus most on e-commerce
aspects, rather than technical aspects, of coventuring.
That is, PrintTalk defines basically a protocol to perform
print-job brokering ― request for quote, quote, order and
so forth.</p>
    <p num="0038">Implementation of such proposals for interASP integration
is strongly hindered by the present state of the
art. The reason for this is that diverse so-called "job
models" ― or "life cycles", or "workflow management" designs
― are barriers to interoperability. These terms
are all in essence synonymous, and refer to the basic
functions of knowing and changing either the <u style="single">status</u> of a
job (whether or not a proof is involved) or <u style="single">actions</u> that
can be taken in relation to a job.</p>
    <p num="0039">For example, a remote-hardcopy-proofing ASP may not
have a job model that supports closed-loop color proofing
in which colors on the printing medium are objectively
measured and checked. As another example, in order to
job-out a single client's work to two different remote
proofing ASPs, a transASP would have to somehow integrate
different remote-proofing workflows with different job
models.</p>
    <p num="0040">These barriers are problematic. Increased copartnering
would benefit not only the consumer (by fostering a
healthy form of efficiency and a healthy degree of competition
while deterring more-savage aspects of competition), 
but also the smaller operators in the field ― by
enabling them to compete more effectively without resorting
to cutthroat strategies. Therefore, enhancement of
stimuli to such coventuring efforts among complementary
ASPs would be beneficial across the board.</p>
    <p num="0041">An example of what is basically a graphic-arts transactional
ASP is the company known as PrintCafe. Examples
of businesses whose primary focus has been service as a
virtual-proof ASP are RealTime Proof and the former Vio.
An example of the private-net ASP is Wam!net.</p>
    <p num="0042">Each of these three businesses has moved into aspects
of the graphic-arts industry that overlap with the primary
functions of one or both of the other two businesses.
<sl><li>(g) <u style="single">The hardcopy proofing service</u> ― Into the classical
picture of the graphic-arts industry, the previously
mentioned patent document of Jodra introduced a new blend
of technology and business relationships. One key characteristic
of that new blend was a novel directionality of
proofing-data flow between a prepress or printing house
and a buyer or primary customer: the prepress/printing
entity prepared a proofing data file containing not only
image data as such but also embedded information about the
production press on which the job was to be printed.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0043">Remote proofing is also the topic of U. S. 6,043,909
and 6,157,735 of Richard A. Holub ― though it seems with
primary emphasis upon soft proofing. His patents focus on
the mathematics of color science.</p>
    <p num="0044">Holub recounts the known facts that it is possible to
characterize the color-rendering details of proofing devices
(and production printers as well) in a way that is
perceptually based and mathematically general. He also 
reminds his readers that it is possible to invert such
characterizations so that a proofing device can generate
perceptually standardized, or nearly standardized, color
appearances.</p>
    <p num="0045">By simply aggregating such known methods Holub outlines
how to operate production and proofing systems over
a broad network so that color variations between proofs
and production runs are minimized, and production of the
same job at widely separated plants produces near-identical
output. By virtue of this essentially conventional
scheme, multiple production facilities can run duplicate
portions of a very large, geographically disparate pressrun
to minimize shipping distances, delays and costs.</p>
    <p num="0046">Holub, however, says little about the dynamic of interplay
between complementary enterprises, or of competition,
within the printing business. Although the Jodra
approach represented an important refinement of relationships
among the classical participants in the industry, it
too stopped short of dealing fully with the newly evolved
application service providers discussed above.
<sl><li>(h) <u style="single">Software application interentity menu sharing</u>
Another known technology, not heretofore associated with
remote hardcopy proofing services for the printing industry,
is the modification of application menus of one business
entity's user software, to incorporate menu items of
another entity's complementary programs. Due to the modularity
of modern programming, particularly in the graphical
user interface (GUI) environment, such incorporation
is usually straightforward and without disruption to operation
of the host application. Below are commercially
important examples relating to the extremely popular Word-Perfect®
word-processing software.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0047">A user of WordPerfect software who installs Lexis®
legal-research software in the user's computer will find
that certain Lexis program icons and dropdown menus thereafter
appear within the WordPerfect menu ― simplifying
extraction of Lexis search results into WordPerfect documents.
If a WordPerfect user installs MathType® software
for generating mathematical equation images, subsequently
a MathType program icon and dropdown menu appear in the
user's WordPerfect menu to facilitate embedding MathType
equation images into WordPerfect documents.</p>
    <p num="0048">After installation of AddressMate® software, which
operates a dedicated small serial printer for printing individual
address labels, an AddressMate icon and dropdown
menu then appear in the WordPerfect menu. Thereafter when
the user drafts a coverletter for a package, the AddressMate
software automatically undertakes to find the recipient
address in that coverletter and copy it into a label
format for automatic addressing of a corresponding package
label on the attached serial printer.</p>
    <p num="0049">Analogous installation of HotDocs® software, and automatic
incorporation of a HotDocs® icon into WordPerfect
menus enables a user to quickly and semiautomatically embed
a HotDocs form commercial lease ― or employment contract,
or promissory note, or other legal form ― into a
WordPerfect document. In some cases these two-application
integrations are by permission of the publisher of the
preexisting host application (<u style="single">i. e.</u> in the foregoing examples
the publisher of the WordPerfect application) and
perhaps even collaborative ― being facilitated by assistance
from the host publisher with necessary source code
and programming recommendations to facilitate and optimize
the integration. </p>
    <p num="0050">Such collaborations sometimes prove so popular that
the host publisher may include the satellite program (as
with <u style="single">e. g.</u> MathType) into later editions of the host application.
In other cases such integrations may be essentially
parasitic, a relatively benign form of commercial
piracy ― perhaps quietly overlooked by the host publisher
when it appears that the incursion is beneficial to users
and therefore garners additional profitable business for
the host publisher.</p>
    <p num="0051">For present purposes it is instructive to contrast
the mutually beneficial commercial symbiosis of all such
incorporations with the recent well-known struggle between
legitimate and arguably illegitimate publishers in a wholly
different industry: the music business. There the piracy
of the seemingly renegade "Napster" enterprise undertook
to convert and disperse the established value of
thousands of copyrights with no benefit whatever to the
original creative artists or their legitimate successors.
Thus in the present context, though it is desirable to
stimulate complementary ASP activities for the remote
hardcopy-proofing art, it would be undesirable to do so by
any mechanism that could facilitate piracy or like efforts
to make off with the value of talented people and industrious
enterprises.
<sl><li>(i) <u style="single">Conclusion</u> ― Accordingly, the prior art in the
remote hardcopy-proofing field has failed to show the way
to effectively integrating the efforts of complementary
ASPs, particularly in ways healthy for competition and
consumers. This failing has continued to impede achievement
of uniformly excellent remote proofing. Thus important
aspects of the technology and business structures 
used in the field of the invention remain amenable to useful
refinement.</li></sl></p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE DISCLOSURE</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0052">The present invention introduces such refinement. In
its preferred embodiments, the present invention has several
aspects or facets that can be used independently, although
they are preferably employed together to optimize
their benefits.</p>
    <p num="0053">In preferred embodiments of a first of its facets or
aspects, the invention is a remote proofing computer system.
The system includes a closed-loop-color remote hardcopy
proofing service (RHCPS).</p>
    <p num="0054">The service provides an RHCPS user interface having
data about a printing job to be hardcopy-proofed. From
this phrasing, "having data about", people skilled in this
field will understand that such an interface enables a
user to read such data, or to enter such data ― or possibly
both, as appropriate.</p>
    <p num="0055">The interface is not necessarily a Windows®-style or
McIntosh®-style graphical user interface ("GUI"), although
this may be preferred for its marketing advantages. Rather
the interface may take any of a great variety of forms,
especially including DOS- or Unix-style control screens
with multiple data-display or -entry fields (but no icons
or other elaborate graphics) ― in the typical style of a
classical DOS or Unix application.</p>
    <p num="0056">The system also includes a graphic-arts application
service provider (ASP). The ASP provides a remotely accessible
ASP FTP site or website having data about its 
service ― meaning, again, that such data can be copied to
the site, or from it, or in appropriate cases both.</p>
    <p num="0057">The RHCPS interface includes an RHCPS link to the ASP
data, when an RHCPS user is also a user of the ASP. Thus,
whether or not the FTP site or website itself provides a
GUI or other high-level interface, when dealing with data
transfers to or from the ASP the user typically (but not
necessarily) enjoys the benefit of some formatting and interactivity
provided by the RHCPS interface.</p>
    <p num="0058">The foregoing may represent a description or definition
of the first aspect or facet of the invention in its
broadest or most general form. Even as couched in these
broad terms, however, it can be seen that this facet of
the invention importantly advances the art.</p>
    <p num="0059">In particular, this aspect of the invention as just
described provides a key feature that enables and facilitates
solutions to the problem of effective and smooth cooperation
or coventuring of complementary graphic-arts enterprises.
As will be seen, this aspect of the invention
tends to soften or remove coventuring barriers discussed
earlier and ranging from distrust to simple interoperability
mismatches. With these obstacles minimized, small and
large enterprises alike ― and consumers as well ― benefit
from a simpler and more efficient way of doing business
that is thereby created.</p>
    <p num="0060">Although the first major aspect of the invention thus
significantly advances the art, nevertheless to optimize
enjoyment of its benefits preferably the invention is
practiced in conjunction with certain additional features
or characteristics. In particular, preferably the closed-loop-color
RHCPS is based on a printer device that prints 
and reads a calibration pattern, and that returns a calibration
report to a user who is in a different location
from that printer device.</p>
    <p num="0061">Another preference is that the RHCPS link to the ASP
data appear only if the ASP is an established copartner
with the RHCPS. Still another basic preference is that,
for each user, the link to the ASP data includes a visible
tabulation of that user's graphic-arts jobs with the ASP.
(As suggested earlier, the ASP interface as considered at
this particular point need not be a GUI or even a multifield
DOS/Unix screen for input and output, provided only
that data elements within the ASP computer system are subject
to reading or manipulation through control screens of
the RHCPS.)</p>
    <p num="0062">If the latter preference (<u style="single">i. e.</u> a visible tabulation
of the user's jobs with the ASP) is observed, then preferably
the tabulation includes an active graphic-arts dialog
window for addition or modification of that user's own
graphic-arts jobs. In this case, then another preference
in turn is that the modification in the graphic-arts dialog
window include an option of deleting that user's own
graphic-arts jobs.</p>
    <p num="0063">Another subpreference to the basic visible-tabulation
feature is that the RHCPS maintain data linking each RHCPS
user to each ASP which has such a remotely accessible FTP
site or website, and with which that user is registered.
In this case, then ― also preferably for each user ― the
RHCPS interface link to the ASP data appears only for an
ASP with which that user is registered. A still-further
subpreference, if this registration constraint is implemented,
is that ― for each particular job that a user has
associated with an ASP ― the RHCPS automatically routes
proof reports and related details to the user through that 
ASP rather than to the user directly, unless the user specifically
instructs the RHCPS to the contrary.</p>
    <p num="0064">Another basic preference, <u style="single">i. e.</u> applicable directly
to the first main aspect of the invention, is that the
ASP's FTP site or website include a user interface with
the data about the ASP services. In this case, a subpreference
is that the ASP interface include a link to the
RHCPS interface when an ASP user is also an RHCPS user.
In other words, this is a link going in the <u style="single">reverse direction</u>
relative to the previously discussed link from RHCPS
to ASP.</p>
    <p num="0065">If this reverse-link preference is put into effect,
then a hierarchy of further subpreferences is applicable:
first, in the ASP interface, the link to the RHCPS interface
preferably appears only if the RHCPS is an established
copartner with the ASP. In this case then further
preferably ― for each user ― the ASP interface link to
the RHCPS interface includes a visible tabulation of that
user's jobs that are subject to remote hardcopy proofing.
If this is so, then in turn it is further preferable that
the tabulation include an active remote-hardcopy-proofing
(RHCP) dialog window for addition or modification of that
user's own RHCP jobs. Yet further preferably, this modification
in the dialog window includes an option of deleting
that user's own RHCP jobs.</p>
    <p num="0066">If the reverse-direction link is present, then in
another hierarchy of preferences the ASP preferably maintains
data linking that ASP's users to the RHCPS. In this
case then also preferably for each user the RHCPS interface
link to the ASP data appears only for an ASP with
which that user is registered. If this is so, then also
preferably for each particular job that a user has associated 
with the RHCPS, the ASP automatically routes proofing
jobs from the user to the RHCPS rather than to another
proofing entity, unless the user specifically instructs
the ASP to the contrary.</p>
    <p num="0067">Some additional basic preferences relate to types of
users and other participants. First, preferably the RHCPS
user interface and the ASP's FTP site or website are for
operation by:
<sl><li>a primary customer, including but not limited to a

   publisher, printing customer, or printing client;
or</li><li>a buyer representing a primary customer; or</li><li>a graphic artist; or</li><li>a printing broker; or</li><li>a user that is any hybrid of two or more of the preceding
four user types.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0068">An alternative basic preference, focusing instead on
ASP types, is that the ASP is preferably:
<sl><li>a printing-brokerage ASP; or</li><li>a soft-proofing ASP; or</li><li>a private-network ASP; or</li><li>an ASP that is any hybrid of two or more of the preceding
three ASP types.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0069">In this ASP-type case, the RHCPS link to the ASP data also
preferably includes access to further service of the ASP
other than RHCPS procedures. If this is so, then further
preferably the further service includes: <sl><li>if the ASP is a printing-brokerage ASP (transASP) or

   hybrid thereof, service relating particularly to

   transactional matters;</li><li>if the ASP is a soft-proofing ASP or hybrid thereof,

   service relating particularly to generation,

   checking or approval of a soft proof; and</li><li>if the ASP is a private-network ASP or hybrid there   of,
service relating particularly to data trans   mission
or storage.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0070">Other preferences, relative to the ASP-type basic preference,
include these: if an RHCPS user is not an established
user of any particular ASP (of any one type of the
three ASP types or a hybrid thereof), then the RHCPS interface
preferably includes an RHCPS link to data of all
ASPs ―
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>which are established copartners with the RHCPS; or</li><li>of that one type or hybrid, which are established
copartners with the RHCPS.</li></ul></p>
    <p num="0071">In preferred embodiments of its second major independent
facet or aspect, the invention is a computerized
remote proofing method. It includes the step of operation,
by a user, of a closed-loop-color remote hardcopy
proofing service (RHCPS) user interface, to gain access to
data about a printing job to be hardcopy-proofed.</p>
    <p num="0072">It also includes the step of granting, by a graphic-arts
application service provider (ASP), of access to data
about the ASP's service. This step is in response to the
user's activation of a link, within the RHCPS interface, 
to a user interface of the ASP. The RHCPS user is also a
user of the ASP.</p>
    <p num="0073">The foregoing may represent a description or definition
of the second aspect or facet of the invention in its
broadest or most general form. Even as couched in these
broad terms, however, it can be seen that this facet of
the invention importantly advances the art.</p>
    <p num="0074">In particular, this aspect of the invention calls for
complementary behavior, on part of the ASP, to system establishment
and operation of the RHCPS itself. More specifically
this is a first one of two distinctly different
kinds of complementary function provided by the ASP ―
this first kind being simple access, for an ASP user, to
the ASP's own data (but through the RHCPS).</p>
    <p num="0075">As suggested earlier, for purposes of this first kind
of ASP cooperation, the ASP's interface can be very simple,
even limited to type-in console-application syntax.
That is because this mode of operation can depend on the
RHCPS to provide for a nice presentation. On the other
hand, as will be seen in the "DETAILED DESCRIPTION" section,
this minimalist arrangement is not a requirement;
<u style="single">i. e.</u> the ASP if desired may provide the data preformatted
in the ASP's own customized GUI or multifield-DOS/Unix
presentation, which may be as elaborate as desired.</p>
    <p num="0076">Although the second major aspect of the invention
thus significantly advances the art, nevertheless to optimize
enjoyment of its benefits preferably the invention
is practiced in conjunction with certain additional features
or characteristics. In particular, preferably the
operating step includes actions supporting preparation of
a remote closed-loop-color hardcopy proof, by a printer
device that prints and reads a calibration pattern and returns 
a calibration report to an entity in a different
location from that printer device.</p>
    <p num="0077">Another basic preference is that the granting step
occur only if the ASP is an established copartner with the
RHCPS. Yet another is that the granting step include presenting
to the user a visible tabulation of that user's
graphic-arts jobs with the ASP.</p>
    <p num="0078">As in the first main aspect of the invention, if this
visible-tabulation preference is met then it is further
preferable that the presenting step include opening an active
graphic-arts dialog window for the user's addition or
modification of that user's own graphic-arts jobs. If
this is done, then it is also preferable in turn that the
opening step include permitting the user to delete that
user's own graphic-arts jobs, by means of the dialog
window.</p>
    <p num="0079">Another subpreference to the visible-tabulation feature
is to include the step of maintenance, by the RHCPS,
of data linking each RHCPS user to each ASP with which
that user is registered. In this case it is further preferable
that, for each user, the granting step be performed
only by an ASP with which that user is registered. If
this registration constraint is in effect, then preferably
the method further includes ― for each particular job
that a user has associated with a particular ASP ― automatic
routing, by the RHCPS, of proof reports and related
details to the user through that ASP rather than to the
user directly. This automatic routing, however, is not
performed if the user specifically instructs the RHCPS to
the contrary. </p>
    <p num="0080">In preferred embodiments of its third major independent
facet or aspect, the invention is a computerized remote
proofing method. It includes the step of operation,
by a user, of a graphic-arts ASP user interface, to gain
access to data about the ASP's service.</p>
    <p num="0081">It also includes the step of granting, by a closed-loop-color
remote hardcopy proofing service (RHCPS), of
access to data about the RHCPS. This granting is in response
to the user's activation of a link, within the ASP
interface, to a user interface of the RHCPS ― <u style="single">i. e.</u> a
reverse link as mentioned earlier. The ASP user is also a
user of the RHCPS.</p>
    <p num="0082">The foregoing may represent a description or definition
of the third aspect or facet of the invention in its
broadest or most general form. Even as couched in these
broad terms, however, it can be seen that this facet of
the invention importantly advances the art.</p>
    <p num="0083">In particular, this aspect of the invention highlights
a second kind of complementary behavior, on the
part of the ASP, to system establishment and operation of
the RHCPS. Here a greater burden is placed on the characteristics
of the ASP's interface.</p>
    <p num="0084">The ASP's interface now is assumed to be sufficiently
user friendly for its customers' purposes ― whether an
elaborate GUI or a type-in console-application syntax or
anything in between (multifield reading/entry etc.). For
some sophisticated operators, type-in syntax is quite sufficient,
although for most at least a multifield control
screen is preferable.</p>
    <p num="0085">In this reverse-link environment, the RHCPS interface
may or may not be invoked: here it is the ASP interface
that may, if preferred, be allocated all the tasks of formatting
and presenting the RHCPS data. As will be understood, 
for most ASPs there will be no adequate motivation
to provide this extra service.</p>
    <p num="0086">Some ASPs, however, may want to distinguish themselves
over their competitors by providing a more-helpful
interface; or may want to provide a richer look and feel;
or simply may wish to obscure, for their customers, the
fact that the service is available through other arrangements.
All of these variations and also all of these
motivations are within the overall flexibility, and also
within the individuality- and competition-enhancing objectives,
of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0087">Although the third major aspect of the invention thus
significantly advances the art, nevertheless to optimize
enjoyment of its benefits preferably the invention is
practiced in conjunction with certain additional features
or characteristics. In particular, preferably the granting
step occurs only if the RHCPS is an established co-partner
with the ASP.</p>
    <p num="0088">When this is so, then for each user the granting step
preferably includes displaying a visible tabulation of
that user's jobs that are subject to remote hardcopy
proofing. If so, then the displaying step preferably includes
opening an active remote-hardcopy-proofing (RHCP)
dialog window for addition or modification of that user's
own RHCP jobs.</p>
    <p num="0089">This opening step in turn preferably includes enabling
the user to delete that user's own RHCP jobs. Other
preferences described above in relation to the reverse-link
preference for the first aspect of the invention are
applicable here as well. </p>
    <p num="0090">In preferred embodiments of its fourth major independent
facet or aspect, the invention is a method of
operating a closed-loop color remote hardcopy proofing
service (RHCPS). The method includes the step of making
available a computerized, network-based RHCPS operated
through at least one user interface.</p>
    <p num="0091">Another step is, for each project of the RHCPS, establishing
functioning computerized relationships among
the RHCPS and entities that include at least a primary
customer and a printshop. Yet another step is enabling
any of those entities to initiate a project ― and thereby
define default operating conditions that determine which
of the entities sees, in the at least one user interface,
each other one of the entities respectively.</p>
    <p num="0092">A still further step is ― regardless of which of the
entities initiates the project and defines the default relationships
― reserving to at least one of the entities
(<u style="single">i. e.</u>, a participant other than the RHCPS) an option of
redefining operating conditions to override the default
conditions.</p>
    <p num="0093">The foregoing may represent a description or definition
of the fourth aspect or facet of the invention in its
broadest or most general form. Even as couched in these
broad terms, however, it can be seen that this facet of
the invention importantly advances the art.</p>
    <p num="0094">In particular, this aspect of the invention as just
described provides another key feature that balances features
associated with the earlier facets. One element
that is especially helpful here is the preservation of a
specified participant's control over the relationships.
As will be seen, selection of the most appropriate participant 
to hold this role may perfect this aspect of the
invention.</p>
    <p num="0095">Although the fourth major aspect of the invention
thus significantly advances the art, nevertheless to
optimize enjoyment of its benefits preferably the invention
is practiced in conjunction with certain additional
features or characteristics. In particular, preferably
the "at least one of the entities" ― <u style="single">i. e.</u>, the entity
that can override the default conditions ― includes the
primary customer.</p>
    <p num="0096">Thus, whereas any of the vendor entities may facilitate
establishment of the relationships, fundamentally it
is the customer who drives the economics of the entire
situation and should usually be entitled to reconfigure
those relationships. A further preference is that the
method include the step of making available to the primary
customer information about the option: it would be a hollow
privilege if the customer didn't know about it.</p>
    <p num="0097">One preferred way of making the information available
is including in an RHCPS user interface seen by the primary
customer a link to <u style="single">terms</u> of the RHCPS, which include
the information about the option. Mere presence of such a
visible link does not itself unduly press upon the customer
― particularly a satisfied one ― the availability of
the option. Plainly these principles are somewhat in tension,
and their proper balance is a matter to be carefully
considered in configuring the wording, graphics and general
level of conspicuousness of the link and of the customer-override
terms, in the RHCPS user interface.</p>
    <p num="0098">Another, more-specific preference is that the reserving
step include enabling the primary customer to redefine 
which of the entities the primary customer can see. By
operation of this fourth facet of the invention, together
with these several preferences, the method stimulates competition
― while tending to deter redundancy ― among enterprises
in the printing industry.</p>
    <p num="0099">Previously described preferences, particularly relating
to the types of entities involved, are applicable for
this fourth aspect of the invention too. As noted earlier,
the several independent aspects of the invention are
most advantageously all practiced together.</p>
    <p num="0100">In preferred embodiments of its fifth major independent
facet or aspect, the invention is a method of operating
a closed-loop color remote hardcopy proofing service
(RHCPS) that stimulates competition while tending to deter
redundancy, among enterprises in the printing industry.
This method includes the step of making available a computerized,
network-based RHCPS operated through at least
one user interface.</p>
    <p num="0101">Another step is, for each project of the RHCPS, establishing
functioning computerized relationships among
the RHCPS and entities that include at least a primary
customer and a printshop. Still another step is enabling
any of the entities to initiate a project and thereby define
default operating conditions that determine which of
the entities sees, in the at least one user interface,
each other of the entities respectively.</p>
    <p num="0102">Yet another step is ― regardless of which of the entities
initiates the project and defines the default relationships
― reserving to the primary customer an option
of redefining operating conditions to override the default
conditions. A further step is making available to the 
primary customer information about the option, by including
the information in the at least one user interface or
in separate communications to the primary customer.</p>
    <p num="0103">The foregoing may represent a description or definition
of the fifth aspect or facet of the invention in its
broadest or most general form. Even as couched in these
broad terms, however, it can be seen that this facet of
the invention importantly advances the art by expressly
preserving a proper position of the primary as in control,
while allowing vendors great latitude in individual style
and character of operation ― as long as, basically, the
primary feels well treated. Preferences here are closely
related to those introduced earlier.</p>
    <p num="0104">In preferred embodiments of its sixth major independent
facet or aspect, the invention is a user interface for
a closed-loop color remote hardcopy proofing service
(RHCPS). The interface includes RHCPS input/output elements
for gaining access to a computerized, network-based
RHCPS. These input/output elements are also for entering
data and instructions into the RHCPS, or reading data and
status from the RHCPS ― or both.</p>
    <p num="0105">The interface also includes application service provider
(ASP) input/output elements for each project of the
RHCPS. These elements reflect functioning computerized
relationships among entities that include the RHCPS and at
least one ASP.</p>
    <p num="0106">The foregoing may represent a description or definition
of the sixth aspect or facet of the invention in its
broadest or most general form. Even as couched in these
broad terms, however, it can be seen that this facet of
the invention importantly advances the art. </p>
    <p num="0107">In particular, this interface provides a basic building-block
mechanism for accomplishing the several advances
discussed in relation to the first five aspects. Preferences
are closely identifiable with preferences for those
earlier-introduced aspects.</p>
    <p num="0108">As mentioned earlier in connection with the first independent
aspect of the invention, the interface is not
necessarily a graphical user interface ("GUI"), although
this may be preferred for some types of users. Rather the
interface may take any of a great variety of forms, especially
including the classical DOS- or Unix-style control
screens with multiple data-display or -entry fields but no
icons or other elaborate graphics. As is well known, such
forms are orders of magnitude more efficient in terms of
using computer resources ― particularly including considerations
of speed, storage, and reliability.</p>
    <p num="0109">All of the foregoing operational principles and
advantages of the present invention will be more fully
appreciated upon consideration of the following detailed
description, with reference to the appended drawings, of
which:</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0110">
      <sl>
        <li>Fig. 1 is a diagram, highly schematic, of a representative
hardware system according to preferred embodiments
of the invention; </li>
        <li>Fig. 2 is a picture of a graphical user interface
(GUI) for a printshop using the remote hardcopy proofing
service (RHCPS), in the case of a direct customer-to-printshop
relationship ― and particularly where the customer
is the <u style="single">first</u> RHCPS customer of that shop (or where
the shop operator has already selected the customer from
among plural customers);</li>
        <li>Fig. 3 is a picture of a related interface screen for
choosing a job-selection log-in mode, where the customer
is not the first RHCPS customer for the shop ― or for
proceeding directly by customer, job-ticket number, JDF,
or date, if the system designers prefer to include such
parameters (and default values) in this mode-selection
screen;</li>
        <li>Fig. 4 is a picture of an interface screen resulting
from the above-described choice of mode, and displaying a
list of customers;</li>
        <li>Fig. 5 is an alternative screen like Fig. 3 but without
the default parameter-entry fields;</li>
        <li>Fig. 6 is a screen that appears ― if the operator
selects the JDF job-ticket entry mode in Fig. 3 or 5, but
in Fig. 3 fills in no JDF number ― for presentation of
the data field for log-in by JDF job-ticket number;</li>
        <li>Fig. 7 is a screen like Fig. 2, but including inactive
jobs;</li>
        <li>Fig. 8 is a GUI screen showing setup for semiautomatic
progression of a job from proofing-file preparation to
transmission, nominally using a hot folder;</li>
        <li>Fig. 9 is a GUI screen for an operator's use in manual
movement of the file into a hot folder;</li>
        <li>Fig. 10 is a screen like Fig. 9, but for the operator's
use in only confirming automatic movement into the
hot folder; </li>
        <li>Fig. 11 is a picture like Fig. 3 for the same case
but for use by the customer, at the customer's facility,
rather than for use by the shop;</li>
        <li>Fig. 12 is a picture of the GUI screen, analogous to
that of Fig. 2 and for the same case of a direct customer-to-shop
relationship, but displaying the job list as the
customer (rather than the printshop) sees it upon log-in
through the Fig. 11 screen;</li>
        <li>Fig. 13 is a set of three views of a log-in GUI dialog
like Fig. 3 in that it is for use at the printing
house, and for job selection ― but for the case of a
proofing ASP added to the parties in the relationship ―
and particularly showing three exemplary link precursors
(<u style="single">i. e.</u>, reflecting knowledge of an ASP's being involved in
at least one of the printshop's jobs): in the "A" view,
displaying the log-in choices within data fields; in the
"B" view, displaying them as an integral part of the GUI
itself, with radio buttons or check-boxes; and in the "C"
view showing the choices in an even more structurally
integrated way, with labeled click-buttons;</li>
        <li>Fig. 14 is a set of four examples of a screen that
may follow <u style="single">after</u> job selection, <u style="single">i. e.</u> once it is known
whether an ASP is involved in the particular job selected
― the operator can connect into the system through the
ASP (rather than directly) if preferred, and this can be
indicated by clicking, as in the "A" view, on a minimal
kind of link (an ordinary URL-style hyperlink) from the
printshop to the ASP site; or as in the "B" view, using an
intermediate level of link (displaying the choices within
data fields); or as in the "C" view, using a still higher
level of link (displaying the log-in choices as an integral 
part of the GUI itself ― with radio buttons or
check-boxes); or as in the "D" view, showing another exemplary
link form that is more highly preferred, a maximal
level of link integration (displaying the log-in choices
as an even more structurally integrated part of the GUI ―
with labeled click-buttons);</li>
        <li>Fig. 15 is a picture like Fig. 14D, but for the GUI
seen by the primary customer rather than operators at the
printing house;</li>
        <li>Fig. 16 is a picture like Fig. 2 ― which is to say,
for use by an operator at the production house ― but for
the Fig. 13 and 14 case of a proofing ASP included in the
parties, together with the customer and printing shop;</li>
        <li>Fig. 17 is a GUI data-display picture like Fig. 16,
but for use by the customer rather than the printshop;</li>
        <li>Fig. 17A is an alternative to Fig. 17, a display that
may be provided if one of the vendors ― here the proofing
ASP ― has been principally responsible for RHCPS arrangements
with the primary customer and wishes to link the
customer to that vendor's own GUI rather than the standard
RHCPS interface (the vendor's interface in the example being
a <u style="single">hybrid</u> with the standard RHCPS interface);</li>
        <li>Fig. 18 is a GUI data-display picture like Figs. 16
and 17 but for use by the proofing ASP rather than the
customer or shop;</li>
        <li>Fig. 19 is a picture like Figs. 2 and 16 (<u style="single">i. e.</u>, once
again for use by an operator at the printing house), but
for the case of a private-network ASP added to at least
the first two of the three parties assumed in Fig. 16;</li>
        <li>Fig. 20 is a picture like Fig. 19, but once again for
the customer; </li>
        <li>Fig. 21 is a picture like Fig. 19 and 20, but again
for the proofing ASP if participating;</li>
        <li>Fig. 22 is a picture like Figs. 19 through 21, but
now for the network ASP;</li>
        <li>Fig. 23 is a picture like Fig. 19 (<u style="single">i. e.</u> for use at
the printshop), but for the case of a middleman or transaction
ASP added to at least the first two of the parties
assumed in Fig. 19 ― and also incorporating yet another
party such as an outside prepress house, supplementing the
efforts of the final offset shop (any other type of specialty
service may be substituted where there is room in
the GUI, or by adding a horizontal scroll bar for further
participants);</li>
        <li>Fig. 24 is a picture like Fig. 23, but for use by the
customer rather than the printing house;</li>
        <li>Fig. 25 is a picture like Figs. 23 and 24, but for
use by the proofing ASP if participating;</li>
        <li>Fig. 26 is a picture like Figs. 23 through 25, but
for use by the network ASP if participating;</li>
        <li>Fig. 27 is a picture like Figs. 23 through 26, but
for use by the transaction ASP; and</li>
        <li>Fig. 28 is a screen with a link to contract terms.</li>
      </sl>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION
OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</u>
    </heading>
    <heading>1. OPEN COVENTURING, WITH PRESERVED CLIENTELE</heading>
    <p num="0111">Preferred embodiments of the invention enable the
several types of participants in the printing industry to 
use a service such as a remote hardcopy proofing service
(RHCPS) ― and in fact services of any of certain other
ASP copartners, and any other vendors that are registered
in the system ― with only a reasonably minimal concern
for the possibility of clientele lost to competitors as a
direct result of participation in the service. Yet each
client, customer, and in fact each participant at any level,
is always free (subject to separate contractual constraints,
of course) to change allegiances at will, provided
only that the client exercises initiative to find a
preferred vendor through means other than behavior of the
copartnering ASPs.</p>
    <p num="0112">For example the yellow pages phonebook, or a trade
directory, can always be used to actively seek an alternative
vendor for any of the services involved. None of the
copartnering entities or other registered vendors can reasonably
expect to prevent such efforts on the seeker's own
initiative, unless the customer and vendor have entered
into an exclusive service contract of some sort. What is,
however, disfavored is subversion of the objectives of copartners
and vendors through seductions on the part of the
copartnering application service providers themselves.</p>
    <p num="0113">These benefits are produced for the participants by
programming into the service infrastructure a capability
to recognize which of the participating business entities
it was that introduced each primary customer to each component,
respectively, of the overall interlinked service.
That customer is thereafter associated with that introducing
entity, or array of introducing entities ― unless the
customer itself undertakes to revise the association.</p>
    <p num="0114">In computer jargon, the customer and the introducing
entity are associated simply as a "default". As those in
the programming field know, the quoted word means that 
this association is the operating assumption, in the absence
of contrary information ― which can be entered into
the system databases by one or more of the parties, perhaps
using some other menu and dialog window.</p>
    <p num="0115">This arrangement does not imply that the customer's
ability to make such revisions should be kept a secret
from the customer. In fact <u style="single">that</u> way of operating would
not be fair to service participants other than the initially
introducing entity. To the contrary, in preferred
embodiments of the invention the customer's option of reconfiguring
the basic relationships is part of the terms
of the RHCPS and is available to be read at some appropriate
level in, for example, the "help" screens of the service.</p>
    <p num="0116">For example, a particular printing house that signs
on for use of the RHCPS should ordinarily be entitled to
use it for any primary customer that elects to buy printing
from that particular house ― including one that wishes
to transfer its business from some other printshop. To
provide the primary customer less flexibility than that
would be rather contrary to the general principle of free
enterprise and possibly subject to legal sanction.</p>
    <p num="0117">Ideally a proper balance is maintained between, on
the one hand, preserving the customer's right to know that
such options are available; and, on the other hand, undermining
the copartners and other participating vendors by
<u style="single">pushing</u> such options onto the customer. In effect the
system as thus configured implements basic traditional
trade courtesies on the part of printers, ad agencies,
graphic artists and ASPs alike ― <u style="single">i. e.</u> to refrain from
rudely abusing a complementary enterprise in return for a
kind referral by sending the customer off to some competitor
of the referring enterprise. </p>
    <p num="0118">In the classical scheme of things, if a customer expressed
to the initial <u style="single">beneficiary</u> of a referral an active
discontent with services of the <u style="single">referring</u> entity ― then
the initial beneficiary would be faced with a difficult
professional and interpersonal task. This might call for
balancing kind words for the referring entity with suggestions
to the customer (based upon principled reasoning as
to the substance of the situation rather than personalities)
that perhaps, "for this type of project", a larger
enterprise, or smaller one, or differently specializing
one, might be more appropriate. (If done well, this behavior
might in truth benefit even the initially referring
entity, if in fact that entity and the customer were a
poor match based upon size, specializations or the like;
for the referring entity constantly might be expending
extra resources in a hopeless effort to please a customer
who represented only marginally profitable business.)</p>
    <p num="0119">That sort of delicate weighing and discreet choice of
wording is generally unavailable in the conventional electronic-commerce
environment; hence the problem outlined in
an earlier section of this document. Preferred embodiments
of the invention therefore construct an alternative
mechanism for striking a different kind of balance, which
approximates the classical trade courtesies without demanding
so much of the participating vendors. In this way
the invention exploits an easily practiced technological
solution to reintroduce and maintain a special kind of
professional integrity within the e-commerce segment of
the trade. </p>
    <heading>
      <b>2. NETWORK ENVIRONMENT</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0120">The technology itself while novel in application is
relatively straightforward technologically, as suggested
by the earlier discussion of integrating software peripherals
into a major word-processing program. The present
invention contemplates establishment and operation of an
RHCPS 11 (Fig. 1) over two or more networks ― one being
the Internet 16, for those participants who are satisfied
with that level of service; and another being at least one
private network 25 such as that operated by the company
called "Wam!net".</p>
    <p num="0121">In general, transactions and services between particular
customers, vendors and e-service entities may proceed
partly by Internet and partly by private network, to the
extent that those participants prefer; or may instead be
entirely on the Internet or entirely on a private network.
Users gain access to the most-local portion of the selected
network by traditional phone dial-up, or by DSL-style
or cable-modem connection, or by ports connected directly
to high-speed optic-fiber or coaxial lines that are linked
directly to the network backbone.</p>
    <p num="0122">A primary customer 12 may itself initiate arrangements
for connection and commerce with the RHCPS or other
participant 13, 21-24 directly ― or one of the other participants
(the RHCPS, or other ASP 22, 24, 25, or a trade
vendor) may offer to set up the customer's initial connections
to get the customer started. As a practical matter,
all or substantially all the relevant services involve
interconnection of apparatuses, <u style="single">i. e.</u> equipment, of the
respective participants; these devices may range from a
common personal computer for soft proofing to an extremely 
specialized prepress ("PP") facility 23, or inkjet proofing
printer 14, 15; or to network equipment itself.</p>
    <p num="0123">An underlying objective of preferred embodiments of
the invention is to preserve the value of business-generating
efforts by all and any participants, <u style="single">i. e.</u> of entrepreneurial
industriousness and goodwill. At the same time
these embodiments preserve a maximum degree of utilization
of available technology, for the benefit of all involved,
<u style="single">i. e.</u> for maximum interoperability of the several systems
involved. As suggested earlier, the relatively open-structured
but essentially coventuring relationship of
entities that is established in preferred embodiments of
the invention tends to deter less-salutary motivations,
<u style="single">e. g.</u> for piracy, parasitic behavior and the like.</p>
    <p num="0124">Shown connected to the networks in Fig. 1 are examples
of the several types of participants in preferred
embodiments of the present invention. These typically include
the principal participants in a basic graphic-arts
transaction, namely the customer 12, printshop 13 and
RHCPS 11.</p>
    <p num="0125">In event those are the <u style="single">only</u> participants, then a
local proofing printer 14 may be housed at the printshop
13 itself rather than in a separate enterprise as illustrated;
and a remote proofing printer 15 may be housed at
the primary customer's facility 12 rather than elsewhere
as also illustrated. Nevertheless both the local and
remote printers are labeled as "RP" (remote proofing)
devices because they preferably are both units in a product
line of inkjet printers particularly designed and
optimized for consistent and reliable closed-loop-color
performance in an overall remote-proofing environment. </p>
    <p num="0126">Ideally the two printers are essentially identical,
and preferably Hewlett Packard products. The principal
users 12, 13 can be connected entirely through the
Internet 16, or entirely through a private-network ASP 25;
or as suggested partway through one and partway through
the other. In such a hybrid network configuration, the
interface between the two nets is not necessarily at the
facility of some other participant (as shown), but rather
may instead at a terminal box or other facility maintained
by, <u style="single">e. g.</u>, the network ASP.</p>
    <p num="0127">Many other possible combinations of participants are
possible and frequently encountered in operation of the
RHCPS. The example illustrated includes a relatively full
complement of such participants: a prepress house 23 associated
with the printshop 13 and possibly providing the
local proofing equipment 14; and a graphic arts ("GA")
house 21 or ad agency etc. somewhat more closely associated
with the customer 12.</p>
    <p num="0128">The PP and GA enterprises may be computerized services,
<u style="single">i. e.</u> e-commerce ASPs, but in their most common forms
they are instead conventional businesses. For example
much or most of the communication and materials passing
between the primary 12 and the GA 21 are commonly implemented
by traditional methods 26 ― telephone, or courier,
or actually going to see one another, or the like.</p>
    <p num="0129">More commonly taking the form of ASPs are the other
participants illustrated: a soft-proofing ASP 22, enhancing
its services by maintaining a remote RP device 15 and
serving also as a terminal for the RHCPS 11; a broker or
middleman ASP 24, here also called a transactional ASP
(transASP); and the private-network ASP 25. In the
particular configuration shown, neither the primary 12 nor
the GA 21 has a remote-proofing device; hence they depend 
on the soft-proof ASP 22 and perhaps typically use
traditional methods 27, 26 in making arrangements for and
in retrieving the hardcopy proof, carrying it to the
primary 12, and giving approval.</p>
    <p num="0130">Emphatically, these methods can be bypassed if the
primary or GA, or both, prefer to invest in equipment 15
for receiving and viewing proofs in-house.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>3. COMPONENTS OF PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0131">For successful operation, it has proven helpful to
provide certain distinct elements ― listed below ― in
preferred embodiments of the invention. This should not,
however, be mistaken as meaning that all these components
are required:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>availability of a printer device able to do closed-loop
remote hardcopy proofing (RHCP), including automatic
return of a definitive report on color reproducibility
― and preferably absolute accuracy ― in
perceptual or colorimetric terms, or both;</li><li>emplacement of a hardware infrastructure for carrying
data ― including queries, approvals, exceptions and
so on ― among or between defined participants;</li><li>establishment of a standardized <u style="single">document-content</u> format
which is widely available to industry
participants ― and which is amenable to streamlining
for efficient and unambiguous specification of images
to be proofed; </li><li>parallel establishment of a standard <u style="single">job-definition</u>
format ― also amenable to streamlined specification,
but of overall commercial/industrial processing
steps; and</li><li>a workflow-management protocol or component that defines
the participants, shapes and constrains all
their interactions, and thereby integrates the above
components to implement the RHCP objective.</li></ul></p>
    <p num="0132">In most-highly-preferred embodiments of the invention, the
printer device is a Hewlett Packard product that has the
above-mentioned RHCP functions built-in. The hardware
infrastructure, for reasons already suggested, is ideally
a hybrid of Internet and participating private networks ―
which latter can be operated by ASPs as noted earlier.</p>
    <p num="0133">One of the network subelements is preferably an electronic
"gateway" or file-server infrastructure operated by
the Hewlett Packard Company or other manufacturer of the
printer device. This subelement helps to ensure a proper
interlinking of the printers, their updating with software
upgrades from time to time, and overseeing of their color-calibration
maintenance and basic operating integrity.</p>
    <p num="0134">The document-content format preferably is a portable
document file ("PDF") of the Adobe company ― but with a
stringently reduced parameter set, for streamlining, as
will be exemplified in a later section of this document.
The job-definition format is likewise a reduced-parameter
version of the industry's job definition file ("JDF").</p>
    <p num="0135">Modernly the PDF specification has branched into
other standards definitions, based on PDF, and
particularly including PDF/X-1 and PDF/X-3. These
specifications go along the same general lines of 
restricting the types of data and parameters that can be
used; and in fact one highly preferred embodiment of the
invention now uses the PDF/X3 specification.
<sl><li>(a) <u style="single">Workflow protocol features</u> ― The "workflow management
protocol", on which the present patent document
particularly focuses, in turn preferably has key features:
<sl><li>(1) a delicately defined set of <u style="single">rules</u> that interlink diverse
participating entities and strike a careful
balance among certain competing measures of fairness,
loyalty, and autonomy ― in an intuitively acceptable
way;</li><li>(2) an interentity <u style="single">interface-sharing technique</u> that implements
those rules in a manner which, once again,
represents a fine balance between discreet, decorous
conduct of business and an open, nonsecretive regime;</li><li>(3) support of JDF-based workflow in the abstract;</li><li>(4) notification of job activity to relevant
participants;</li><li>(5) logging of job activity; and</li><li>(6) a user interface ― preferably but not necessarily a
graphical interface, <u style="single">e. g.</u> based on extensible markup
language (XML) ― that is compatible with the inter-entity
interface-sharing objective ― while
interacting with all interested users to expedite the
entry, retrieval, modification and use of all the
information in the system.</li></sl></li></sl></p>
    <p num="0136">As to feature (1) in this list, the principles of loyalty
and autonomy are intrinsically in tension with each other;
in other words, they trend oppositely ― and the principle
of fairness is a kind of moderating influence that may
keep them from tearing each other apart or destroying potentially
beneficial business relationships. As to
feature (2), analogously, discreet and decorous behavior
trend in directions that often conflict with openness or
nonsecretiveness.</p>
    <p num="0137">In preferred embodiments, the workflow-management
protocol is not complex so much as it is carefully
contoured, at difficult points ― so as to accomplish the
desired balancing of the contrary-trending business and
societal considerations that have been introduced here.</p>
    <p num="0138">Features (3) through (5) in the list are more
mechanistic. They essentially represent backbone chores
that the procedures should accomplish. Feature (6), a
programmed computer interface used directly by all or most
participants in the system, is at once a medium of
communication, an automatic implementer of the mechanistic
tasks, and an enforcer of the rules and the technique.
<sl><li>(b) <u style="single">Proofing ASPs (or primary customers) and the
work protocol</u> ― A service ASP that wishes to offer a remote-proofing
service to its own customers can use the
workflow-management component or protocol of the present
invention to delegate the management of proof status, as
will be explained shortly. In such a situation the ASP
infrastructure can <u style="single">itself</u> implement the following
functions, or parts of them.
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>the method for sharing a proof between the originator
and the receiver or receivers, possibly using different 
models ― for example, a mailbox for each user
or a shared working site on the network

   (The corresponding element in the classical environment,
previously mentioned, is the printer's
makeready room, with its job bins and sometimes an
adjacent conference room.)</li><li>the transport method and protocols for the proof
files, for example provision of a high-bandwidth private
network to connect users

   (The classical analog of this element, also mentioned
earlier, is a courier.)</li><li>the method or methods for interaction between the final
user and the interfaces provided according to the
invention

   (Here the earlier-noted classical analog is work
of the prepress manager, or the business proprietor,
or a salesman.)</li><li>integration with other services provided by the ASP,
such as digital-asset management

   (This function corresponds to file cabinets, or
a safe-deposit box, or a vault ― for holding archival
plates, negatives and artwork.)</li></ul></li></sl></p>
    <p num="0139">The ASP, however, would delegate the management of
the proof jobs to the workflow-management component (or
protocol) of the present invention. As stated in an earlier
section, this workflow- or proof-management function
consists of knowing and changing (1) the status of the
proofs, and (2) possible actions that can be performed on
a proof job at any given moment. </p>
    <p num="0140">The service ASP is therefore free to establish a system
and protocol that are independent of the details of
the "life cycle" of a proof. These elements of the ASP's
operations need not be changed when proof-management details
are changed.</p>
    <p num="0141">The workflow-management protocol or component of the
present invention provides an interface that is based on,
but moves beyond, industry-standard hypertext transfer
protocols (HTTP) and extensible markup language (XML), to
provide three groups of functions:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li><u style="single">proof activity</u> ― The ASP uses these functions whenever
an action is to be taken on a proof, as for example
when a user uploads a proof document to the ASP
service. The actions are used as input by the workflow-management
component and may cause changes in
the status of proofs.</li><li><u style="single">proof status queries</u> ― The ASP can perform queries
on the status of a certain proof or a set of proofs.
The workflow-management component provides replies,
which the ASP can use to provide information to the
primary customer.</li><li><u style="single">proof event notifications</u> ― These events are initiated
by the workflow-management component itself, to
notify the ASP and its client of changes in status of
a proof job.</li></ul>
While these functions represent a relatively high degree
of interaction between the ASP and the workflow-management
component ― as to details of a proofing project ― that 
is true in large part because this first example discussed
here is for a proofing-service ASP.</p>
    <p num="0142">As indicated previously, upon logging on to the RHCPS
the service ASP sees only its own projects ― and, once
the particular customer involved has been identified, sees
only its own projects with that customer. This is normally
true even if the same customer has projects with, for
instance, other service ASPs.</p>
    <p num="0143">In many cases such an ASP operates essentially <u style="single">on behalf
of</u> a primary customer. A generally comparable degree
of close interaction occurs if the workflow-management
protocol is operated by the primary's own technical people
directly, rather than through the ASP.</p>
    <p num="0144">As seen in the following subsections, however, the
workflow-management component is also capable of
interacting with other types of ASPs beneficially but much
less intimately than described above.
<sl><li>(c) <u style="single">Transaction ASPs (or buyers) and the work
protocol</u> ― A broker, agent, intermediary, middleman,
matchmaker or other print-transaction ASP (transASP) can
use the workflow-management component or protocol of the
present invention in ways generally analogous to those
described above. Such a transaction ASP, however, most
commonly does not wish to set up full remote proofing
capabilities in its environment.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0145">The focus of a transASP is in fact the commercial
aspects of the industry rather than the operational
aspects. Accordingly the transASP more commonly prefers
to use remote proofing services provided by service ASPs
to supply operational functions for the transactional
service. </p>
    <p num="0146">In this case, most transASPs, using the workflow-management
protocol or component of the present invention, do
not care to know specific details of the remote proofing
service operations provided by the service ASP. The
transASP can use several different ASPs simultaneously for
different clients or even for different projects of a
common client.</p>
    <p num="0147">A transASP that does not implement its own remote-proofing
service most typically uses only the proof status
query interface module (mentioned in the preceding
subsection), to occasionally consult information about
proof status. The transaction ASP usually does not want
to see the proof, or its approval, or any other related
activity unless the transaction is in danger of failing.</p>
    <p num="0148">At that point, however, the transaction ASP ― if a
participant in the RHCPS ― at its own facilities can log
on to the service. The transaction ASP can then quickly
determine whether and exactly when proof material was
transmitted to the proofer, when and how a proof was returned,
what response was made upon inspection of the
proof by the authorized party, and thereby generally just
when, how and why the process may have broken down.</p>
    <p num="0149">Concerned for the satisfaction of its client, upon
which a commission ordinarily depends, the transaction ASP
can promptly and efficiently learn what might be done to
put the transaction back on track to completion. To accomplish
this, as in the other situations described in
this document, the transaction ASP will <u style="single">not</u> have to search
through many entries pertaining either to its competitors,
or to transactions that happen to use no transaction ASP
at all, or to transactions with the same printer but other
customers of the same ASP, or perhaps even to transactions 
which the same customer may have placed with <u style="single">a different</u>
transaction ASP.</p>
    <p num="0150">Rather, the transaction ASP simply need identify its
own customer. The ASP then sees only relevant projects,
<u style="single">i. e.</u> its own projects with that customer.</p>
    <p num="0151">A similar degree of arm's-length interaction with the
workflow-management component of the present invention may
be appropriate for, <u style="single">e.g.</u>, the business manager or
financial officer of a primary customer using the RHCPS of
the present invention ― where the primary customer's
technical people are operating the protocol directly as
mentioned at the end of the last subsection.
<sl><li>(d) <u style="single">Transport ASPs (or IT managers, or couriers) and
the work protocol</u> ― Yet another kind and degree of
interaction arises between the workflow-management
component of the present invention and a different entity
entrusted with transmission of proofing materials for use
in proofing, or with return delivery of a proof for
viewing. This sort of interaction is ordinarily limited
to information about the transmission or delivery itself,
a function that usually arises only when some aspect of
those events is not fully automatic.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0152">For instance, if the primary customer or a service
ASP has elected to use the services of a transport ASP
(private network operator) for such transmissions and deliveries,
ordinarily the transport ASP in such workflow is
transparent ― and also essentially content neutral. The
transmitting entity logs on to the network in a generally
conventional (and usually automatic) way, and sends; the
receiving entity logs on likewise and receives.</p>
    <p num="0153">Ordinarily there is no need to otherwise contact or
communicate with the transport ASP. If, however, deliveries 
fail because the connection drops out or is noisy
during transmission ― or if the sender believes that
transmission was complete but the recipient does not have
the file ― then they can query the transport ASP.</p>
    <p num="0154">In preferred embodiments of the invention, if the
transport ASP is an active coventurer in the RHCPS, then
that ASP can supplement its usual procedures for checking
into such situations. Specifically, and very advantageously,
at its own facilities the ASP can log on to the
RHCPS interface to inspect technical data about the
transmission.</p>
    <p num="0155">Where there has actually been any passage of data to
the private net, the transport ASP can see log-ins by the
sender, associated with traceable information about the
transmission to see what happened next. This level of interaction
with the service is comparable to the contact
which occurs if the sender is in a large firm with its own
"information-technology" (computer) department, and the
sender contacts that department to investigate a failed
transmission.</p>
    <p num="0156">Another example of the same degree of contact is the
relatively unlikely instance of a buyer, prepress service
etc. that actually uses a courier service to complete
proof delivery through the last leg of a delivery chain,
to a primary customer who is not on-line at all. In that
case the entity which logs on to determine status may be
the courier service.</p>
    <p num="0157">In these various situations, as in the earlier sections
and subsections of this document related to interactions
with the workflow-management component of the RHCPS,
what the courier, or IT department, or transport ASP sees
tabulated is only its own relevant tasks with relevant
parties. This is ordinarily the case even if those 
parties are engaged in other projects using other
couriers, or other transport ASPs, respectively.
<sl><li>(e) <u style="single">Advantages of the workflow-management component
of the RHCPS</u> ― The service thus promotes and enhances
cooperative coexistence and complementary operations by
<u style="single">separate</u> (as opposed to vertically integrated) small and
large printshops, ASPs, primary customers, and incidental
service firms such as manual couriers. While the primary
customers and indeed all of the participants are at
liberty to realign themselves with other participants, the
RHCPS does not encourage them to do so.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0158">If a printshop wishes to use the RHCPS to transmit
data for proofs, and actually create proofs, for customers,
the printshop can do so without concern that the
customer ― in the actual process of checking projects
with that printshop ― will see the names of <u style="single">competing</u>
printshops. If the customer were directly led by the
RHCPS to see those competitors, the printshop might be
disposed to make other remote-proofing arrangements.</p>
    <p num="0159">On the other hand, if a customer on its own
initiative wishes to search the RHCPS for participating
printshops, the customer is able to do so. All the same
can be said of ASPs and incidental services that has been
said of printshops.</p>
    <p num="0160">In this way the operating rules of the service
promote ― but do not enforce ― loyalty within the trade.
Participants in promoting their own services, whether by
direct one-to-one marketing contacts or by media
advertising, are at liberty to advertise that they can
provide remote hardcopy printing through the RHCPS.</p>
    <p num="0161">This protocol thus tends to mitigate and sometimes
resolve the previously outlined difficult problems within 
the industry. In this way the service benefits the economy
in general and the several different kinds of participants
in particular.</p>
    <p num="0162">Further, the workflow-management component is
advantageously centralized for use by plural different
remote proofing services. In this situation the protocols
can be adapted to take advantage of the operating
characteristics of specific proofing printers. To
consider a case in pertinent point, when a printer is
manufactured to perform remote closed-loop color
operations, the service can be programmed to facilitate
such operations.</p>
    <p num="0163">More generally the service can be refined or enhanced
internally without requiring any change by participants.
The latter simply are free to benefit from whatever
additional services or features the RHCPS brings on line
― as for instance to support new proof-printer features.</p>
    <p num="0164">By virtue of sharing a common job model, or workflow-management
protocol, different remote-proofing services
can be interoperable. Proofs created by a user in one
service can be used by users in other services.</p>
    <p num="0165">If a proofing service chooses to provide its own user
interface to its users, each of those users can operate
with that particular distinctive interface ― without
needing to know details of features in a counterpart service.
Yet plural counterpart proofing services using the
centralized RHCPS can communicate with each other through
the RHCPS's master interface, sharing and trading excess
capacity, overflow work, jobs requiring specialized
capabilities, etc. ― for the benefit of all.</p>
    <p num="0166">The RHCPS also has the benefit of naturally giving
users of every type only the information those users require 
or want. For instance a transASP ― perhaps using
the workflow-management component simply to obtain a
proof-status report ― need not know details of the remote
proofing services being used.</p>
    <heading>4. USER INTERFACE</heading>
    <p num="0167">This section takes up the element identified as (6)
in subsection 3(a) above. A journeyman programmer of ordinary
skill can straightforwardly create this interface.</p>
    <p num="0168">Its craftsmanly execution is key to success, since
most of the advantages discussed above depend upon
implementation of the stated principles by the user
interface itself. For purposes of definiteness the
following presentation will show and discuss a <u style="single">graphical</u>
user interface ("GUI"), but as noted elsewhere in this
document a much less resource-demanding user interface can
be used instead. An overall benefit of the invention is
that the objectives and principles are easily but directly
embedded in a DOS/Unix-style interface or in a GUI as
preferred.</p>
    <p num="0169">Once that is done, those objectives and principles
become in essence self-fulfilling as the users collectively
operate the system from that interface through their
respective computers. Here are examples for several different
cases:
<sl><li>(a) <u style="single">Primary customer direct to printshop</u> ― Suppose
that a primary customer uses no intermediary ASP and has
sent materials for a printing job to a printing house
directly, and the customer itself has a proofing press at 
its own facility. When that printshop has the proofing
file ready, the shop personnel log onto the RHCPS.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0170">If this is the shop's first-ever RHCPS customer (direct
or indirect), then the RHCPS interface simply
displays the name of that customer and a list of all that
customer's jobs (Fig. 2); otherwise, the shop's operator
looks on the screen for the direct customer, either:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>searching by name in a list of established customers
(moving from the screen of Fig. 3, solely for
selection of finding-by-customer mode; to that of
Fig. 4 for actual entry of initials for, and/or
scrolling to, a particular customer); or</li><li>manually typing in the direct customer's name in a
data-entry field (Fig. 3).</li></ul></p>
    <p num="0171">In the first, mode-selection screen, the specific default
entries (the entries last used) are grayed out for the
mode options next to inactive radio buttons. In the option
next to the active button (here "customer"), the default
entry appears in reverse characters on a dark field,
as shown ― so that an operator who wishes to return to
that entry can do so simply by clicking "OK" or pressing
"Enter" on the keyboard. If instead the operator types
anything in that field, the reverse-character default entry
disappears and the operator's entry appears in normal
(not reverse) characters.</p>
    <p num="0172">Searching in a list (the first option noted above) is
often better, to avoid using a nonstandard or nonpreferred
form of the customer's name; nevertheless the second,
type-in option may be preferred by fast typists, and can
be used even if the customer is an established customer of 
the shop. In that event, however, the system ordinarily
completes the customer's name based upon the operator's
entry of just the first few letters ― as is nowadays familiar
in the address-book functions of e-mail handling
programs and the like.</p>
    <p num="0173">In either case the RHCPS interface responds with a
listing (Fig. 2) of all of that customer's projects ― and
also, at the top, information about the customer and the
printshop itself. This upper part of the display
indicates by headings and also by font distinctions which
data are for the customer and which for the printshop. To
further keep these differences very clear, the printshop
data (at right) may be displayed as an integral part of
the virtual control panel pictured on the screen, while
the customer data (at left) may instead appear within a
data subwindow as shown.</p>
    <p num="0174">The displayed listing includes several key parameters
of the current project, for ready reference ― but <u style="single">not all</u>
of the parameters for that project. Such a fuller
tabulation would typically occupy a large fraction of the
screen for just one project, and would contain many pieces
of data interesting only to prepress technicians at the
printshop, or proofing technicians at the proofing
facility. A full or categorized partial tabulation for
any project of the current customer is available to the
operator upon operating a related control in the RHCPS
interface ― such as the buttons marked "details/edit" in
the bottom half of Fig. 2, at left of the individual job
entries.</p>
    <p num="0175">Much of the displayed data may be in the database of
the RHCPS. Certain other data, however, available in the
fuller tabulation ― or even in the abbreviated summary 
(Fig. 2) ― may instead reside in the computers of the
printshop itself or of the primary customer.</p>
    <p num="0176">Those data are called up by links into the shop's or
customer's own site. The customer's reference number
("HU-241") in the example may be such a value, which changes
as the operator moves the dark-background selection
bar vertically through the ten entries visible in the
list, or operates the scroll bar to move other entries
into view, or both.</p>
    <p num="0177">Up-to-date information for reaching the customer by
phone, e-mail, or physical shipment may also be picked up
by link into the customer's site, for use by the shop in
quickly contacting the customer ― as seen from the
cluster of controls under the heading "CUSTOMER" at left.
Replacing such data, however, with information for
specific contact personnel at the customer's facilities is
possible too, and represented by the "change" buttons in
the same region of the screen.

   (Analogous "change" controls at the right end of the
screen are for actually revising the printshop's own site,
as telephone and mail contact data change. These are
available to the customer by links to the printshop site
in the GUI [Fig. 12] as seen by the customer.)</p>
    <p num="0178">The operator at the shop next scans the listing for
the project whose proofing file is ready. The customer or
the printshop may already have entered the project at hand
into the RHCPS system; if not, the operator at the shop
clicks the "File" menu item at top left, to obtain a generally
conventional drop-down menu (not shown) that includes
an entry "New" for creating a new entry for the
project. Creation of a new job entry typically requires
initial entry of some basic facts about the job. </p>
    <p num="0179">There is another entirely different way for the shop
operator to get to the job at hand, within the RHCPS system
― namely, to type-in the printing house's own
internal job-ticket number, which the operator knows.
This can be done by entering the number directly into Fig.
3 ― or, in event it is preferred by the system designer
not to include that data-entry block in the mode-selection
screen ― then instead moving from Fig. 5, for selection
of job-number finding mode, to Fig. 6 for scrolling to the
specified number.

   (Throughout almost all of this document, the phrase
"job ticket" refers to a strictly <u style="single">standardized</u> document
and computer file known as "JDF" or "job definition
format". At this particular point in the discussion, however,
particularly with reference to the illustrations
mentioned above, two different kinds of job tickets are
under discussion at the same time: here [1] the phrase
"job ticket" <u style="single">without more</u> refers to the printshop's
conventional <u style="single">internal</u> job ticket, whereas [2] "JDF" refers
to the strictly standardized document with its computer
file. The JDF is the <u style="single">only</u> kind of job ticket whose use is
fully integrated into the RHCPS ― but for purposes of
meshing with the internal systems of many and probably
most printing houses, it is necessary to deal, in the same
breath, with the simple, traditional paper job ticket, and
its nomenclature "job ticket". Ideally, where the
printshop's internal procedures can stand the change,
those procedures are revised so that the JDF is the <u style="single">only</u>
job ticket used for any job that is in the RHCPS, and thus
the JDF number is the <u style="single">only</u> job-ticket number for those
jobs.)</p>
    <p num="0180">An operator may know the job-ticket number because,
for instance, the operator is holding a paper job ticket 
in hand. Alternatively a colleague may have just finished
the proofing-file preparation and asked the operator to
take the project to the next stage.</p>
    <p num="0181">As will be seen, the job-ticket number may be known
to the RHCPS interface intrinsically through association
with the service's own JDF entries; or may be picked up
from the shop's site when needed. The operator, however,
alternatively can search by (Fig. 3) JDF number or date.
(The system can be configured to use the date of entry
into the system, or instead the deadline date.)</p>
    <p num="0182">For preferred embodiments of the invention the
parameters displayed in the mode-selection screen (Fig. 3)
are themselves determined by the commercial environment
surrounding the job. If the printshop does business with
parties other than primary customers, then presumably the
shop operator may find it easier to search for some jobs
by the names of those other parties ― brokers, proofers,
network couriers etc. In such a printshop advantageously
the list of possible search modes in the mode-selection
screen includes additional choices (<u style="single">e. g.</u> Fig. 13B).</p>
    <p num="0183">If desired for comparative or other purposes, the operator
at the shop may elect to display not only current,
open projects but also earlier, now-closed jobs of the
subject customer (Fig. 7). More commonly, to focus quickly
on needed information for a task at hand, the operator
elects to exclude those from the displayed list ― when
the operator's chore is simply to send a current proof to
the customer. If preferred, the designers may also
provide the operator yet another display alternative,
namely that of listing closed jobs only (not shown). </p>
    <p num="0184">Once the shop's operator has an entry on-screen for
the project, the operator verifies that this entry includes
the already prepared proofing file. Then the operator
may click on an icon or button (advantageously in
the "details/edit" screen, not shown) to transmit that
file through (for the present example) the Internet ― including
necessary color characterizations based on the
production printer and any custom inking etc. that will be
used.</p>
    <p num="0185">A related way for the proof to be expedited along its
path is for the proof-generating equipment (Fig. 8), or
operator (Fig. 9), to place the file in a so-called "hot
folder" ― a known phenomenon in the remote-proofing
field, and in other related computer fields (<u style="single">e. g.</u> FAXing
software) as well. This can be an entirely automatic operation
triggered by completion of the preceding step, or
can be a drag-and-drop operation performed by the
operator; or can be both of these, <u style="single">e. g.</u> with an operator
confirming (Fig. 10) the step initiated by completion of
the previous equipment operation. (For this last-mentioned
case if desired the system designers can include
another choice, namely "Remove from hot folder" ― with
suitable new status commands on the same or a following
screen.)</p>
    <p num="0186">The system is programmed to monitor the hot folder
and send whatever file is found in it. The transmission
path is preset when the arrangements between the customer
and printshop are established at the outset, with other
parameters of the job.</p>
    <p num="0187">At the customer's facility the file may be received
automatically or on demand. Depending on the specific Internet
access provisions (<u style="single">e. g.</u> DSL line or 56k modem) in 
use ― and operating options or settings selected ― at
the customer's facility, the customer's RHCPS terminal (1)
may simply acquire the proofing file, or (2) may acquire
only a notification that the proofing file is available
for downloading, or (3) may acquire nothing unless an
operator of the customer's staff logs on to the RHCPS system,
via the 'Net, and checks for incoming documents.</p>
    <p num="0188">In some of these cases, if the customer patronizes
more than one printing shop the customer's operator may be
called upon to locate the job that corresponds to the incoming
proof ― a procedure analogous to that described
above for the printshop operator in finding an entry in
the system for the then-outgoing proof. If this step is
required, the customer's operator eventually notes from
the RHCPS interface a list of printing houses which that
particular customer uses.</p>
    <p num="0189">If the customer uses more than one printshop, then,
in a procedure like that already pursued at the printshop,
the customer selects or types-in the name of the shop
(Fig. 11). As the RHCPS design variants at this point are
directly analogous to those previously described at length
for the printshop operator, pictures of the corresponding
screen views that follow are omitted here.</p>
    <p num="0190">If the customer uses only one printer then the system
simply bypasses the printshop-selection step. In any
event the RHCPS interface displays (Fig. 12) all the customer's
jobs with the particular identified printing shop.
(From this it will be understood that the customer's operator
can log on to the system to see whether any proof
file is waiting, even when no such file is waiting ― and
naturally will find that there is no proof to be printed
just then.) </p>
    <p num="0191">This operator selects, from the displayed list, a
desired job that has a proofing file waiting ― and by operations
at the GUI (advantageously through the associated
"details/edit" screen, not shown) queues that job to the
proofing printer device. For fullest realization of the
RHCPS objectives, that printer device is one of the model
line which provides closed-loop color functions ― particularly
including the ability to print, read and interpret
a color-calibration test pattern.</p>
    <p num="0192">Alternatively the proofing printer device too may operate
on a hot-folder principle. In this case any
proofing file that is downloaded, even automatically, from
an authorized entity ― as in this exemplary case the
printing house ― proceeds to the printer device,
preferably, or at least to the printer-device queue.</p>
    <p num="0193">The printer device may also have the capability to
scan and interpret color data for particular selected regions
of the image area within an actual proof to be printed,
as distinguished from a calibration pattern. These
two kinds of information have their own respective
advantages for various kinds of printing jobs and
situations.</p>
    <p num="0194">A key characteristic of preferred embodiments of the
RHCPS is that the proofing printer device automatically
transmits back to the <u style="single">printshop</u>, in a different location
from the printer device ― <u style="single">i. e.</u> not only provides to the
proofing operator at the customer's own facility ― a report
of the pseudocolorimetry operations just described.
Thus all parties to the core technical transaction which
constitutes "showing proof" can satisfy themselves that
what the customer is seeing is truly representative of
what the final product (not yet produced) will be ― or,
in the alternative, can know for themselves in just what 
ways the proof appearance diverges from a truly
representative image.</p>
    <p num="0195">If the customer finds that what the proof shows is
not acceptable ― in particular in terms of color ― then
the customer may simply send back a notification to that
effect, through the RHCPS user interface as before; or may
instead, or in addition, communicate with the printshop by
phone, e-mail etc. to help pinpoint the objection. The
parties usually consult the closed-loop-color technical
data to determine whether perhaps the problem may actually
be only one of inaccuracy in rendering at the proof press.</p>
    <p num="0196">If not, then the printshop usually tries to correct
the color in the data file from which it intends to print;
and iterates the proofing and review process until the
customer is satisfied with the representation of the final
product-to-be. Advantageously the operator initiates all
of these detailed steps by using controls in one of the
"edit/details" screens (not shown), where all of the relevant
image technical data are assembled and directly seen
― and where there is no question which image or which job
is under consideration.</p>
    <p num="0197">As before, the data in such screens are assembled by
links into both participants' sites as well as the RHCPS
database ― particularly including the site that is remote
from the user at each end of the proofing respectively.
Preferred embodiments of the invention thus make the most
of both the business and the technical aspects of linking
from the RHCPS user interface into the vendor's site, and
possibly the vendor's user interface. As will be seen,
however, these interlinkings are particularly striking and
beneficial for transactions involving one or more additional
participants. </p>
    <p num="0198">The foregoing chronology has been made rather
complete as to not only the contribution of the GUI to the
communication process but also several details of the interaction
between the customer and the shop ― so that it
can be seen clearly how the GUI fits into or in some ways
simulates parts of the classical interaction between these
parties. This level of detail has been presented here because
this example is perhaps the simplest commercial situation
which the RHCPS implements. Many of these details
are the same in the more-complex commercial situations described
below, and so will be omitted from descriptions of
those situations, which now follow.
<sl><li>(b) <u style="single">Primary customer via a proofing ASP, to the
printshop</u> ― This case encompasses several variants or
subcases. The customer may use the proofing ASP for only
some jobs, or for all; the customer may use only one such
ASP exclusively ― or may use one for certain jobs and one
or more other such ASPs for other jobs.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0199">The customer may use the ASP to make all the arrangements
with a printshop; or instead may use the ASP only
for soft proofing and nothing else. Still again, the customer
may use the service ASP as an intermediary to the
RHCPS, for all the functions of the RHCPS. (Although a
customer in purest principle needs no intermediary to the
RHCPS, this last option may be beneficial to a customer
that is not adept in the workings of the printing industry
and seeks a more-gentle buffer to the production people.)</p>
    <p num="0200">The customer may use <u style="single">other types</u> of ASPs for some
projects, or for all; or may never use other types of
ASPs. The customer may either use or elect not to use
traditional outside consultants or service entities such
as graphic artists, advertising agencies, and couriers. </p>
    <p num="0201">To consider fully and separately each of the possible
combinations of these several arrangements would be
bewildering, and also unnecessary as the basic principles
are straightforwardly extended from a description of just
one or two ASPs. Therefore, with the basic operation in
mind as described in subsection (a) above, only the more-significant
departures from that basic operation are noted
here.</p>
    <p num="0202">The user interface established by the RHCPS has a
link to that established by the proofing ASP ― and thereby
to data on the ASP's site (<u style="single">i. e.</u> computer or computers).
There may be a semantic question whether the
link is to (1) the ASP's <u style="single">interface</u>, or (2) the ASP's site,
or (3) the ASP's <u style="single">computer system</u>. To avoid debates over
any such question, for purposes of this document those
three concepts shall be considered synonymous.</p>
    <p num="0203">In preferred embodiments of the invention the link is
not merely a common hyperlink that leads (when "clicked")
to the ASP's site, but rather is a graphical modification
of the RHCPS interface itself, which selectively
incorporates certain data, and graphical elements if
desired, and related functions <u style="single">of the ASP</u> into operation
of the remote hardcopy service's GUI.</p>
    <p num="0204">The first manifestation of expanded participation
when an ASP is involved appears when the printshop's or
customer's operator wishes to locate data for a job at
hand. Once again it is necessary to begin by deciding how
to search ― and now there is another option not encountered
before, namely to search by proofing ASP (rather
than by customer, job number etc.).</p>
    <p num="0205">Behind this option is a difference in the character
and number of <u style="single">links</u> from the RHCPS site to sites of the 
customer, printing house, and ASP. In accordance with
preferred embodiments of the invention, links to an ASP
are now incorporated where before only the RHCPS, customer
and printshop were interlinked.</p>
    <p num="0206">The degree of apparent integration into the structure
of the GUI is advantageously chosen by the system
designers. The selection of job-search mode may give the
different modes the appearance of <u style="single">data</u>, presented in data
windows (Fig. 13A); or the appearance of a part of the
virtual control panel <u style="single">flat labeling</u>, selected by marking
within radio buttons (Fig. 13B); or the appearance of a
part of the virtual controls, selected by clicking virtual
r<u style="single">aised pushbuttons</u> (Fig. 13C). Similar and other choices
are made with regard to the degree of integration suggested
in screens (Figs. 14A through 15) for selecting customer,
printshop or ASP, after mode selection is complete.</p>
    <p num="0207">It will be understood that in reality all of these
modes are equally structural ― namely, not structural at
all but only a matter of different graphics. The
different graphics styles nevertheless are important in
that they convey to operators of the system some conceptualization
of the business relationships among the RHCPS
operator, the ASP and even the customer.</p>
    <p num="0208">Where an ordinary Worldwide-Web URL notation is used
for a link (Fig. 14A), most Web-wise users will receive a
connotation of little or no proprietary connection between
parties. It suggests little more than a courtesy
referral. A data-window presentation (Fig. 14B) may
instead possibly suggest that the parties' relationship is
in the nature of arm's-length service by the RHCPS to the
other participants: the RHCPS recognizes the parties but
treats their data, their identities, and even their
functions as essentially fungible. </p>
    <p num="0209">A radio-button or check-box presentation (Fig. 14C),
with the parties' identities and even their types (<u style="single">e. g.</u>
"proofer") appearing as part of flat-panel labeling, probably
connotes strongly to many GUI users that the parties
have at least some sort of mutual cooperative agreement.
Presenting the identities or even their types at the faces
of virtual raised pushbuttons (Figs. 14D and 15) can suggest
to observant users that the parties may be engaged in
a copartnering or coventuring form of enterprise.</p>
    <p num="0210">Thus ― now extending the customer/printshop example
of subsection (a) above ― when either the customer's or
the printshop's operator brings up the opposite party's
listing of transactions, a reference to the <u style="single">service ASP</u>
may appear in addition (Figs. 16 through 17A), or instead.
The specific situations, and the specific ways, in which
this interception of transactions by the ASP, or
interjection of the ASP into the printshop/customer
workflow, depends intimately upon the specifics of the
relationship between the customer and ASP.</p>
    <p num="0211">For example if the ASP is handling all proofing details
for the client, then when the printshop's proofing
file is ready ― and the shop personnel log onto the RHCPS
to transmit the file ― what will be displayed may at
first be an identification not of the primary customer but
rather of the service ASP. In the same transaction some
functions unrelated to proofing as such may instead bypass
the ASP and go directly to the primary, provided that the
customer or ASP has set up the account that way for the
particular job. In that case, if the printshop attempts
to brings up the ASP to arrange <u style="single">e. g.</u> delivery, then the
GUI can reroute the shop staff to the customer directly. </p>
    <p num="0212">Examples of these sorts of shielding or diversion of
contacts will be presented shortly in connection with broker-ASP
arrangements. As to the proofing ASP under
discussion here, however, no such guarded presentation appears.
Thus Fig. 16 shows to the printshop operator, in
an evenhanded way, all the information needed to contact
the primary or the ASP.</p>
    <p num="0213">This interface leaves it to an operator's preknowledge
of the participants, or otherwise to that operator's
experience, intelligence and best instincts, to select the
appropriate party for each kind of contact. Such
selection may be <u style="single">e. g.</u> technical people for technical
questions, business people for business questions, proofer
for matters relating to proofing, and so forth.</p>
    <p num="0214">Fig. 17 conversely shows the customer all the information
all that is needed to contact the printshop or the
proofer. An interesting example of a hybrid setup appears
in the alternative form of Fig. 17A: here the RHCPS has
linked the customer through to the proofer's site
including custom graphics that encourage the primary to
contact the proofer rather than the printing house ― but
do not actively constrain the primary to do so. The data
portions of the interface are strictly drawn from the
standard RHCPS setup.</p>
    <p num="0215">For showing proof, the GUI as seen at the printshop
too may lead the shop staff to transmit to the proofing
ASP ― whether the particular proof is to be a soft/virtual
proof for viewing on-screen, or a hardcopy proof.
(Here, however, the ASP has perhaps wisely chosen not to
approach the shop operator with a conspicuously marketingoriented
style, rather hewing to a just-business-betweentradesmen
sort of presentation.) The proofing ASP, most
commonly close to the primary customer geographically, is 
then responsible for contacting the customer to arrange
for actual viewing of the proof.</p>
    <p num="0216">In the hardcopy case, that contact generally entails
arranging a physical movement of printed document to customer,
or of the customer to the ASP's facility. The ASP
operators can take the opportunity to check the proof
themselves, preliminarily, if they in fact see part of
their function as providing the "buffer" suggested earlier.</p>
    <p num="0217">In this case the ASP may choose to advise the primary
how best to deal with irregularities in the proof ― what
the options and associated cost/benefit relationships are,
etc. Alternatively the ASP may instead undertake, on its
own responsibility, to reject or even to accept the proof,
if that reasonably appears to be within the scope of the
understanding between primary and ASP.

   (Such understanding is probably best reduced to writing,
but such writing may be conveyed and approved through
the same electronic systems as other portions of the communications.
In any event, such contractual specifics are
outside the scope of this document.)</p>
    <p num="0218">Fig. 18, the view as seen by the <u style="single">proofer's</u> operator,
reverts to fully standardized form. These four views thus
represent a relatively low-key, open and trusting set of
relationships, and this is one very popular business style
in the trade.</p>
    <p num="0219">As these views suggest, if the ASP elects to use the
RHCPS service for part of its communications with the primary
customer, then the primary can either be set up to
see the RHCPS interface or ― if one exists ― the ASP's
own interface. If the arrangement is the former, <u style="single">i. e.</u> if
the customer is to see the RHCPS interface, then in effect 
the ASP and the customer are operating in parallel; they
both see some of the same lists and data from the RHCPS.</p>
    <p num="0220">On the RHCPS interface as seen on the customer's computer,
however, what appears is the ASP in addition to the
printshop ― or instead of the printshop ― again
depending upon the arrangements made. In either event,
the customer will see only its own jobs, not <u style="single">other</u>
customers' jobs, with the ASP and/or the printshop.</p>
    <p num="0221">What appears on the ASP's computer (Fig. 18) in this
case is either (1) the <u style="single">customer</u> and the customer's jobs,
if the ASP operator elects to call them up that way, or
(2) the <u style="single">printshop</u> and the customer's jobs, if the ASP operator
elects that approach. The same group of jobs is
displayed in either event, provided that the ASP in fact
elects to see that customer's jobs (as distinguished from
checking on all its jobs with the same printshop).</p>
    <p num="0222">If instead the customer is set up to see the ASP's
user interface rather than the RHCPS's, then in preferred
embodiments of the invention the customer will see its
same jobs at the printshop ― but only those being handled
by this particular ASP. Those data are passed through by
the ASP's interface to the customer, but not necessarily
with identification of the printshop.</p>
    <p num="0223">The latter issue is determined by the setup of the
ASP's own interface, which in turn is configured based
upon the ASP's preferred way of doing business. Some will
operate on the philosophy that openness is an ideal basis
for dealing with customers; others on the philosophy that
the customer will sooner or later decide to eliminate the
middleman and should not be tempted.</p>
    <p num="0224">Thus as noted earlier the RHCPS workflow-management
component of the present invention accommodates many different
business and interpersonal styles, and in many ways 
encourages divergent healthy forms of competition. What
it does not do, in the example under discussion, is either
force the ASP to be open when there is concern that this
will lead to loss of business; or conversely force the ASP
to be guarded when the ASP's philosophy is open ― or when
there is concern that, for instance, the customer will
eventually perceive the guardedness and change vendors as
a result.</p>
    <p num="0225">The workflow-management protocol is extremely flexible
and versatile. In particular the ASP is at liberty to
follow the guarded philosophy with <u style="single">one</u> customer ― as for
instance a customer who is regarded as volatile, or overly
price conscious ― but simultaneously to follow the open
philosophy with <u style="single">another</u> customer, as for instance one who
seems inclined toward vendor loyalty, or toward
interpersonal criteria in selecting or maintaining
vendors, or perhaps simply one who is too sophisticated to
be kept in the dark. The RHCPS interface options are set
up as a tool whereby the ASP can implement its own philosophies
as convolved with its assessment of individual
customers.</p>
    <p num="0226">Although the array of these several variants may seem
complex in discussion, as will be understood indication of
the selections is very straightforward in terms of user-interface
options. Once so entered, the RHCPS system continues
to implement the agreed-upon arrangements unless
and until others are substituted.
<sl><li>(c) <u style="single">Primary customer via a network ASP to the proof
ASP or printshop, or both</u> ― The variants of this case,
in comparison with those taken up in the preceding
section, represent both a different function and another
level of complexity. Functional contributions of a 
network or "transport" ASP to completion of projects that
entail remote proofing is qualitatively different from
those of the proofing ASP considered in subsection (b)
above; yet as will be seen the RHCPS workflow-management
component readily accommodates the transport function as
well as the proofing function.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0227">As to complexity, the involvement of a network/transport
ASP is not necessarily simply a substitute for the
proofing ASP arrangements discussed above, but can instead
be an <u style="single">overlay</u> on the several variants of the proofing ASP.
In other words, the commercial relationships are not limited
to being linear or three cornered at most, but can involve
four and five parties to the same transaction.</p>
    <p num="0228">In fact the feasibility of using so many different
specializing enterprises for the same job is strongly and
distinctly enhanced, not obstructed, by preferred
embodiments of the present invention. The workflow-managing
module helps greatly in keeping all the
participants in step, informed, and ready to make their
contributions at the right times without tripping over one
another ― as they might if all the arrangements had to be
made by, for instance, FAXes and telephone calls.</p>
    <p num="0229">First as to the different function, again positing
the basic situation of a printshop that has a proofing
file ready for transmission, suppose first that there is a
network ASP involved but <u style="single">no proofing</u> ASP. The printshop
then seeks to provide the file to the primary customer.</p>
    <p num="0230">The network ASP may be engaged either by the printshop
or by the customer. Furthermore, if it is the shop
that elects to use the private network it may do so either
for all customers or for just the particular customer in 
question ― or even for just certain jobs, or certain jobs
of that customer.</p>
    <p num="0231">Conversely if it is the customer's election to use a
network ASP, that may be for all printing work, or only
for jobs with the particular printshop, or only for just
certain jobs, or certain jobs with that printshop. In any
event, when the printing-house operator is ready to send
the proof to the customer, as with the proofing ASP the
operator can log onto the RHCPS interface and locate the
job <u style="single">either</u> by customer or by ASP (in this case, probably
the ASP whose function is involved, namely the network
provider).</p>
    <p num="0232">Also if preferred, the operator can identify the job
by searching with some internal indicator (job ticket number,
for instance) which the operator happens to know ―
just as in the linear or two-party case. Here as before,
once the operator has called up the job on the remote-proofing
interface the correct contact is invoked
inherently by those same keystrokes. (Other options
mentioned earlier, including a hot folder, are equally
applicable here.)</p>
    <p num="0233">The system, in other words, is ordinarily preconfigured,
when the job is first set up, to transmit in some
particular way specified at the outset as between the customer
and the shop. Thus if a network ASP is to be used,
then when the operator instructs the system to proceed
with the transmission it is most commonly ready to do so
by routing the file through that designated network. Most
typically the necessary connections for the transmission
are preset for that network.</p>
    <p num="0234">All of these choices are directly analogous to those
illustrated earlier. Accordingly the illustrations (Figs.
3 through 6, 11, and 13A through 15) presented in the preceding 
subsections for job search shall be considered to
illustrate the present subject matter as well ― the differences
in screen appearance being only a matter of inserting
a different participant type and identity, manifesting
the involvement of links to a different sort of
participant.</p>
    <p num="0235">At the other end of the transmission, in this relatively
simple case of printshop and primary customer working
through a private network, from the perspective of the
customer's operator the scene is again rather simple. As
before, that operator can receive, or watch for, or look
up, its pending jobs by printshop, or by network ASP (unless
that information is inhibited by arrangements with
the printing house, as will be explained shortly) ― or
once again by an RHCPS JDF job ticket number, or simply by
the customer's own internal reference number for the project,
or a relevant date.</p>
    <p num="0236">In any of these events the customer operator is drawn
quickly to the incoming proofing file. An alternative arrangement,
as mentioned in an earlier example, is along
the model of a hot folder that sets up the job to run on
the customer's proofing printer upon receipt, without necessarily
involving any operator action.</p>
    <p num="0237">This subsection focuses upon participation of the
network ASP, and positive benefits flow from the present
invention in this regard as well. More specifically, when
any question arises about the transmission, not only the
primary-customer and the printing-house operators but also
an network-ASP technician readily gain access to all the
identical particulars of the transmission.</p>
    <p num="0238">This means that precisely the data seen by the two
operators about the transmission, as initiated from the
printing house and into the ASP's own equipment, can be 
seen by the ASP technician. Usually the net-ASP's screen
display is augmented with additional technical data
developed at the point of launching the file into the
network.</p>
    <p num="0239">In the absence of this RHCPS workflow control, the
scene is instead one that is nowadays very familiar. An
upset user telephones a harried technician, trying to describe
something relatively nebulous that happened
sometime earlier in the day, or perhaps the previous day.</p>
    <p num="0240">When instead two or all three concerned parties can
quickly be looking at the same data, at the same time, the
results are salutary in several ways. This commonality of
information among three parties to a troubleshooting conference
contributes greatly to a valuable calming <u style="single">sense</u> of
orderliness and confidence, as well as to speediest
possible <u style="single">actual</u> resolution of any flaw in the
transmission. This collaborative model is strikingly
different from an all-too-common scenario of the computer
era ― two vendors each telling a primary customer to
check with the <u style="single">other</u> vendor.</p>
    <p num="0241">These technological benefits, however, to a certain
extent are transcended by commercial advantages introduced
earlier. Thus for example the printing-house operator may
be concerned that in conversation with the customer the
network ASP may give away too much information about competing
printshops that also happen to use the net ASP; and
in this case the workflow-management service can be
configured to minimize contact between customer and ASP.</p>
    <p num="0242">Even in attempting to resolve a transmission-failure
situation it is not strictly necessary to convene all
three of the operators. Rather, if the printshop has a
policy of minimizing exposure of customers to use of the 
network ASP then ordinarily the problem can be promptly
resolved between the shop and the ASP.</p>
    <p num="0243">In such a situation the printshop elects to take on a
slightly greater part of the burden of resolving the matter,
in return for maintaining its more-guarded stance as
to its supporting net ASP. Even the use of the private
network itself can be made particularly inconspicuous if
that network serves primarily a leg of the connections
which is between the printshop and the Internet.</p>
    <p num="0244">If desired, the RHCPS interface as seen at a customer's
facility can be made to see only the printshop identification,
and not the network ASP's at all. The net-ASP
activities in effect then become a part of the printshop
services.</p>
    <p num="0245">Of course the customer is always free to inquire separately
into the full character of the RHCPS or of the net
ASP. In that event the customer can if desired establish,
or reestablish as the case may be, a fuller control of its
own commerce.</p>
    <p num="0246">Now secondly, as stated at the beginning of this subsection
(c) it is possible that the participants are not
only three ― the customer, shop, and net ASP ― but <u style="single">also</u>
a proofing ASP such as discussed in the previous subsection
(b). Representative forms of the user interface for
these four-cornered situations appear in Figs. 19 through
22 ― here too the basic model being one that is relatively
open, yet with room for fine adjustments. In this case
once again the RHCPS workflow manager seamlessly
integrates all these elements, sending the file to the
right party (whether customer or proofing ASP, or both)
and through the prearranged network. </p>
    <p num="0247">In this environment any failure of smooth operations
would ordinarily ― that is, in the absence of the RHCPS
workflow component ― be a source of major abrasion. It
is a well-known irritant, in the computer age, that every
participant seems to suggest some other participant as the
root source of any failure. The greater the number of
parties involved, the more frustrating and even exasperating
this phenomenon can be.</p>
    <p num="0248">The RHCPS, however, instead enables efficient resolution
of service interruptions on a participative basis,
in even a four- or five-cornered transaction, where the
participants are operating in a relatively open
understanding about the relationships among the several
services. At the same time preferred embodiments of the
RHCPS can accommodate other forms of understanding ―
<u style="single">e. g.</u> they may permit some of the vendors involved to
shoulder some added fraction of effort required to keep
operations running smoothly, in return for the ability to
partly isolate customers from other operators in the
trade.</p>
    <p num="0249">Although the desire to work openly or guardedly has
been discussed above in relation to printshops, other parties
may wish to exercise such options. Preferences of
this sort may be felt by ASPs and even by customers ― for
reasons of simply wishing to control their own costs, or
business confidences, or operating image; or whatever personal
reasons may arise.</p>
    <p num="0250">In these ways the RHCPS resolves many of the business
tensions discussed in the "BACKGROUND" section of this
document. It thereby promotes and enhances competition of
an economically healthy kind, and minimizes the problems
set forth in that earlier section. <sl><li>(d) <u style="single">Primary customer via a transaction ASP to other
parties</u> ― Here too, this transASP may be in a relatively
simple direct business relation between the primary and
the printshop, with no other ASPs involved; or this ASP's
relationship may be only one of several. That is, in
addition to the middleman ASP there may also be any of the
previously described relationships with ASPs for proofing
or for data transmission, or both.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0251">The general principles for preferred embodiments of
the invention here, however, are analogous to those
discussed above. In view of the relatively extensive
earlier discussions, these general principles are only
summarized here: the RHCPS interface, as before
preferably though not necessarily a graphical type, gives
each user log-in options custom-established for that
specific user ― and based upon several factors.</p>
    <p num="0252">Factors include (1) all entities that are party to
the particular transaction of interest; and (2) preferences
of the entity that initiates the RHCPS arrangements
for the particular transaction ― sometimes subject to
understandings with some other entity or entities, as noted
earlier. In particular, usually log-in and other operating
options are set up as a so-called "default" (in
the computer-jargon sense, not the financial sense).</p>
    <p num="0253">The default settings are usually subject to override
by the user or users who are ― or who are positioned in
the chain of commerce relatively closer to ― the primary
customer. Although the primary customer, and those in position
to act on the primary's behalf, thus most commonly
have authority to override the default arrangements, the
full extent of such options may not always be clear to
parties that have them. </p>
    <p num="0254">Of all the parties that may purposely leave such options
incompletely explained, transaction or broker ASPs
are perhaps the most prominent. This may be a natural and
understandable result of the nature of such businesses, in
view of the following considerations.</p>
    <p num="0255">As most transASPs do not participate directly in
physical creation of the final product, the primary economic
reward for their activity cannot be linked to any
esthetic or mechanical function. Rather they provide convenience,
and familiarity with trade practice, and ideally
sound guidance of the primary customer to a printing house
and other vendors that are optimum for the nature of the
project.</p>
    <p num="0256">These functions ― although real, and potentially of
extremely great value ― are hard to quantify, and may be
difficult for some primary customers to appreciate at all.
Vulnerability to diversion of clientele therefore may be
greatest for the transASP, of all the participants in
these transactions.</p>
    <p num="0257">Representative versions of a GUI for broker-ASP situations
appear in Figs. 23 through 27. In the example
here, only the broker (transASP) has full view (Fig. 27)
of all details and data.</p>
    <p num="0258">At the opposite extreme is the sharply restricted
visibility of the primary customer, who in this example
sees (Fig. 24) only two ASPs ― the broker and the proofer.
The proofer's <u style="single">business</u> contact line in the upper,
data-window screen section is removed entirely ―
obscuring absence of the contact's name ― as are the
"business" radio-button legends for both e-mail and shipping
label. Additional screen titles within the frame
appear automatically, adjusting to the absence of
information in two columns ― which as shown can be kept 
in their usual positions if desired to minimize confusion
between different participating operators.</p>
    <p num="0259">Between these two poles of relative visibility are
some intermediate information-access levels. Thus in the
printshop operator's screen (Fig. 23) the names of all
contacts at the primary customer's facility are unlisted,
the phone and e-mail controls for contacting that facility
are grayed out, and the GUI reveals only the customer's
project reference number, and address data for a mailing
label ― so that finished magazines can be shipped to the
customer.</p>
    <p num="0260">A like level of information access is accorded to the
network ASP (Fig. 26), who it is presumed may have to ship
some piece of network equipment to the primary customer,
or even service such an item at that customer's facility.
Contours of information access are formed in yet another
way for the proofing ASP (Fig. 25), who is enabled to consult
with the primary customer's artistic or technical
people ― but not with management: the proscribed
contact's name is unlisted in the "CUSTOMER" column, and
the phone and e-mail "business" options are grayed out.</p>
    <p num="0261">This example is constructed to include another ASP,
in the column headed "PREPRESS/SPECIAL" ― <u style="single">e. g.</u> a trade
prepress house, or other special-purpose vendor. (In the
event that <u style="single">both</u> a prepress firm <u style="single">and</u> another special vendor
are present, either condensed [narrow] fonts can be used
to permit displaying all participants within the width of
the screen or as noted earlier suitable horizontal-scroll
capability can be provided for the upper portion of the
screen.)</p>
    <p num="0262">The prepress house is functionally closest to the
printshop and proofer. Prepress therefore might logically
receive <u style="single">e. g.</u> access to both those entities ― plus the 
same need-to-know customer artistic/technical access as
the proofer.</p>
    <p num="0263">As shown, the system primarily directs the customer
to the broker ASP, who in effect becomes symbolic of the
customer's overall project or projects. From the customer's
perspective, in effect the sole vendor involved is
the broker.</p>
    <p num="0264">In the most-highly preferred embodiments of the invention,
as noted earlier the primary customer has the option
of overriding all such arrangements. This option is
enabled ― but not encouraged, and certainly never pushed
on the customer ― by making available to the primary customer
information about the option.</p>
    <p num="0265">The information is ideally included in an RHCPS user
interface seen by the primary customer. This can be done
in the form of an external link to the contractual terms
of the RHCPS, which include the information about the option;
or in the form of an internal "help" screen that includes
the terms.</p>
    <p num="0266">In implementing either of these arrangements, careful
attention must be given to the wording and graphics used
in leading to and presenting the customer's override option.
It is a sensitive point and best worked out among
specialists in law, marketing, customer relations, and
professional editing.</p>
    <p num="0267">The extent to which the link and terms are
conspicuous, in the RHCPS user interface, is important.
The basic mechanics may encompass use of the "Help" menu
item that appears in the many tabulation screens shown in
the accompanying drawings.</p>
    <p num="0268">As one presentational technique, words such as "RHCPS
contract terms" simply may be included in the drop-down 
submenu that appears when that main menu item is clicked.
This may seem overly conspicuous, but it should be borne
in mind that the terms themselves are typically lengthy,
including many more clauses than just the user-override
option that is under discussion here.</p>
    <p num="0269">Another technique is to respond to a user's click on
the "Help" item in the main menu by opening an
intermediate selection dialog box (not shown) that
contains a button or link to invoke the contract terms
(instead of moving along to the main help screens).
Alternatively such a button or link can be incorporated
directly into a main help screen itself (Fig. 28).
Depending on the layout and wording in such an
intermediate help dialog or main help screen, the impact
of the contract-terms availability may be either strengthened
or weakened, relative to putting it into the help
menu as first suggested above.</p>
    <p num="0270">In either event, the placement of the override option
within the terms, and the nature of the wording used as a
title for it, are extremely variable. This variability
still leaves room for further fine tuning of the content
and tone of the presentation.</p>
    <heading>5. INTEGRATION WITH A SOFT-PROOFING A. S. P.</heading>
    <p num="0271">To facilitate some aspects of the invention, advantageously
some features are implemented within printer-device
systems, and complementary features appear in the
remote soft-proofing ASP. Although these implementations
may not be strictly necessary, the result is an
optimization of the invention that also optimizes 
integration between the remote soft-proofing ASP and the
remote hardcopy proofing service.</p>
    <p num="0272">The new printer-device systems will be characterized
here as "remote-proof enabled" or "RP-enabled". They include
a printing device with front-end software.</p>
    <p num="0273">These features make it realistic for users to trust
the integrated service, basically by ensuring output consistency
of hardcopy proofs ― <u style="single">i. e.</u>, by providing for
consistent printing (same contents, layout, color etc.) on
any remote-proof printer of the line. The features also
facilitate the remote-proofing workflow.
<sl><li>(a) <u style="single">PDF plus JDF as a basis for workflow</u> ― To ensure
output consistency, it is very helpful to provide
that:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>all the information required to correctly print a
proof is included in the data sent from the proof
originator to the proof receiver; and</li><li>the setups used both on the originating and receiving
printers to print the proofs are consistent.</li></ul>
These requirements are achieved by using a combination of
PDF (Adobe "portable document file") and JDF ("Job Definition
File") to carry all the required information, as
follows.</li><li>▪ Contents of the proof itself are carried in the PDF.
This file preferably meets very strict requirements
in terms of the information included ― <u style="single">i. e.</u>, for
ideal results it includes all the color, relevant information,
fonts and images. </li><li>▪ The JDF job ticket stores all the information on <u style="single">how</u>
the proof has to be printed to ensure a consistent
output. It can also store the information on status
of the remote proofing workflow for the specific
proof.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0274">The RP-enabled printer systems include the tools required
to create the PDF and JDF parts of a remote proof. These
tools are fully integrated into the front-end software
(for example in a raster image processor that is in or
associated with the printer), so that a user can easily
create a proof to be sent to a remote user ― and not only
send it but also print it in the user's local printer.</p>
    <p num="0275">On the receiver side, before printing a remote proof
some checking is performed. This ensures that the proof
data meet the requirements to ensure output consistency.
<sl><li>(b) <u style="single">Managed and calibrated color system</u> ― Use of
the automatic color calibration and the color-management
features in the printer ensures that the color behavior of
RP-enabled printers is consistent. This means that any
proof which contains the correct color information can be
printed consistently, in terms of color, in any RP-enabled
printer or at least any such printer of the product line.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0276">Both the automatic color calibration and color-management
features are implemented by interaction of the
printer device and the front-end software.
<sl><li>(c) <u style="single">Proof checking and feedback</u> ― The RP-enabled
printer systems has the ability to check for successful
and correct printing of a hardcopy proof, and its quality
as well. This information can be made available to the
user who printed the proof, and also sent back through the 
RHCPS to the proof originator (<u style="single">e. g.</u> the user who
originated the proof) so that the originator can know when
the proof was printed and what the quality of that proof
was.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0277">Thus the entire RHCPS operates on a closed-loop basis.
In this way the system is made very <u style="single">trustable</u>, thus
resolving one of the major inadequacies of the art.</p>
    <p num="0278">The proof-checking functionality advantageously uses
the same hardware in the printer that is used in automatic
color calibration. The entire procedure (proof checking
and status feedback) is integrated into the front-end
software so that it can be triggered automatically ― and
can be transparent to the user, depending on the settings
of the RHCPS or the proof itself, or both.
<sl><li>(d) <u style="single">Obligations imposed on the remote soft-proofing
ASP</u> ― To enable the RHCPS to make full use of the RP-enabling
features integrated into the printer system, several
provisions should be made by the soft-proof ASP:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li><u style="single">support PDF-plus-JDF workflow</u> ― The soft-proof ASP
should be able to transfer the proof data from the
sender to the receiver. Ideally the ASP should also
use the JDF job ticket to store essentially all information
related to its own services ― for example
the originator and intended receiver(s), and the
status of the proof ― so that the JDF ticket is the
<u style="single">only</u> job ticket used.</li><li><u style="single">integration of the proof-generating tools and the
soft-proof ASP</u> ― As described above, proof-generating
tools are integrated into the printer
front-end software. There should be some way to pass 
proof data, once generated, to the soft-proofing ASP.
For this purpose the ASP can provide a hot folder
(discussed earlier) or equivalent arrangement.</li><li><u style="single">integration of the proof-consuming tools and the
soft-proof ASP</u> ― When proofing data are received
through the soft-proofing ASP, the data should be
passed to the printer front end for processing and
printing. Again, this calls for a hot folder or other
feature ― most typically a feature of the user
interface, graphical or otherwise.</li><li><u style="single">support status feedback</u> ― The printer front end
triggers automatic checking of the proof, once printed,
and generation of information on the printing
result. There should be a way to send this information
from the front end to the soft-proof ASP so that
it can be forwarded to the proof originator.</li><li><u style="single">support user-collaboration features</u> ― The ASP should
make provision for the proof receiver to add comments,
<u style="single">i. e.</u> annotations, and preferably to <u style="single">approve</u> the proof
in writing after having printed it. All such
information should be accessible to the proof
originator.</li></ul>
These may be considered basic obligations of the ASP, although
people skilled in this field will appreciate that a
reduced level of functionality and service may yet be obtained
in the absence of some such provisions. In
addition to these basic features, some additional
provisions improve workflow and usability: <ul list-style="bullet"><li><u style="single">proof data checking</u> ― To ensure output consistency,
ideally a check is always performed at the receiver
side before the proof is printed. To save time and
bandwidth, however, it is useful that either the ASP
or RHCPS itself ― depending on the circumstances ―
also prevalidate the data before downloading by the
receiver.</li><li><u style="single">hosting proof-generation tools by the ASP</u> ― Since
the RP-enabled printer systems integrate the tools
for generating correct proofing data, any user with
such a printer can generate remote proofs. In some
cases, however, it is also useful to have the ability
to run those tools on the <u style="single">ASP's</u> system ― thereby enabling
collaboration by ASP subscribers who have no
such printer.</li><li><u style="single">integration of soft and hardcopy proofing</u> ― Some
soft-proofing ASPs may themselves use a commercial
service, such as RealTimeProof<sup>tm</sup> service, for soft
proofing. That service allows soft proofing of several
types of files.</li></ul></li></sl></p>
    <p num="0279">In order to integrate it with the RHCPS, the
soft-proofing application (<u style="single">i. e.</u> the ASP) should be
able to:
<sl><li>(i) send data to the RHCPS that satisfies the obligations
outlined above (PDF-plus-JDF, containing
all the color characterization, fonts, and so
on); and </li><li>(ii) process RHCPS proofs and use the embedded color-characterization
data (color profiles in the PDF
file, etc.)</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0280">The first of these can be accomplished by integrating
into the ASP software at least a part of the proof-generation
tools of the present invention, <u style="single">e. g.</u> a
software kernel.
<sl><li>(e) <u style="single">Integration between the ASP and RHCPS</u> ― The
present invention encompasses a service that can be
offered by a sponsoring company ― to consider an example
in point, the Hewlett Packard Company. The service is
made available, possibly for a fee, to users who register
their RP-enabled printer systems in that sponsor's customer-registration
system.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0281">The RHCPS is a <u style="single">basic</u> service that itself provides remote
hardcopy proofing only. A user desiring other services
than that ― <u style="single">e. g.</u> high-bandwidth transmission, file
storage (so-called "digital asset management") or soft
proofing ― should engage one or more ASPs to obtain those
services.</p>
    <p num="0282">To facilitate an upgrade path to such ASP services,
as well as interaction between customers of the RHCPS and
ASP respectively, preferably these features are included:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>As indicated at some length in previous sections of
this document, the RHCPS customer database is able to
identify the users who have decided to be customers
of, <u style="single">e. g.</u>, a soft-proofing ASP. Proofs sent to or
from one of these users through the RHCPS are
<u style="single">redirected</u> to the ASP, through the agency of the many
interface features previously detailed. </li><li>The database also advantageously enables each user to
search for other registered users, of any type, including
both potential vendors and customers ― except
for registrants who elect privacy, <u style="single">i. e.</u> elect
to opt out of such tabulation.</li><li>The RHCPS and the soft-proofing ASP each allow
specifying, as a proof receiver, a user that is on
the other service. For example, a remote-proof
originator who is using a soft-proof ASP can specify
that the receiver is using the RHCPS ― and in this
case the proof is forwarded from the ASP to the
RHCPS.</li><li>Accordingly a protocol is included for forwarding
proofs between the two services. This protocol is
advantageously bidirectional so that that receiving
service can return to the originator various kinds of
information such as error data, closed-loop proofing
feedback. The protocol is a standard one and can be
used to expand the integration ― between the two
companies, to include other services of theirs ― and
also to encompass ASPs of other types as discussed
earlier.</li></ul></p>
    <p num="0283">All such integration can be accomplished through the Internet
or by more-direct backbone connection as preferred.
Generally integration is facilitated thus:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>The RHCPS maintains a full user database for all participating
ASPs as well as its own. </li><li>A data field flags each respective ASP's subset of
these users. These can overlap, since customers are
at liberty to engage multiple ASPs of different types
and even of the same type for different jobs.</li><li>The RHCPS <u style="single">tests</u> that data field on receipt of a proof
for transmission to a user.</li><li>These arrangements are regarded as nominally
reciprocal ― each ASP is expected, though not
required, to do the same.</li><li>Both exclusive and nonexclusive forms of these
arrangements are encompassed within the invention as
defined in certain of the appended claims, and may be
regarded as species of the invention. Exclusivity is
thus a matter of business preference and business
arrangements between the participants.</li></ul></p>
    <p num="0284">In these ways, as earlier pointed out, the RHCPS expands
the capabilities of the soft-proofing ASP ― which already
has a useful service. The RHCPS does not obsolete that
service, which continues to be particularly viable for
highest speed, for concept proofing, and for preliminary
proofing. Thus the RHCPS of the present invention does
not compete with so much as mutually complement the soft-proofing
ASP.</p>
    <heading>6. INTEGRATION WITH A TRANSACTION A. S. P.</heading>
    <p num="0285">As described earlier, a transaction or buyer ASP focuses
on management of a job, and order data ― and the 
integration of order processing and status tracking with
various functions managed by a printshop. Typically this
type of ASP provides very little support (representatively
perhaps just an FTP server) to the sharing of content
files between a buyer and a printer, or digital asset management.
It usually imposes no restriction on the
contents shared, and provides no tool for proof generation
or related functions.</p>
    <p num="0286">One representative transASP offers customized and
branded websites for both buyers and printers, with
ongoing management and support. The firm does not have a
general standard website design.</p>
    <p num="0287">This sort of enterprise concerns itself with management
of the electronic commerce between buyer and printer,
particularly job specification and status tracking. Such
operation is well complemented by the RHCPS of the present
invention or, alternatively, by another service ASP such
as a soft proofer or private network.</p>
    <p num="0288">The transASP sets up websites for both the buyer and
printer, and directs the two to each other through a protocol.
Thereafter the ASP continues as a sort of arm's-length
printing broker or facilitator.
<sl><li>(a) <u style="single">Workflow</u> ― Integration of a transASP with an
RHCPS, according to the present invention, produces workflow
generally as described below.
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>When creating a project, the buyer specifies (by a
computer-interface checkbox or the like) that remote
proofing should be used on the project or at least
certain components. If the buyer is using the printer's
site to specify the job, the remote-proofing 
proof <u style="single">type</u> appears only if the printer has remote-proofing
capabilities.</li></ul></li></sl></p>
    <p num="0289">The converse is also true: if the buyer is
using the buyer's own site to specify the job, the
"remote proofing" option will only appear if the buyer
has remote-proofing capabilities. The main
difference is that, in this case, the remote proofing
capabilities of the printer could be used as selection
criteria. That is, only printers that can generate
remote proofs would be able to bid for that job
when an RFQ is promulgated.</p>
    <p num="0290">In any case, there is preferably a link from the
corresponding transASP page to a page served by the
RHCPS sponsor, describing the RHCPS. This link is a
particularly nonintrusive way to promote the RHCPS
concept, provided that it is offered in a low-key
manner ― and at a strategically situated point in
the process, where the user is likely to be amenable
to education on basics of such a service.
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>The RFQ, bidding and ordering process otherwise proceeds
as in any other project of the transASP.</li><li>When the printer generates the proof(s) for the job,
or contracted component of it, the transASP accesses
the RHCPS (or a soft-proof ASP) to send those proofs
to the buyer. The RHCPS has all necessary
information to establish that this particular user
(<u style="single">e. g.</u>, the printer) is also using the particular
transASP.</li></ul></p>
    <p num="0291">Accordingly, before sending the proof the RHCPS
offers the possibility of linking it to an order (or
order component) of the specified transASP. This 
function is readily implemented in the form of a
checkbox ― one that <u style="single">may</u> appear to linked parties,
depending on what setup has been put in place.</p>
    <p num="0292">For example, when a printshop operator ― using
the RHCPS interface ― enters the intended receiver
of a proof, a window appears with all the open
projects in that printshop operator's transASP
website (assuming that the printer has one)
corresponding to that buyer, <u style="single">i. e.</u> the proof receiver.
The printshop operator can then select a
project (or component) as the one to which the proof
being sent is linked.</p>
    <p num="0293">Alternatively, the remote proofing process can
be launched directly from the transASP web page for
the job. Through a web link, the user directly accesses
the RHCPS page to create the proof, with all
the information about sender, receiver and link to
the transASP project already filled in.
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>The remote-proofing workflow is managed by the RHCPS
as a regular remote proof (upload, download, then
print, approval, etc.). The only difference is that,
when there is a change in the proof status, the data
about the new status is sent to the transASP system
for use in updating the project status.</li><li>Printers or buyers, or both, can consult the remote-proof
status through the transASP website or RHCPS.
As will now be clear, in accordance with the invention
the two are crosslinked ― in other words, from
the transASP site, when accessing the proofing status
of a project, the user should be able to access the
RHCPS page for that proof; and vice versa.</li></ul></p>
    <p num="0294">Workflow is very similar if the entree to the RHCPS is
through a different sort of provider ― <u style="single">e. g.</u> a soft-proof
or network ASP.
<sl><li>(b) <u style="single">Interface</u> ― The following interfaces are defined.
Parallels to the arrangements for the soft-proof
ASP should now be recognized.
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>an interface for retrieving information on open
projects for a certain pair of users ― printer and
buyer

   (Implementation calls for a well-defined way of
mapping users between the RHCPS user space and the
transASP user space.)</li><li>a programmatic interface to allow the creation of
remote-proofing jobs and filling-in part of the
information

   (This is a user-operational facility for "programming
in" new jobs, actually data entry.)</li><li>a method for linking proofs with transASP projects or
components ― <u style="single">i. e.</u> a job (or component) identifier
that can be stored in the proof job ticket and vice
versa;</li><li>an interface for retrieving information on status of
a certain proofing job, so that it can be displayed
in the transASP's site

   (This interface should support two kinds of operating
modes: synchronous, <u style="single">i. e.</u> status queries
about a certain proof; and event-trapping, <u style="single">i. e.</u> automatic 
update whenever status of a certain proof job
changes.)</li></ul></li></sl></p>
    <p num="0295">Some transASPs, as well as the other ASP types, may have a
tendency to respond to marketplace pressures by expanding
their services beyond the original and natural areas of
interest ― and perhaps talent ― of their operators. The
present invention can relieve them of that, fostering competition
without redundancy (in particular wasteful, inefficient
redundancy).
<sl><li>(c) <u style="single">Additional transASP features</u> ― Advantageously
the user sees some new elements in the transASP website.
One of these is a new RHCPS proof type added to the prepress
parameters in the project or component description,
preferably with links from that page to descriptions of
the RHCPS.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0296">Also preferably added is a new display area within
the previous project-status tabulations ― to display remote-proofing
status of the various components. This area
displays summarized status and log-in information for the
proofs, and provides links for access to the proof itself
and its more-detailed status in the RHCPS.
<sl><li>(d) <u style="single">Additional RHCPS features</u> ― Conversely, for an
RHCPS user who creates and uploads a proof into the
system, if the user is also a transASP user, the RHCPS
opens a window showing all the user's open projects ―
with that transASP ― corresponding to the intended.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0297">The RHCPS window showing proof status also provides a
link to the transASP website page that has data on the related
transASP project. If a proof relates to a transASP 
project, the project or component identifier is stored in
the job ticket.</p>
    <heading>7. CONTENT AND TRANSACTION STANDARDIZATION FORMATS</heading>
    <p num="0298">Because the number of parameters to be brought under
control as between different printing systems is high,
this topic is potentially encyclopedic. Comprehensive
presentation of all those variables, however, would be of
little service to a person of ordinary skill in the art,
because this part of the RHCPS operation simply comes down
to a massive technological-bookkeeping problem.</p>
    <p num="0299">On the other hand, since that problem is rather openended
and does involve many variables it is one that can
leave the person of ordinary skill groping for a solid
place to begin. To avoid any need for extensive trial and
error, there follows below a presentation of a preferred
accounting methodology, together with selected examples,
providing a clear picture of the approach adopted by the
present inventors.
<sl><li>(a) <u style="single">Data subdivision, standard formatting, and
restriction</u> ― The fundamental orientation begins with use
of two industry-standard formats for, respectively,
document appearance and processing information. Here
"appearance" encompasses color, layout, and content ―
which in turn means all the graphic objects (text, images,
graphics) with their correct respective fonts and
dimensions.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0300">Processing information includes printing conditions
and settings ― the printer model and all parameters peculiar
to that model, the printing-medium type, resolution 
for each image, and the print quality (and printmode).
The appearance and processing data are complementary: to
perform remote proofing, both are required.</p>
    <p num="0301">While appearance information is carried in a special
form of the industry-standard Adobes Portable Document
File ("PDF"), the processing information is held in a job
ticket ― for which the standard Job Definition Format
("JDF") is used. Thus the JDF job ticket is part of the
data exchange, but is a separate entity from the appearance
information.</p>
    <p num="0302">This division of the data greatly facilitates any
needed proof retargeting, <u style="single">i. e.</u> changing printer-setting
characteristics to use a different printer model or medium.
Retargeting should be performed at the proof originator
site, as suggested in the previously mentioned Jodra
patent document; however, the JDF should be configured to
accommodate information relevant to different printer models,
so that the system in the originating site need not
be told the specific printer model that will be used in
the receiver's site.</p>
    <p num="0303">Key to the most highly preferred embodiments of the
invention is use of these standard formats with, in
essence, reduced parameter sets ― that is to say, with:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>entries in many standard fields prohibited or
ignored, and</li><li>only limited ranges or discrete values, of the respective
variables, permitted or accepted in certain
other standard fields.</li></ul></p>
    <p num="0304">For several reasons this has been found greatly preferable
to creating a custom format with only the desired fields
present.
<sl><li>(b) <u style="single">Additional nomenclature</u> ― The PDF and JDF together
constitute the data exchange or "proofing file".
Some workers in the industry have come to instead call
this computer-readable <u style="single">file</u> simply the "proof" ― but in
the present text and appended claims the more traditional
usage is followed, <u style="single">i. e.</u> the word "proof" refers to the
hardcopy document or on-screen computer image that is directly
visible to the human eye.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0305">In a specific implementation of the RHCPS, a particular
entity may have the ability to act as an originator or
a receiver; however, it is convenient for the
specification to view them as separate entities. A
routing service such as a network ASP may add information
to enable or facilitate transmission from an originator to
a receiver, but any such changes must be transparent to
the requirements of the data exchange ― in other words,
data both into and out from the routing service should
comply with all rules established for the exchange.</p>
    <p num="0306">To avoid ambiguity the terms "local" and "remote"
sometimes require a point of reference. For present purposes
"local" usually refers to the location of the
<u style="single">generator</u> of a proofing file; hence unless otherwise
specified or suggested by context a "local proof" is one
printed (or viewed on-screen) in the same location where
its proofing file is generated; and a "local proofing
file" is a proofing document generated in a local system
and susceptible to transmission through the RHCPS to a
<u style="single">receiver</u>. </p>
    <p num="0307">Correspondingly unless otherwise specified "remote"
refers to the location of the receiver, and a "remote
proofing file" is one that has been received through the
RHCPS by the entity "remote" from the originator (the "local"
entity). A hardcopy proof physically printed at that
remote location is accordingly a "remote proof"; hence the
phrases "remote proofing", "remote hardcopy proofing service"
etc.
<sl><li>(c) <u style="single">Proof types</u> ― It is important that the RHCPS be
able to handle not only single-page proofs but also signature
proofs (sometimes called "imposition proofs"). Although
consistent, accurate remote hardcopy color proofing
of page modules is extremely useful and valuable in
itself, the power of the invention is greatly expanded by
incorporation of signature-proofing capability.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0308">Accordingly the proofing data contain (in the PDF)
information on the contents of each page, and (in the JDF)
layout information describing the signature scheme to be
used in printing the document on a press. In preferred
embodiments of the invention, the proof generator can produce
two types of proofs: page, and signature.</p>
    <p num="0309">The difference between them is not in the proofing
data, but rather in how the layout information is used by
the recipient's proofing device when printing the proof:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>For page proofs the device <u style="single">may</u> use the layout information
to print the proof, but is not required to do
so. If the proofing device cannot print the
signature(s) as described in the layout, it is not
required to so inform the user. </li><li>For signature proofs the proofing device <u style="single">must</u> use the
layout information to print the proof. If the proofing
device cannot print the signature(s) as described
in the layout (due, most commonly, to media-size limitations)
it must inform the user and provide
different options for printing the proof or canceling
it. The specific user interface is device dependent.</li></ul></p>
    <p num="0310">For example, suppose that an originating entity creates a
proofing file for an eight-A4-page document, describing an
eight-up signature that will be used in the press. If
those proofing data are sent to an A3-size proofer, the
behavior may depend on the type of proof requested:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>If a page proof was requested, the proofer can print
four A3 sheets, each containing two of the original
document pages. To group the document pages, the
device may use the information in the layout data to
ensure that the two A4 pages printed in each sheet
are adjacent in the signature; or it may use any
other algorithm ― such as printing pages in the order
in which they appear in the assembled document.</li><li>If a signature proof was requested, the proofer issues
a warning informing the user that it cannot
print the signature because that would exceed the
maximum page size of the device. It may offer the
user several options, such as dividing the signature
(tiling), scaling down the whole form proof or reverting
to a page proof.</li></ul><sl><li>(d) <u style="single">PDF/Proof contents</u> ― To ensure that the output
proof can be printed consistently in different devices it 
is helpful to strictly define the characteristics of the
file. PDF is a very powerful, general-purpose format,
whose features and functionality are far more versatile
than the RHCPS can use; hence many of these features and
functionality are restricted. In this document a file
that complies with these requirements is sometimes called
a "PDF/Proof file".</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0311">Compliance with PDF/Proof restrictions does <u style="single">not</u> ensure
output hardcopy consistency. A receiver must process
the data in a specific way to achieve it.</p>
    <p num="0312">Thus a conforming PDF/Proof file is a PDF in which
are found those features necessary for the exchange of
proofing data and to <u style="single">enable</u> output consistency at any receiving
entity. Receiving entities must <u style="single">ensure</u> output
consistency for files conforming to PDF/Proof constraints.</p>
    <p num="0313">In the embodiment now preferred, a PDF/Proof file
must be a valid PDF 1.3 file, as described in the "<u style="single">PDF
Reference Manual / Version 1.3</u>". Thus any requirement of
PDF 1.3 or higher is also a requirement of PDF/Proof but
is not further mentioned or repeated below.</p>
    <p num="0314">Although nonprinting-related PDF constructs ― such
as annotations and thumbnails ― might be present in a
PDF/Proof file, they are ignored by the remote-proofing
entities and consequently are not included in this discussion
of the file format. (It can make sense to use
these features if it is desired to use other PDF standard
tools in the workflow.) In particular, specification of
the PDF/Proof format contemplates only the objects in the
pages tree, catalog, and file information dictionaries in
a PDF.</p>
    <p num="0315">Advantageously there are two versions of PDF/Proof,
defined relative to a raster image processor ("RIP") that 
is currently used in the preferred printing systems to
prepare images for the printing engine:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>"PDF/Proof-Image" supports only "postRIPped" remote-proofing
workflow.</li><li>"PDF/Proof-Object" supports both "postRIPped" and
"preRIPped" remote-proofing workflow. As these relationships
suggest, PDF/Proof-Image is a subset of
PDF/Proof-Object; <u style="single">i. e.</u> any file that complies with
PDF/Proof-Image also complies with PDF/Proof-Image.</li></ul></p>
    <p num="0316">The presentation of exemplary PDF/Proof restrictions will
begin now with "PDF/Proof-<u style="single">Image</u>".</p>
    <p num="0317">All the components of the proof <u style="single">contents</u> are
contained in the <u style="single">body</u> of a <u style="single">single</u> PDF/Proof-Image file.
It is not permitted to present only as an embedded file
any component required to process the proof contents.</p>
    <p num="0318">To help see how to implement the general rules, following
are only just a few examples of several dozen constraints
that make up a PDF/Proof-Image specification.
This part of the present document assumes familiarity with
parameter and field names (such as "DefaultForPrinting",
"OutputIntent", "ExtGState", "MediaBox", etc.) defined in
the PDF 1.3 specification.</p>
    <p num="0319">As a consequence of the contents-in-body requirement
last stated above, streams cannot reference external
files. That is to say, the F, FFilter and FDecodeParams
entries in a stream dictionary cannot be used.</p>
    <p num="0320">As examples of constraints to contents, each page can
contain only image objects; they can be either external 
images (so-called "image "XObjects") or inline images.
The only commands allowed in a page "Contents" stream are:
<dl compact="compact" tsize="11"><dt>q, Q:</dt><dd>save and restore the graphics state;</dd><dt>cm:</dt><dd>modify the current transformation
matrix;</dd><dt>Do:</dt><dd>include an external object (so-called
"XObject") ― and images are the only
XObject types allowed;</dd><dt>BI, ID, EI:</dt><dd>inline images</dd></dl></p>
    <p num="0321">As examples of constraints to bounding boxes, each
page object must include a MediaBox and TrimBox; MediaBox
may be included by the object-oriented programming concept
known as "inheritance". A CropBox or BleedBox, or both,
may also be included in the page. If the BleedBox is
present, the TrimBox will not extend beyond the BleedBox
boundaries. If the CropBox is present, the TrimBox will
not extend beyond the boundaries of the CropBox.</p>
    <p num="0322">As examples of constraints to color, the only color
spaces allowed are DeviceCMYK and DeviceGray; all the
images (either inlined in the contents stream of pages or
in an image XObject) must be in DeviceCMYK, DeviceGray or
Indexed color space. If Indexed color is used, the base
color space should be DeviceGray or DeviceCMYK.</p>
    <p num="0323">Still as to PDF/Proof-Image constraints ― as examples
of restrictions on Identification, a PDF/Proof-Image
file is so identified using the HWEP_PDFProofVersion key
in the Info dictionary; the type of a HWEP_PDFproofVersion
key is string, and its value is (<u style="single">HWEPProofImage0.1</u>).</p>
    <p num="0324">Turning now to PDF/Proof-Object constraints, a
PDF/Proof-Object file must meet additional requirements, 
on top of the requirements described in the "<u style="single">PDF Reference
Manual, Version1.3</u>". As examples of data-structure restrictions,
all components of the proof contents must be
contained in the body of a single PDF/Proof-Object file ―
and this refers to all the PDF resources (as described under
"Resource Dictionaries" in the previously mentioned
<u style="single">PDF Manual</u>) used in the file including all fonts, font
metrics, font encodings, full resolution images, ICC
profiles etc.; and print elements must be included in the
file.</p>
    <p num="0325">As examples of content restrictions, operators not
allowed in the Contents stream for a page are PS (PostScript
code embedded in page contents); BX, EX
(compatibility operators); and in general any operator not
described in the <u style="single">PDF Manual</u>. Images cannot have the OPI
entry in the image dictionary set. If the Alternates
entry in the dictionary is set, none of the alternate
images can have the DefaultForPrinting entry set to <u style="single">true;</u>
that is, the base image is the one that must be used for
printing the proof.</p>
    <p num="0326">As examples of constraints to bounding boxes, the
same rules apply as stated above for PDF/Proof-Image. As
examples of constraints to color, a color rendering intent
must be specified for the contents for all pages;
rendering intent can be specified in the ExtGState
resource or in the Image dictionary for images. Color
space and Identification restrictions are generally as
stated above for PDF/Proof-Image.
<sl><li>(e) <u style="single">JDF contents</u> ― As suggested in earlier discussion,
a JDF job ticket is required to ensure that the
front end of the remote printing system processes the
proofing file with the correct settings, compatible with 
those used when printing the proof on the local file, in
order to ensure output consistency. Specification of the
"JDF Job Ticket" requirements for remote proofing are
based on the "<u style="single">JDF Specification Release 1.0</u>", with a few
variant details (names and permitted values of some
elements in the resource elements).</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0327">That specification covers two areas: processes allowed
in the remote-proofing JDF job ticket, and resources
(and their syntax) required for those processes. The specification
does not cover other areas in that job ticket,
such as customer-related information, or audit. Although
such information may appear in the job ticket it is not
required ― for purposes of this invention ― that
originating entities generate it or receiving entities
process it.</p>
    <p num="0328">The RHCPS is an implementation of the JDF proofing
process and inherits the characteristics of that process.
Extensions are added to support the specifics of the remote-proofing
use case and thermal-inkjet printing technology.
Also, due to limitations on printing devices and
to simplify implementation, just as for the PDF some restrictions
are desired on possible values and characteristics.
The JDF job ticket should have one node (the
root node) specifying the Proofing process.</p>
    <p num="0329">For examples of constraints as to resources, if the
ColorantControl, ColorPool, or ColorSpaceConversionParams
resources are present in the proofing-input resources they
are ignored in the proofing file; the color space used
(press CMYK) has to be fully defined using an ICC profile.
The Layout resource is required if the ProofType field in
the ProofingParams resource is set to Imposition (<u style="single">i. e.</u>
signature). </p>
    <p num="0330">As to constraints concerning media, since the JDF job
ticket is generated without knowing on which device or
devices the hardcopy proof will be printed, this resource
is only a hint. Behavior when the media available on the
proofing device fail to match the requirements in this resource
is device dependent. As examples of constraints on
interpretation of each of the fields in the Media
resource, Dimension is not required but if present
describes the minimum printing-medium dimension required
to print the proof. If the proof type is set to
Imposition, this is the size of the signature; if it is
instead set to Color, this is the size of the largest page
in the document.</p>
    <p num="0331">As examples of constraints to the ProofingParams resource,
ProofType is required and describes the type of
proof requested. ColorConceptual or Contone is used for
page proofs and Imposition of signature proofs. Halftone
proof types are not supported. Several parameters that
are just ignored if present include ImageViewingStrategy,
DisplayTraps, and ProoferProfile.</p>
    <p num="0332">The document RunList describes the document that is
to be proofed and includes a link to the document contents
file. In the initial version of the RHCPS that is the
current most highly preferred embodiment, proofing is restricted
to documents contained in a single PDF/Proof
file. In consequence there are some restrictions on the
characteristics of the document RunList.</p>
    <p num="0333">For example Npages, if defined, should be set to the
total number of pages in the document; and Run can only
contain one RunElement. Examples of constraints on the
RunElement include these: if EndOfDoc or DynamicInput is
present, the field contents are ignored. The RunElement
can contain only one RunSeparation. </p>
    <p num="0334">Yet further limits in turn apply to RunSeparation,
including its LayoutElement, and still further constraints
apply to contents of the LayoutElement. RunList "marks"
are not supported in the present version of the RHCPS. If
a proof must include printing marks, they should be
included in the page descriptions in the proofing file.</p>
    <p num="0335">For local proofs, the two components of the proofing
data are packaged using the MIME File Packaging method
descried in Appendix A of the "<u style="single">JDF Specification Release
1.0</u>". References to external files are allowed neither in
the job ticket nor the document contents.</p>
    <p num="0336">For remote proofs, the two components can be packaged
using the same MIME method. It is also possible that the
job ticket contains only a URL specifying the location of
the document contents portion of the proof data. Constraints
on URL type can be helpful.</p>
    <p num="0337">Again, the foregoing specification details are only
examples of some dozens of such restrictions actually
used. From the considerable length of this merely
exemplary presentation it will be clear why the full set
is not detailed here. Those presented are intended to
convey a clearer understanding of the reduced-parameter-set
approach to use of industry-standard PDF and JDF
formats.</p>
    <p num="0338">The above disclosure is intended as merely exemplary,
and not to limit the scope of the invention ― which is to
be determined by reference to the appended claims.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A remote proofing computer system comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a closed-loop-color remote hardcopy proofing service
"RHCPS", (11) that provides an RHCPS user interface (2-28)
having data (2, 7, 12 and 16-27) about a printing job to
be hardcopy-proofed (14, 15); and</claim-text><claim-text>a graphic-arts application service provider ("ASP",
21-25) that provides a remotely accessible ASP FTP site or
website having data about its service;</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the RHCPS interface comprises an RHCPS link
(13-15; 2, 7, 12 and 16-27) to the ASP data when an RHCPS
user (12) is also a user of the ASP.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The system of claim 1, wherein:
<claim-text><claim-text>the closed-loop-color RHCPS is based on a printer device
(14, 15) that prints and reads a calibration pattern,
and that returns a calibration report to a user who is in
a different location (12, 13, 21) from the printer device.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The system of claim 1, wherein:
<claim-text><claim-text>the RHCPS link to the ASP data appears only if the
ASP is an established copartner with the RHCPS.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The system of claim 1, wherein:
<claim-text><claim-text>for each user, the link to the ASP data comprises a
visible tabulation (2, 7, 12 and 16-27) of that user's
graphic-arts jobs with the ASP;</claim-text><claim-text>the tabulation comprises an active graphic-arts
dialog window for addition or modification (2, 7, 12 and
16-27) of that user's own graphic-arts jobs; and</claim-text></claim-text>
said modification in the graphic-arts dialog window
comprises an option of deleting that user's own graphic-arts
jobs.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The system of claim 4, wherein:
<claim-text><claim-text>the RHCPS maintains data linking each RHCPS user (12)
to each ASP (21-25) which has such a remotely accessible
FTP site or website, and with which that user is
registered;</claim-text><claim-text>for each user, the RHCPS interface link to the ASP
data appears only for an ASP with which that user is
registered; and</claim-text><claim-text>for each particular job that a user has associated
with an ASP, the RHCPS automatically routes proof reports
and related details to the user through that ASP rather
than to the user directly, unless the user specifically
instructs the RHCPS to the contrary.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The system of claim 1, wherein:
<claim-text><claim-text>the ASP's FTP site or website comprises a user interface
(2, 7, 12 and 16-27) with said data about the ASP
services;</claim-text><claim-text>the ASP interface comprises a link to the RHCPS interface
when an ASP user is also an RHCPS user;</claim-text><claim-text>in the ASP interface, the link to the RHCPS interface
appears only if the RHCPS is an established copartner with
the ASP;</claim-text><claim-text>for each user, the ASP interface link to the RHCPS
interface comprises a visible tabulation of that user's
jobs that are subject to remote hardcopy proofing;</claim-text><claim-text>the tabulation comprises an active remote-hardcopy-proofing
(RHCP) dialog window for addition or modification
of that user's own RHCP jobs; and</claim-text></claim-text>
said modification in the dialog window comprises an
option of deleting that user's own RHCP jobs.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>The system of claim 6, wherein:
<claim-text><claim-text>for each user, the RHCPS interface link to the ASP
data appears only for an ASP with which that user is
registered; and</claim-text><claim-text>for each particular job that a user has associated
with the RHCPS, the ASP automatically routes proofing jobs
from the user to the RHCPS rather than to another proofing
entity, unless the user specifically instructs the ASP to
the contrary.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The system of claim 1, wherein:
<claim-text><claim-text>the RHCPS user interface and the ASP's FTP site or
website are for operation by any user selected from the
group consisting of:
<claim-text><claim-text>a primary customer (12), including but not
limited to a publisher, printing customer,
or printing client,</claim-text><claim-text>a buyer representing a primary customer;</claim-text><claim-text>a graphic artist (21),</claim-text><claim-text>a printing broker (24), and</claim-text><claim-text>a user that is any hybrid of two or more of the
preceding four user types; and</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>the ASP is selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text><claim-text>a printing-brokerage ASP (24),</claim-text><claim-text>a soft-proofing ASP (22),</claim-text><claim-text>a private-network ASP (25), and</claim-text><claim-text>an ASP that is any hybrid of two or more of the
preceding three ASP types.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>The system of claim 8, wherein:
<claim-text><claim-text>the RHCPS link to the ASP data also comprises access
to further service of the ASP other than RHCPS procedures;
and</claim-text><claim-text>said further service comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>if the ASP is a printing-brokerage ASP (24) or
hybrid thereof, service relating
particularly to transactional matters,</claim-text><claim-text>if the ASP is a soft-proofing ASP (22) or hybrid
thereof, service relating particularly to
generation, checking or approval of a soft
proof, and</claim-text><claim-text>if the ASP is a private-network ASP (25) or hybrid
thereof, service relating particularly
to data transmission or storage.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>The system of claim 8, wherein:
<claim-text><claim-text>if an RHCPS user is not an established user of any
particular ASP, of any one type of said three ASP types or
a hybrid thereof, the RHCPS interface comprises an RHCPS
link to data of either:
<claim-text><claim-text>all ASPs which are established copartners with
the RHCPS; or</claim-text><claim-text>all ASPs of that one type or hybrid, which are
established copartners with the RHCPS.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>A computerized remote proofing method comprising the
steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>operation, by a user (12), of a closed-loop-color
remote hardcopy proofing service ("RHCPS", 11) user
interface (Figs. 2-28), to gain access to data about a
printing job to be hardcopy-proofed (14, 15); and</claim-text><claim-text>granting, by a graphic-arts application service provider
("ASP", 21-25), of access to data about the ASP's
service;</claim-text><claim-text>said granting being in response to the user's
activation of a link (Figs. 13-15; and lower half of Figs.
2, 7, 12 and 16-27), within the RHCPS interface, to a user
interface of the ASP;</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the RHCPS user is also a user of the ASP.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>The method of claim 11, wherein:
<claim-text><claim-text>the operating step comprises actions supporting preparation
of a remote closed-loop-color hardcopy proof, by a
printer device (14, 15) that prints and reads a
calibration pattern and returns a calibration report to an
entity in a different location from the printer device;</claim-text><claim-text>the granting step occurs only if the ASP is an
established copartner with the RHCPS; and</claim-text><claim-text>the granting step comprises presenting to the user a
visible tabulation (2, 7, 12 and 16-27) of that user's
graphic-arts jobs with the ASP.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>The method of claim 12, wherein:
<claim-text><claim-text>the presenting step comprises opening an active
graphic-arts dialog window for the user's addition or
modification of that user's own graphic-arts jobs; and</claim-text><claim-text>the opening step comprises permitting the user to
delete that user's own graphic-arts jobs, by means of the
dialog window; and</claim-text><claim-text>further comprising the step of maintenance, by the
RHCPS, of data linking each RHCPS user to each ASP with
which that user is registered.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>A method of operating a closed-loop color remote
hardcopy proofing service "RHCPS" (11); said method
comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>making available a computerized, network-based RHCPS
operated through at least one user interface (2-28);</claim-text><claim-text>for each project of the RHCPS, establishing functioning
computerized relationships among the RHCPS and
entities that include at least a primary customer (12) and
a printshop (13);</claim-text><claim-text>enabling the RHCPS or any of said entities to
initiate a project and thereby define default operating
conditions that determine which of said entities sees, in
the at least one user interface, each other one of the
entities respectively; and</claim-text><claim-text>regardless of which of the RHCPS or said entities
initiates the project and defines the default relationships,
reserving to at least one of said entities an
option of redefining operating conditions to override the
default conditions.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>The method of claim 14, wherein:
<claim-text><claim-text>said at least one of said entities comprises the primary
customer (12); and</claim-text><claim-text>further comprising the step of making available (28)
to the primary customer information about the option.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>The method of claim 15, wherein:
<claim-text><claim-text>the making-available step comprises including in an
RHCPS user interface seen by the primary customer a link
(Fig. 28) to terms of the RHCPS, which include the information
about the option.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>The method of claim 14, wherein:
<claim-text><claim-text>the reserving step comprises enabling the primary
customer to redefine which of the entities the primary
customer can see;</claim-text><claim-text>whereby the method stimulates competition while
tending to deter redundancy, among enterprises in the
printing industry.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
