<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1225393-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1225393" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="18871321" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020724">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1225393-A2" status="new" fvid="23523742">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1225393</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20020724</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02250112-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02250112</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020108</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001002890-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001002890</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010110</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23D  14/12        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23D  14/16        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23D  14/46        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23D  14/70        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F24C   3/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F24C   3/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F24C   3/06B</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Gasherd mit einer flachen Heizfläche</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Flat heating surface type gas stove</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Cuisinière à gaz du type à surface chauffante plane.</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TOKYO GAS CO LTD</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TOKYO GAS COMPANY LIMITED</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Tokyo Gas Company Limited</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>5-20 Kaigan 1-chome, Minato-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo 105-8527</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NAKAYAMA KIYOSHI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YAMADA YUTAKA</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NAKAYAMA, KIYOSHI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YAMADA, YUTAKA</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Nakayama, Kiyoshi, c/o Tokyo Gas Company Limited</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>5-20, Kaigan 1-chome, Minato-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo 105-8527</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Yamada, Yutaka, c/o Tokyo Gas Company Limited</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>5-20, Kaigan 1-chome, Minato-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo 105-8527</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Nicholls, Michael John</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>J.A. KEMP &amp;amp; CO. 14, South Square Gray's Inn</street>
              <city>London WC1R 5LX</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>There is disclosed a novel flat heating surface type gas stove which is capable
of heating a heating substance across a heat resistance glass at practically
applicable heating efficiency, overcoming any inconvenience resulting from the
exposure of flame and facilitating the cleaning of the gas stove. This gas stove
10 comprises a heat resistance glass top plate 12 which is disposed over a burner
15, wherein a gas-permeable porous body 40 is disposed below said top plate 12, and
a space between said top plate 12 and a surface of said gas-permeable porous body
40 is assigned to a combustion space S. Combustion gas generated is designed to be
discharged through said gas-permeable porous body 40. As high-temperature
combustion gas passes through said gas-permeable porous body 40, radiant heat B is
generated from the surface of said gas-permeable porous body 40. Since the heating
substance 4 is heated by both of heat conduction and radiation, high heating
efficiency can be achieved.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="76" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="85"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <heading>1. Field of the Invention</heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a gas stove which is adapted for cooking in
office or home, and in particular, to a flat heating surface type gas stove wherein
a heat-resisting glass top plate is used as a flat heating surface, thereby preventing
flame from being exposed out of the heating surface during the heating operation
thereof.</p>
    <heading>2. Description of the Related Art</heading>
    <p num="0002">The conventional gas stove is generally designed such that a heating substance
(i.e. substance to be heated) is directly heated by combustion gas (including flame)
that is generated by the combustion of gas. Specifically, as shown in FIG. 5, a
heating substance 4, such as a pot or a frying pan (skillet), which is supported by
means of a pan support 3 is placed over the combustion burner 2 that is exposed out
of the top plate 1 of the stove. In the case of a conventional stove of this type,
since the burner and the pan support are exposed, the stove is required to be
frequently cleaned, and at the same time, since the surface structure thereof is
rather complicated, it is difficult to completely sweep away soils from the surface
of stove. Additionally, since flame is exposed during heating, radiant heat is
transmitted directly to a person using the stove, thus occasionally imparting a
feeling of heat to the person. Therefore, the person using the stove is required
to pay some degree of attention to ensure safety in dealing with the stove.</p>
    <p num="0003">With a view to avoiding such an inconvenience, there has been proposed an
electric stove as shown in FIG. 6, which is constructed, as represented by an 1H stove,
a halogen stove or a radiant heat stove, such that the top plate 5 of stove is 
constituted by heat resistant glass such as ceramic glass, and that the heating
substance 4 is heated by means of electromagnetic wave (including visible light and
infrared ray) which is designed to pass through this glass top plate 5 as it is
generated from a heater 6.</p>
    <p num="0004">It is now studied for enabling the same heating method as employed in the
aforementioned electric stove to be realized in a gas stove where gas is employed
as a fuel. However, since only the visible light and infrared ray to be generated
through the combustion of gas can be utilized in heating a heating substance instead
of directly utilizing the combustion gas if the aforementioned method is adopted in
a gas stove, the heating efficiency of such a gas stove would greatly deteriorate
even if the gas stove is of an infrared burner type. Namely, it has been considered
very difficult in such a gas stove to improve the heating efficiency thereof to a
practically applicable level.</p>
    <p num="0005">The present invention has been accomplished under the circumstances explained
above, and therefore, an object of this invention is to provide a novel flat heating
surface type gas stove which is capable of heating a heating substance across a heat
resistance glass at such high heating efficiency that is applicable to practical use
in spite of the fact that the gas stove employs gas as a fuel, thus making it possible
to overcome any inconvenience that may be brought about due to the exposure of flame,
and to facilitate the cleaning of the gas stove.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0006">Namely, the gas stove according to the present invention is a flat heating
surface type gas stove, which fundamentally comprises a heat resistance glass top
plate which is disposed over a burner, wherein a gas-permeable porous body is disposed
below said top plate, a space between said top plate and a surface of said gas-permeable
porous body is assigned to a combustion space, and combustion gas to be
generated is designed to be discharged through said gas-permeable porous body.</p>
    <p num="0007">It is known that when a high-temperature gas is passed through a gas-permeable 
porous body, thermal energy is transferred from the high-temperature gas to the porous
body and is then radiated from the surface of the porous body ("The improvements on
the combustion and radiant heat in porous solid body", a collection of articles 52-475,
B-1136; Japan Society of Mechanical Engineers). By increasing the porosity of porous
body, or by employing a material of high emissivity as a porous body, the radiation
from the porous body can be increased, thus lowering the temperature of porous body
and rapidly lowering the temperature of gas. As a high-temperature gas is passed
through a gas-permeable porous body, even though the temperature of gas on the gas
inlet side of the porous body is high, the temperature of gas on the gas outlet side
of the porous body becomes low. Therefore, the radiation from the porous body can
be effected selectively on the high-temperature gas side, i.e. the upstream side of
gas.</p>
    <p num="0008">According to the present invention, the flat heating surface type gas stove which
is provided with a heat resistance glass top plate disposed over a burner is
technically featured in that the aforementioned phenomenon to be realized by the
gas-permeable porous body is effectively utilized. Therefore, it is now possible
to obtain a flat heating surface type gas stove which is capable of exhibiting such
high-heating efficiency that can be practically used in spite of the fact that the
gas stove employs gas as a fuel.</p>
    <p num="0009">Namely, in the case of the gas stove according to the present invention, the
combustion heat from the burner is transmitted to a heating substance by two ways,
i.e. by the energy of heat conduction originating directly from the heat resistant
glass top plate (flat heating surface) and by the radiation energy originating from
the surface of gas-permeable porous body, that can be generated as the combustion
gas of high-temperature produced inside the combustion chamber is permitted to pass
through the gas-permeable porous body which is disposed below the top plate, the
combustion gas entering the gas-permeable porous body from the top surface thereof
and discharged from the rear surface thereof. As a result, it is now possible, with
this gas stove, to realize high heating efficiency. </p>
    <p num="0010">Moreover, in the gas stove according to the present invention, since the surface
to support and heat a heating substance, such as a pot or a frying pan, is flat, the
cleaning can be easily performed even if this surface is soiled by boiled-over matter.
Additionally, since the combustion space of this gas stove is substantially closed
so that the flame of combustion gas is not permitted to expose out of the combustion
space, it is possible to ensure a high operational safety.</p>
    <p num="0011">As for the material of gas-permeable porous body which enables the
aforementioned combustion gas to pass therethrough, there is not any particular
limitation as long as it has a predetermined heat resistance. However, it is more
preferable that the material of gas-permeable porous body is capable of emitting a
higher radiation toward the upstream side as a high-temperature gas is passed
therethrough. Preferable examples of such a gas-permeable porous body are those
which are formed into a porous body by making use of silicon carbide exhibiting a
high emissivity (0.9 or more) or a material containing silicon carbide as a main
component. For example, an aggregate of silicon carbide fibers or ceramic filters
can be preferably employed as the material of gas-permeable porous body.</p>
    <p num="0012">The surface of gas-permeable porous body is heated up to almost the same
temperature as that of the combustion gas as the high-temperature combustion gas
passes through the gas-permeable porous body, thereby radiating thermal energy. In
the course of the passage of combustion gas across the gas-permeable porous body,
the temperature of combustion gas is lowered to become a low temperature gas, which
is then discharged out of the gas stove. Even this low temperature gas, the
temperature thereof is maintained generally at 600°C or so. Therefore, heat
radiation is caused to generate even on the gas outlet side, i.e. rear side of the
gas-permeable porous body, the heat radiation thus generated being directed toward
the exhaust side of the gas stove, thus resulting in a heat loss to the gas stove.</p>
    <p num="0013">With a view to minimize this heat loss, there is provided another embodiment
of gas-permeable porous body wherein a second gas-permeable porous body having a lower
emissivity than that of the first mentioned gas-permeable porous body is laminated 
on the gas outlet side of the first mentioned gas-permeable porous body. As for the
material of the second gas-permeable porous body also, there is not any particular
limitation as long as it has a predetermined heat resistance. However, it is more
preferable that the material of the second gas-permeable porous body is formed of
silica/alumina-based ceramic exhibiting an emissivity ranging from 0.2 to 0.3 or a
material containing as a main component such a silica/alumina-based ceramic. For
example, an aggregate of silica/alumina-based ceramic fiber can be preferably
employed. Alternatively, a ceramic filter exhibiting a relatively low emissivity
can be employed as the second gas-permeable porous body.</p>
    <p num="0014">According to the flat heating surface type gas stove of the present invention,
there is not any particular limitation with regard to the burner to be employed therein.
For example, the burner may be a pipe burner which is disposed to surround a region
immediately above the gas-permeable porous body or a surface combustion type burner.
In the case of the former burner, the flame ports thereof are preferably disposed
in such a manner that the flame from each flame port can be horizontally ejected in
the direction toward the center of the region immediately above the gas-permeable
porous body. If a sufficient combustion of gas can be achieved with only a primary
air, the arrangement of the burner may be such as mentioned above. Generally however,
when it is desired to achieve a desired combustion of gas with only a primary air,
the blow-off of flame or the generation of unburnt gas is caused to occur. In order
to prevent such phenomena, the burner should preferably be designed such that a
secondary combustion air can be supplied from the vicinity of each of the flame ports.
In any cases, it is preferable to provide the burner with a suitable flame stabilizing
mechanism.</p>
    <p num="0015">In a structure where a surface combustion burner is employed, the combustion
surface thereof, together with the surface of gas-permeable porous body, is disposed
so as to face the combustion space. As a result, the combustion heat of the surface
combustion burner can be effectively conducted to the flat heating surface
constituted by the heat resistant glass top plate. Preferably, the combustion 
surface of the surface combustion burner should be formed of a material exhibiting
a high emissivity, such as silicon carbide or a material containing silicon carbide
as a main component. In this case, in addition to the heating by way of heat
conduction, the heating by way of radiation energy can be proceeded, thereby making
it possible to realize high heating efficiency by the surface combustion burner.</p>
    <p num="0016">If the surface combustion burner is to be employed, the combustion surface
thereof may be disposed on the periphery of the surface of the gas-permeable porous
body, or the gas-permeable porous body may be disposed on the periphery of the
combustion surface of the surface combustion burner. In any cases, a high-temperature
combustion gas from the surface combustion burner is permitted to be
discharged through the gas-permeable porous body, during which the gas--permeable
porous body is heated to a red heat state, thus radiating thermal energy.</p>
    <p num="0017">According to another embodiment of the gas stove of the present invention, the
gas stove essentially comprises a combustion gas passageway communicated with a space
located on a downstream side of combustion gas flow channel of gas-permeable porous
body; an air passageway for combustion, and a heat-exchanging means to be acted
between the combustion gas passageway and the air passageway for combustion, wherein
a mixed gas comprising a combustion gas and combustion air which has been heated
through heat exchange thereof with the combustion gas by means of heat-exchanging
means is designed to be fed to a burner. In the case of gas stove of this embodiment,
the quantity of heat retained in the combustion gas after the passage thereof through
the gas-permeable porous body is transferred via the heat-exchanging means to the
combustion air to thereby perform exhaust heat recovery. As a result, the air thus
heated up and the combustion gas is enabled to be mixed together to form a mixed gas,
which is then transferred to the burner for the combustion thereof, resulting in
improved heating efficiency as a whole.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE SEVERAL VIEWS OF THE DRAWING</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0018">
      <sl>
        <li>FIG. 1 is a cross-sectional view illustrating one embodiment of the flat heating 
surface type gas stove of the present invention;</li>
        <li>FIG. 2 is a cross-sectional view illustrating another embodiment of the flat
heating surface type gas stove of the present invention;</li>
        <li>FIG. 3 is a cross-sectional view illustrating a further embodiment of the flat
heating surface type gas stove of the present invention;</li>
        <li>FIG. 4 is a cross-sectional view illustrating still another embodiment of the
flat heating surface type gas stove of the present invention;</li>
        <li>FIG. 5 is a side view schematically illustrating one example of conventional
gas stove; and</li>
        <li>FIG. 6 is a side view schematically illustrating one example of conventional
radiation type stove where an electric heater is disposed.</li>
      </sl>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0019">Next, the flat heating surface type gas stove according to this invention will
be explained with reference to specific embodiments.</p>
    <p num="0020">FIG. 1 shows a cross-sectional view of one embodiment of the flat heating surface
type gas stove according to this invention. The gas stove 10 shown in FIG. 1 is of
a closed type wherein the open top face of an outer casing 11 having a cylindrical
configuration is closed by a flat heat resistant glass top plate. A ring-like pipe
burner 15 is disposed along an upper inner wall portion of the outer casing 11. The
pipe burner 15 is provided with a plurality of flame ports 16 which are disposed at
predetermined intervals in such a manner that each flame port 16 is directed so as
to enable the flame to be ejected horizontally toward the center of the outer casing
11. The pipe burner 15 is also provided with a suitable number of vertical pipes
17, the lower ends of which are respectively directed toward the bottom face 13 of
the outer casing 11. Further, each of the vertical pipes 17 is provided, at the lower
end thereof, with an opening with which a gas nozzle 20 is engaged. Moreover, the
bottom face 13 of the outer casing 11 is connected with the outlet 22 of an air blower
21. </p>
    <p num="0021">A cylindrical inner casing 31 having an open top and closed bottom 32 is disposed
so as to cover the inner peripheral wall of the pipe burner 15. The cylindrical inner
casing 31 is provided, at the portions each facing each flame port 16 of the pipe
burner 15, with flame supply ports 33. A gas-permeable porous body 40 having a flat
board-like configuration and made of an aggregate of silicon carbide fiber is disposed
at a level of the inner casing 31 which is somewhat below where the flame supply ports
33 are disposed. A substantially closed space S is formed between the gas-permeable
porous body 40 and the top plate 12. A metallic rectifying plate 42 provided with
a large number of holes 41 is disposed below the gas-permeable porous body 40.
Further, an exhaust pipe 43 is disposed below the rectifying plate 42 in such a way
that the exhaust pipe 43 is pierced through the peripheral wall of the inner casing
31.</p>
    <p num="0022">The top plate 12 functions as a heating surface so that a heating substance 4
such as a pot or a frying pan is permitted to be directly placed thereon. The heat
resistant glass to be employed as the top plate 12 may be any kind of materials which
are conventionally known. However, a heat resistant glass imparted with a fine
quartz crystalline structure and almost the same degree of thermal expansion
coefficient as that of quartz, is especially preferable. Since the thermal expansion
coefficient of such a heat resistant glass is relatively low, there is little
possibility that the glass can be cracked even if the glass is quenched under a high
temperature state thereof as it is heated by a burner. Although the gas-permeable
porous body 40 is constituted by a single-layer structure of the aggregate of silicon
carbide fiber in the embodiment shown in FIG. 1, the gas-permeable porous body 40
may be constituted by a 2-ply structure consisting of an upper layer formed of the
aggregate of silicon carbide fiber, and a lower layer formed of the aggregate of
silica/alumina-based ceramic fiber which is lower in emissivity than the silicon
carbide fiber. This 2-ply structure is advantageous in improving the heating
efficiency of gas stove.</p>
    <p num="0023">On the occasion of combustion operation of gas stove, a predetermined quantity 
of fuel gas is fed from the gas nozzle 20 with the air blower 21 being actuated. The
air supplied by this air blower 21 to a space between the outer casing 11 and the
inner casing 31 is permitted to flow into the vertical pipe 17 so as to be mixed with
fuel gas to form a mixed gas, which is then ejected from the flame ports 16 of the
pipe burner 15 to form a flame. This flame is then permitted to pass through the
flame supply ports 33 provided in the inner casing 31 and to spread throughout the
combustion space S. Part of the air that has been supplied by the air blower 21 is
permitted to enter into the combustion space S together with the flame ejected from
the flame supply ports 33 of the inner casing 31 so as to assist the secondary
combustion of flame. As a result, the complete combustion of the mixed gas can be
promoted. The combustion heat produced by the combustion gas is thermally conducted
from the top plate 12 to the heating substance 4 to thereby heat the heating substance
4.</p>
    <p num="0024">The temperature of the combustion gas generally exceeds over 1000°C. As shown
by the arrows "A" in FIG. 1, this high-temperature combustion gas is permitted to
pass through the gas-permeable porous body 40 and the rectifying plate 42 before it
is discharged from the exhaust pipe 43. As this high-temperature combustion gas is
permitted to pass through the gas-permeable porous body 40, the top surface (the
surface facing the top plate 12) of the gas-permeable porous body 40 is heated up
to almost the same temperature as that of the combustion gas. As a result, thermal
energy is radiated from the surface of the gas-permeable porous body 40 toward the
top plate 12 (as shown by the arrows "B"), thereby providing this radiation energy,
through the top plate 12, to the heating substance 4 in addition to the heating by
way of the aforementioned conduction of heat.</p>
    <p num="0025">Namely, in the case of gas stove 10 according to the present invention, the
combustion heat from the burner is transmitted to a heating substance 4 in two ways,
i. e. by heat conduction originating directly from the heat resistant glass top plate
12 and by radiant heat produced from the surface of gas-permeable porous body 40 as
high-temperature combustion gas passes through the gas-permeable porous body 40 which 
is disposed below the top plate 12. As a result, it is now possible, even with this
type of gas stove where the flame is not permitted to expose outside, to realize such
high heating efficiency that is sufficiently suited for practical use. It has been
confirmed, through the experiments conducted by the present inventors, that the gas
stove constructed as described in the above embodiment is capable of achieving heating
efficiency which is comparable to that of the conventional gas stove as shown in FIG.
5 under the same condition with respect to the input.</p>
    <p num="0026">By the way, the gas stove 10 of the above embodiment is provided with the
rectifying plate 42, so that the combustion gas is prevented from generating a drift
current in the course wherein the combustion gas is transferred from the combustion
space S via the gas-permeable porous body 40 to the exhaust pipe 43. However, this
rectifying plate 42 may not be essential and can be omitted, provided that the drift
current of the combustion gas can be confined within a tolerable degree through the
adjustment of the mounting position or configuration of the exhaust pipe 43.</p>
    <p num="0027">Further, in the above embodiment, although air for secondary combustion is
utilized in the combustion of burner, the mechanism for introducing the air for
secondary combustion may be omitted, provided that the complete combustion of gas
without substantial unburnt gas can be achieved by making use of only the primary
air and by providing the gas stove with a suitable means such as a flame stabilizing
mechanism which is conventionally known. In that case, the structure of the gas stove
can be more simplified. The outer casing 11 and the inner casing 31 may not be
circular in horizontal cross-sectional configuration thereof, and hence may be
rectangular in horizontal cross-sectional configuration thereof. In that case, the
pipe burner may be constructed such that it is configured so as to be installed
entirely along the inner peripheral wall or to be installed only at a couple of longer
sidewalls facing each other.</p>
    <p num="0028">FIG. 2 shows a cross-sectional view of another embodiment of the flat heating
surface type gas stove according to this invention. The gas stove 10A shown in FIG.
2 differs from that shown in FIG. 1 in the respect that the burner is constituted 
by a surface combustion burner. Namely, the gas stove 10A shown in FIG. 2 is the
same as that shown in FIG. 1 in the respect that the open top face of an outer casing
11 having a cylindrical configuration is closed by a flat heat resistant glass top
plate 12. However, the gas stove 10A is featured in that an inner casing wall 31A
is coaxially disposed inside the outer casing 11 in such a manner that the
circumferential top end of the inner casing wall 31A is not contacted with the top
plate 12, and that a ring-shaped combustion face-forming body 50 is horizontally
interposed between the outer peripheral wall of the inner casing wall 31A and the
inner peripheral wall of the outer casing 11. Further, the outlet 22 of an air blower
21 is connected with the peripheral wall of the outer casing 11, and the gas nozzle
20 is disposed on an upstream side of the outlet 22.</p>
    <p num="0029">The combustion face-forming body 50 may be selected from any kinds of combustion
face-forming body that have been employed in the conventional surface combustion
burner. In this embodiment however, a material exhibiting a high emissivity, such
as an aggregate of silicon carbide fibers (the emissivity thereof is 0.9 or more)
is employed.</p>
    <p num="0030">As shown in FIG. 2, on the top end of the inner casing wall 31A, there is mounted
a disc-shaped gas-permeable porous body 40 which is located preferably at the same
level as that of the combustion face-forming body 50. Although it is not essential,
a ring-shaped metallic rectifying plate 52 provided with a large number of holes 51
is disposed below the combustion face-forming body 50, and additionally, a disc-shaped
metallic rectifying plate 42 provided with a large number of holes 41 is
disposed below the gas-permeable porous body 40. Moreover, an exhaust hole 43A is
formed at a region of the bottom 13 of the outer casing 11, which is encircled by
the inner casing wall 31A.</p>
    <p num="0031">In the case of this gas stove 10A, the substantially closed space formed between
the gas-permeable porous body 40 and the combustion face-forming body 50 functions
as a combustion space S. Namely, on the occasion of combustion operation, when the
air blower 21 is actuated and a predetermined quantity of fuel gas is supplied from 
the gas nozzle 20, the mixed gas consisting of the fuel gas and combustion air is
permitted to enter into a space between the outer casing 11 and the inner casing wall
31A, and is stirred and mixed by means of the rectifying plate 52 to form a homogeneous
gas mixture, which is then passed through the combustion face-forming body 50 and
ejected therefrom so as to be ignited and burnt by a suitable means.</p>
    <p num="0032">The combustion heat produced by the combustion gas is thermally conducted from
the top plate 12 to the heating substance 4 to thereby heat the heating substance
4. Additionally, since the combustion face-forming body 50 is formed of an
aggregation of silicon carbide fiber exhibiting an excellent emissivity, the heating
substance 4 is also heated by the radiation energy (indicated by the arrows "C")
originating from the surface of the combustion face-forming body 50, thereby making
it possible to achieve high heating efficiency. Moreover, as in the case of the gas
stove shown in FIG. 1, this high-temperature combustion gas is permitted to pass
through the gas-permeable porous body 40 and the rectifying plate 42 before it is
discharged from the exhaust hole 43A. During this process, thermal energy is
radiated also from the surface of the gas-permeable porous body 40 toward the top
plate 12 (as shown by the arrows "B"), thereby further enhancing the heating
efficiency.</p>
    <p num="0033">FIG. 3 shows a cross-sectional view of another embodiment of the flat heating
surface type gas stove according to this invention. The gas stove 10B shown in FIG.
3 differs, just like the gas stove 10A shown in FIG. 2, from the gas stove 10 shown
in FIG. 1 in the respect that the burner is constituted by a surface combustion burner.
Furthermore, while the gas stove 10A shown in FIG. 2 is featured in that the combustion
face of surface combustion burner (the combustion face-forming body 50) is disposed
on the outer peripheral side of the gas-permeable porous body 40, the gas stove 10B
shown in FIG. 3 is featured in that the gas-permeable porous body 40 is disposed on
the outer peripheral side of the combustion face of surface combustion burner (the
combustion face-forming body 50). Therefore, the outlet 22 of an air blower 21 is
connected with a region of the bottom 13 of the outer casing 11, which is encircled 
by the inner casing wall 31A, and an exhaust hole 33A is formed in the peripheral
wall of the outer casing 11.</p>
    <p num="0034">The manner of heating to the heating substance 4 on the occasion of combustion
operation is substantially the same as in the case of the gas stove 10A shown in FIG.
2, so that the details thereof will be omitted by denoting the corresponding
components or members by the corresponding reference numbers.</p>
    <p num="0035">FIG. 4 shows a cross-sectional view of a further embodiment of the flat heating
surface type gas stove according to this invention. The gas stove 10C shown in FIG.
4 differs from the gas stove 10B shown in FIG. 3 in the respect that a heat exchange
is executed between the air being supplied for combustion and the combustion gas being
discharged. In other respects, the constitution of gas stove 10C is substantially
the same as that of gas stove 10B shown in FIG. 3, so that the details thereof will
be omitted by denoting the corresponding components or members by the corresponding
reference numbers.</p>
    <p num="0036">The gas stove 10C shown in FIG. 4 comprises a combustion gas passageway 62 which
is communicated with a combustion gas flow channel 61 constituting a downstream side
space of the gas-permeable porous body 40. This combustion gas passageway 62 is
disposed so as to pass, via a partition wall 64, through the interior of a combustion
air passageway 63 which is connected with the air blower 21. According to the gas
stove 10C of this embodiment, the quantity of heat retained in the combustion gas
after the passage thereof through the gas-permeable porous body 40 is transferred
via the partition wall 64 functioning as heat-exchanging means to the combustion air
flowing inside the combustion air passageway 63 while the combustion gas passes
through the combustion gas passageway 62 to thereby perform exhaust heat recovery.
As a result, a mixed gas consisting of the air thus heated up and the fuel gas is
enabled to be transferred to the surface combustion burner for the combustion thereof,
resulting in further improved heating efficiency as a whole.</p>
    <p num="0037">By the way, the aforementioned means for performing the heat exchange between
the combustion gas and the combustion air to thereby execute the exhaust heat recovery 
can be applied as it is not only to the gas stove 10B which is provided with the surface
combustion burner as shown in FIG. 2, but also to the gas stove 10 which is provided
with the pipe burner as shown in FIG. 1.</p>
    <p num="0038">According to the present invention, it is possible to provide a novel flat
heating surface type gas stove which is capable of heating a heating substance across
a heat resistance glass at high heating efficiency sufficient for practical use in
spite of the fact that the gas stove employs gas as a fuel, thus making it possible
to overcome any inconvenience that may be brought about due to the exposure of flame,
and to facilitate the cleaning of the gas stove.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A flat heating surface type gas stove comprising;
<claim-text><claim-text>a heat resistance glass top plate which is disposed over a burner;</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein a gas-permeable porous body is disposed below said top plate, a space
between said top plate and a surface of said gas-permeable porous body is assigned
to a combustion space, and combustion gas to be generated is designed to be discharged
through said gas-permeable porous body.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The flat heating surface type gas stove according to claim 1, wherein said
gas-permeable porous body is formed of silicon carbide or a material containing
silicon carbide as a main component.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The flat heating surface type gas stove according to claim 1 or 2, wherein a second
gas-permeable porous body having a lower emissivity than that of the first mentioned
gas-permeable porous body is laminated on a gas outlet side of the first mentioned
gas-permeable porous body.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The flat heating surface type gas stove according to claim 3, wherein said second
gas-permeable porous body is formed of silica/alumina-based ceramic or a material
containing said ceramic as a main component.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The flat heating surface type gas stove according to any one of claims 1 to 4,
wherein said burner is disposed around said gas-permeable porous body.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The flat heating surface type gas stove according to any one of claims 1 to 5,
wherein said burner is a surface combustion burner, and a combustion surface thereof,
together with the surface of said gas-permeable porous body, is disposed to face said
combustion space.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>The flat heating surface type gas stove according to claim 6, wherein the
combustion surface of said surface combustion burner is formed of silicon carbide
or a material containing silicon carbide as a main component.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The flat heating surface type gas stove according to claim 6 or 7, wherein the
combustion surface of said surface combustion burner is placed on the outer peripheral
side of the surface of said gas-permeable porous body.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>The flat heating surface type gas stove according to claim 6 or 7, wherein the
surface of said gas-permeable porous body is placed on the outer peripheral side of
the combustion surface of said surface combustion burner.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>The flat heating surface type gas stove according to any one of claims 1 to 9,
wherein said gas stove further comprises a combustion gas passageway communicated
with a space located on a downstream side of combustion gas flow channel of gas-permeable
porous body; an air passageway for combustion; and a heat-exchanging means
acting between the combustion gas passageway and the air passageway for combustion;
   wherein a mixed gas comprising a combustion gas and combustion air, which has
been heated through heat exchange thereof with the combustion gas by means of said
heat-exchanging means is designed to be fed to said burner.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
