<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1237200-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1237200" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="18915205" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020904">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1237200-A2" status="new" fvid="23539866">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1237200</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20020904</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02004311-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02004311</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020228</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001054945-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001054945</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010228</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01L  21/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01L  21/331       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01L  21/336       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01L  29/66        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01L  29/739       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01L  29/78        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H01L  21/331G2</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H01L  21/331G2R</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H01L  29/739C2B2</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Hochspannungshalbleiteranordnung und Verfahren zur Herstellung</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">High voltage semiconductor device and method for manufacturing the same</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Dispositif semi-conducteur à haute tension et procédé pour sa fabrication</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TOKYO SHIBAURA ELECTRIC CO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KABUSHIKI KAISHA TOSHIBA</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Kabushiki Kaisha Toshiba</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1-1, Shibaura 1-chome, Minato-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MATSUDAI TOMOKO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NAKAGAWA AKIO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MATSUDAI, TOMOKO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NAKAGAWA, AKIO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Matsudai, Tomoko, Intell.Prop.Div., K.K. Toshiba</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1-1, Shibaura 1-chome, Minato-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo 105-8001</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Nakagawa, Akio, Intell.Prop.Div., K.K. Toshiba</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1-1, Shibaura 1-chome, Minato-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo 105-8001</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>HOFFMANN - EITLE</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Patent- und Rechtsanwälte Arabellastrasse 4</street>
              <city>81925 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>In an IGBT, an n buffer layer (23) is formed under
an n<sup>-</sup> high resistance layer (21) in which a MOS gate
structure is formed. An n<sup>+</sup> buffer layer (31) is formed
between the n buffer layer (23) and a p<sup>+</sup> drain layer
(22). Since the p<sup>+</sup> drain layer (22) is doped at a low
dose, the efficiency of carrier injection can be
reduced and a high-speed operation is possible without
lifetime control. Since no lifetime control is
performed, the on-state voltage can be low. Since the
n buffer layer (23) does not immediately stop the
extension of the depletion layer during a turn-off
period, oscillation of the current and voltage is
prevented. The n<sup>+</sup> buffer layer (31) maintains a
sufficient withstand voltage when a reverse bias is
applied.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="117" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="108"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a semiconductor
device which withstands a high voltage, for example, an
IGBT (Insulating Gate Bipolar Transistor).</p>
    <p num="0002">FIG. 18A shows a conventional vertical IGBT of
a punch-through type. In the IGBT 10, an n<sup>+</sup>-type
buffer layer (hereinafter referred to as the n<sup>+</sup> buffer
layer) 12 and an n<sup>-</sup>-type high resistance layer
(hereinafter referred to as the n<sup>-</sup> high resistance
layer) 13 are formed by epitaxial growth on a p<sup>+</sup>
substrate 11. A p-type base layer 14 is formed in
a surface region of the n<sup>-</sup> high resistance layer 13.
An n<sup>+</sup> source region (cathode) 15 is formed in a surface
region of the base layer 14. A trench-type gate
electrode 16 is formed in the source region 15, the
base layer 14 and the n<sup>-</sup> high resistance layer 13.
The gate electrode 16 is insulated from the source
region 15, the base layer 14 and the n<sup>-</sup> high resistance
layer 13 by a gate insulating film 17.</p>
    <p num="0003">The IGBT 10 is produced with, for example,
an epitaxial substrate, on which an epitaxial layer
is formed in advance. However, the epitaxial substrate
is disadvantageous in that the cost for manufacturing
an element is high since the wafer is expensive.</p>
    <p num="0004">Further, in the aforementioned IGBT 10, the
substrate 11, which is relatively thick, is used as
a p<sup>+</sup> drain layer (anode). Therefore, to lower 
the carrier injection efficiency, it is necessary to
control the lifetime. Typically, a process for
shortening the lifetime of 5-10 µs to about 100 ns
is performed. As a result, a high-speed turn-off
characteristic can be obtained, although the process
has a drawback that the on-state voltage rises. This
is because the carrier density in the n<sup>-</sup> high
resistance layer 13 is lowered by shortening the
lifetime.</p>
    <p num="0005">On the other hand, the on-state voltage can be
lower if the lifetime is not shortened. However, in
this case, the turn-off time will be considerably long.
Thus, there is a tradeoff relationship between the on-state
voltage and the turn-off time.</p>
    <p num="0006">Further, a depletion layer extends from the base
layer 14 due to a voltage applied to the element when
the current is turned off. When the depletion layer
reaches the n<sup>+</sup> buffer layer 12, it is immediately
stopped. For this reason, the drain current is
instantaneously dropped to zero, so that the drain
voltage oscillates, resulting in generation of noise.</p>
    <p num="0007">FIG. 18B shows another conventional IGBT, in which
the characteristic of the element described above is
improved. The IGBT 20 shown in FIG. 18B has a p<sup>+</sup> anode
structure injected with a small amount of impurities at
a low dose, which is adopted in a non-punch-through
IGBT. Therefore, the operation speed can be increased
without controlling the lifetime. The IGBT 20
comprises an n-type buffer layer (hereinafter referred
to as the n buffer layer) 23 formed between the n<sup>-</sup> high
resistance layer 21 and the p<sup>+</sup> drain layer (anode) 22.
The n buffer layer 23 maintains the static breakdown
voltage.</p>
    <p num="0008">In this structure, the drain layer 22 must be
injected with impurities at a low dose but have such a
high concentration in the surface portion thereof that
can establish ohmic contact. Therefore, the region 
where the impurities injected to form the drain layer
22 are diffused must be limited to a very shallow
depth. The total thickness of the IGBT is equal to the
thickness of the n<sup>-</sup> high resistance layer 21, which is
determined in accordance with the static breakdown
voltage, plus the thickness of the n buffer layer 23
and the p<sup>+</sup> drain layer 22. More specifically, in the
case of an element of the 600V voltage series, the
total thickness is as small as about 60 µm.</p>
    <p num="0009">Thus, the element is very thin. Therefore, for
example, when the element is lapped, if the thickness
is thinner or thicker than the design value by several
microns, the thickness of the buffer layer 23 is
varied. The variation in thickness of the buffer layer
23 is reflected on a variation in dose into the buffer
layer 23, with the result that the characteristics of
the element are considerably influenced. Therefore,
when the element is manufactured, it is necessary to
finish the element to the designed thickness with
a minimum error. However, according to the current
lapping technique, the lapping error is ± 5 to 10 µm,
which is significantly large relative to the overall
thickness of 60 µm.</p>
    <p num="0010">As described above, in the conventional vertical
IGBTs, there is a tradeoff relationship between the
on-state voltage and the turn-off time. Therefore, in
the IGBT of the punch-through type using a thick p<sup>+</sup>
substrate as a p<sup>+</sup> anode, since lifetime control is
inevitable, there is a limit to reduction in ON
characteristic. In the IGBT of the non-punch-through
type in which the static breakdown voltage is
maintained by the n buffer layer 23 formed between the
p<sup>+</sup> drain layer 22 and the n<sup>-</sup> high resistance layer 21,
the element must be very thin. However, this type of
IGBT is disadvantageous in that the lapping error is
large and the element characteristic is varied
considerably. Therefore, there is a demand for 
a semiconductor device which has an element having
required turn-off time and ON characteristic using a
thin substrate and which can suppress the influence of
the lapping error on the element characteristic.</p>
    <p num="0011">According to an aspect of the present invention,
there is provided a semiconductor device comprising:
<sl><li>a first buffer layer of a first conductivity type;
a high resistance layer of the first conductivity type
formed on the first buffer layer; a base layer of a
second conductivity type formed on the high resistance
layer; a source region of the first conductivity type
in a surface region of the base layer; a gate electrode
insulated from the source region, the base layer and
the high resistance layer; a drain layer of the second
conductivity type formed on an opposite side of the
first buffer layer from a surface on which the high
resistance layer is formed; and a second buffer layer
of the first conductivity type formed between the
first buffer layer and the drain layer, an impurity
concentration of the second buffer layer being higher
than that of the first buffer layer.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0012">According to another aspect of the present
invention, there is provided a method for manufacturing
a semiconductor device comprising: forming a high
resistance layer of a first conductivity type on a
main surface of a first buffer layer of the first
conductivity type, an impurity concentration of the
high resistance layer being lower than that of the
first buffer layer; forming a base layer of a second
conductivity type in a surface region of the high
resistance layer; forming a source region of the first
conductivity type in a surface region of the base
layer; forming a gate electrode insulated from the
source region, the base layer and the high resistance
layer; lapping a rear surface of the first buffer
layer; injecting impurities through the rear surface of
the first buffer layer, thereby forming a second buffer 
layer of the first conductivity type, an impurity
concentration of the second buffer layer being higher
than that of the first buffer layer; and forming a
drain layer of the second conductivity type on a rear
surface of the second buffer layer.</p>
    <p num="0013">This summary of the invention does not necessarily
describe all necessary features so that the invention
may also be a sub-combination of these described
features.</p>
    <p num="0014">The invention can be more fully understood from
the following detailed description when taken in
conjunction with the accompanying drawings, in which:
<sl><li>FIG. 1 is a cross-sectional view of a semiconductor
device according to a first embodiment of the
present invention;</li><li>FIG. 2 is a diagram showing a turn-off characteristic
of the semiconductor device shown in FIG. 1;</li><li>FIG. 3 is a diagram showing an impurity
concentration profile of the semiconductor device shown
in FIG. 1;</li><li>FIG. 4 is a diagram showing an impurity concentration
profile of the semiconductor device shown in
FIG. 1, in a case where an OSL (One Side Lap) wafer is
used;</li><li>FIGS. 5A to 5C are cross-sectionals views showing
a first method for manufacturing a semiconductor device
of the present invention;</li><li>FIG. 6 is a cross-sectional view showing a step
subsequent to the step shown in FIG. 5C;</li><li>FIGS. 7A to 7C are cross-sectionals views showing
a second method for manufacturing a semiconductor
device of the present invention;</li><li>FIGS. 8A to 8D are cross-sectionals views showing
a third method for manufacturing a semiconductor device
of the present invention;</li><li>FIGS. 9A to 9D are cross-sectional views showing
steps subsequent to the step shown in FIG. 8D; </li><li>FIGS. 10A to 10D are cross-sectional views showing
a fourth method for manufacturing a semiconductor
device of the present invention;</li><li>FIGS. 11A to 11D are cross-sectional views showing
steps subsequent to the step shown in FIG. 10D;</li><li>FIGS. 12A to 12D are cross-sectionals views
showing a fifth method for manufacturing a semiconductor
device of the present invention;</li><li>FIGS. 13A to 13C are cross-sectional views showing
steps subsequent to the step shown in FIG. 12D;</li><li>FIGS. 14A to 14D are cross-sectionals views
showing a sixth method for manufacturing a semiconductor
device of the present invention;</li><li>FIGS. 15A and 15B are cross-sectional views
showing steps subsequent to the step shown in FIG. 14D;</li><li>FIGS. 16A and 16B are cross-sectional views
showing a seventh method for manufacturing a semiconductor
device of the present invention;</li><li>FIGS. 17A to 17D are cross-sectional views showing
steps subsequent to the step shown in FIG. 16B; and</li><li>FIGS. 18A and 18B are cross-sectional views
showing conventional semiconductor devices.</li></sl> </p>
    <p num="0015">Embodiments of the present invention will now be
described with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
    <heading>(First Embodiment)</heading>
    <p num="0016">FIG. 1 is a cross sectional view of a vertical
IGBT, which uses a thin layer substrate, according to a
first embodiment of the present invention. In FIG. 1,
the same parts as those shown in FIGS. 18A and 18B are
identified by the same reference numerals as those used
in FIGS. 18A and 18B.</p>
    <p num="0017">As shown in FIG. 1, the IGBT of the first
embodiment has a p<sup>+</sup> drain layer (anode) 22 injected
with a small amount of impurities, which is employed in
a non-punch-through element. It also comprises an n<sup>+</sup>
buffer layer 31 formed between the p<sup>+</sup> drain layer 22
and an n buffer layer 23. The impurity concentration 
of the n<sup>+</sup> buffer layer 31 is higher than that of the
n buffer layer 23.</p>
    <p num="0018">The n buffer layer 23 has an impurity concentration
as low as, for example, about 3×10<sup>14</sup> cm<sup>-3</sup> and a
thickness of, for example, 30 µm. The p<sup>+</sup> drain layer
22 has a surface concentration of about 3×10<sup>18</sup> cm<sup>-3</sup>
with a low concentration and a thickness of, for
example, 0.3 µm. In this case, the total amount of
the impurity in the drain layer 22 is 9×10<sup>13</sup> cm<sup>-2</sup>. In
general, it is preferable that the total amount of the
impurity in the drain layer 22 be 1×10<sup>15</sup> cm<sup>-2</sup> or less.</p>
    <p num="0019">The n<sup>+</sup> buffer layer 31 has an impurity concentration
of, for example, 1×10<sup>18</sup> cm<sup>-3</sup> and a thickness of,
for example, 0.5 µm or more and 3 µm or less,
preferably, for example, 1.5 µm.</p>
    <p num="0020">A source electrode 41 is connected to the base
layer and a source region. A drain electrode 42 is
connected to the p<sup>+</sup> drain layer 22.</p>
    <p num="0021">The above IGBT adopts the p<sup>+</sup> drain layer 22
injected with a small amount of impurities. Therefore,
the efficiency of injecting carriers from the anode can
be reduced, with the result that the switching speed
can be increased without controlling the lifetime.</p>
    <p num="0022">In addition, the carrier density of the n<sup>-</sup> high
resistance layer 21 can be increased without
controlling the lifetime. Therefore, the voltage drop
in the ON time can be about 1.2 V, which is much lower
as compared to that in the conventional IGBT.</p>
    <p num="0023">Thus, the structure of the first embodiment can
improve the trade-off relationship between the increase
in switching speed and the decrease in ON voltage.</p>
    <p num="0024">Further, since the n<sup>+</sup> buffer layer 23 of a low
impurity concentration is present under the n<sup>-</sup> high
resistance layer 21, the depletion layer extending from
the base layer 14 is not immediately stopped during
a turn-off period. Therefore, as shown in FIG. 2,
the drain current density is reduced gradually in the 
turn-off period. Consequently, oscillation of the
drain current or the drain voltage is prevented.</p>
    <p num="0025">If only the n buffer layer 23 is used, the static
breakdown voltage cannot be maintained, when a high
reverse bias is applied. In general, therefore, the
thickness of the n buffer layer 23 is increased to
maintain the static breakdown voltage. However,
according to this method, since the substrate as a
whole is thickened, the on-state voltage is inevitably
increased.</p>
    <p num="0026">To avoid this, in the first embodiment, the n<sup>+</sup>
buffer layer 31 and the n buffer layer 23 formed
thereon are used in combination. With this structure,
even if a reverse bias is applied, the static breakdown
voltage can be sufficiently maintained. It is
necessary to set the concentration of the n buffer
layer 23 such that the depletion layer is gradually
formed in accordance with the applied voltage.
In other words, the concentration must be set such that
the depletion layer extends in the n buffer layer 23 to
maintain the static breakdown voltage of the element,
but does not reach the n<sup>+</sup> buffer layer 31 of a high
concentration to avoid oscillation in the turn-off
time.</p>
    <p num="0027">Specifically, the impurity concentration of
the n buffer layer 23 falls in a range, preferably,
for example, from 2×10<sup>14</sup> cm<sup>-3</sup> to 2×10<sup>15</sup> cm<sup>-3</sup>,
particularly preferably, for example, from 3×10<sup>14</sup> cm<sup>-3</sup>
to 1×10<sup>15</sup> cm<sup>-3</sup>. The n<sup>+</sup> buffer layer 31 must have such
a high concentration as to maintain the static
breakdown voltage. To ease the process, it is assumed
that the n<sup>+</sup> buffer layer 31 is formed by impurity ion
injection and a heating step. In this case, the
impurity concentration of the n<sup>+</sup> buffer layer 31 falls
in a range, preferably, for example, from 1×10<sup>16</sup> cm<sup>-3</sup>
to 1×10<sup>19</sup> cm<sup>-3</sup>, particularly preferably, for example,
from 1×10<sup>17</sup> cm<sup>-3</sup> to 5×10<sup>18</sup> cm<sup>-3</sup>. </p>
    <p num="0028">FIG. 3 shows an impurity concentration profile,
representing a case where the n buffer layer 23 having
an impurity concentration of 3×10<sup>14</sup> cm<sup>-3</sup> and a
thickness of 30 µm and the n<sup>+</sup> buffer layer 31 having
an impurity concentration of 1×10<sup>18</sup> cm<sup>-3</sup> are used in
combination.</p>
    <p num="0029">FIG. 4 shows an impurity concentration profile,
representing a case where the n buffer layer 23 is
formed by using an OSL (One Side Lap) wafer.</p>
    <p num="0030">A method for manufacturing the IGBT with the
above structure will be described. In the following
description, the same parts as those shown in FIG. 1
are identified by the same reference numerals as those
used in FIG. 1. The p<sup>+</sup> type contact region adjacent to
the source region 15 in FIG. 1 is omitted from the
description.</p>
    <heading>(First Manufacturing Method)</heading>
    <p num="0031">FIGS. 5A to 5C and 6 show a case in which a wafer
including an n buffer layer 23 formed in advance by
epitaxial growth is used.</p>
    <p num="0032">As shown in FIG. 5A, a wafer 51 includes an n
buffer layer 23 formed in advance by epitaxial growth.
The n buffer layer 23 is, for example, 625 µm thick.</p>
    <p num="0033">First, as shown in FIG. 5B, an n<sup>-</sup> high resistance
layer 21, having a thickness of, for example, 25 to
60 µm, is formed by epitaxial growth on the n buffer
layer 23. Accordingly, the total thickness of the
n buffer layer 23 and the n<sup>-</sup> high resistance layer 21
is about 685 to 650 µm.</p>
    <p num="0034">Thereafter, as shown in FIG. 5C, a p base layer
14, an n<sup>+</sup> source region 15, a trench-type gate
electrode 16, a gate insulating film 17 and a source
electrode 41 are sequentially formed by a known
process.</p>
    <p num="0035">Then, as shown in FIG. 6, the rear surface of the
buffer layer 23 is lapped. In the case of the IGBT of
the static breakdown voltage of 600V, the total 
thickness from the main surface of the base layer 14 to
the rear surface of the n buffer layer 23 is, for
example, 60 to 80 µm.</p>
    <p num="0036">Thereafter, phosphorus and boron are sequentially
ion-injected through the rear surface of the n buffer
layer 23. Then, a heat treatment, such as laser
annealing, flash annealing, sintering or diffusion, is
performed, thereby forming an n<sup>+</sup> buffer layer 31 and
a p<sup>+</sup> drain layer 22. Subsequently, a drain electrode
42 is formed. As a result, the IGBT shown in FIG. 1 is
completed.</p>
    <p num="0037">The source electrode 41 may be formed after the n<sup>+</sup>
buffer layer and the drain layer 22 are formed.</p>
    <heading>(Second Manufacturing Method)</heading>
    <p num="0038">FIGS. 7A to 7C show a case in which an OSL wafer
including an n buffer layer 23 is used. In the second
manufacturing method, the step of forming a MOS
transistor and the step of forming an n<sup>+</sup> buffer layer
31 and a drain layer 22 are the same as those in the
first manufacturing method.</p>
    <p num="0039">As shown in FIG. 7A, an OSL wafer 71 includes
an n buffer layer 23 and an n<sup>-</sup> high resistance
layer 21. The surface of the n<sup>-</sup> high resistance
layer 21 is lapped in advance so that the wafer has
a thickness of, for example, 250 µm.</p>
    <p num="0040">FIG. 7B shows the relationship between the
impurity concentration and the thickness in the buffer
layer 23 and the n<sup>-</sup> high resistance layer 21. These
layers have the concentrations as mentioned above.</p>
    <p num="0041">As shown in FIG. 7C, a p base layer 14, an n<sup>+</sup>
source region 15, a trench-type gate electrode 16,
a gate insulating film 17 and a source electrode 41
are sequentially formed by the known process as in the
first manufacturing method. Then, the rear surface of
the n buffer layer 23 is lapped such that the total
thickness is, for example, 60 to 80 µm. Thereafter,
an n<sup>+</sup> buffer layer 31 and a drain layer 22 are formed 
in the same manner as in the first manufacturing
method.</p>
    <p num="0042">The effect of the second manufacturing method is
the same as that of the first manufacturing method.</p>
    <p num="0043">A manufacturing method for stabilizing the film
thickness after lapping will next be described.</p>
    <heading>(Third Manufacturing Method)</heading>
    <p num="0044">FIGS. 8A to 8D and 9A to 9D show a third manufacturing
method according to the present invention, in
which an IGBT having a drain layer doped at a low dose
is used. With this method, the thickness after lapping
can be controlled with high accuracy.</p>
    <p num="0045">Referring to FIG. 8A, a wafer 81 is made of n-type
silicon. To form an n buffer layer 32, for example,
phosphorus is ion-injected into one surface of the
wafer 81. Then, a heat treatment is performed, thereby
forming the n buffer layer 23, as shown in FIG. 8B.
Subsequently, an oxide film 82 is formed on the one
surface of the wafer 81.</p>
    <p num="0046">Then, as shown in FIGS. 8C and 8D, the wafer 81
is caused to adhere to a supporting substrate 83.
The supporting surface 83, as well as the wafer 81, is
an n-type silicon wafer. It has an oxide film 84 in
one surface portion. The oxide film 82 of the wafer 81
and the oxide film 84 of the supporting substrate 83
are faced each other, and joined together by van der
Waals force. These oxide films 82 and 84 may have any
thickness. Oxide films need not be formed on both the
wafer 81 and the supporting substrate 82, but may be
formed on only one of them. Thus, the substrate of
a SOI structure is formed.</p>
    <p num="0047">Thereafter, as shown in FIG. 9A, the other surface
of the wafer 81 is lapped. For example, in the case of
an IGBT of the 600V voltage series, the wafer 81 is
lapped to a thickness of about, for example, 60 µm.
Thus, the n<sup>-</sup> high resistance layer 21 is formed on the
n buffer layer 23. </p>
    <p num="0048">Then, as shown in FIG. 9B, a trench-type IGBT MOS
gate structure 85 is formed in the n<sup>-</sup> high resistance
layer 21 through the same process as in the first and
second methods.</p>
    <p num="0049">Subsequently, as shown in FIG. 9C, the supporting
substrate 83 is lapped and removed. Then, the oxide
films 82 and 84 are removed by, for example, CDE
(Chemical Dry Etching). The oxide films 82 and 84
and the silicon wafer can be selectively etched.
Therefore, the etching of the oxide films 82 and 84 is
stopped at the interface between the n buffer layer 23
and the oxide films 82 and 84. Thus, the thickness of
the wafer 81 can be maintained after the etching. In
other words, the lapping error that was inevitable in
the conventional device can be eliminated by etching
the supporting substrate 83 in the above SOI structure.</p>
    <p num="0050">Thereafter, as shown in FIG. 9D, the anode side is
processed. More specifically, for example, boron is
ion-injected to a surface region of the n buffer layer
23. Then, a heat treatment, such as laser annealing,
flash annealing, sintering or diffusion, is performed,
thereby forming a p<sup>+</sup> drain layer 22. Finally, a drain
electrode is formed, with the result that the IGBT is
completed.</p>
    <p num="0051">With the third manufacturing method, the SOI
structure comprised of the wafer 81 and the supporting
substrate 83 is used. The wafer 81 is lapped and the
MOS gate structure 85 is formed, and thereafter
the supporting substrate 83 is removed. Further,
the oxide films 82 and 84 are removed by selective
etching. Thus, since the total thickness of the IGBT
is not changed after the MOS gate structure 85 is
formed, the third method is advantageous in that the
IGBT having designed characteristics can be
manufactured.</p>
    <heading>(Fourth Manufacturing Method)</heading>
    <p num="0052">FIGS. 10A to 10D and 11A to 11D show a fourth 
manufacturing method according to the present
invention. The same parts as those in the third
method are identified by the same reference numerals
as those used in the description of the third method.
The fourth manufacturing method is different from the
third manufacturing method in the following respect:
an n buffer layer and a p<sup>+</sup> drain layer are formed after
the substrate is thinned.</p>
    <p num="0053">As shown in FIGS. 10A and 10B, an oxide film 82 is
formed on one surface of a wafer 81 made of n-type
silicon.</p>
    <p num="0054">Then, as shown in FIGS. 10C and 10D, the wafer
81 is caused to adhere to a supporting substrate 83.
The supporting surface 83, as well as the wafer 81, is
an n-type silicon wafer. It has an oxide film 84 in
one surface portion. The oxide film 82 of the wafer 81
and the oxide film 84 of the supporting substrate 83
are faced each other, and joined together by van der
Waals force. These oxide films 82 and 84 may have any
thickness. Oxide films need not be formed on both the
wafer 81 and the supporting substrate 82, but may be
formed on only one of them. Thus, the substrate of
a SOI structure is formed.</p>
    <p num="0055">Thereafter, as shown in FIG. 11A, the other
surface of the wafer 81 is lapped. For example, in the
case of an IGBT of the 600V voltage series, the wafer
81 is lapped to a thickness of about, for example,
60 µm. Thus, an n<sup>-</sup> high resistance layer 21 is
formed.</p>
    <p num="0056">Then, as shown in FIG. 11B, a trench-type IGBT MOS
gate structure 85 is formed in the n<sup>-</sup> high resistance
layer 21 of the wafer 81 through the same process as in
the first to third methods.</p>
    <p num="0057">Subsequently, as shown in FIG. 11C, the supporting
substrate 83 is lapped and removed. The oxide films 82
and 84 are removed by, for example, CDE. The etching
is stopped at the interface between the n<sup>-</sup> high 
resistance layer 21 and the oxide films 82 and 84.
Thus, the thickness of the wafer 81 can be maintained
after the etching. Thereafter, the anode side is
processed. More specifically, for example, phosphorus
is ion-injected to the rear surface of the n<sup>-</sup> high
resistance layer 21, thereby forming an n buffer
layer 23.</p>
    <p num="0058">Then, as shown in FIG. 11D, for example, boron is
ion-injected to a surface region of the n buffer layer
23. Then, a heat treatment, such as laser annealing,
flash annealing, sintering or diffusion, is performed,
thereby forming a p<sup>+</sup> drain layer 22. Finally, a drain
electrode is formed, with the result that the IGBT is
completed.</p>
    <p num="0059">The effect of the fourth manufacturing method is
the same as that of the third manufacturing method.
Moreover, since the p<sup>+</sup> drain layer 22 is formed in a
close-to-final step, the fourth method has advantages
that the influence of the heat treatment is less and
variation in dose or thickness can be prevented.</p>
    <heading>(Fifth Manufacturing Method)</heading>
    <p num="0060">FIGS. 12A to 12D and 13A and 13B show a fifth
manufacturing method according to the present
invention. The same parts as those in the third method
are identified by the same reference numerals as those
used in the description of the third method. The fifth
manufacturing method is different from the fourth
manufacturing method in the following respect: impurity
ions are injected into a wafer 81 to form an n buffer
layer 23 and a p<sup>+</sup> drain layer 22 before a SOI structure
is formed.</p>
    <p num="0061">As shown in FIG. 12A, for example, phosphorus (P)
to form an n buffer layer 23 is ion-injected into one
surface of an n-type silicon wafer 81. Further, boron
(B) to form a p<sup>+</sup> drain layer 22 is ion-injected to
the wafer 81. Thereafter, an oxide film 82 is formed
on the one surface of the wafer 81, as shown in </p>
    <heading>FIG. 12B.</heading>
    <p num="0062">Then, as shown in FIGS. 12C and 12D, the wafer 81
is caused to adhere to a supporting substrate 83.
The supporting surface 83, as well as the wafer 81, is
an n-type silicon wafer. It has an oxide film 84 in
one surface portion. The oxide film 82 of the wafer 81
and the oxide film 84 of the supporting substrate 83
are faced each other, and joined together by van der
Waals force. These oxide films 82 and 84 may have any
thickness. Oxide films need not be formed on both the
wafer 81 and the supporting substrate 82, but may be
formed on only one of them. Thus, the substrate of
a SOI structure is formed.</p>
    <p num="0063">Thereafter, as shown in FIG. 13A, the other
surface of the wafer 81 is lapped, thereby forming an
n<sup>-</sup> high resistance layer 21. For example, in the case
of an IGBT of the 600V voltage series, the wafer 81 is
lapped to a thickness of about, for example, 60 µm.</p>
    <p num="0064">Then, as shown in FIG. 13B, a trench-type IGBT MOS
gate structure 85 is formed in the n<sup>-</sup> high resistance
layer 21 of the wafer 81 in the same process as in
the first to fourth methods. At the same time, the
phosphorus and boron ions that have been injected in
the wafer 81 are diffused by heat processes. As a
result, an n buffer layer 23 and a p<sup>+</sup> drain layer 22
are formed.</p>
    <p num="0065">Subsequently, as shown in FIG. 13C, the supporting
substrate 83 is lapped and removed. The oxide films 82
and 84 are removed by, for example, CDE. The oxide
films 82 and 84 and the silicon wafer can be
selectively etched. Therefore, the etching can be
stopped at the interface between the n buffer layer 23
and the oxide films 82 and 84. Thus, the thickness of
the wafer 81 can be maintained after the etching.
In other words, the lapping error that was inevitable
in the conventional device can be eliminated by etching
the supporting substrate 83 in the above SOI structure. </p>
    <p num="0066">According to the fifth manufacturing method, the
impurity ions to form the n buffer layer 23 and the p<sup>+</sup>
drain layer 22 are injected into the wafer 81 before
the SOI structure is formed. Therefore, since the ions
are injected successively, the manufacturing process is
simplified. In addition, since the ions are injected
to the thick wafer, the process can be eased.</p>
    <heading>(Sixth Manufacturing Method)</heading>
    <p num="0067">FIGS. 14A to 14D and 15A and 15B show a sixth
manufacturing method according to the present
invention. The same parts as those in the third method
are identified by the same reference numerals as those
used in the description of the third method. In the
third to fifth manufacturing methods, the SOI structure
is formed by joining the wafer 81 and the supporting
substrate 83. According to the sixth method, the SOI
structure is formed by using a substrate of a SIMOX
(Separation by IMplanted OXide).</p>
    <p num="0068">As shown in FIG. 14A, for example, oxygen is ion-injected
into one surface of an n-type silicon wafer
81. As a result, an oxide film 82 is formed at a depth
of several microns from the surface of the wafer 81, as
shown in FIG. 14B.</p>
    <p num="0069">Then, as shown in FIG. 14C, an n<sup>-</sup> high resistance
layer 21 is formed on the surface of the wafer 81 by,
for example, epitaxial growth. The epitaxial growth is
controlled such that the n<sup>-</sup> high resistance layer 21
has a thickness of, for example, 60 µm from the oxide
film 82. Thus, the substrate of the SOI structure is
formed.</p>
    <p num="0070">Thereafter, as shown in FIG. 14D, a trench-type
IGBT MOS gate structure 85 is formed in the n<sup>-</sup> high
resistance layer 21 of the wafer 81 in the same process
as in the first to fifth methods.</p>
    <p num="0071">Subsequently, as shown in FIG. 15A, the rear
surface of the wafer 81 is lapped and removed. Then,
the oxide film 82 is removed by, for example, CDE. 
The oxide film 82 and the silicon wafer can be
selectively etched. Therefore, the thickness of the
wafer 81 on the n<sup>-</sup> high resistance layer 21 side can be
maintained after the etching. In other words, the
lapping error that was inevitable in the conventional
device can be eliminated by etching the wafer 81 in the
above SOI structure.</p>
    <p num="0072">Thereafter, as shown in FIGS. 15A and 15B,
phosphorus and boron are sequentially ion-injected
through the rear surface of the wafer 81, so that an
n buffer layer 23 and a p<sup>+</sup> drain layer 22 are formed.</p>
    <p num="0073">According to the sixth manufacturing method, the
IGBT is manufactured by using a substrate of the SIMOX
structure. Since it is unnecessary to use a supporting
substrate, the manufacturing cost can be reduced.</p>
    <heading>(Seventh Manufacturing Method)</heading>
    <p num="0074">FIGS. 16A, 16B and 17A to 17D show a seventh
manufacturing method according to the present
invention. The same parts as those in the third method
are identified by the same reference numerals as those
used in the description of the third method. In the
third to fifth manufacturing methods, the SOI structure
is formed by joining the supporting substrate 83 and
the wafer 81. The seventh method uses a porous silicon
instead.</p>
    <p num="0075">As shown in FIG. 16A, for example, a porous
silicon layer 91 is formed on one surface of a wafer 81
made of n type silicon, which serves as a supporting
substrate.</p>
    <p num="0076">Then, as shown in FIG. 16B, an n<sup>-</sup> high resistance
layer 21 is formed on the surface of the porous silicon
layer 91 by, for example, epitaxial growth.
The epitaxial growth is controlled such that the n<sup>-</sup>
high resistance layer 21 has a thickness of, for
example, 60 µm.</p>
    <p num="0077">Thereafter, as shown in FIG. 17A, a trench-type
IGBT MOS gate structure 85 is formed in the n<sup>-</sup> high 
resistance layer 21 in the same process as in the first
to sixth methods.</p>
    <p num="0078">Then, as shown in FIG. 17B, the n<sup>-</sup> high resistance
layer 21 and the wafer 81 are separated from each other
at the porous silicon layer 91. Thereafter, the porous
silicon layer 91 is removed by, for example, CDE.</p>
    <p num="0079">Subsequently, as shown in FIGS. 17C and 17D,
phosphorus and boron are sequentially ion-injected
through the rear surface of the n<sup>-</sup> high resistance
layer 21, so that an n buffer layer 23 and a p<sup>+</sup> drain
layer 22 are formed.</p>
    <p num="0080">According to the seventh manufacturing method,
the porous silicon layer 91 is formed on the wafer 81.
After the MOS gate structure 85 is formed in the n<sup>-</sup>
high resistance layer 21 on the porous silicon layer
91, the wafer 81 is separated from the n<sup>-</sup> high
resistance layer 21 at the porous silicon layer 91.
Thus, since no lapping process is required, the seventh
method has an advantage that the thickness of the n<sup>-</sup>
high resistance layer 21 does not vary.</p>
    <p num="0081">In addition, the wafer 81 serving as a supporting
substrate can be reused after being separated from the
n<sup>-</sup> high resistance layer 21 at the porous silicon layer
91. Therefore, the manufacturing cost can be reduced.</p>
    <p num="0082">In the third to seventh manufacturing methods,
an n<sup>+</sup> buffer 31 may be formed between the n buffer
layer 23 and the p<sup>+</sup> drain layer 22 as in the embodiment
shown in FIG. 1.</p>
    <p num="0083">In the third to sixth manufacturing methods, the
oxide films 82 and 84 are used to form a SOI structure.
However, it is possible to use any other material for
the same purpose so far as that can be selectively
etched from silicon.</p>
    <p num="0084">The above descriptions of the embodiments refer to
a trench-type IGBT as an example. However, the present
invention is not limited to this type. The present
invention can be applied to a planar-type IGBT.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A semiconductor device characterized by
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a first buffer layer (23) of a first conductivity
type;</claim-text><claim-text>a high resistance layer (21) of the first
conductivity type formed on the first buffer layer;</claim-text><claim-text>a base layer (14) of a second conductivity type
formed on the high resistance layer;</claim-text><claim-text>a source region (15) of the first conductivity
type in a surface region of the base layer;</claim-text><claim-text>a gate electrode (16) insulated from the source
region, the base layer and the high resistance layer;</claim-text><claim-text>a drain layer (22) of the second conductivity type
formed on an opposite side of the first buffer layer
from a surface on which the high resistance layer is
formed; and</claim-text><claim-text>a second buffer layer (31) of the first
conductivity type formed between the first buffer layer
and the drain layer, an impurity concentration of the
second buffer layer (31) being higher than that of the
first buffer layer.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The device according to claim 1, characterized
in that the second buffer layer (31) is at least
0.5 µm and at most 3 µm thick.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The device according to claim 1, characterized
in that the impurity concentration of the second buffer
layer (31) is 1×1016 cm-3 to 1×1019 cm-3 at a maximum.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The device according to claim 1, characterized
in that a total amount of impurities contained in the
drain layer (22) is at most 1×1015 cm-2.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A method for manufacturing a semiconductor
device characterized by comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>forming a high resistance layer (21) of a first
conductivity type on a main surface of a first buffer
layer (23) of the first conductivity type, an impurity
concentration of the high resistance layer (21) being
lower than that of the first buffer layer;</claim-text><claim-text>forming a base layer (14) of a second conductivity
type in a surface region of the high resistance layer;</claim-text><claim-text>forming a source region (15) of the first
conductivity type in a surface region of the base
layer;</claim-text><claim-text>forming a gate electrode (16) insulated from the
source region, the base layer and the high resistance
layer;</claim-text><claim-text>lapping a rear surface of the first buffer
layer (23);</claim-text><claim-text>injecting impurities through the rear surface of
the first buffer layer, thereby forming a second buffer
layer (31) of the first conductivity type, an impurity
concentration of the second buffer layer (31) being
higher than that of the first buffer layer; and</claim-text><claim-text>forming a drain layer (22) of the second
conductivity type on a rear surface of the second
buffer layer.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The method according to claim 5, characterized
in that the first buffer layer (23) and the high
resistance layer (21) are formed by using an OSL wafer.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A method for manufacturing a semiconductor
device characterized by comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>forming a first buffer layer (23) of a first
conductivity type on a first surface of a first
substrate (81) of the first conductivity type having
a high resistance;</claim-text><claim-text>forming a first insulating film (82) on the first
surface of the first substrate (81);</claim-text><claim-text>joining the first substrate (81) to a second
substrate (83), the second substrate (83) having a
second insulating film (84) on a first surface thereof,
the second insulating film (84) being brought into
contact with the first insulating film (82);</claim-text><claim-text>lapping a second surface of the first substrate
(81) to a thickness that corresponds to a predetermined
withstand voltage, the second surface being opposite to
the first surface;</claim-text><claim-text>forming a MOS gate structure (85) including a base
region, a source region and a gate electrode on the
second surface of the first substrate;</claim-text><claim-text>removing the second substrate (83) and the first
and second insulating films (82, 84);</claim-text><claim-text>forming a drain layer (22) of a second
conductivity type on the first surface of the first
substrate (81), the drain layer (22) being formed in a
portion shallower than the first buffer layer (23); and</claim-text><claim-text>forming a second buffer layer (31) of the first
conductivity type between the first buffer layer (23)
and the drain layer (22), an impurity concentration of
the second buffer layer (31) being higher than that of
the first buffer layer (23).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A method for manufacturing a semiconductor
device characterized by comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>forming a first insulating film (82) on a first
surface of a first substrate (81) having a high
resistance;</claim-text><claim-text>joining the first substrate (81) to a second
substrate (83), the second substrate (83) having a
second insulating film (84) on a first surface thereof,
the second insulating film (84) being brought into
contact with the first insulating film (82);</claim-text><claim-text>lapping a second surface of the first substrate
(81) to a thickness that corresponds to a predetermined
withstand voltage, the second surface being opposite to
the first surface;</claim-text><claim-text>forming a MOS gate structure (85) including a base
region, a source region and a gate electrode on the
second surface of the first substrate (81);</claim-text><claim-text>removing the second substrate (83) and the first
and second insulating films (82, 84);</claim-text><claim-text>forming a first buffer layer (23) of a first
conductivity type on the first surface of the first
substrate (81);</claim-text><claim-text>forming a drain layer (22) of a second
conductivity type on the first surface of the first
substrate (81), the drain layer (22) being formed in a
portion shallower than the first buffer layer (23); and</claim-text><claim-text>forming a second buffer layer (31) of the first
conductivity type between the first buffer layer (23)
and the drain layer (22), an impurity concentration of
the second buffer layer (31) being higher than that of
the first buffer layer (23).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>A method for manufacturing a semiconductor
device characterized by comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>forming a first buffer layer (23) of a first
conductivity type and a drain layer (22) of a second
conductivity type on a first surface of a first
substrate (81) having a high resistance;</claim-text><claim-text>forming a first insulating film (82) covering
the drain layer on the first surface of the first
substrate (81);</claim-text><claim-text>joining the first substrate (81) to a second
substrate (83), the second substrate (83) having a
second insulating film (84) on a first surface thereof,
the second insulating film (84) being brought into
contact with the first insulating film (82);</claim-text><claim-text>lapping a second surface of the first substrate
(81) to a thickness that corresponds to a predetermined
withstand voltage, the second surface being opposite to
the first surface;</claim-text><claim-text>forming a MOS gate structure (85) including a base
region, a source region and a gate electrode on the
second surface of the first substrate (81);</claim-text><claim-text>removing the second substrate (83) and the first
and second insulating films (82, 84); and</claim-text><claim-text>forming a second buffer layer (31) of the first
conductivity type between the first buffer layer (23)
and the drain layer (22), an impurity concentration of
the second buffer layer (31) being higher than that of
the first buffer layer (23).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>A method for manufacturing a semiconductor
device characterized by comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>forming an insulating film (82) in a portion of
a first depth from a first surface of a substrate (81)
having a first impurity concentration;</claim-text><claim-text>forming a semiconductor layer (21) of a first
conductivity type on the first surface, the
semiconductor layer having a thickness that corresponds
to a predetermined withstand voltage and a second
impurity concentration lower than the first impurity
concentration;</claim-text><claim-text>forming a MOS gate structure (85) including a base
region, a source region and a gate electrode in the
semiconductor layer (21);</claim-text><claim-text>removing a second surface of the substrate (81)
and the insulating film (82), the second surface being
opposite to the first surface;</claim-text><claim-text>forming a first buffer layer (23) of the first
conductivity type and a drain layer (22) of a second
conductivity type on the first surface, the drain layer
(22) being formed in a portion shallower than the first
buffer layer (23); and</claim-text><claim-text>forming a second buffer layer (31) of the first
conductivity type between the first buffer layer (23)
and the drain layer (22), an impurity concentration of
the second buffer layer (31) being higher than that of
the first buffer layer (23).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>A method for manufacturing a semiconductor
device characterized by comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>forming a porous silicon layer (91) on a surface
of a substrate (81);</claim-text><claim-text>forming a semiconductor layer (21) of a first
conductivity type on the porous silicon layer (91),
the semiconductor layer (21) having a thickness that
corresponds to a predetermined withstand voltage and
a first impurity concentration;</claim-text><claim-text>forming a MOS gate structure (85) including a
base region, a source region and a gate electrode on
a first surface of the semiconductor layer (21),
the first surface being opposite to the porous silicon
layer (91);</claim-text><claim-text>removing the substrate (81) and the porous silicon
layer (91);</claim-text><claim-text>forming a first buffer layer (23) of the first
conductivity type and a drain layer (22) of a second
conductivity type on a second surface of the semiconductor
layer (81), the second surface being opposite to
the first surface and the drain layer being formed in a
portion shallower than the first buffer layer (23); and</claim-text><claim-text>forming a second buffer layer (31) of the first
conductivity type between the first buffer layer (23)
and the drain layer (22), an impurity concentration of
the second buffer layer (31) being higher than that of
the first buffer layer (23).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>The method according to any one of claim 5 and
claims 7 through 11, characterized in that the second
buffer layer (31) is at least 0.5 µm and at most 3 µm
thick.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>The method according to any one of claim 5
and claims 7 through 11, characterized in that the
impurity concentration of the second buffer layer (31)
is 1×1016 cm-3 to 1×1019 cm-3 at a maximum.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>The method according to any one of claim 5 and
claims 7 through 11, characterized in that a total
amount of impurities contained in the drain layer (22)
is at most 1×1015 cm-2.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
