<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1245464-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1245464" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="18940809" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021002">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1245464-A2" status="new" fvid="23562706">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1245464</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021002</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02251770-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02251770</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020313</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001085268-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001085268</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010323</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B60N   2/22        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B60N   2/22        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B60N   2/44        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B60N   2/44        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B60N   2/68        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B60N   2/68        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B60R  22/26        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B60R  22/26        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B60N   2/68J</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B60N   2/68S</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B60R  22/26</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Sitzrückenlehnenrahmen für Fahrzeugsitz</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Seatback frame for vehicle seat</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Ensemble chassis pour dossier de siège d'un véhicule</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>JOHNSON CONTR AUTOMOTIVE SYS</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>JOHNSON CONTROLS AUTOMOTIVE SYSTEMS CORPORATION</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Johnson Controls Automotive Systems Corporation</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>771, Kozono</street>
              <city>Ayase-shi, Kanagawa-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MATSUNUMA NORIYOSHI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MATSUNUMA, NORIYOSHI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Matsunuma, Noriyoshi, Johnson Controls</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Automotive Systems Corp., 771, Kozono</street>
              <city>Ayase-shi, Kanagawa-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Dealtry, Brian</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Eric Potter Clarkson, Park View House, 58 The Ropewalk</street>
              <city>Nottingham NG1 5DD</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>In a seatback frame for a vehicle seat having a seatback and a seat
cushion and equipped with a seat belt of a three-point type, a pipe frame
formed along an external shape of the seatback and a vertically extending
tower frame located in the seatback at the same side as a belt-through
member of the seat belt of the three-point type and fixedly connected to the
pipe frame are provided. The tower frame includes an outer side bracket, an
inner side bracket, both of which are formed of vertically extending,
elongated metal sheets each formed in a substantially C-shaped cross
section and both of which are coupled to one another in abutting
engagement with one another to form an internal space, and an intermediate
brace member incorporated in the internal space to provide a reinforcement
rib structure.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="76" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="108"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <b>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a seatback frame for a vehicle seat and,
more particularly, to a seatback frame for a vehicle seat equipped with a
seat belt of the three-point type wherein a retractor for winding a seat belt is
mounted at a lower portion of the seatback and allows a shoulder belt to be
pulled out for restraining a seat occupant, a belt-through member is mounted
at an upper distal end of the seatback for guiding the shoulder belt, fixture
segments are mounted at both sides of a seat cushion for supporting both
ends of a lap belt which restrains the waist of the seat occupant, and a distal
end of the shoulder belt is supported with one of the fixture segments.</p>
    <p num="0002">In general, seat belts in practical use are divided into two types, a first
type in which a retractor is fixedly mounted to a pillar of a vehicle body and
a second type in which the retractor is directly fixed to a seatback frame.
The seat belt in normal use is constructed of a lap belt portion for
restraining the waist of a seat occupant and a shoulder belt portion for
restraining an area covering the shoulder and the waist of the seat occupant,
which are arranged in a three-point support structure which includes lap
anchor points located at both sides of a seat cushion and a shoulder anchor
point located at an upper distal end of a seatback.</p>
    <p num="0003">Since the vehicle seat, wherein the shoulder anchor point is located on
the seatback frame, encounters a significantly large impact shock delivered
from the shoulder belt and acting on the shoulder anchor point, it is required
for the seatback frame to be reinforced. An example of such a seatback
frame with a reinforced structure is exemplarily shown in FIG. 5. As shown
in FIG. 5, the seatback frame 1 is comprised of a pipe frame 2 which is
shaped to conform along an external shape of a seatback, and a tower frame
3 on which a belt-through member (not shown) for a shoulder anchor point
is mounted. To provide a reinforced structure for the tower frame 3,
particularly, a cross member 4 is obliquely placed so as to extend between
an upper distal end of the tower frame 3 and a bracket 2a opposed thereto
and welded to both of these components.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0004">In the seatback frame 1 for the vehicle seat equipped with the seat belt 
of the related art practice, the cross member 4 located so as to extend from
the upper distal end of the tower frame 3 toward the opposing side portion
of the seatback frame for reinforcement has an increased weight, providing
a degraded operability during a reclining operation of the seatback.</p>
    <p num="0005">Further, the presence of the cross member 4 obliquely located in a
substantially central area of the seatback so as to cross over the same
encounters a difficulty in enhancing a space for locating an active-type
headrest (which is of the type wherein when exerted with impact shocks,
lower distal ends of the headrest stays are urged rearward to cause the
headrest to move forward for thereby preventing the head of the seat
occupant from being swayed rearward to protect the same). As a result, only
a general-purpose headrest can only be employed in the seatback, with a
difficulty in adopting the active type headrest with an increased functional
property.</p>
    <p num="0006">During rearward collisions, also, the tower frame 3 is exerted with the
impact load and, so, is required to have the structure reinforced in forward
and rearward directions. However, with such a reinforced structure using the
cross member 4, although a rigidity is provided in structure in a widthwise
direction of a vehicle body, a relatively unsatisfied result takes place in the
presence of the impact shocks imparted in the forward and rearward
directions of the vehicle body.</p>
    <p num="0007">It is therefore an object of the present invention to provide a seatback
frame, for a vehicle seat equipped with a three-point support type seat belt,
which has a tower frame with a strong rigidity in structure sufficient for
resisting impact load exerted thereto, which is lighter in weight than the
related art cross member, and which enables an active type headrest to be
employed. Furthermore, it is another object of the present invention to
provide a vehicle seat to which such a seatback frame is applied.</p>
    <p num="0008">According to an aspect of the present invention, there is provided a
seatback frame for a vehicle seat having a seatback and a seat cushion and
equipped with a seat belt of a three-point type, wherein a retractor is
mounted at a lower portion of the seatback to wind up the seat belt, a
belt-through member is mounted at an upper distal end of the seatback to
guide a shoulder belt of the seat belt, which is pulled out from the retractor,
so as to restrain a shoulder portion of a seat occupant, both ends of a lap
belt of the seat belt, which restrain a waist portion of the seat occupant, are 
supported with fixed portions located at both sides of the seat cushion, and a
distal end of the shoulder belt is further supported with one of the fixed
portions. The seatback frame is provided with: a pipe frame formed along an
external shape of the seatback; and a vertically extending tower frame
located in the seatback at the same side as the belt-through member and
fixedly connected to the pipe frame. The tower frame includes an outer side
bracket, an inner side bracket, both of which are formed of vertically
extending, elongated metal sheets each formed in a substantially C-shaped
cross section and both of which are coupled to one another in abutting
engagement with one another to form an internal space, and an intermediate
brace member incorporated in the internal space to provide a reinforcement
rib structure.</p>
    <p num="0009">According to another aspect of the present invention, a vehicle seat is
provided with: a seatback; a seat cushion; a seat belt of a three-point type,
wherein a retractor is mounted at a lower portion of the seatback to wind up
the seat belt, a belt-through member is mounted at an upper distal end of the
seatback to guide a shoulder belt of the seat belt, which is pulled out from
the retractor, so as to restrain a shoulder portion of a seat occupant, both
ends of a lap belt of the seat belt, which restrain a waist portion of the seat
occupant, are supported with fixed portions located at both sides of the seat
cushion, and a distal end of the shoulder belt is further supported with one
of the fixed portions; and a seatback frame. The seatback frame is provided
with: a pipe frame formed along an external shape of the seatback; and a
vertically extending tower frame located in the seatback at the same side as
the belt-through member and fixedly connected to the pipe frame. The tower
frame includes an outer side bracket, an inner side bracket, both of which
are formed of vertically extending, elongated metal sheets each formed in a
substantially C-shaped cross section and both of which are coupled to one
another in abutting engagement with one another to form an internal space,
and an intermediate brace member incorporated in the internal space to
provide a reinforcement rib structure.</p>
    <p num="0010">Other and further features, advantages, and benefits of the present
invention will become more apparent from the following description taken
in conjunction with the following drawings. </p>
    <heading>
      <b>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0011">
      <sl>
        <li>FIG. 1 is a perspective view illustrating a vehicle seat employing a
seatback frame of an embodiment according to the present invention;</li>
        <li>FIG. 2 is a perspective view illustrating a structure of the seatback
frame of the embodiment;</li>
        <li>FIG. 3 is an enlarged exploded view of a tower frame forming part of
the seatback frame shown in FIG. 2;</li>
        <li>FIG. 4A is a cross sectional view illustrating a mounting area of an
upper pipe component, FIG. 4B is a cross sectional view illustrating a
mounting area of a center pipe component, and FIG. 4C is a cross sectional
view illustrating a structural configuration of the tower frame; and</li>
        <li>FIG. 5 is a perspective view of a seatback frame for a unitary type seat
assembled with a seat belt used in the related art practice.</li>
      </sl>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <b>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0012">To describe the present invention more in detail, a seatback frame of an
embodiment of the present invention to be applied to a vehicle seat will be
explained below in detail with reference to the drawings.</p>
    <p num="0013">FIG. 1 is a perspective view of the vehicle seat employing the seatback
frame according to the present invention. FIG. 2 is a perspective view
illustrating a structure of the seatback according to the present invention.
FIG. 3 is an exploded perspective view illustrating a structure of a tower
frame which forms the seatback frame shown in FIG. 3. FIGS. 4A, 4B and
4C are cross sectional views illustrating the tower frame, shown in FIG. 3,
in conjunction with associated component parts shown in FIG. 2. In FIGS,
frontward and rearward directions of a vehicle body are respectively
represented by arrows FR and RR, rightward and leftward directions of the
vehicle body are respectively represented by arrows R and L, upward and
downward directions of the vehicle body are respectively represented by
arrows UPR and LWR, and a right side front seat is typically illustrated.</p>
    <p num="0014">In FIG. 1, the vehicle seat 10 is equipped with a seat belt of a
three-point support type and includes a seat cushion 11 on which a seat
occupant seats, a seatback 12 standing upright from a rear distal end of the
seat cushion 11 through a reclining mechanism operatively coupled to the
seat cushion 11 and the seatback 12 permitting the seatback 12 to be
adjusted in a reclined state at a given angular position, and a headrest 13 
fixedly located at an upper edge of the seatback 12 for supporting an head H
of a seat occupant.</p>
    <p num="0015">A seat belt equipped in the vehicle seat 10 is comprised of a retractor 20
internally incorporated in a lower side portion of the seatback 12 and
fixedly secured to the vehicle body side, and a shoulder belt 21 with its one
lowest end portion stored in the retractor 20 and having an intermediate
portion passing through a belt-through member 22 fixedly secured to an
upper distal end of the seat back 12. When applying the seat belt, the seat
occupant pulls out the shoulder belt 21 downward in an oblique direction
through the belt-through member 22 so as to restrain a shoulder S of the seat
occupant.</p>
    <p num="0016">Further, the seat belt includes a lap belt 23 with its one end stored in a
retractor 60, which is fixedly secured to the vehicle body side at a lower
side of the seat cushion 11, to allow free movement of the lap belt 23 for
restraining a waist W of the seat occupant, with the other end of the lap belt
23 being firmly connected to a lower distal end of the shoulder belt 21. The
both ends of the shoulder belt 21 and the lap belt 23 are tightly connected to
a coupling tongue 24 which can be fixedly coupled to a release buckle 25
fixedly mounted to the other side of the seat cushion 11, providing a
three-point support structure wherein the shoulder belt 21 and the lap belt
23, which form a waving configuration of the seat belt, are supported at a
fixed point lying on the belt-through member 22, located at the upper distal
end of the seatback 12, and at two fixed points lying on both sides of the
seat cushion 11. In FIG.1, a pulling-out direction of the shoulder belt 21 and
the lap belt 23 is designated by an arrow PO. Incidentally, as appropriate,
the retractor 60 can be replaced with a pivotably fixed member. In such a
simple structure, an end of the lap belt 23 opposed to the coupling tongue
24 is simply connected to the pivotably fixed member and not wound around
to be elongated.</p>
    <p num="0017">FIG. 2 shows a structure of the seatback frame 30 of the seatback 12. In
FIG. 2, the seatback frame 30 is formed by bending a pipe material and is
generally comprised of a substantially L-shaped pipe frame 40 and a tower
frame 50 located at one side of the seatback 12 and vertically extending to
provide a reinforced rigid structure.</p>
    <p num="0018">More particularly, the pipe frame 40 includes a horizontally extending
upper pipe component 41, a side pipe component 42 which is laterally 
spaced from the tower frame 50, and a horizontally extending lower pipe
component 43. These components are so shaped as to conform to an upper
edge, one of side edges and a lower edge, respectively, which form three
sides of an external shape of the seatback 12. A side bracket 44 is fixedly
secured to a lower distal end of the side pipe component 42 by some
suitable means such as welding. Located below the upper pipe component
41 is a center pipe component 45 which transversely extends between the
side pipe component 42 and the tower frame 50 to reinforce the structure of
the seatback frame 30.</p>
    <p num="0019">Below the center pipe component 45, further, S-shaped springs 46 are
supported between the side pipe component 42 and the tower frame 50. Also,
the upper pipe component 41 of the pipe frame 40 has a pair of guide
sleeves 47 fixedly connected thereto by welding for receiving stays 13a, 13a
of the headrest 13.</p>
    <p num="0020">As seen in FIG. 2, the retractor 20 is received in a joined area between
one end of the lower pipe component 43 of the pipe frame 40 and a lower
distal end of the tower frame 50 and is fixedly secured to a pair of brackets
26, 27, fastened to the lower pipe component 43 by a welding, by tightening
screws 28. Also, a recliner 14, which forms the reclining mechanism
discussed above, is fixedly coupled to a lower and side wall of the tower
frame 50 by fixture bolts 14a.</p>
    <p num="0021">By the way, an important feature of the seatback frame 30 of the present
invention concerns a capability of contributing to a reduction in weight and
an increase in rigidity in structure to have a strength sufficient for resisting
impact shocks exerted to the seatback 12 during a collision of a vehicle
while adequately enhancing a space permitting free movement of an
active-type headrest 13 having an impact shock absorbing ability.</p>
    <p num="0022">That is, as shown in FIG. 3, the tower frame 50 is constructed of an
outer side bracket 51 formed of a vertically extending, elongated metal
sheet, an inner side bracket 52 formed of a vertically extending, elongated
metal sheet, and an intermediate, elongated brace member 53 with a
reinforcement rib function which is interposed between the outer and inner
side brackets 51, 52. Also, reference numeral 54 designates a cap and
bracket to be coupled to an upper opening of the tower frame 50.</p>
    <p num="0023">As seen in FIG. 3, each of the outer side bracket 51 and the inner side
bracket 52 has a substantially C-channeled configuration in cross section. 
The outer and inner side brackets 51, 52 have their front edges formed with
front flanges 51a, 52a, respectively. Besides, rear sections of the outer side
bracket 51 and the inner side bracket 52 are formed with vertically
extending, elongated rear walls 51b, 52b. Further, the intermediate brace
member 53 is composed of a vertically extending, elongated central top wall
53a, a pair of elongated longitudinal wall segments 53b, 53b bent sideward
from both sides of the top wall 53a, and vertically extending, elongated
front and rear flanges 53c, 53c which extends from front and rear edges of
the respective longitudinal wall segments 53b, 53b in forward and rearward
directions of the seatback 12.</p>
    <p num="0024">As viewed in FIGS. 4A to 4C which show the relationships among the
outer side bracket 51, the inner side bracket 52 and the intermediate brace
member 53, the rear walls 51b and 52b formed along the rear sections of the
outer side bracket 51 and the inner side bracket 52, respectively, have
overlapped margin 55, extending in a vertical direction, at which the rear
walls 51b and 52b are joined to one another with suitably spaced welding
intervals by some suitable welding means such as CO<sub>2</sub> welding.</p>
    <p num="0025">In addition, the front flanges 51a, 52a formed along the front edges of
the outer side bracket 51 and the inner side bracket 52, respectively, are
held in mating engagement with one another and are fixedly joined to one
another with suitably spaced welding intervals by some suitable welding
means from the vertical direction such as spot welding. As a result, any
unbalances present in a mated condition between the both side brackets can
be overcome by adjusting the joint margin 55 of the respective rear walls
51b, 52b of the side brackets 51, 52. Further, the above joining method for
the side brackets 51, 52 provides a highly improved workability in the
welding operation of the tower frame 50 in the seatback frame 30.</p>
    <p num="0026">Located in an internal space between the outer side bracket 51 and the
inner side bracket 52 is the intermediate brace member 53, whose top wall
53a is joined to the inner surface of the inner side bracket 52 with vertically
spaced welding intervals by welding and the front and rear flanges 53c, 53c
are joined to an inner surface of the outer side bracket 51 with vertically
spaced welding intervals by welding such that the longitudinal wall
segments 53b, 53b constitute rib structures.</p>
    <p num="0027">As viewed in FIG. 4A, a distal end of the upper pipe component 41 is
joined to a laterally and inwardly facing vertical wall 52c, of the inner side 
bracket 52, to which a distal end of the center pipe component 45 is also
connected by welding (see FIG.4B). In addition, a distal end of the lower
pipe component 43 is connected to a lower end of the vertical wall 52c (see
FIG. 2).</p>
    <p num="0028">With a configuration discussed above, the seatback frame 30 has a
reinforced structure with the tower frame 50 containing the intermediate
brace member 53 while, in addition thereto, the center pipe component 45
and the lower pipe components 43 laterally extend between the side pipe
component 42 and the tower frame 50. In particular, the seatback frame 30
utilizes the longitudinal wall segments 53b of the intermediate brace
member 53, contained in the tower frame 50, as the reinforced member for
the joint portions between the upper pipe component 41 and the center pipe
component 45. Therefore, even when the connected areas of the upper pipe
component 41 and the center pipe component 45 encounter the impact load,
the connected areas are not deformed. Thus, the seatback frame 30 has an
effective function to resist the impact load or stress exerted to the seatback
12 in a widthwise direction of the vehicle, precluding a buckling
deformation to be caused in the tower frame 50 while enabling the tower
frame 50 to have a strong rigidity and an increased durability in the whole
structure of the seatback 12.</p>
    <p num="0029">Also as previously noted above, the seatback frame 30 has a reinforced
function effective for overcoming bending load exerted to the seatback 12 in
the forward and rearward directions of the vehicle owing to the joint portion
between the inner side bracket 52 and the upper pipe component 41 shown
in FIG. 4A, the joint portion between the inner side bracket 52 and the
center pipe component 45 shown in FIG. 4B, and the closed box-shaped
structure of the tower frame 50 as well as the joined structure between the
vertically extending front flanges 51a, 52a which are welded together. In
addition, one of the front flanges 51a, 52a of the outer side bracket 51 and
the inner side bracket 52 is bent or curled to have a round shape RS, thereby
preventing a seat pad and a decorative seat cover, which conceals the
seatback frame, from being damaged such that it is possible for the seatback
to maintain a favorable operating performance with a comfortable feeling
and an outer appearance. Also, the provision of the center pipe component
45 located in the area to compel the center pipe component 45 to avoid
interference with an impact receiving portion P of the stays 13a, 13a of the 
headrest 13 enables the headrest 13 to be structured as the active type.</p>
    <p num="0030">Furthermore with such a structure discussed above, when encountering
traffic accidents such as rearward collisions of the vehicle, the impact force
imparted to the seat occupant is transferred through the shoulder belt 21 and
is then applied through the belt-through 22 to the tower frame 50 of the
seatback frame 30. When this occurs, the favorable degree of the reinforced
structure in rigidity provided by the specific configuration of the seatback
frame 30 including the joined structure of the front flanges 51a, 52a or the
like is effective for adequately overcoming the impact load exerted in the
forward and rearward directions of the vehicle to preclude a fear of bending
deformation.</p>
    <p num="0031">It will now be understood from the foregoing description that in
accordance with of the seatback frame for the vehicle seat of the present
invention, the important feature concerns the structure constructed of the
pipe frame, which is formed in the same shape as the external shape of the
seatback, and the vertically extending tower frame located at one side of the
seatback, together with the tower frame, which supports the shoulder belt to
be pulled out from the retractor mounted at the lower part of the seatback,
including the intermediate brace member located in the internal space
formed by the outer side bracket and the inner side bracket, which are
fixedly joined to one another, to provide the reinforced structure whereby
even when the vehicle encounters the collision in the widthwise or forward
and rearward directions, the tower frame is not subjected to the buckling
phenomenon while enabling the provision of the light weight and compact
structure, with a resultant highly improved safety in operation.</p>
    <p num="0032">The entire content of a Patent Application No. TOKUGAN 2001-85268
with a filing date of March 23, 2001 in Japan is hereby incorporated by
reference.</p>
    <p num="0033">Although the invention has been described above by reference to a
certain embodiment of the invention, the invention is not limited to the
embodiment described above. Modifications and variations of the
embodiment described above will occur to those skilled in the art, in light of
the teachings. The scope of the invention is defined with reference to the
following claims.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A seatback frame for a vehicle seat having a seatback and a seat
cushion and equipped with a seat belt of a three-point type, wherein a
retractor is mounted at a lower portion of the seatback to wind up the seat
belt, a belt-through member is mounted at an upper distal end of the
seatback to guide a shoulder belt of the seat belt, which is pulled out from
the retractor, so as to restrain a shoulder portion of a seat occupant, both
ends of a lap belt of the seat belt, which restrain a waist portion of the seat
occupant, are supported with fixed portions located at both sides of the seat
cushion, and a distal end of the shoulder belt is further supported with one
of the fixed portions, the seatback frame comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a pipe frame formed along an external shape of the seatback; and</claim-text><claim-text>a vertically extending tower frame located in the seatback at the same
side as the belt-through member and fixedly connected to the pipe frame,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the tower frame includes an outer side bracket, an inner side
bracket, both of which are formed of vertically extending, elongated metal
sheets each formed in a substantially C-shaped cross section and both of
which are coupled to one another in abutting engagement with one another
to form an internal space, and an intermediate brace member incorporated in
the internal space to provide a reinforcement rib structure.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A seatback frame for a vehicle seat according to claim 1, further
comprising a center pipe component interconnected between the pipe frame
and the tower frame.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A seatback frame for a vehicle seat according to claim 2, wherein the
center pipe component is arranged to avoid interfering with stays of a
headrest of an active type.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A seatback frame for a vehicle seat according to claim 1, wherein the
outer side bracket and the inner side bracket respectively have front edges
formed with vertically extending flanges both of which are welded to be
fixed to one another to form a unitary structure between the outer side
bracket and the inner side bracket.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A seatback frame for a vehicle seat according to claim 4, wherein
either one of distal ends of the flanges of the outer side bracket and the
inner side bracket has a round shape.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A seatback frame for a vehicle seat according to claim 5, wherein the
either one of distal ends of the flanges of the outer side bracket and the
inner side bracket is bent or curled to form the round shape.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A seatback frame for a vehicle seat according to claim 2, wherein an
upper pipe component of the pipe frame and the center pipe component have
their respective distal ends welded to the inner side bracket at the
reinforcement rib structure of the intermediate brace member.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A vehicle seat comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a seatback;</claim-text><claim-text>a seat cushion;</claim-text><claim-text>a seat belt of a three-point type, wherein a retractor is mounted at a
lower portion of the seatback to wind up the seat belt, a belt-through
member is mounted at an upper distal end of the seatback to guide a
shoulder belt of the seat belt, which is pulled out from the retractor, so as to
restrain a shoulder portion of a seat occupant, both ends of a lap belt of the
seat belt, which restrain a waist portion of the seat occupant, are supported
with fixed portions located at both sides of the seat cushion, and a distal end
of the shoulder belt is further supported with one of the fixed portions; and</claim-text><claim-text>a seatback frame having:
<claim-text><claim-text>a pipe frame formed along an external shape of the seatback; and</claim-text><claim-text>a vertically extending tower frame located in the seatback at the same
side as the belt-through member and fixedly connected to the pipe frame,</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the tower frame includes an outer side bracket, an inner side
bracket, both of which are formed of vertically extending, elongated metal
sheets each formed in a substantially C-shaped cross section and both of
which are coupled to one another in abutting engagement with one another
to form an internal space, and an intermediate brace member incorporated in
the internal space to provide a reinforcement rib structure.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
