<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1260991-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1260991" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="26967695" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021127">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1260991-A1" status="new" fvid="23610404">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1260991</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20021127</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02253445-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02253445</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020515</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="US-29301501-P" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>29301501</doc-number>
          <kind>P</kind>
          <date>20010523</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
      <priority-claim ucid="US-96180801-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>96180801</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010924</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  38/00        20060101ALI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  38/00        20060101CLI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   9/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   9/26        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01B   3/30        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01B   3/30        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01B   3/46        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01B   3/46        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01B  17/56        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01B  17/56        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01L  21/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01L  21/314       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01L  21/316       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01L  21/70        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01L  21/768       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01L  23/52        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01L  23/522       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H01B   3/46</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H01L  21/316P</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Poröse Materialien</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Porous materials</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Matériaux poreux</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SHIPLEY CO LLC</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SHIPLEY CO. L.L.C.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Shipley Co. L.L.C.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>455 Forest Street</street>
              <city>Marlborough, MA 01752</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GALLAGHER MICHAEL K</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GORE ROBERT H</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>LAMOLA ANGELO A</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YOU YUJIAN</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GALLAGHER, MICHAEL K.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GORE, ROBERT H.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>LAMOLA, ANGELO A.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>YOU, YUJIAN</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>GALLAGHER, MICHAEL K.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>15 Washington Lane</street>
              <city>Hopkinton, Massachusetts 01748</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>GORE, ROBERT H.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1388 Cushmore Road</street>
              <city>Southampton, Pennsylvani 18966</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>LAMOLA, ANGELO A.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1655 Woodbridge Lane</street>
              <city>Worcester, Pennsylvania 19490</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>YOU, YUJIAN</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1 Kipling Court</street>
              <city>Lansdale, Pennsylvania 19446</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Kent, Venetia Katherine</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Rohm and Haas (UK) Ltd European Operations Patent Dept. Lennig House 2 Mason's Avenue</street>
              <city>Croydon, CR9 3NB</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>Porous dielectric materials having low dielectric constants &gt; 30% porosity and a closed
cell pore structure are disclosed along with methods of preparing the materials. Such materials
are particularly suitable for use in the manufacture of electronic devices.</p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Background of the Invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0001">This invention relates generally to the field of porous materials. In particular, this
invention relates to porous dielectric materials useful in the manufacture of electronic devices.</p>
    <p num="0002">As electronic devices become smaller, there is a continuing desire in the electronics
industry to increase the circuit density in electronic components, such as integrated circuits,
circuit boards, multichip modules, chip test devices, and the like, without degrading electrical
performance. At the same time, it is desirable to increase the speed of signal propagation in
these components. One method of accomplishing these goals is to reduce the dielectric constant
of the interlayer, or intermetal, insulating material used in the components. A method for
reducing the dielectric constant of such interlayer, or intermetal, insulating material is to
incorporate within the insulating film very small, uniformly dispersed pores or voids.</p>
    <p num="0003">Porous dielectric matrix materials are well-known in the art. One known process of
making a porous dielectric involves co-polymerizing a thermally labile monomer with a
dielectric monomer to form a block copolymer, followed by heating to decompose the thermally
labile monomer unit. See, for example, U.S. Patent No. 5,776,990 (Hedrick et al.). In this
approach, the amount of the thermally labile monomer unit is limited to amounts less than about
30% by volume. If more than about 30% by volume of the thermally labile monomer is used,
the resulting dielectric material has cylindrical or lamellar domains, instead of pores or voids,
which lead to interconnected or collapsed structures upon removal, e.g., heating to degrade the
thermally labile monomer unit. See, for example, Carter et. al., <i>Polyimide Nanofoams from
Phase-Separated Block Copolymers,</i><u style="single">Electrochemical Society Proceedings</u>, volume 97-8, pages
32-43 (1997). Thus, the block copolymer approach provides only a limited reduction in the
dielectric constant of the matrix material.</p>
    <p num="0004">Dielectric materials for use in integrated circuit manufacture have been reported having
up to 30% porosity with closed cells. However, such report failed to describe how to achieve
such high porosity while maintaining closed cells, i.e. with no interconnectivity between the
pores. Conventional methods of making porous dielectric materials fail to achieve closed cell
porosity above 30%. As a result, conventional methods provide porous dielectric materials 
having 30% porosity with interconnected pores. This pore interconnectivity can lead to
degraded electrical performance, such as crosstalk.</p>
    <p num="0005">Therefore, there is a need for porous dielectric materials having 30% porosity or greater,
wherein the pores are not interconnected, particularly for use in the manufacture of electronic
devices.</p>
    <p num="0006">In general, the size and nature of porosity is easy to probe in a solid bulk sample.
Typical techniques to probe the pore structure and pore dimensions include nitrogen and
mercury porosimetry, xenon nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy, and ultrasound. Methods
of analyzing particles in solutions and adsorption of gases are outlined in Hemnitz, <u style="single">Principles of
Colloid and Surface Chemistry</u>, Marcel Dekker, New York, p 489-544. However, all of these
techniques are unsuitable when trying to elucidate the nature of a thin film on a silicon wafer. In
this special case the volume of material is too small relative to the weight and mass of the silicon
substrate so that these techniques do not effectively probe the pore structure present in the film.
Thus new techniques have been applied to this problem such as PALS or SANS which require
nuclear reactors to generate the positronium ions or neutron particles respectively and therefore
are too expensive and complex for use in a commercial laboratory or manufacturing facility.</p>
    <p num="0007">Therefore, there is a need for an improved method for determining the interconnectivity
of pores in a thin, porous dielectric film.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Summary of the Invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0008">It has been surprisingly found that porous dielectric materials can be prepared having
grater than 30% porosity while maintaining a closed cell pore structure. Nanoporous closed cell
films above 30% can be prepared by selecting the pore-forming particle and its particle size.</p>
    <p num="0009">In a first aspect, the present invention provides a closed cell porous dielectric material
suitable for use in electronic device manufacture, the porous dielectric material having greater
than or equal to 30% porosity.</p>
    <p num="0010">In a second aspect, the present invention provides a closed cell porous organo polysilica
dielectric film suitable for use in electronic device manufacture, the porous organo polysilica
dielectric material having greater than or equal to 30% porosity. </p>
    <p num="0011">In a third aspect, the present invention provides a method of manufacturing a porous
dielectric material suitable for use in electronic device manufacture including the steps of: a)
dispersing a plurality of removable polymeric porogen particles in a B-staged dielectric material,
b) curing the B-staged dielectric material to form a dielectric matrix material without
substantially degrading the porogen particles; c) subjecting the dielectric matrix material to
conditions which at least partially remove the porogen to form a porous dielectric material
without substantially degrading the dielectric material; wherein the porogen is substantially
compatible with the B-staged dielectric material; wherein the dielectric material is ≥ 30%
porous; and wherein the mean particle size of the plurality of porogen particles is selected to
provide a closed cell pore structure.</p>
    <p num="0012">In a fourth aspect, the present invention provides a method of manufacturing a porous
organo polysilica dielectric material suitable for use in electronic device manufacture including
the steps of: a) dispersing a plurality of removable polymeric porogen particles in a B-staged
organo polysilica dielectric material, b) curing the B-staged organo polysilica dielectric material
to form a dielectric matrix material without substantially degrading the porogen particles; c)
subjecting the organo polysilica dielectric matrix material to conditions which at least partially
remove the porogen to form a porous dielectric material without substantially degrading the
organo polysilica dielectric material; wherein the porogen is substantially compatible with the B-staged
organo polysilica dielectric material and wherein the porogen includes as polymerized
units at least one compound selected from silyl containing monomers or poly(alkylene oxide)
monomers; wherein the dielectric material is ≥ 30% porous; and wherein the mean particle size
of the plurality of porogen particles is selected to provide a closed cell pore structure.</p>
    <p num="0013">In a fifth aspect, the present invention provides a method of preparing an integrated
circuit with a closed cell porous film including the steps of: a) depositing on a substrate a layer
of a composition including B-staged organo polysilica dielectric material having polymeric
porogen dispersed therein; b) curing the B-staged organo polysilica dielectric material to form an
organo polysilica dielectric matrix material without substantially removing the porogen; c)
subjecting the organo polysilica dielectric matrix material to conditions which at least partially
remove the porogen to form a porous organo polysilica dielectric material layer without
substantially degrading the organo polysilica dielectric material; d) patterning the porous
dielectric layer; e) depositing a metallic film onto the patterned porous dielectric layer; and f) 
planarizing the film to form an integrated circuit; wherein the porogen is substantially
compatible with the B-staged organo polysilica dielectric material and wherein the porogen
includes as polymerized units at least one compound selected from silyl containing monomers or
poly(alkylene oxide) monomers; and wherein the dielectric material is ≥ 30% porous.</p>
    <p num="0014">In a sixth aspect, the present invention provides a method of preparing an integrated
circuit with a closed cell porous film including the steps of: a) depositing on a substrate a layer
of a composition including B-staged dielectric material having a plurality of polymeric porogens
dispersed therein; b) curing the B-staged dielectric material to form a dielectric matrix material
without substantially removing the porogens; c) subjecting the dielectric matrix material to
conditions which at least partially remove the porogens to form a porous dielectric material layer
without substantially degrading the dielectric material; d) patterning the porous dielectric layer;
e) depositing a metallic film onto the patterned porous dielectric layer; and f) planarizing the
film to form an integrated circuit; wherein the porogen is substantially compatible with the B-staged
dielectric material; and wherein the dielectric material is ≥ 30% porous; and wherein the
mean particle size of the porogens is selected to provide a closed cell pore structure.</p>
    <p num="0015">In a seventh aspect, the present invention provides an integrated circuit including a
porous dielectric material wherein the porous dielectric material ≥ 30% porous; wherein the
pores are substantially non-interconnected; and wherein the mean particle size of the pores is
selected to provide a closed cell pore structure.</p>
    <p num="0016">In an eighth aspect, the present invention provides an electronic device including a
porous dielectric layer free of an added cap layer, wherein the porous dielectric layer has ≥ 30%
porosity.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Brief Description of the Drawing</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0017">FIG. 1 illustrates a modified Randles circuit.</p>
    <p num="0018">FIG. 2 illustrates a test cell for determining the pore structure of porous thin film
materials.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Detailed Description of the Invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0019">As used throughout this specification, the following abbreviations shall have the
following meanings, unless the context clearly indicates otherwise: °C = degrees centigrade; µm
= micron; UV = ultraviolet; ppm = parts per million; nm = nanometer; S/m = Siemens per meter;
g = gram; wt% = weight percent; Hz = herz; kHz = kiloherz; mV = millivolts; MIAK = methyl
iso-amyl ketone; MIBK = methyl iso-butyl ketone; PMA = poly(methyl acrylate); CyHMA =
cyclohexylmethacrylate; EG = ethylene glycol; DPG = dipropylene glycol; DEA = diethylene
glycol ethyl ether acetate; BzA = benzylacrylate; BzMA = benzyl methacrylate; MAPS = MATS
= (trimethoxylsilyl)propylmethacrylate; PETTA = pentacrythriol tetra/triacetate; PPG4000DMA
= polypropyleneglycol 4000 dimethacrylate; DPEPA = dipentaerythriol pentaacrylate; TMSMA
= trimethylsilyl methacrylate; MOPTSOMS =
methacryloxypropylbis(trimethylsiloxy)methylsilane; MOPMDMOS = 3-methacryloxypropylmethyldimethoxysilane;
TAT = triallyl-1,3,5-triazine-2,4,6-(1H,3H,5H)-trione;
IBOMA isobornyl methacrylate; PGMEA = propyleneglycol monomethylether acetate;
and PGDMA = propyleneglycol dimethacrylate; PPODMMST = poly(propylene oxide),
bis(dimethoxymethylsilyl); TMOPTMA =trimethylolpropane trimethacrylate; TMOPTA =
trimethylolpropane triacrylate; BPEPDMS = bis polyetherpolydimethylsilane; PPGMEA260 =
poly(propylene glycol) methyl ether acrylate having a molecular weight of about 260;
PPGMEA475 = poly(propylene glycol) methyl ether acrylate having a molecular weight of
about 475; VTMS = vinyltrimethylsilane; and VTMOS = vinyltrimethoxysilane.</p>
    <p num="0020">The term "(meth)acrylic" includes both acrylic and methacrylic and the term
"(meth)acrylate" includes both acrylate and methacrylate. Likewise, the term
"(meth)acrylamide" refers to both acrylamide and methacrylamide. "Alkyl" includes straight
chain, branched and cyclic alkyl groups. The term "porogen" refers to a pore forming material,
that is a polymeric material or particle dispersed in a dielectric material that is subsequently
removed to yield pores, voids or free volume in the dielectric material. Thus, the terms
"removable porogen," "removable polymer" and "removable particle" are used interchangeably
throughout this specification. The terms "pore," "void" and "free volume" are used
interchangeably throughout this specification. "Cross-linker" and "cross-linking agent" are used
interchangeably throughout this specification, "Polymer" refers to polymers and oligomers. The
term "polymer" also includes homopolymers and copolymers. The terms "oligomer" and
"oligomeric" refer to dimers, trimers, tetramers and the like. "Monomer" refers to any 
ethylenically or acetylenically unsaturated compound capable of being polymerized. Such
monomers may contain one or more double or triple bonds.</p>
    <p num="0021">The term "B-staged" refers to uncured dielectric matrix materials. By "uncured" is
meant any material that can be polymerized or cured, such as by condensation, to form higher
molecular weight materials, such as coatings or films. Such B-staged material may be
monomeric, oligomeric or mixtures thereof. B-staged material is further intended to include
mixtures of polymeric material with monomers, oligomers or a mixture of monomers and
oligomers. The dielectric films described herein are described as either the polymerized or cured
materials, or as the monomer units or oligomers used to prepare such polymerized or cured
dielectric films.</p>
    <p num="0022">"Halo" refers to fluoro, chloro, bromo and iodo. Likewise, "halogenated" refers to
fluorinated, chlorinated, brominated and iodinated. Unless otherwise noted, all amounts are
percent by weight and all ratios are by weight. All numerical ranges are inclusive and
combinable.</p>
    <p num="0023">The present invention relates to porous dielectric materials having a closed cell pore
structure and ≥ 30% porosity. Such porous materials are useful in the fabrication of electronic
and optoelectronic devices.</p>
    <p num="0024">Thus, the present invention provides a closed cell porous dielectric material suitable for
use in electronic device manufacture, the porous dielectric material having greater than or equal
to 30% porosity. A wide variety of dielectric materials may be used in the present invention.
Suitable dielectric materials include, but are not limited to: inorganic matrix materials such as
carbides, oxides, nitrides and oxyfluorides of silicon, boron, or aluminum; silicones; siloxanes,
such as silsesquioxanes; organo polysilica materials; silicates; silazanes; and organic matrix
materials such as benzocyclobutenes, poly(aryl esters), poly(ether ketones), polycarbonates,
polyimides, fluorinated polyimides, polynorbornenes, poly(arylene ethers), polyaromatic
hydrocarbons, such as polynaphthalene, polyquinoxalines, poly(perfluorinated hydrocarbons)
such as poly(tetrafluoroethylene), and polybenzoxazoles. Particularly suitable dielectric
materials are those available under the tradenames TEFLON, SILK, AVATREL, BCB, AEROGEL,
XEROGEL, PARYLENE F, and PARYLENE N. </p>
    <p num="0025">Suitable organo polysilica materials are those including silicon, carbon, oxygen and
hydrogen atoms and having the formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/">((RR<sup>1</sup>SiO)<sub>n</sub>(R<sup>2</sup>SiO<sub>1.5</sub>)<sub>b</sub>(R<sup>3</sup>SiO<sub>1.5</sub>)<sub>c</sub>(SiO<sub>2</sub>)<sub>d</sub>)<sub>n</sub></st32:che>
wherein R, R<sup>1</sup>, R<sup>2</sup> and R<sup>3</sup> are independently selected from hydrogen, (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkyl, aryl, and
substituted aryl; a, c and d are independently a number from 0 to 1; b is a number from 0.2 to 1;
n is integer from about 3 to about 10,000; provided that a + b + c + d = 1; and provided that at
least one of R, R<sup>1</sup> and R<sup>2</sup> is not hydrogen. "Substituted aryl" refers to an aryl group having one
or more of its hydrogens replaced by another substituent group, such as cyano, hydroxy,
mercapto, halo, (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkyl, (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkoxy, and the like. In the above formula, a, b, c and d
represent the mole ratios of each component. Such mole ratios can be varied between 0 and
about 1. It is preferred that a is from 0 to about 0.8. It is also preferred that c is from 0 to about
0.8. It is further preferred that d is from 0 to about 0.8. In the above formula, n refers to the
number of repeat units in the B-staged material. Preferably, n is an integer from about 3 to about
1000. It will be appreciated that prior to any curing step, the B-staged organo polysilica
dielectric matrix materials may include one or more of hydroxyl or alkoxy end capping or side
chain functional groups. Such end capping or side chain functional groups are known to those
skilled in the art.</p>
    <p num="0026">Suitable organo polysilica dielectric matrix materials include, but are not limited to,
silsesquioxanes, partially condensed halosilanes or alkoxysilanes such as partially condensed by
controlled hydrolysis of tetraethoxysilane having number average molecular weight of about 500
to about 20,000, organically modified silicates having the composition RSiO<sub>3</sub> or R<sub>2</sub>SiO<sub>2</sub> wherein
R is an organic substituent, and partially condensed orthosilicates having Si(OR)<sub>4</sub> as the
monomer unit. Silsesquioxanes are polymeric silicate materials of the type RSiO<sub>1.5</sub> where R is
an organic substituent. Suitable silsesquioxanes are alkyl silsesquioxanes such as methyl
silsesquioxane, ethyl silsesquioxane, propyl silsesquioxane, butyl silsesquioxane and the like;
aryl silsesquioxanes such as phenyl silsesquioxane and tolyl silsesquioxane; alkyl/aryl
silsesquioxane mixtures such as a mixture of methyl silsesquioxane and phenyl silsesquioxane;
and mixtures of alkyl silsesquioxanes such as methyl silsesquioxane and ethyl silsesquioxane.
B-staged silsesquioxane materials include homopolymers of silsesquioxanes, copolymers of 
silsesquioxanes or mixtures thereof. Such dielectric materials are generally commercially
available or may be prepared by known methods.</p>
    <p num="0027">It is preferred that the organo polysilica is a silsesquioxane, and more preferably methyl
silsesquioxane, ethyl silsesquioxane, propyl silsesquioxane, iso-butyl silsesquioxane, tert-butyl
silsesquioxane, phenyl silsesquioxane or mixtures thereof. Particularly useful silsesquioxanes
include mixtures of hydrido silsesquioxanes with alkyl, aryl or alkyl/aryl silsesquioxanes. Other
particularly useful silsesquioxanes include combinations of alkyl or aryl silsesquioxanes with
tetra(C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkylorthosilicates such as tetraethylorthosilicate, or copolymers or composites
thereof. Exemplary combinations of alkyl silsesquioxanes with tetra(C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkylorthosilicate are
disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 4,347,609 (Fukuyama et al.). Also suitable are cohydrolysates of
tetra(C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkylorthosilicates or silicon tetrachloride with a compound of the formula RSiX<sub>3</sub>,
wherein R is selected from (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkyl or aryl; and X is selected from halo, (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>4</sub>)alkoxy or
acyloxy. Typically, the silsesquioxanes useful in the present invention are used as oligomeric
materials, generally having from about 3 to about 10,000 repeating units.</p>
    <p num="0028">Other suitable silsesquioxane compositions include, but arc not limited to: hydrogen
silsesquioxane, alkyl silsesquioxane such as methyl silsesquioxane, aryl silsesquioxane such as
phenyl silsesquioxane, and mixtures thereof, such as alkyl/hydrogen, aryl/hydrogen, alkyl/aryl
silsesquioxane or alkyl/aryl/hydrido silsesquioxane. It is preferred that the dielectric material
comprises a silsesquioxane, more preferably a combination of a silsesquioxane with a tetra(C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkylorthosilicates,
and still more preferably a combination of methyl silsesquioxane with
tetraethylorthosilicate.</p>
    <p num="0029">Also provided by the present invention is a closed cell porous organo polysilica dielectric
film suitable for use in electronic device manufacture, the porous organo polysilica dielectric
film having greater than or equal to 30% porosity. The present invention further provides a
closed cell porous film comprising hydrogen silsesquioxane as monomer units for use in
electronic device manufacture, the porous film having greater than or equal to 30% porosity.</p>
    <p num="0030">It will be appreciated that a mixture of dielectric materials may be used, such as two or
more organo polysilica dielectric materials or a mixture of an organo polysilica dielectric matrix
material with one or more other dielectric matrix materials, i.e. not an organo polysilica
dielectric matrix material. Suitable other dielectric matrix materials include, but are not limited 
to, inorganic matrix materials such as carbides, oxides, nitrides and oxyfluorides of silicon,
boron, or aluminum; and organic matrix materials such as benzocyclobutenes, poly(aryl esters),
poly(ether ketones), polycarbonates, polyimides, fluorinated polyimides, polynorbornenes,
poly(arylene ethers), polyaromatic hydrocarbons, such as polynaphthalene, polyquinoxalines,
poly(perfluorinated hydrocarbons) such as poly(tetrafluoroethylene), and polybenzoxazoles.</p>
    <p num="0031">It is preferred that when a mixture of an organo polysilica dielectric matrix material and
another dielectric matrix material is used, the organo polysilica dielectric matrix material is
present as a predominant component. It is further preferred that the organo polysilica dielectric
matrix material in such admixtures is methyl silsesquioxane, phenyl silsesquioxane or mixtures
thereof.</p>
    <p num="0032">Porous dielectric materials having a wide variety of porosities can be prepared according
to the present invention. Typically, the porous materials have a porosity of ≥ 30% by volume,
preferably ≥ 35%, more preferably ≥ 40%, and even more preferably ≥ 45%. Porosities of 50%
can also be achieved according to the present invention. Such porosity is a measure of the total
volume of pores in the dielectric material.</p>
    <p num="0033">The pore structure of the porous thin film dielectric materials of the present invention can
be determined by a variety of methods. Preferably, an electrochemical test is used to measure an
electrical property of the material, such as impedance, conductivity and the like. Particularly
suitable is electrochemical impedance spectroscopy ("EIS").</p>
    <p num="0034">Dielectric films typically have a very high impedance. When the film matrix contains
open channels, a decrease in impedance is recorded as solvent and ions penetrate the film. When
monitored by EIS, these phenomena can evaluate the porosity of the dielectric film.</p>
    <p num="0035">In an EIS experiment, a variable frequency alternating current ("AC") potential is applied
to a system and the current is measured. The response follows Ohm's law, (E = IZ) where the
current ("I") and the impedance ("Z") are represented by complex numbers. The frequency-independent
impedance is related to resistance ("R") and the frequency-dependent impedance is
related to capacitance ("C"), When the data are computer modeled, a modified Randles circuit
adequately describes the sample's behavior. A suitable Randles circuit is shown in FIG. 1,
where R<sub>ct</sub> is the resistance for the charge transfer and C<sub>dl</sub> is the double layer capacitance. This 
model accounts for electrode interfacial reactions ("<img id="img-00100001" orientation="unknown" wi="4" img-format="tif" img-content="ff" file="00100001.tif" inline="no" he="4"/>") as well as the sample's resistance
("R<sub>po</sub>") and sample's capacitance ("C<sub>c</sub>").</p>
    <p num="0036">This R<sub>po</sub> resistance is an indication of the rate of mass transport of ions into ionically
conducting low resistive channels in the film. Values of R<sub>po</sub> are, therefore, related to the film's
ionic conductivity, according to the formula
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">R<st32:sub pos="post">po</st32:sub> = ρd = (σ)<st32:sup pos="post">-1</st32:sup> =(µ c n z)<st32:sup pos="post">-1</st32:sup></st32:df>
where ρ is resistivity, d is electrode separation distance, σ is conductance, µ is mobility, c is the
charge on an electron, n is the number of electrons, and z is charge on an ion.</p>
    <p num="0037">A capacitor is formed when a non-conducting media separates two conducting plates. In
the case of a doped silicon wafer, coated with a dielectric, and immersed in solution, the wafer is
one plate, the film is the non-conducting media, and the solution is the second plate. The
capacitance of this system is dependent on solvent penetration into the film. In the case of water,
the large difference between the dielectric constant of water (78) and that of the non-conducting
film (1.1-4.1) results in changes to C<sub>c</sub> reflecting changes in the dielectric constant of the film.
Changes in C<sub>c</sub> reflect changes in the dielectric constant of the sample according to the formula
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">C<st32:sub pos="post">c</st32:sub> = (εε<st32:sub pos="post">o</st32:sub>/d) A</st32:df>
where ε is the dielectric constant, ε<sub>o</sub> is the permittivity of free space, and A is the electrode area.</p>
    <p num="0038">Referring to FIG. 2, the pore interconnectivity of a porous dielectric film is measured by
placing a glass ball joint <b>1</b>, such as a PYREX™ glass ball, along with a rubber o-ring against the
thin, porous dielectric layer <b>2</b> deposited onto a conductive silicon wafer <b>3</b>. The resistivity ("R")
of such a conductive silicon wafer is typically &lt;0.02 Ohm-cm. The ball joint is held in place by
a fastening means, such as a clamp, and an aqueous reference standard solution <b>4</b> is charged into
the ball joint. Suitable reference solutions include, but are not limited to a 10,000 ppm of copper
(as copper nitrate) ICP standard solution in 5% nitric acid or 0.1 molar copper chloride in water.
A platinum electrode <b>5</b> is placed into the reference solution and then a second reference
electrode is also inserted into the solution. The back side of the wafer, i.e. the side opposite the
film, is also contacted with an electrode <b>6.</b> A measuring or monitoring system <b>7</b> is used to record
an electrical measurement, such as impedance, capacitance, leakage current and the like. When
measuring impedance, a suitable measuring system is a Solartron 1260 Gain/Phase Analyzer, 
EG&amp;G Princeton Applied Research (PAR) 273 potentiostat/Galvanostat, and Zplot Impedance
Software (available from Scribner Associates) used to measure impedance. Individual data files
collected are fitted to a modified Randles circuit, (Zsim Impedance software from Scribner
Associates), and their impedance parameters are plotted and compared as a function of time.</p>
    <p num="0039">The reference standard solution is allowed to remain in contact with the film for 24 hours
and the impedance is measured again. The values are compared to those for a film of the same
composition that is non-porous. Differences in conductivity values of less than 1 S/m, as
determined using the EIS method, indicate closed cell pore structures. Differences in
conductivity values of greater than 1 S/m, as determined using the EIS method, indicate open
cell pore structures.</p>
    <p num="0040">One of the advantages of the present invention is that the porous dielectric materials have
closed cell pore structures. By "closed cell" pore structures, it is meant that the pores within the
porous dielectric material are substantially non-interconnected, and preferably are not
interconnected. By "substantially" non-interconnected it is meant that less than 10%, preferably
less than 5%, and more preferably less than 2% of the pores are interconnected.</p>
    <p num="0041">The high levels of porosity and the closed cell pore structures of the present porous
dielectric materials are achieved by selecting porogens that are substantially compatible with the
dielectric material and that have a mean particle size such that a closed cell pore structure is
obtained.</p>
    <p num="0042">By "compatible" it is meant that a composition of B-staged dielectric material and
porogen are optically transparent to visible light. It is preferred that a solution of B-staged
dielectric material and porogen, a film or layer including a composition of B-staged dielectric
material and porogen, a composition including a dielectric matrix material having porogen
dispersed therein, and the resulting porous dielectric material after removal of the porogen are all
optically transparent to visible light. By "substantially compatible" it is meant that a
composition of B-staged dielectric material and porogen is slightly cloudy or slightly opaque.
Preferably, "substantially compatible" means at least one of a solution of B-staged dielectric
material and porogen, a film or layer including a composition of B-staged dielectric material and
porogen, a composition including a dielectric matrix material having porogen dispersed therein, 
and the resulting porous dielectric material after removal of the porogen is slightly cloudy or
slightly opaque.</p>
    <p num="0043">To be compatible, the porogen must be soluble or miscible in the B-staged dielectric
material, in the solvent used to dissolve the B-staged dielectric material or both. When a film or
layer of a composition including the B-staged dielectric material, porogen and solvent is cast,
such as by spin casting, much of the solvent evaporates. After such film casting, the porogen
must be soluble in the B-staged dielectric material so that it remains substantially uniformly
dispersed. If the porogen is not compatible, phase separation of the porogen from the B-staged
dielectric material occurs and large domains or aggregates form, resulting in an increase in the
size and non-uniformity of pores. Such compatible porogens provide cured dielectric materials
having substantially uniformly dispersed pores having substantially the same sizes as the
porogen particles. Thus, the mean diameter of the resulting pores is substantially the same as the
mean particle size of the porogen used to form the pores.</p>
    <p num="0044">The compatibility of the porogens and dielectric matrix material is typically determined
by a matching of their solubility parameters, such as the Van Krevelen parameters of delta h and
delta v. See, for example, Van Krevelen et al., <u style="single">Properties of Polymers. Their Estimation and
Correlation with Chemical Structure,</u> Elsevier Scientific Publishing Co., 1976; Olabisi et al.,
<u style="single">Polymer-Polymer Miscibility</u>, Academic Press, NY, 1979; Coleman et al., <u style="single">Specific Interactions
and the Miscibility of Polymer Blends,</u> Technomic, 1991; and A. F. M. Barton, <u style="single">CRC Handbook
of Solubility Parameters and Other Cohesion Parameters</u>, 2<sup>nd</sup> Ed., CRC Press, 1991. Delta h is a
hydrogen bonding parameter of the material and delta v is a measurement of both dispersive and
polar interaction of the material. Such solubility parameters may either be calculated, such as by
the group contribution method, or determined by measuring the cloud point of the material in a
mixed solvent system consisting of a soluble solvent and an insoluble solvent. The solubility
parameter at the cloud point is defined as the weighted percentage of the solvents. Typically, a
number of cloud points are measured for the material and the central area defined by such cloud
points is defined as the area of solubility parameters of the material.</p>
    <p num="0045">When the solubility parameters of the porogen and dielectric matrix material are
substantially similar, the porogen will be compatible with the dielectric matrix material and
phase separation and/or aggregation of the porogen is less likely to occur. It is preferred that the 
solubility parameters, particularly delta h and delta v, of the porogen and dielectric matrix
material are substantially matched. It will be appreciated by those skilled in the art that the
properties of the porogen that affect the porogen's solubility also affect the compatibility of that
porogen with the B-staged dielectric material. It will be further appreciated by those skilled in
the art that a porogen may be compatible with one B-staged dielectric material, but not another.
This is due to the difference in the solubility parameters of the different B-staged dielectric
materials,</p>
    <p num="0046">The compatible, i.e., optically transparent, compositions of the present invention do not
suffer from agglomeration or long range ordering of porogen materials, i.e. the porogen is
substantially uniformly dispersed throughout the B-staged dielectric material. Thus, the porous
dielectric materials resulting from removal of the porogen have substantially uniformly
dispersed pores. Such substantially uniformly dispersed, very small pores are very effective in
reducing the dielectric constant of the dielectric materials.</p>
    <p num="0047">The porogens used to form the present highly porous dielectric materials have a particle
size selected to maintain a closed cell structure at a given porosity. Too small a pore size may
result in an open cell, or interconnected, pore structure for a give porosity of the dielectric
material. A porogen having a particular particle size that provides a closed cell structure at 30%
porosity may provide an open cell pore structure at higher levels of porosity. For example, for
porous dielectric materials having ≥ 30% porosity, the porogens must have a particle size greater
than 2,5 nm. For 30% porosity, it is preferred that the porogen has a particle size ≥ 2.75 nm, and
preferably ≥ 3 nm. Typically, for dielectric materials having a porosity of 30% to 35%, a
porogen having a particle size in the range of 2,75 to 4 nm is selected, and preferably 3 to 3.5
nm. For dielectric materials having a porosity of 35% to 40%, a porogen having a particle size
in the range of 3.5 to 8 nm, and preferably 4 to 7 nm, is selected. For dielectric materials having
a porosity of 40% to 45%, a porogen having a particle size in ≥ 5 nm is selected, preferably 5 to
15 nm, more preferably 5 to 11 nm, and even more preferably 5 to 7 nm. If the size of the
porogen is too large, the resulting pores in the dielectric material will be too large to be suitable
for advanced electronic devices having very narrow linewidths. Thus, there is an optimum range
of pore sizes useful for providing porous dielectric materials having closed cell pore structures. </p>
    <p num="0048">A wide variety of porogens are suitable for use in the present invention. The porogen
polymers are typically cross-linked particles and have a molecular weight and particle size
suitable for use as a modifier in advanced interconnect structures in electronic devices.
Typically, the useful particle size range for such applications is up to about 100 nm, such as that
having a mean particle size in the range of about 0.5 to about 100 nm. However, for the present
closed cell porous dielectric materials, it is preferred that the mean particle size is in the range of
about 2.75 to about 20 nm, more preferably from about 3 to about 15 nm, and most preferably
from about 3 nm to about 10 nm. An advantage of the present process is that the size of the
pores formed in the dielectric matrix are substantially the same size, i.e., dimension, as the size
of the removed porogen particles used. Thus, the porous dielectric material made by the process
of the present invention has substantially uniformly dispersed pores with substantially uniform
pore sizes having a mean pore size in the range of from 2.75 to 20 nm, preferably 3 to 15 nm,
and more preferably 3 and 10 nm.</p>
    <p num="0049">The polymers suitable for use as porogens in the present invention are derived from
ethylenically or acetylenically unsaturated monomers and are removable, such as by the
unzipping of the polymer chains to the original monomer units which are volatile and diffuse
readily through the host matrix material. By "removable" is meant that the polymer particles
depolymerize, degrade or otherwise break down into volatile components which can then diffuse
through the host dielectric matrix film. Suitable unsaturated monomers include, but are not
limited to: (meth)acrylic acid, (meth)acrylamides, alkyl (meth)acrylates, alkenyl
(meth)acrylates, aromatic (meth)acrylates, vinyl aromatic monomers, nitrogen-containing
compounds and their thio-analogs, and substituted ethylene monomers.</p>
    <p num="0050">Typically, the alkyl (meth)acrylates useful in the present invention are (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>24</sub>) alkyl
(meth)acrylates. Suitable alkyl (meth)acrylates include, but are not limited to, "low cut" alkyl
(meth)acrylates, "mid cut" alkyl (meth)acrylates and "high cut" alkyl (meth)acrylates.</p>
    <p num="0051">"Low cut" alkyl (meth)acrylates are typically those where the alkyl group contains from
1 to 6 carbon atoms. Suitable low cut alkyl (meth)acrylates include, but are not limited to:
methyl methacrylate ("MMA"), methyl acrylate, ethyl acrylate, propyl methacrylate, butyl
methacrylate ("BMA"), butyl acrylate ("BA"), isobutyl methacrylate ("IBMA"), hexyl
methacrylate, cyclohexyl methacrylate, cyclohexyl acrylate and mixtures thereof. </p>
    <p num="0052">"Mid cut" alkyl (meth)acrylates are typically those where the alkyl group contains from 7
to 15 carbon atoms. Suitable mid cut alkyl (meth)acrylates include, but are not limited to: 2-ethylhexyl
acrylate ("EHA"), 2-ethylhexyl methacrylate, octyl methacrylate, decyl methacrylate,
isodecyl methacrylate ("IDMA", based on branched (C<sub>10</sub>)alkyl isomer mixture), undecyl
methacrylate, dodecyl methacrylate (also known as lauryl methacrylate), tridecyl methacrylate,
tetradecyl methacrylate (also known as myristyl methacrylate), pentadecyl methacrylate and
mixtures thereof. Particularly useful mixtures include dodecyl-pentadecyl methacrylate
("DPMA"), a mixture of linear and branched isomers of dodecyl, tridecyl, tetradecyl and
pentadecyl methacrylates; and lauryl-myristyl methacrylate ("LMA").</p>
    <p num="0053">"High cut" alkyl (meth)acrylates are typically those where the alkyl group contains from
16 to 24 carbon atoms. Suitable high cut alkyl (meth)acrylates include, but are not limited to:
hexadecyl methacrylate, heptadecyl methacrylate, octadecyl methacrylate, nonadecyl
methacrylate, cosyl methacrylate, eicosyl methacrylate and mixtures thereof. Particularly useful
mixtures of high cut alkyl (meth)acrylates include, but are not-limited to: cetyl-eicosyl
methacrylate ("CEMA"), which is a mixture of hexadecyl, octadecyl, cosyl and eicosyl
methacrylate; and cetyl-stcaryl methacrylate ("SMA"), which is a mixture of hexadecyl and
octadecyl methacrylate.</p>
    <p num="0054">The mid-cut and high-cut alkyl (meth)acrylate monomers described above are generally
prepared by standard esterification procedures using technical grades of long chain aliphatic
alcohols, and these commercially available alcohols are mixtures of alcohols of varying chain
lengths containing between 10 and 15 or 16 and 20 carbon atoms in the alkyl group. Examples
of these alcohols are the various Ziegler catalyzed ALFOL alcohols from Vista Chemical
company, i.e., ALFOL 1618 and ALFOL 1620, Ziegler catalyzed various NEODOL alcohols from
Shell Chemical Company, i.e. NEODOL 25L, and naturally derived alcohols such as Proctor &amp;
Gamble's TA-1618 and CO-1270, Consequently, for the purposes of this invention, alkyl
(meth)acrylate is intended to include not only the individual alkyl (meth)acrylate product named,
but also to include mixtures of the alkyl (meth)acrylates with a predominant amount of the
particular alkyl (meth)acrylate named.</p>
    <p num="0055">The alkyl (meth)acrylate monomers useful in the present invention may be a single
monomer or a mixture having different numbers of carbon atoms in the alkyl portion. Also, the 
(meth)acrylamide and alkyl (meth)acrylate monomers useful in the present invention may
optionally be substituted. Suitable optionally substituted (meth)acrylamide and alkyl
(meth)acrylate monomers include, but are not limited to; hydroxy (C<sub>2</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkyl (meth)acrylates,
dialkylamino(C<sub>2</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)-alkyl(meth)acrylates, dialkylamino(C<sub>2</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkyl (meth)acrylamides.</p>
    <p num="0056">Particularly useful substituted alkyl (meth)acrylate monomers are those with one or
more hydroxyl groups in the alkyl radical, especially those where the hydroxyl group is found at
the β-position (2-position) in the alkyl radical. Hydroxyalkyl (meth)acrylate monomers in which
the substituted alkyl group is a (C<sub>2</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkyl, branched or unbranched, are preferred. Suitable
hydroxyalkyl (meth)acrylate monomers include, but are not limited to: 2-hydroxyethyl
methacrylate ("HEMA"), 2-hydroxycthyl acrylate ("HEA"), 2-hydroxypropyl methacrylate, 1-methyl-2-hydroxyethyl
methacrylate, 2-hydroxy-propyl acrylate, 1-methyl-2-hydroxyethyl
acrylate, 2-hydroxybutyl methacrylate, 2-hydroxybutyl acrylate and mixtures thereof. The
preferred hydroxyalkyl (meth)acrylate monomers are HEMA, 1-methyl-2-hydroxyethyl
methacrylate, 2-hydroxypropyl methacrylate and mixtures thereof. A mixture of the latter two
monomers is commonly referred to as "hydroxypropyl methacrylate" or "HPMA."</p>
    <p num="0057">Other substituted (meth)acrylate and (meth)acrylamide monomers useful in the present
invention are those with a dialkylamino group or dialkylaminoalkyl group in the alkyl radical.
Examples of such substituted (meth)acrylates and (meth)acrylamides include, but are not limited
to: dimethylaminoethyl methacrylate, dimethylaminoethyl acrylate, N,N-dimethylaminoethyl
methacrylamide, N,N-dimethyl-aminopropyl methacrylamide, N,N-dimethylaminobutyl
methacrylamide, N,N-di-ethylaminoethyl methacrylamide, N,N-diethylaminopropyl
methacrylamide, N,N-diethylaminobutyl methacrylamide, N-(1,1-dimethyl-3-oxobutyl)
acrylamide, N-(1,3-diphenyl-1-ethyl-3-oxobutyl) acrylamide, N-(1-methyl-1-phenyl-3-oxobutyl)
methacrylamide, and 2-hydroxyethyl acrylamide, N-methacrylamide of aminoethyl ethylene
urea, N-methacryloxy ethyl morpholine, N-maleimide of dimethylaminopropylamine and
mixtures thereof.</p>
    <p num="0058">Other substituted (meth)acrylate monomers useful in the present invention are silicon-containing
monomers such as γ-propyl tri(C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkoxysilyl (meth)acrylate, γ-propyl tri(C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkylsilyl
(meth)acrylate, γ-propyl di(C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkoxy(C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkylsilyl (meth)acrylate, γ-propyl
di(C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkyl(C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkoxysilyl (meth)acrylate, vinyl tri(C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkoxysilyl (meth)acrylate, vinyl 
di(C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkoxy(C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkylsilyl (meth)acrylate, vinyl (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkoxydi(C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkylsilyl
(meth)acrylate, vinyl tri(C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkylsilyl (meth)acrylate, and mixtures thereof.</p>
    <p num="0059">The vinylaromatic monomers useful as unsaturated monomers in the present invention
include, but are not limited to: styrene ("STY"), α-methylstyrene, vinyltoluene, <i>p</i>-methylstyrene,
ethylvinylbenzene, vinylnaphthalene, vinylxylenes, and mixtures thereof. The
vinylaromatic monomers also include their corresponding substituted counterparts, such as
halogenated derivatives, i.e., containing one or more halogen groups, such as fluorine, chlorine
or bromine; and nitro, cyano, (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>10</sub>)alkoxy, halo(C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>10</sub>)alkyl, carb(C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>10</sub>)alkoxy, carboxy,
amino, (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>10</sub>)alkylamino derivatives and the like.</p>
    <p num="0060">The nitrogen-containing compounds and their thio-analogs useful as unsaturated
monomers in the present invention include, but are not limited to: vinylpyridines such as 2-vinylpyridine
or 4-vinylpyridine; lower alkyl (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>8</sub>) substituted N-vinyl pyridines such as 2-mcthyl-5-vinyl-pyridine,
2-ethyl-5-vinylpyridine, 3-methyl-5-vinylpyridine, 2,3-dimethyl-5-vinyl-pyridine,
and 2-methyl-3-ethyl-5-vinylpyridine; methyl-substituted quinolines and
isoquinolines; N-vinylcaprolactam; N-vinylbutyrolactam; N-vinylpyrrolidone; vinyl imidazole;
N-vinyl carbazole; N-vinyl-succinimide; (meth)acrylonitrile; <i>o</i>-, <i>m</i>-, or <i>p</i>-aminostyrene;
maleimide; N-vinyl-oxazolidone; N,N-dimethyl aminocthyl-vinyl-ether; ethyl-2-cyano acrylate;
vinyl acctonitrile; N-vinylphthalimide; N-vinyl-pyrrolidones such as N-vinyl-thio-pyrrolidone, 3
methyl-1-vinyl-pyrrolidone, 4-methyl-1-vinyl-pyrrolidone, 5-methyl-1-vinyl-pyrrolidone, 3-ethyl-1-vinyl-pyrrolidone,
3-butyl-1-vinyl-pyrrolidone, 3,3-dimethyl-1-vinyl-pyrrolidone, 4,5-dimethyl-1-vinyl-pyrrolidone,
5,5-dimethyl-1-vinyl-pyrrolidone, 3,3,5-trimethyl-1-vinyl-pyrrolidone,
4-ethyl-1-vinyl-pyrrolidone, 5-methyl-5-ethyl-1-vinyl-pyrrolidone and 3,4,5-trimethyl-1-vinyl-pyrrolidone;
vinyl pyrroles; vinyl anilines; and vinyl piperidines.</p>
    <p num="0061">The substituted ethylene monomers useful as unsaturated monomers is in the present
invention include, but are not limited to: vinyl acetate, vinyl formamide, vinyl chloride, vinyl
fluoride, vinyl bromide, vinylidene chloride, vinylidene fluoride and vinylidene bromide.</p>
    <p num="0062">When the dielectric material is an organo polysilica material, it is preferred that
polymeric porogens include as polymerized units at least one compound selected from silyl
containing monomers or poly(alkylene oxide) monomers. Such silyl containing monomers or
poly(alkylene oxide) monomers may be used to form the uncrosslinked polymer, used as the 
crosslinker, or both. Any monomer containing silicon may be useful as the silyl containing
monomers in the present invention. The silicon moiety in such silyl containing monomers may
be reactive or unreactive. Exemplary "reactive" silyl containing monomers include those
containing one or more alkoxy or acetoxy groups, such as, but not limited to, trimethoxysilyl
containing monomers, triethoxysilyl containing monomers, methyl dimethoxysilyl containing
monomers, and the like. Exemplary "unreactive" silyl containing monomers include those
containing alkyl groups, aryl groups, alkenyl groups or mixtures thereof, such as but are not
limited to, trimethylsilyl containing monomers, triethylsilyl containing monomers,
phenyldimethylsilyl containing monomers, and the like. Polymeric porogens including silyl
containing monomers as polymerized units are intended to include such porogens prepared by
the polymerization of a monomer containing a silyl moiety. It is not intended to include a linear
polymer that contains a silyl moiety only as end capping units.</p>
    <p num="0063">Suitable silyl containing monomers include, but are not limited to, vinyltrimethylsilane,
vinyltriethylsilane, vinyltrimethoxysilane, vinyltriethoxysilane, γ-trimethoxysilylpropyl
(meth)acrylate, divinylsilane, trivinylsilane, dimethyldivinylsilane, divinylmethylsilane,
methyltrivinylsilane, diphenyldivinylsilane, divinylphenylsilane, trivinylphenylsilane,
divinylmethylphenylsilane, tetravinylsilane, dimethylvinyldisiloxane,
poly(methylvinylsiloxane), poly(vinylhydrosiloxane), poly(phenylvinylsiloxane), allyloxy-tert-butyldimethylsilane,
allyloxytrimethylsilane, allyltriethoxysilane, allyltri-iso-propylsilane,
allyltrimethoxysilane, allyltrimethylsilane, allyltriphenylsilane, diethoxy methylvinylsilane,
diethyl methylvinylsilane, dimethyl ethoxyvinylsilane, dimethyl phenylvinylsilane, ethoxy
diphenyrvinylsilane, methyl bis(trimcthylsilyloxy)vinylsilane, triacetoxyvinylsilane,
triethoxyvinylsilane, triethylvinylsilane, triphenylvinylsilane, tris(trimethylsilyloxy)vinylsilane,
vinyloxytrimethylsilane and mixtures thereof.</p>
    <p num="0064">The amount of siliyl containing monomer useful to form the porogens of the present
invention is typically from about 1 to about 99 %wt, based on the total weight of the monomers
used. It is preferred that the silyl containing monomers are present in an amount of from 1 to
about 80 %wt, and more preferably from about 5 to about 75 %wt.</p>
    <p num="0065">Suitable poly(alkylene oxide) monomers include, but are not limited to, poly(propylene
oxide) monomers, poly(ethylene oxide) monomers, poly(ethylene oxide/propylene oxide) 
monomers, poly(propylene glycol) (meth)acrylates, poly(propylene glycol) alkyl ether
(meth)acrylates, poly(propylene glycol) phenyl ether (meth)acrylates, poly(propylene glycol) 4-nonylphenol
ether (meth)acrylates, poly(ethylene glycol) (meth)acrylates, poly(ethylene glycol)
alkyl ether (meth)acrylates, poly(ethylcne glycol) phenyl ether (meth)acrylates,
poly(propylene/ethylene glycol) alkyl ether (meth)acrylates and mixtures thereof. Preferred
poly(alkylene oxide) monomers include trimethoylolpropane ethoxylate tri(meth)acrylate,
trimethoylolpropane propoxylate tri(meth)acrylate, poly(propylene glycol) methyl ether acrylate,
and the like. Particularly suitable poly(propylene glycol) methyl ether acrylate monomers are
those having a molecular weight in the range of from about 200 to about 2000. The
poly(ethylene oxide/propylene oxide) monomers useful in the present invention may be linear,
block or graft copolymers. Such monomers typically have a degree of polymerization of from
about 1 to about 50, and preferably from about 2 to about 50.</p>
    <p num="0066">Typically, the amount of poly(alkylene oxide) monomers useful in the porogens of the
present invention is from about 1 to about 99 %wt, based on the total weight of the monomers
used. The amount of poly(alkylene oxide) monomers is preferably from about 2 to about 90
%wt, and more preferably from about 5 to about 80 %wt.</p>
    <p num="0067">The silyl containing monomers and the poly(alkylene oxide) monomers may be used
either alone or in combination to form the porogens of the present invention. It is preferred that
the silyl containing monomers and the poly(alkylene oxide) monomers are used in combination.
In general, the amount of the silyl containing monomers or the poly(alkylene oxide) monomers
needed to compatiblize the porogen with the dielectric matrix depends upon the level of porogen
loading desired in the matrix, the particular composition of the organo polysilica dielectric
matrix, and the composition of the porogen polymer. When a combination of silyl containing
monomers and the poly(alkylene oxide) monomers is used, the amount of one monomer may be
decreased as the amount of the other monomer is increased. Thus, as the amount of the silyl
containing monomer is increased in the combination, the amount of the poly(alkylene oxide)
monomer in the combination may be decreased.</p>
    <p num="0068">The polymers useful as porogens in the present invention may be prepared by a variety of
polymerization techniques, such as solution polymerization or emulsion polymerization, and
preferably by solution polymerization. The solution polymers useful in the present invention 
may be linear, branched or grafted and may be copolymers or homopolymers. Particularly
suitable solution polymers include cross-linked copolymers. Typically, the molecular weight of
the porogen polymers is in the range of 5,000 to 1,000,000, preferably 10,000 to 500,000, and
more preferably 10,000 to 100,000. The particle size polydispersity of the porogen polymer
particles is in the range of 1 to 20, preferably 1.001 to 15, and more preferably 1.001 to 10.</p>
    <p num="0069">The solution polymers of the present invention are generally prepared in a non-aqueous
solvent. Suitable solvents for such polymerizations are well known to those skilled in the art.
Examples of such solvents include, but are not limited to: hydrocarbons, such as alkanes,
fluorinated hydrocarbons, and aromatic hydrocarbons, ethers, ketones, esters, alcohols and
mixtures thereof. Particularly suitable solvents include dodecane, mesitylene, xylenes, diphenyl
ether, gamma-butyrolactone, ethyl lactate, propyleneglycol monomethyl ether acetate,
caprolactone, 2-hepatanone, methylisobutyl ketone, diisobutylketone, propyleneglycol
monomethyl ether, decanol, and t-butanol.</p>
    <p num="0070">The solution polymers of the present invention may be prepared by a variety of methods,
such as those disclosed in US Patent No. 5,863,996 (Graham) and European Patent Application 1
088 848 (Allen et al.). The emulsion polymers useful in the present invention are generally
prepared the methods described in European Patent Application 1 088 848 (Allen et al.).</p>
    <p num="0071">It is preferred that the polymers of the present invention are prepared using anionic
polymerization or free radical polymerization techniques. It is also preferred that the polymers
useful in the present invention are not prepared by step-growth polymerization processes.</p>
    <p num="0072">The polymer particle porogcns of the present invention include cross-linked polymer
chains. Any amount of cross-linker is suitable for use in the present invention. Typically, the
porogens of the present invention contain at least 1% by weight, based on the weight of the
porogen, of cross-linker. Up to and including 100% cross-linking agent, based on the weight of
the porogen, may be effectively used in the particles of the present invention. It is preferred that
the amount of cross-linker is from about 1% to about 80%, and more preferably from about 1%
to about 60%. It will be appreciated by those skilled in the art that as the amount of cross-linker
in the porogen increases, the conditions for removal of the porogen from the dielectric matrix
may change. </p>
    <p num="0073">Suitable cross-linkers useful in the present invention include di-, tri-, tetra-, or higher
multi-functional ethylenically unsaturated monomers. Examples of cross-linkers useful in the
present invention include, but are not limited to: trivinylbenzene, divinyltoluene,
divinylpyridine, divinylnaphthalene and divinylxylene; and such as ethyleneglycol diacrylate,
trimethylolpropane triacrylate, diethyleneglycol divinyl ether, trivinylcyclohexane, allyl
methacrylate ("ALMA"), ethyleneglycol dimethacrylate ("EGDMA"), diethyleneglycol
dimethacrylate ("DEGDMA"), propyleneglycol dimethacrylate, propyleneglycol diacrylate,
trimethylolpropane trimethacrylate ("TMPTMA"), divinyl benzene ("DVB"), glycidyl
methacrylate, 2,2-dimethylpropane 1,3 diacrylate, 1,3-butylene glycol diacrylate, 1,3-butylene
glycol dimethacrylate, 1,4-butanediol diacrylate, diethylene glycol diacrylate, diethylene glycol
dimethacrylate, 1,6-hexanediol diacrylate, 1,6-hexanediol dimethacrylate, tripropylene glycol
diacrylate, triethylene glycol dimethacrylate, tetraethylene glycol diacrylate, polyethylene glycol
200 diacrylate, tetraethylene glycol dimethacrylate, polyethylene glycol dimethacrylate,
ethoxylated bisphenol A diacrylate, ethoxylated bisphenol A dimethacrylate, polyethylene glycol
600 dimethacrylate, poly(butanediol) diacrylate, pentaerythritol triacrylate, trimethylolpropane
triethoxy triacrylate, glyceryl propoxy triacrylate, pentaerythritol tetraacrylate, pentaerythritol
tetramethacrylate, dipentaecrythritol monohydroxypentaacrylate, and mixtures thereof. Silyl
containing monomers that are capable of undergoing cross-linking may also be used as cross-linkers,
such as, but not limited to, divinylsilane, trivinylsilane, dimethyldivinylsilane,
divinylmethylsilane, methyltrivinylsilane, diphenyldivinylsilane, divinylphenylsilane,
trivinylphenylsilane, divinylmethylphenylsilane, tetravinylsilane, dimethylvinyldisiloxane,
poly(methylvinylsiloxane), poly(vinylhydrosiloxane), poly(phenylvinylsiloxane),
tetraallylsilane, 1,3-dimethyl tetravinyldisiloxane, 1,3-divinyl tetramethyldisiloxane and
mixtures thereof.</p>
    <p num="0074">The porogen particles of the present invention may be directly added to the B-staged
dielectric matrix material as is or may be first purified to remove impurities that might effect the
electrical or physical properties of electronic devices. Purification of the porogen particles may
be accomplished either by precipitation of the porogen particles or adsorption of the impurities.</p>
    <p num="0075">To be useful as porogens in forming porous dielectric materials, the porogens of the
present invention must be at least partially removable under conditions which do not adversely
affect the dielectric matrix material, preferably substantially removable, and more preferably 
completely removable. By "removable" is meant that the polymer depolymerizes or otherwise
breaks down into volatile components or fragments which are then removed from, or migrate out
of, the dielectric material yielding pores or voids. Any procedures or conditions which at least
partially remove the porogen without adversely affecting the dielectric matrix material may be
used. It is preferred that the porogen is substantially removed. Typical methods of removal
include, but are not limited to, chemical, exposure to heat or exposure to radiation, such as, but
not limited to, UV, x-ray, gamma ray, alpha particles, neutron beam or electron beam. It is
preferred that the matrix material is exposed to heat or UV light to remove the porogen.</p>
    <p num="0076">The porogens of the present invention can be thermally removed under vacuum, nitrogen,
argon, mixtures of nitrogen and hydrogen, such as forming gas, or other inert or reducing
atmosphere. The porogens of the present invention may be removed at any temperature that is
higher than the thermal curing temperature and lower than the thermal decomposition
temperature of the organo polysilica dielectric matrix material. Typically, the porogens of the
present invention may be removed at temperatures in the range of 150° to 500° C and preferably
in the range of 250° to 425° C. Typically, the porogens of the present invention are removed
upon heating for a period of time in the range of 1 to 120 minutes. An advantage of the
porogens of the present invention is that 0 to 20% by weight of the porogen remains after
removal from the organo polysilica dielectric matrix material.</p>
    <p num="0077">In one embodiment, when a porogen of the present invention is removed by exposure to
radiation, the porogen polymer is typically exposed under an inert atmosphere, such as nitrogen,
to a radiation source, such as, but not limited to, visible or ultraviolet light. The porogen
fragments generated from such exposure are removed from the matrix material under a flow of
inert gas. The energy flux of the radiation must be sufficiently high to generate a sufficient
number of free radicals such that porogen particle is at least partially removed. It will be
appreciated by those skilled in the art that a combination of heat and radiation may be used to
remove the porogens of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0078">In preparing the dielectric matrix materials of the present invention, a plurality of
porogen particles described above are first dispersed within, or dissolved in, a B-staged dielectric
material. Any amount of porogen may be combined with the B-staged dielectric materials
according to the present invention. The amount of porogen used will depend on the particular 
porogen employed, the particular B-staged dielectric material employed, the extent of dielectric
constant reduction desired in the resulting porous dielectric material, i.e. the particular porosity
desired, and the mean pore size of the porogen particles. Typically, the amount of porogen used
is in the range of from 30 to 50 wt%, based on the weight of the B-staged dielectric material,
preferably from 30 to 45 wt%, and more preferably from 30 to 40 wt%. A particularly useful
amount of porogen is in the range of form about 30 to about 35 wt%.</p>
    <p num="0079">The porogens of the present invention may be combined with the B-staged dielectric
material by any methods known in the art. Typically, the B-staged dielectric material is first
dissolved in a suitable high boiling solvent, such as, but not limited to, methyl isobutyl ketone,
diisobutyl ketone, 2-heptanone, γ-butyrolactone, ε-caprolactone, ethyl lactate propyleneglycol
monomethyl ether acetate, propyleneglycol monomethyl ether, diphenyl ether, anisole, n-amyl
acetate, n-butyl acetate, cyclohexanone, N-methyl-2-pyrrolidone, N,N'-dimethylpropyleneurea,
mesitylene, xylenes, or mixtures thereof, to form a solution. The porogen particles are then
dispersed or dissolved within the solution. The resulting dispersion is then deposited on a
substrate by methods known in the art, such as spin coating, spray coating or doctor blading, to
form a film or layer.</p>
    <p num="0080">After being deposited on a substrate, the B-staged dielectric material is then substantially
cured to form a rigid, cross-linked dielectric matrix material without substantially removing the
porogen particles. The curing of the dielectric material may be by any means known in the art
including, but not limited to, heating to induce condensation or e-beam irradiation to facilitate
free radical coupling of the oligomer or monomer units. Typically, the B-staged material is
cured by heating at an elevated temperature, e.g. either directly, e.g. heated at a constant
temperature such as on a hot plate, or in a step-wise manner. Typically, the dielectric material
containing polymeric porogens is first annealed at a temperature of from about 200° to about
350° C, and then heated to a higher temperature, such as from about 400° to about 450° C to at
least partially remove the porogens. Such curing conditions are known to those skilled in the art.</p>
    <p num="0081">Once the B-staged dielectric material is cured, the film is subjected to conditions which
remove the porogen without substantially degrading the organo polysilica dielectric matrix
material, that is, less than 5% by weight of the dielectric matrix material is lost. Typically, such
conditions include exposing the film to heat and/or radiation. It is preferred that the matrix 
material is exposed to heat or light to remove the porogen. To remove the porogen thermally,
the dielectric matrix material can be heated by oven heating or microwave heating. Under
typical thermal removal conditions, the polymerized dielectric matrix material is heated to about
350° to 400° C. It will be recognized by those skilled in the art that the particular removal
temperature of a thermally labile porogen will vary according to composition of the porogen.
Upon removal, the porogen polymer depolymerizes or otherwise breaks down into volatile
components or fragments which are then removed from, or migrate out of, the dielectric matrix
material yielding pores or voids, which fill up with the carrier gas used in the process. Thus, a
porous dielectric material having voids is obtained, where the size of the voids is substantially
the same as the particle size of the porogen. By "substantially the same" it is meant that the
diameter of the pores is within 10% of the mean particle size of the porogens used. The resulting
dielectric material having voids thus has a lower dielectric constant than such material without
such voids.</p>
    <p num="0082">The present invention provides a method of manufacturing a porous dielectric material
suitable for use in electronic device manufacture including the steps of: a) dispersing a plurality
of removable polymeric porogen particles in a B-staged dielectric material, b) curing the B-staged
dielectric material to form a dielectric matrix material without substantially degrading the
porogen particles; c) subjecting the dielectric matrix material to conditions which at least
partially remove the porogen to form a porous dielectric material without substantially degrading
the dielectric material; wherein the porogen is substantially compatible with the B-staged
dielectric material; wherein the dielectrze material is ≥ 30% porous; and wherein the mean
particle size of the plurality of porogen particles is selected to provide a closed cell pore
structure. Also provided by the present invention is a method of manufacturing a porous organo
polysilica dielectric material suitable for use in electronic device manufacture including the steps
of: a) dispersing a plurality of removable polymeric porogen particles in a B-staged organo
polysilica dielectric material, b) curing the B-staged organo polysilica dielectric material to form
a dielectric matrix material without substantially degrading the porogen particles; c) subjecting
the organo polysilica dielectric matrix material to conditions which at least partially remove the
porogen to form a porous dielectric material without substantially degrading the organo
polysilica dielectric material; wherein the porogen is substantially compatible with the B-staged
organo polysilica dielectric material and wherein the porogen includes as polymerized units at 
least one compound selected from silyl containing monomers or poly(alkylene oxide)
monomers; wherein the dielectric material is ≥ 30% porous; and wherein the mean particle size
of the plurality of porogen particles is selected to provide a closed cell pore structure.</p>
    <p num="0083">A further advantage of the present invention is that low dielectric constant materials are
obtained having uniformly dispersed voids, a higher volume of voids than known dielectric
materials and/or smaller void sizes than known dielectric materials. The resulting porous
dielectric matrix material has low stress, low dielectric constant, low refractive index, improved
toughness and improved compliance during mechanical contacting to require less contact force
during compression.</p>
    <p num="0084">The porous dielectric material made by the process of the present invention is suitable for
use in any application where a low refractive index or low dielectric material may be used.
When the porous dielectric material of the present invention is a thin film, it is useful as
insulators, anti-reflective coatings, sound barriers, thermal breaks, insulation, optical coatings
and the like. The porous dielectric materials of the present invention are preferably useful in
electronic and optoelectronic devices including, but not limited to, the fabrication of multilevel
integrated circuits, e.g. microprocessors, digital signal processors, memory chips and band pass
filters, thereby increasing their performance and reducing their cost.</p>
    <p num="0085">The porous dielectric matrix materials of the present invention are particularly suitable
for use in integrated circuit manufacture. In one embodiment of integrated circuit manufacture,
as a first step, a layer of a composition including B-staged dielectric material having a polymeric
porogen dispersed or dissolved therein and optionally a solvent is deposited on a substrate.
Suitable deposition methods include spin casting, spray casting and doctor blading. Suitable
optional solvents include, but are not limited to: methyl isobutyl ketone, diisobutyl ketone, 2-heptanone,
γ-butyrolactone, ε-caprolactone, ethyl lactate propyleneglycol monomethyl ether
acetate, propyleneglycol monomethyl ether, diphenyl ether, anisole, n-amyl acetate, n-butyl
acetate, cyclohexanone, N-methyl-2-pyrrolidone, N,N'-dimethylpropyleneurea, mesitylene,
xylenes or mixtures thereof. Suitable substrates include, but are not limited to: silicon, silicon
dioxide, silicon oxycarbide, silicon germanium, silicon-on-insulator, glass, silicon nitride,
ceramics, aluminum, copper, gallium arsenide, plastics, such as polycarbonate, circuit boards,
such as FR-4 and polyimide, and hybrid circuit substrates, such as aluminum nitride-alumina. 
Such substrates may further include thin films deposited thereon, such films including, but not
limited to: metal nitrides, metal carbides, metal silicides, metal oxides, and mixtures thereof. In
a multilayer integrated circuit device, an underlying layer of insulated, planarized circuit lines
can also function as a substrate.</p>
    <p num="0086">In a second step in the manufacture of integrated circuits, the layer of the composition is
heated to an elevated temperature to cure the B-staged dielectric material to form a dielectric
matrix material without degrading the polymeric porogen. A catalyst, such as a Brønsted or
Lewis base or Brønsted or Lewis acid, may also be used. In a third step, the resulting cured
organo polysilica dielectric matrix material is then subjected to conditions such that the porogen
contained therein is substantially removed without adversely affecting the dielectric matrix
material to yield a porous organo polysilica dielectric material.</p>
    <p num="0087">The porous dielectric material is then lithographically patterned to form vias and/or
trenches in subsequent processing steps. The trenches generally extend to the substrate and
connect to at least one metallic via. Typically, lithographic patterning involves (i) coating the
dielectric material layer with a positive or negative photoresist, such as those marketed by
Shipley Company (Marlborough, MA); (ii) imagewise exposing, through a mask, the photoresist
to radiation, such as light of appropriate wavelength or e-beam; (iii) developing the image in the
resist, e.g., with a suitable developer; and (iv) transferring the image through the dielectric layer
to the substrate with a suitable transfer technique such as reactive ion beam etching. Optionally,
an antireflective composition may be disposed on the dielectric material prior to the photoresist
coating. Such lithographic patterning techniques are well known to those skilled in the art.</p>
    <p num="0088">A metallic film is then deposited onto the patterned dielectric layer to fill the trenches.
Preferred metallic materials include, but are not limited to: copper, tungsten, gold, silver,
aluminum or alloys thereof. The metal is typically deposited onto the patterned dielectric layer
by techniques well known to those skilled in the art. Such techniques include, but are not limited
to: chemical vapor deposition ("CVD"), plasma-enhanced CVD, combustion CVD ("CCVD"),
electro and electroless deposition, sputtering, or the like. Optionally, a metallic liner, such as a
layer of nickel, tantalum, titanium, tungsten, or chromium, including nitrides or silicides thereof,
or other layers such as barrier or adhesion layers, e.g. silicon nitride or titanium nitride, is
deposited on the patterned and etched dielectric material. </p>
    <p num="0089">In a fifth step of the process for integrated circuit manufacture, excess metallic material
is removed, e.g. by planarizing the metallic film, so that the resulting metallic material is
generally level with the patterned dielectric layer. Planarization is typically accomplished with
chemical/mechanical polishing or selective wet or dry etching. Such planarization methods are
well known to those skilled in the art.</p>
    <p num="0090">It will be appreciated by those skilled in the art that multiple layers of dielectric material,
including multiple layers of organo polysilica dielectric material, and metal layers may
subsequently be applied by repeating the above steps. It will be further appreciated by those
skilled in the art that the compositions of the present invention are useful in any and all methods
of integrated circuit manufacture.</p>
    <p num="0091">Thus, the present invention provides a method of preparing an integrated circuit with a
closed cell porous film including the steps of: a) depositing on a substrate a layer of a
composition including B-staged dielectric material having a plurality of polymeric porogens
dispersed therein; b) curing the B-staged dielectric material to form a dielectric matrix material
without substantially removing the porogens; c) subjecting the dielectric matrix material to
conditions which at least partially remove the porogens to form a porous dielectric material layer
without substantially degrading the dielectric material; d) patterning the porous dielectric layer;
c) depositing a metallic film onto the patterned porous dielectric layer; and f) planarizing the
film to form an integrated circuit; wherein the porogen is substantially compatible with the B-staged
dielectric material; and wherein the dielectric material is ≥ 30% porous; and wherein the
mean particle size of the porogens is selected to provide a closed cell pore structure.</p>
    <p num="0092">It is preferred that the dielectric material is an organo polysilica material. Thus, the
present invention also provides a method of preparing an integrated circuit with a closed cell
porous film including the steps of: a) depositing on a substrate a layer of a composition
including B-staged organo polysilica dielectric material having polymeric porogen dispersed
therein; b) curing the B-staged organo polysilica dielectric material to form an organo polysilica
dielectric matrix material without substantially removing the porogen; c) subjecting the organo
polysilica dielectric matrix material to conditions which at least partially remove the porogen to
form a porous organo polysilica dielectric material layer without substantially degrading the
organo polysilica dielectric material; d) patterning the porous dielectric layer; c) depositing a 
metallic film onto the patterned porous dielectric layer; and f) planarizing the film to form an
integrated circuit; wherein the porogen is substantially compatible with the B-staged organo
polysilica dielectric material and wherein the porogen includes as polymerized units at least one
compound selected from silyl containing monomers or poly(alkylene oxide) monomers; and
wherein the dielectric material is ≥ 30% porous.</p>
    <p num="0093">Also included in the present invention is an integrated circuit including a porous
dielectric material wherein the porous dielectric material ≥ 30% porous; wherein the pores are
substantially non-interconnected; and wherein the mean particle size of the pores is selected to
provide a closed cell pore structure. It is preferred that the porous dielectric material is an
organo polysilica material, and more preferably methylsilsesquioxane. It is further preferred that
the dielectric material has a porosity ≥ 35%.</p>
    <p num="0094">A still further advantage provided by the close cell pore structure of the present porous
dielectric materials is that a cap layer for the porous dielectric layer is not needed. Such cap
layers are typically applied directly to the porous dielectric layer and act as a barrier preventing
intrusion for the next applied layer into the pores of the dielectric material. Thus, the present
invention provides an electronic device including a porous dielectric layer free of an added cap
layer/wherein the porous dielectric layer has ≥ 30% porosity.</p>
    <p num="0095">The following examples are presented to illustrate further various aspects of the present
invention, but are not intended to limit the scope of the invention in any aspect.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Example 1</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0096">A methyl silsesquioxane ("MeSQ") sample is prepared by combining a methyl
silsesquioxane resin (0.80 g), with a plurality of porogen particles having as polymerized units
PEGMEMA475/VTMOS/TMPTMA (80/10/10) in propylene glycol methyl ether acetate (1.33
g, 15 wt%) and propylene glycol methyl ether acetate (1.43 g). The mean particle size of the
plurality of porogen particles is varied. The sample is deposited on a silicon wafer as a thin
coating using spin casting. The thickness (estimated at ∼ 1.1 µm) of the film is controlled by the
duration and spin rate of spread cycle, drying cycle and final spin cycle. The wafer is processed
at 150° C for 1 minute followed by heating in a PYREX™ container in an oven to 200° C under 
an argon atmosphere. The oxygen content of the container is monitored and is maintained below
5 ppm before heating of the sample. After 30 minutes at 200° C, the furnace is heated at a rate
of 10° C per minute to a temperature of 420° C and is held for 60 minutes. The decomposition
of the polymer particle is accomplished at this temperature without expansion of the polymer.</p>
    <p num="0097">The above procedure is repeated using various levels of porogen.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Example 2</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0098">A sample is prepared by combining benzocyclobutene ("BCB") "B-staged" matrix
polymer, available from Dow Chemical Company, Midland, Michigan (0.80 g), mesitylene (1.43
g), and a plurality of porogen particles having as polymerized units VAS/STYRNE/TMPTMA
(80/10/10) in cyclohcxanonc (1.33 g, 15 wt%). The mean particle size of the plurality of porogen
particles is varied. The sample is deposited on a silicon wafer as a thin coating using spin
casting. The thickness (estimated at ∼ 1.1 µm) of the film is controlled by the duration and spin
rate of spread cycle, drying cycle and final spin cycle. The wafer is processed at 150° C for 1
minute followed by heating in a PYREX™ container in an oven to 350° C under an argon
atmosphere. The oxygen content of the container is monitored and is maintained below 5 ppm
before heating of the sample. After 30 minutes at 250° C, the furnace is heated at a rate of 10° C
per minute to a temperature of 350° C and is held for 60 minutes. The decomposition of the
polymer particle is accomplished at this temperature without expansion of the polymer.</p>
    <p num="0099">The above procedure is repeated using various levels of porogen.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Example 3</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0100">The procedure of Example 2 is repeated except that the polyarylene ether "B-staged"
matrix polymer is available under the SILK tradename from Dow Chemical Company and
cyclohexane is used as the solvent. The procedure is repeated using various levels of porogen.
With the following changes to the thermal history to accommodate the new matrix material: after
30 minutes at 350° C, the furnace is heated at a rate of 10° C per minute to a temperature of 420°
C and is held for 60 minutes. The decomposition of the polymer particle is accomplished at this
temperature without expansion of the polymer. </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Example 4</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0101">The procedure of Example 3 is repeated except that the polyarylene ether "B-staged"
matrix polymer is available under the FLARE tradename from Honeywell Electronic Materials,
Morristown, New Jersey, The procedure is repeated using various levels of porogen.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Example 5</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0102">The procedure of Example 3 is repeated except that the polyarylene ether "B-staged"
matrix polymer is available under the VELOX tradename from Air Products, Allentown,
Pennsylvania. The procedure is repeated using various levels of porogen</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Example 6</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0103">The wall thickness of the resulting porous dielectric samples from Examples 1 to 6 is
then calculated to determine the extent of pore interconnectivity. Such calculations are
performed according to the following formula: wall thickness is the difference between unit cell
length and the diameter of a porogen particle, where the unit cell length is equal to the cube root
of the volume of porogen particle divided by the total pore volume. Wall thickness of 0.5 nm
or greater are required to maintain a closed cell pore structure. The results are reported in Table
1.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Porogen Loading Level (%)</entry><entry align="center">Porogen Particle Size (nm)</entry><entry align="center">Calculated Wall Thickness (nm)</entry><entry align="center">Interconnectivity</entry></row><row><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">0.38</entry><entry align="center">Open Cell</entry></row><row><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry><entry align="center">0.57</entry><entry align="center">Close Cell</entry></row><row><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">0.76</entry><entry align="center">Close Cell</entry></row><row><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">0.41</entry><entry align="center">Open Cell</entry></row><row><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry><entry align="center">0.51</entry><entry align="center">Close Cell</entry></row><row><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">3.5</entry><entry align="center">0.61</entry><entry align="center">Close Cell</entry></row><row><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">0.43</entry><entry align="center">Open Cell</entry></row><row><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">3.5</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry><entry align="center">Close Cell </entry></row><row><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">0.57</entry><entry align="center">Close Cell</entry></row><row><entry align="center">40</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">0.47</entry><entry align="center">Open Cell</entry></row><row><entry align="center">40</entry><entry align="center">6</entry><entry align="center">0.56</entry><entry align="center">Close Cell</entry></row><row><entry align="center">40</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">0.66</entry><entry align="center">Close Cell</entry></row><row><entry align="center">45</entry><entry align="center">9</entry><entry align="center">0.47</entry><entry align="center">Open Cell</entry></row><row><entry align="center">45</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">0.52</entry><entry align="center">Close Cell</entry></row><row><entry align="center">45 1</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">0.57</entry><entry align="center">Close Cell</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Example 7</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0104">The procedure of Example 1 is repeated using a plurality of porogen particles having a
mean particle size of 3,5 nm.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Example 8</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0105">The interconnectivity of the porous films from Example 7 are measured by placing a
PYREX™ glass ball joint complete with a rubber o-ring against the thin, porous dielectric layer
deposited onto a conductive silicon wafer, having a resistivity ("R") = &lt;0.02 Ohm-cm. The ball
joint is held in place by a clamp and then an aqueous 10,000 ppm of copper (as copper nitrate)
ICP standard solution in 5% nitric acid is charged into the ball joint. A platinum electrode is
placed into the solution and then a second reference electrode is also inserted into the solution.
The back side of the wafer, i.e. the side opposite the film, is also contacted with an electrode. A
measuring or monitoring system is used to record the impedence spectra with a Solartron 1260
Gain/Phase Analyzer, EG&amp;G Princeton Applied Research (PAR) 273 potentiostat/Galvanostat,
and Zplot Impedance Software (available from Scribner Associates). Individual data files are fit
to a modified Randles circuit, (Zsim Impedance software from Scribner Associates), and their
impedance parameters are plotted and compared as a function of time.</p>
    <p num="0106">The copper ICP standard solution is allowed to remain in contact with the film for 24
hours and the impedance is measured again. These values are compared to those for a non-porous
film, Differences in conductivity values of less than 1 indicate closed cell pore
structures. Differences in conductivity values of greater than 1 indicate open cell pore
structures. <tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">Experimental parameters:</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Frequency range</entry><entry align="left">100 KHz to 0.5 Hz</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sine wave amplitude</entry><entry align="left">10mV</entry></row><row><entry align="left">DC Potential</entry><entry align="left">1 volt</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Points/decade</entry><entry align="left">5</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0107">The porous films of Example 7 are analyzed using this electrochemical test. For each
sample film, the impedance value is reduced to the resistance which is then normalized for each
of the films by dividing by the film thickness. The results are reported in Table 2. <tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Porogen Loading (%)</entry><entry align="center">Conductivity (S/m)</entry><entry align="center">Interconnectivily</entry></row><row><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0.017</entry><entry align="center">Close Cell</entry></row><row><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">0.214</entry><entry align="center">Close Cell</entry></row><row><entry align="center">22</entry><entry align="center">0.205</entry><entry align="center">Close Cell</entry></row><row><entry align="center">24</entry><entry align="center">0.159</entry><entry align="center">Close Cell</entry></row><row><entry align="center">26</entry><entry align="center">0.298</entry><entry align="center">Close Cell</entry></row><row><entry align="center">28</entry><entry align="center">0.136</entry><entry align="center">Close Cell</entry></row><row><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">0.543</entry><entry align="center">Close Cell</entry></row><row><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">0.439</entry><entry align="center">Close Cell</entry></row><row><entry align="center">40</entry><entry align="center">1.771</entry><entry align="center">Open Cell</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0108">From these data, it can be seen that when a 3.5 nm particle is used, closed cell pore
structures having between 35 and 40% porosity can be obtained.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A closed cell porous dielectric material suitable for use in electronic device
manufacture, the porous dielectric material having a plurality of pores and having greater than or
equal to 30% porosity.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The closed cell porous dielectric material of claim 1 wherein the dielectric material is
selected from inorganic matrix materials such as carbides, oxides, nitrides and oxyfluorides of
silicon, boron, or aluminum; silicones; siloxanes; organo polysilica materials; silicates; silazanes;
benzocyclobutenes, poly(aryl esters), poly(ether ketones), polycarbonates, polyimides,
fluorinated polyimides, polynorbornenes, poly(arylene ethers), polyaromatic hydrocarbons,
polyquinoxalines, poly(perfluorinated hydrocarbons) and polybenzoxazoles.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The closed cell porous dielectric material of any one of claims 1 to 2 wherein the
dielectric material comprises hydrogen silsesquioxane.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The closed cell porous dielectric material of any one of claims 1 to 3 wherein the
plurality of pores has a mean particle size of 3 nm or greater and the porosity is ≥ 35%.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The closed cell porous dielectric material of any one of claims 1 to 4 wherein the
plurality of pores has a mean particle size of greater than 5 nm and the porosity is ≥ 40%.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A method of manufacturing a porous dielectric material suitable for use in electronic
device manufacture comprising the steps of: a) dispersing a plurality of removable polymeric
porogen particles in a B-staged dielectric material, b) curing the B-staged dielectric material to
form a dielectric matrix material without substantially degrading the porogen particles; c)
subjecting the dielectric matrix material to conditions which at least partially remove the porogen
to form a porous dielectric material without substantially degrading the dielectric material;
wherein the porogen is substantially compatible with the B-staged dielectric material; wherein
the dielectric material is ≥ 30% porous; and wherein the mean particle size of the plurality of
porogen particles is selected to provide a closed cell pore structure.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A method of manufacturing a porous organo polysilica dielectric material suitable for
use in electronic device manufacture comprising the steps of: a) dispersing a plurality of
removable polymeric porogen particles in a B-staged organo polysilica dielectric material, b)
curing the B-staged organo polysilica dielectric material to form a dielectric matrix material
without substantially degrading the porogen particles; c) subjecting the organo polysilica
dielectric matrix material to conditions which at least partially remove the porogen to form a
porous dielectric material without substantially degrading the organo polysilica dielectric
material; wherein the porogen is substantially compatible with the B-staged organo polysilica
dielectric material and wherein the porogen comprises as polymerized units at least one
compound selected from silyl containing monomers or poly(alkylene oxide) monomers; wherein
the dielectric material is ≥ 30% porous; and wherein the mean particle size of the plurality of
porogen particles is selected to provide a closed cell pore structure.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A method of preparing an integrated circuit with a closed cell porous film comprising
the steps of: a) depositing on a substrate a layer of a composition including B-staged dielectric
material having a plurality of polymeric porogens dispersed therein; b) curing the B-staged
dielectric material to form a dielectric matrix material without substantially removing the
porogens; c) subjecting the dielectric matrix material to conditions which at least partially
remove the porogens to form a porous dielectric material layer without substantially degrading
the dielectric material; d) patterning the porous dielectric layer; e) depositing a metallic film onto
the patterned porous dielectric layer; and f) planarizing the film to form an integrated circuit;
wherein the porogen is substantially compatible with the B-staged dielectric material; and
wherein the dielectric material is ≥ 30% porous; and wherein the mean particle size of the
porogens is selected to provide a closed cell pore structure.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>An integrated circuit comprising a porous dielectric material wherein the porous
dielectric material is ≥ 30% porous; wherein the pores are substantially non-interconnected; and
wherein the mean particle size of the pores is selected to provide a closed cell pore structure.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>An electronic device including a porous dielectric layer free of an added cap layer,
wherein the porous dielectric layer has ≥ 30% porosity</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
