<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1258268-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1258268" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="25335126" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021120">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1258268-A2" status="new" fvid="23615271">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1258268</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021120</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02010772-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02010772</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020514</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="US-86118901-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>86118901</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010518</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A43B   3/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A43B   3/26        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A43B   5/16        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A43B   5/16        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A63C   1/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A63C   1/26        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A63C  17/04        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A63C  17/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">A43B   3/26</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">A43B   5/16A</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">A63C  17/06</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Werkzeugloser Einspurrollschuh mit veränderbarer Grösse</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Tool-less size adjustable in-line skate</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Patins à roues alignées ajustable en taille sans outil</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>K 2 CORP</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>K-2 CORPORATION</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>K-2 CORPORATION</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>19215 Vashon Highway Southwest</street>
              <city>Vashon, Washington 98070</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HAUGEN DARRIN JOHN</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SAUTER THOMAS M</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HAUGEN, DARRIN JOHN</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SAUTER, THOMAS M.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>HAUGEN, DARRIN JOHN</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>9144 45th Avenue S.W. Apt. 7</street>
              <city>Seattle Washington 98136</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>SAUTER, THOMAS M.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>6724 Jones Ave. N.W.</street>
              <city>Seattle, Washington 98117</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Schulz, Rütger, Dr. Dipl.-Phys.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Patentanwälte Mitscherlich &amp;amp; Partner, Sonnenstrasse 33</street>
              <city>80331 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>NL</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A size-adjustable in-line skate having a base carrying a plurality of wheels
thereon. An upper is secured to a top surface of the base and defines a heel portion, a
toe portion, and diametrically opposed side wall portions. The upper is supported by
a support structure that includes a heel cup and a toe cup. The toe cup is secured to
the toe portion of the upper and slideably coupled to the base so that the toe cup can
slide longitudinally with respect to the base. An actuator is coupled to the toe cup
and travels therewith. When the actuator is translated, engagement members on the
actuator disengage with detents on the base to allow the toe cup to freely slide
between longitudinal positions to adjust the shoe size of the skate.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="144" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="108"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to skates such as in-line skates, and in particular
to an in-line skate having a tool-less size adjustment mechanism for adjusting the
shoe size of the skate.</p>
    <heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0002">In recent years, the sport of roller skating, and in particular in-line roller
skating, has enjoyed a tremendous growth in popularity. Generally described,
conventional in-line roller skates include an upper boot secured to or integrally
formed with a rigid or semi rigid base. The base, in turn, is secured along its length,
including at heel and toe ends, to a rigid frame. A plurality of wheels are journaled
transversely along a longitudinal axis between the side walls of the frame.</p>
    <p num="0003">One segment of the population that has enjoyed the sport of roller skating is
children. The costs associated with the sport can be limiting for parents. With the
new developments in features and the advancements in materials, high quality in-line
skates can be expensive. This expense is compounded when buying in-line skates for
children because as a child grows, their foot size expands necessitating frequent
replacement of the in-line skates.</p>
    <p num="0004">To address this problem, several skates have been proposed that are size
adjustable to accommodate the feet of growing users. One such skate is disclosed in 
U.S. Patent No. 5,913,526. The in-line skate includes a skate boot secured to a frame
and contains a liner. The frame carries a plurality of wheels. The skate boot includes
a heel portion, a cuff, a tongue, and a toe portion. The toe portion is selectively
connected to the frame via a bolt, which is received by a nut. The bottom wall of the
toe portion includes an elongate slot extending in the longitudinal dimension of the
skate through which the bolt passes. When assembled with the heel portion, the toe
portion may move along a line of travel which is generally parallel to the longitudinal
dimension of the skate by loosening the nut. This configuration requires a tool,
inserted upwardly between the wheels, to adjust the size of the skate, which is
inconvenient. Repeated adjustment may lead to stripping of the nut, thus limiting the
skate's ability to adjust. During adjustment, the bolt and/or nut may be lost.</p>
    <heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0005">The present invention overcomes the deficiencies in the prior art by providing
a size-adjustable skate having at least one ground engaging member which comprises
a base having a top surface for supporting a skater's foot. The base defines a plurality
of detents. An upper for receiving a skater's foot is coupled to the base and includes
a toe portion, a heel portion, and diametrically opposed side wall portions. The skate
also includes a support structure for supporting the upper. The support structure
includes a toe member having top and bottom surfaces and coupled to the toe portion
of the upper and slideably coupled to the base. The toe member is slideably
' adjustable between a plurality of longitudinal positions on the base and has an
actuator coupled thereto. The actuator is operable to move in a plane coplaner with
the top surface of the base. The toe member is selectively slideable on the base to
adjust the shoe size of the skate.</p>
    <p num="0006">In an embodiment, the toe member is selectively slideably on the base to
adjust the shoe size of the skate by operation of a size adjustment mechanism formed
between the detents of the base and a portion of the actuator.</p>
    <p num="0007">In accordance with another aspect of the present invention, an size-adjustable
skate having at least one ground engaging member is provided which comprises a
base having a top surface for supporting a skater's foot, and a bottom surface. The 
base defines a plurality of detents. An upper for receiving a skater's foot is coupled
to the base and includes a toe portion, a heel portion, and diametrically opposed side
wall portions. The skate also includes a support structure for supporting the upper.
The support structure includes a toe member coupled to the toe portion of the upper
and slideably coupled to the base. The toe member is slideably adjustable between a
plurality of longitudinal positions. The skate further includes an actuator that is
coupled to the toe member and translatable with the toe cup. The actuator is operable
to fix the toe cup to the base in a desired longitudinal position relative to the heel
portion and is operable to adjust the toe member so that the toe member slides
longitudinally to achieve a second desired longitudinal position relative to the heel
portion.</p>
    <p num="0008">In accordance with yet another aspect of the present invention, a size-adjustable
skate having at least one ground engaging member is provided which
comprises a base having a top surface for supporting a skater's foot and a bottom
surface. A frame is coupled to the bottom surface of the base and includes an
aperture positioned between ground engaging members. An upper is coupled to the
base for receiving a skater's foot and defines a toe portion, a heel portion, and
diametrically opposed side wall portions. An elongate member is coupled to the
bottom surface of the toe cup and translatable within the slot. The skate also includes
a second elongate member cantilevered to the elongate member and extending
through the aperture, the second elongate member including a first engagement
member. A second engagement member having a plurality of detents is coupled to
the base. The first engagement member engages the one of the plurality of detents to
fix the toe cup to the base in a desired longitudinal position relative to the heel
portion and the first engagement member disengaging with the one of the plurality of
the detents to slideably adjust the toe cup in a longitudinal dimension relative to the
heel portion.</p>
    <p num="0009">In accordance with still yet another aspect of the present invention, an size-adjustable
skate having at least one ground engaging member is provided which
comprises a base having a top surface for supporting a skater's foot, and a bottom 
surface. The base defines a plurality of detents. An upper for receiving a skater's
foot is coupled to the base and includes a toe portion, a heel portion, and
diametrically opposed side wall portions. The skate also includes a support structure
for supporting the upper. The support structure includes a toe member coupled to the
toe portion of the upper and slideably coupled to the base. The toe member is
selectively adjustable between a plurality of longitudinal positions. The skate further
includes an actuator that is operably coupled in a horizontal plane to the toe member
and slideable with the toe member. The actuator is selectively operable to engage
with a portion of the base to fix the toe cup in a desired longitudinal position, and is
operable to disengage with a portion of the base to allow the toe cup to slideably
translate on the base to a second desired longitudinal position. The actuator is further
operable to move in a plane substantially coplaner with the toe surface of the base.</p>
    <p num="0010">In accordance with still yet another aspect of the present invention, an size-adjustable
skate having at least one ground engaging member is provided which
comprises a base having a top surface for supporting a skater's foot, and a bottom
surface. The base defines a plurality of detents. An upper for receiving a skater's
foot is coupled to the base and includes a toe portion, a heel portion, and
diametrically opposed side wall portions. The side wall portions defining a vamp
opening extending upwardly from the toe portion of the upper. The upper further
including a tongue disposed within the upper and having a lower end fastened to the
toe portion of the upper and extending upwardly along the vamp opening, and an
elastic web fastened to the upper on the diametrically opposed side wall portions and
spanning across at least a portion of the vamp opening over the instep of the skater's
foot, compressing the tongue under the vamp portion. The skate also includes a
support structure for supporting the upper. The support structure includes a toe
member coupled to the toe portion of the upper and slideably coupled to the base.
The toe member is selectively adjustable between a plurality of longitudinal
positions. The skate further includes an actuator that is operably coupled in a
horizontal plane to the toe member and slideable with the toe member. The actuator
is selectively operable to engage with a portion of the base to fix the toe cup in a 
desired longitudinal position, and is operable to disengage with a portion of the base
to allow the toe cup to slideably translate on the base to a second desired longitudinal
position. The actuator is further operable to move in a plane substantially coplaner
with the toe surface of the base.</p>
    <heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
    <p num="0011">The foregoing aspects and many of the attendant advantages of this invention
will become more readily appreciated as the same become better understood by
reference to the following detailed description, when taken in conjunction with the
accompanying drawings, wherein:
<sl><li>FIGURE 1 illustrates an isometric view of a tool-less size-adjustable in-line
skate constructed in accordance with aspects of the present invention;</li><li>FIGURE 2 illustrates a side assembly view of the skate shown in FIGURE 1;</li><li>FIGURE 3 illustrates an isometric view of the actuator shown in FIGURE 2;</li><li>FIGURE 4 illustrates a top view of the toe end of the base shown in
FIGURE 2;</li><li>FIGURE 5 illustrates a top view of the toe cup shown in FIGURE 2;</li><li>FIGURE 6 illustrates a bottom view of the toe cup shown in FIGURE 2;</li><li>FIGURE 7 illustrates a top cut-away view of the toe cup slideably mounted to
the base in a fixed position;</li><li>FIGURE 8 illustrates a to cut-away view of the actuator being depressed and
disengaged with the detents, and the toe cup translated in the longitudinal dimension
to a second position;</li><li>FIGURE 9 illustrates a front cross-section of an alternative embodiment of a
tool-less size-adjustable in-line skate constructed in accordance with aspects of the
present invention;</li><li>FIGURE 10 illustrates a front cross-section view of the skate shown in
FIGURE 9 having a cantilevered elongate member displaced from a detent;</li><li>FIGURE 11 illustrates a side elevation view of the skate shown in FIGURE 9; </li><li>FIGURE 12 illustrates an exploded side elevation view of an inside surface of
a side wall of the skate shown in FIGURE 9;</li><li>FIGURE 13 illustrates an isometric view of another embodiment of a tool-less
size-adjustable in-line skate constructed in accordance with aspects of the
present invention;</li><li>FIGURE 14 illustrates an isometric view of an actuator for yet another
embodiment of a tool-less size-adjustable in-line skate constructed in accordance
with aspects of the present invention; and</li><li>FIGURE 15 illustrates an isometric cut-away view of yet another
embodiment of a tool-less size-adjustable in-line skate utilizing the actuator shown in
FIGURE 14.</li></sl></p>
    <heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
    <p num="0012">The present invention will now be described with reference to the
accompanying drawings where like numerals correspond to like elements. A suitable
embodiment of a tool-less size-adjustable in-line skate 10 constructed in accordance
with the present invention is illustrated in FIGURE 1. The skate 10 includes a
substantially non-rigid upper 12 that receives and surrounds a skater's foot and ankle.
The upper 12 is mounted on and secured to the upper surface of a base 14. The
upper 12 is supported by a substantially rigid external support, including a slideably
adjustable toe cup 16 extending upwardly from the toe end 18 of the base 14, a heel
cup 20 extending upwardly from the heel end 22 of the base 14, and an ankle cuff 24
pivotally secured to the base 14. The base 14 is mounted to or integrally formed with
a frame 26, which extends longitudinally beneath the base 14. A plurality of ground
engaging members such as wheels 28A, 28B, 28C, and 28D are journaled between
first and second opposing longitudinal side walls 32A and 32B of the frame 26. The
toe cup 16 includes an actuator 34 such as a push-button which can be depressed or
translated so that the slideably adjustable toe cup 16 may slide along the longitudinal
axis of the skate to adjust the shoe size of the skate 10.</p>
    <p num="0013">Suitable materials and construction (except for adjustable aspects) for the
non-rigid upper 12 and substantially rigid outer support are disclosed in U.S. Patent 
B1 5,437,466, hereby expressly incorporated by reference. Alternatively, an internal
support structure can be used with the non-rigid upper, as described in U.S. Patent
6,168,172, hereby expressly incorporated by reference. Further, various components
of the non-rigid portions of the support can be modified for a higher degree of
rigidity.</p>
    <p num="0014">Referring to the illustrative embodiment of FIGURE 2, the upper 12 includes
a toe end 36, a heel end 38, and diametrically opposed sides 40A and 40B which
define a vamp opening 42. The toe end 36 is separate from the rest of the upper 12
and when assembled, overlaps with the sides 40A and 40B. A tongue 44 is fastened
to the upper 12, extending upwardly beneath the vamp opening 42. The vamp
opening 42 is drawn closed and the soft upper is fitted and drawn about the skater's
foot by a lacing system 46. Alternate constructions that do not use a lacing system
are within the scope of the invention and will be described below. An ankle cuff
strap 48, connected to the ankle cuff 24, may be selectively secured to fasten the
cuff 24 about the skater's lower leg, above the ankle cuff 24. The upper 12 may
include other components such as a sole or the like.</p>
    <p num="0015">As shown in FIGURE 13 and briefly discussed above the upper 12 may be
drawn closed by an alternative closure system to securely couple the upper to a
rider's foot. In the alternative closure system, the vamp opening 42 of the upper 12
of skate 10 may be drawn closed by an elastic web 54 which extends across a lower
portion of the vamp opening 42, overlying the tongue 44. The closure system of the
skate may further includes an instep strap 56 secured across the upper 12, extending
from a lateral side of the heel cup to a medial side of the heel cup, below the ankle.
A more detailed description of the alternative closure system utilizing an elastic web,
is found in co-pending U.S. Application No. 09/847,959, entitled FAST ENTRY
ELASTIC VAMP CLOSURE SKATE to Bennett, and filed May 2, 2001, the
disclosure of which is hereby incorporated by reference.</p>
    <p num="0016">Referring to FIGURE 2, the skate 10 will now be described in more detail.
The upper 12 of the skate 10 is constructed of a majority of substantially non-rigid
materials, and is supported by a rigid or at least semi-rigid external support. The 
substantially non-rigid upper 12 is suitably constructed from flexible materials such
as fabric, leather, flexible plastics, and cushioning materials such as fiber fleece,
batting or elastomeric foams. The toe end 36 of the upper 12 is securely fastened to
the toe cup 16, such as by riveting, stitching, bolts or the like. The toe cup 16
includes a bottom wall 60 and medial and lateral side walls 62A and 62B that extend
upwardly around the toe end 36 of the upper 12. The toe cup 16 is slideably coupled
to the toe end 18 of the base 14 with a fastener 52, such as a rivet, bolt, screw or the
like, that will be described in more detail below. The toe cup 16 includes an
actuator 34 operatively connected within the medial side wall 62A and is a part of a
size adjustment mechanism 64 for adjusting the shoe size of the skate. The
actuator 34 and the size adjustment mechanism 64 will be described in more detail
below.</p>
    <p num="0017">The heel end 38 of upper 12 is securely fastened to the base 14, such as by
riveting, adhesion, stitching, bolts or the like, and is supported by a rigid heel cup 20.
The rigid heel cup 20 may be integrally formed with the base 14, or secured to the
base 14, and extends upwardly therefrom on the lateral and medial sides of the heel
end 38 of the upper 12. The ankle cuff 24 is pivotally secured to the upper lateral
and medial ends of the heel cup 20, to pivot forwardly and rearwardly at about the
natural pivot axis of the ankle. The ankle cuff 24 wraps the rear, lateral and medial
sides of the leg, above the ankle. The ankle cuff strap 48 includes a quick release
ratcheting buckle assembly to selectively secure and tighten the cuff about the leg.</p>
    <p num="0018">The upper 12 of the skate 10 extends continuously upward from the base to
above the upper edge of the ankle cuff 24. However, it should be apparent that the
present invention is also suitably used with skates having an upper that is
discontinuous, having a separate cuff pad, or that terminates below the ankle.</p>
    <p num="0019">Still referring to FIGURE 2, the frame 26 is mounted below or integrally
formed with the base 14, and extends downwardly from the base 14. The frame 26
includes first and second opposing longitudinal side walls 32A and 32B. The
frame 26 carries four wheels, 28A, 28B, 28C, and 28D, journaled between the
opposing side walls 32A and 32B. Each wheel includes a center hub 70 and bearing 
assembly (not shown) that is mounted rotatably on an axle 74 that is inserted through
aligned apertures 76 of the side walls 32A and 32B and is retained by cap screws 78.
The frame 26 can be formed from any suitable rigid material, such as aluminum,
titanium, other metals and alloys, engineering thermoplastics, and fiber reinforced
thermoplastics or thermosetting polymers. An optional brake member may be
fastened to the frame, rearward of the wheel 28D, which is well known in the art.</p>
    <p num="0020">In accordance with an aspect of the present invention, the skate 10 includes a
size adjustment mechanism 64 having an actuator 34 for adjusting the shoe size of
the skate 10, which was briefly discussed above and will now be described in greater
detail with reference to FIGURES 4-9. As shown in FIGURE 4, the toe end 18 of the
base 14 extends as a generally oval shaped member having a substantially flat top
surface 80 suitably sized for supporting the slideably adjustable toe cup. The toe
end 18 includes an elongate, generally rectangular recess or slot 82 open to the top
surface thereof, and extending in the longitudinal dimension of the skate for
receiving a boss of corresponding shape located at the bottom surface of the toe cup.
The slot 82 includes an aperture 84 on the bottom surface of the slot 82, and is
positioned at the forward portion of the slot 82 and extends through the base 14. The
aperture 84 is of a suitable shape and size to receive a fastener such as rivet 52
(FIGURE 2) to securely couple the toe cup to the base 14.</p>
    <p num="0021">Positioned at the rear portion of the slot 82 and formed into the medial side
thereof is a series of detent notches 88A, 88B, 88C, 88D, and 88E. In one
embodiment, the detent notches form teeth that are frusto-conical in shape and
protrude horizontally inward toward the centerline of the slot 82. While shown in
FIGURE 4 as frusto-conical in shape, the detent notches can be of any suitable size
or geometry without departing from the scope of the present invention. The detent
notches 88A, 88B, 88C, 88D, and 88E are operable to engage or mesh with
correspondingly shaped teeth on the actuator to form the indexing size adjustment
mechanism, the operation of which will be described in more detail below. In the
embodiment shown, five detent notches are formed in the base. However, it will be
appreciated that any number of detent notches may be formed in the base. The top 
surface 80 of the toe end 18 further includes an elongate rib member 90 that extends
substantially parallel with the slot 82. The elongate rib member 90 mates with and
slides within a slot of corresponding shape within the bottom wall of the toe cup to
provide a guide mechanism that prevents rotation of the toe cup as it slideably
translates on the toe end 18.</p>
    <p num="0022">Referring now to FIGURES 5 and 6, the toe cup 16 includes a bottom wall 92
having a substantially flat bottom surface 94 for slideably engaging with the top
surface of the base. The toe cup16 also includes medial and lateral side walls 96A
and 96B that extend upwardly from the bottom wall 92 to form a cavity 98. The
cavity 98 is of a suitable dimension to receive. the forefoot of a skater. While shown
as a toe cup, it will be appreciated that the slideable support member can be a toe
member such as a substantially flat plate or bottom wall 92. In either case, the
bottom wall 92 of the toe cup 16 includes a longitudinally disposed slot 109 open to
the bottom surface 94 for mating with the elongate rib member of the base described
above. Extending downwardly from the bottom surface 94 of the toe cup 16 is a
generally rectangular shaped boss 102 with rounded edges. The boss 102 extends
lengthwise in the longitudinal dimension of the skate and is suitably shaped and
positioned at the forward end of the bottom surface 94 to be slideably received within
the slot 82 of the base 14 (FIGURE 4). The boss 102 and corresponding slot of the
toe end form a guide mechanism which, along with the guide mechanism described
above comprised of the slot 108 and the elongate rib member, prevents rotation of the
toe cup as it slideably translates on the toe end of the base.</p>
    <p num="0023">The boss 102 is provided with an elongated slot 104 open to the bottom
surface and also extending in the longitudinal dimension of the skate for passing a
fastener such as rivet 52 when the toe cup 16 is slideably translated with respect to
the base. As best shown in FIGURE. 5, the top surface of the bottom wall 92 includes
an elongate slot 106 formed by downwardly descending side walls of the boss that is
concentric with slot 104. The slot 106 is similar in shape, but larger in size, than
slot 104 to form a shoulder 109 for supporting the head of the fastener 52 as the
slots 104 and 106 pass the fastener when the toe cup16 is slideably translated with 
respect to the base. The fastener 52 can be removable such as a bolt or screw, or can
be nonremovable or permanent such as a rivet. In either case, the fastener 52
securely retains the toe cup on the base during adjustment.</p>
    <p num="0024">Still referring to FIGURES 5 and 6, the bottom wall 92 includes a
horizontally disposed slot 110, which is transverse to the longitudinally dimension of
the skate. The slot 110 is suitably dimensioned to receive the actuator 34 of the size
adjustment mechanism in a slideable fashion. The slot 110 also includes a tab
portion 112 integrally formed at its innermost surface for receiving a biasing
member 118 such as a spring. Integrally formed in the bottom wall 92 are two
diametrically opposed tabs 114A and 114B for supporting the actuator as it slides
horizontally within the slot 110. The rear portion of the medial side wall 96A
includes an aperture 116 for allowing a portion of the actuator to protrude through
the medial side wall 96A. When assembled, the toe cup 16 includes a cover plate or
liner that over lays the top surface of the toe cup to prevent the actuator from falling
out of the slot and to prevent adhesive, fabric, etc. from interfering with the sliding
operation of the actuator.</p>
    <p num="0025">Referring now to FIGURE 3, the actuator 34 of the size adjustment
mechanism will be described in more detail. The actuator 34 is constructed as a
unitary body having a generally T-shaped cross section. The actuator includes an
upper member 120 and a lower member 122 extending transversely from the upper
member 120 to form the T-shaped actuator. At one end, the actuator 34 includes a
generally triangular shaped face 124 preferably grooved and suitably sized for
engagement with the thumb or forefinger of a rider. The upper member 120 of the
actuator 34 is substantially flat to slideably seat within the slot, flush with the top
surface of the toe cup. The lower member 122 extends from the upper member 120
in a downward direction between the diametrically opposed tabs, which supports the
actuator 34 and guides the horizontal translation of the actuator 34. Integrally
formed from the upper member 122 at the end opposite of the face 120 are
engagement members or teeth 126A and 126B. In one embodiment, the teeth are
frusto-conical in geometry and face toward the face 120 of the actuator 34. While 
shown in FIGURE 3 as generally frusto-conical in shape, the teeth 126A and 126B
can be of any suitable size or geometry without departing from the scope of the
present invention. It will be appreciated that the size and geometry of the teeth will
correspond to the size and geometry of the detent notches so that the teeth may
properly mesh with the detent notches. When slideably received in the slot of the
base, the teeth 126A and 126B are disposed substantially horizontal and outwardly
facing. The actuator 34 also includes a tab 130 connected to the rear end surface of
the actuator for receiving one end of the biasing member 118 (FIGURES 5 and 6).
The biasing member 118 biases the actuator 34 outward toward the medial side wall
of the toe cup so that the teeth 126A and 126B mesh with the detent notches of the
base.</p>
    <p num="0026">The operation of the size adjustment mechanism will now be described in
detail with reference to FIGURES 7 and 8. FIGURE 7 depicts the toe cup16 fixed at
a desired longitudinal position relative to the heel end of the base (not shown). The
toe cup 16 is supported by the top surface of the base 14, whereby the boss 102 is
nested within the elongate slot 82 of the base 14. The toe cup 16 is securely fastened
to the base 14 via the fastener 52, which is slideably received within the slot 104 with
the head portion of the fastener 52 supported by the shoulder 108. The actuator 34 is
biased by the biasing member 18 outward such that the teeth 126A and 126B located
on the bottom of the actuator 34 mesh with two of the detent notches 88A-E formed
within the slot 82 (FIGURE 7 shows teeth 126 and 126 meshing with detent
nothing 88 and 88B). In this position, a skater may skate without the toe cup sliding
relative to the base.</p>
    <p num="0027">If the rider wishes to change the size of the skate so that the skate may fit a
skater with a larger foot, the skater may translate the actuator 34 by depressing the
actuator inward with her finger, which is depicted in FIGURE 8. As shown in
FIGURE 8, the actuator 34 is linearly translated in the horizontal plane against the
force of the biasing member 118 to disengage the teeth 126A and 126B of the
actuator 34 from the detent notches 88A-E of the slot 82. In this position, the toe
cup 16 may slide or translate in the longitudinal dimension relative to the heel end of 
the base (note shown) to increase the size of the cavity formed by the upper so that
the upper 12 may receive a larger foot of a skater. The toe cup 16 and actuator 34
travel together during adjustment. In the embodiment shown, this can be easily done
by grasping the toe cup with one hand and in one movement, depress the actuator
with the thumb and translate the toecup.</p>
    <p num="0028">As the toe cup 16 translates to a final or second desired longitudinal position
shown in FIGURE 8, the boss 102 and elongate rib member 90 slide with the slots 82
and 108, respectively, preventing the toe cup 16 from rotating. Accordingly, the
rivet 52 securably coupling the toe cup 16 to the base passes or translates in the
slot 104 of the boss 102. Once the toe cup 16 is in a desired longitudinal position
relative to the heel end of the base, the actuator 34 may be released by removing the
finger of the rider. After the finger of the rider is released, the biasing force of the
biasing member 118 linearly translates the actuator 34 outward and meshes the
teeth 126A and 126B of the actuator 34 with the detent notches 88A-E of the slot 82,
as described above with reference to FIGURE 7. The tapered shape of the teeth on
the actuator guide the actuator into locking engagement when the actuator is released.</p>
    <p num="0029">An alternative embodiment of a tool-less size-adjustable in-line skate
constructed in accordance with aspects of the present invention is illustrated in
FIGURES 9-12 and will now be described in detail. FIGURE 9 illustrates a front
cross-section of a skate 210. The skate 210 is constructed similar to skate 10
illustrated in FIGURES 1-8, except for differences that will now be described. The
skate 210 includes a toe cup 212 having a bottom wall 214 and upwardly extending
side walls 216A and 216B which define a cavity 218. Downwardly descending from
the bottom wall 214 of the toe cup 212 are two flanges 222A and 222B which define
slots 224A and 224B for receiving a base 226. The base 226 includes a top plate 228
which is slideably coupled with the slots 224A and 224B. The base 226 includes a
centrally located, longitudinal dimensioned slot 230 and two downwardly descending
side walls 232A and 232B. Joumaled between the side walls 232A and 232B are a
plurality of ground engaging members such as wheels 234. </p>
    <p num="0030">The toe cup 212 further includes an elongate member 236 coupled to the
bottom surface of the toe cup 212 and extending downward within the slot 230.
Cantilevered to the end of the elongate member 236 by a fastener such as a screw 238
is a second elongate member 240 to form an actuator. The elongate member 240 is a
resilient member, thus may be deformed and is inherently spring biased to return to
its initial position. The other end of the elongate member 240 extends in a
substantially horizontal plane through an aperture 242 in side wall 232A and
terminates with a knob 246. The elongate member 240 further includes an
engagement member 248 coupled to the elongate member 240 and extending in a
substantially vertical plane. Mounted to the inner surface of side wall 232A, below
the aperture 242, is a second engagement member 250 having a plurality of vertically
arranged detent notches 252A-252D.</p>
    <p num="0031">Another alternative embodiment of a tool-less size-adjustable in-line skate
constructed in accordance with aspects of the present invention is illustrated in
FIGURES 14 and 15 and will now be described in detail. FIGURE 15 illustrates an
isometric cut-away view of a skate 310. The skate 310 is constructed similar to
skate 10 illustrated in FIGURES 1-8, except for differences that will now be
described. The skate 310 includes a toe cup 312 having a bottom wall 314 and
upwardly extending side walls 316A and 316B which define a cavity 318.
Downwardly descending from the bottom wall 314 of the toe cup 212 are two side
walls 322A and 322B. Extending in an outward direction, transverse from the end of
side walls 322A and 322B are flanges 324A and 324B which define slots 326A and
326B for receiving a base 328. Mounted in a slot (not shown) through side
wall 322A in a slideable fashion is an actuator 340.</p>
    <p num="0032">As best shown in FIGURE 14, the actuator 340 is of a unitary construction
substantially rectangular in shape. One end of the actuator is contoured to define an
engagement face 342 for engagement with the thumb or forefinger of a rider. At the
opposite end of the actuator is an integrally formed biasing member 344, which abuts
against the inner surface of side wall 322 B (FIGURE 15). The upper surface of the
actuator 340 is substantially flat to slideably seat within the slot in the toe cup 312 
(FIGURE 15). Integrally formed in the bottom surface of the actuator 340 are
engagement members or teeth 346A and 346B. In one embodiment, the teeth are
rectangular in geometry and extend in the direction of the face 342. While shown in
FIGURE 14 as rectangular in shape, the teeth 346A and 346B may be of any suitable
size and geometry without departing from the scope of the present invention. When
slideably received in the slot of side wall 322A, the teeth 346A and 346B are
disposed substantially horizontal and outwardly facing. The biasing member 344
biases the actuator 34 outward toward the side wall 322A of the toe cup so that the
teeth 346A and 346B mesh with detent notches 350 in the base 328.</p>
    <p num="0033">Referring now to FIGURE 15, the base 328 includes a top plate 360 having a
longitudinal slot 362 therein which defines rails 364A and 364B. The slot 362 is
centrally located for receiving the side walls 322A and 322B of the toe cup 312. The
rails 364A and 364B slide within the slots 326A and 326B of the toe cup 312 to
slideably coupled the toe cup to the base 328. Formed in the inner surface of the
slot 362 are a plurality of detent notches 350, which mesh with teeth 346A and 346B
of the actuator to fix the toe cup in a stationary position. Downwardly descending
from the top plate 360 are side walls 368A and 368B. Journaled between the side
walls 368A and 368B are a plurality of ground engaging members such as
wheels 370.</p>
    <p num="0034">While the exemplary embodiments of the size adjustment mechanism
described above and illustrated herein has been shown to utilize teeth and detent
notches selectively secure the toe cup to the base, it should be readily evident that the
size adjustment mechanism may utilize other detent mechanisms, such as a biased
plunger meshing with grooves, without departing from the scope of the present
invention.</p>
    <p num="0035">Additionally, while the exemplary embodiments of the size adjustment
mechanism described above and illustrated herein has been shown to adjust the toe
cup in a longitudinal direction, it should be readily evident that the size adjustment
mechanism may be utilize to adjust the toe cup in the lateral direction to 
accommodate a wider foot or to expand the volume of the upper without departing
from the scope of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0036">The embodiments above have been illustrated and described in terms of an in-line
roller skate. It should be understood that the size adjustment mechanism may
also be utilized with other types of roller skates and with ice skates. Additionally, the
size adjustment mechanism may be adapted for use with other types of athletic boots
for sports.</p>
    <p num="0037">While the preferred embodiment of the invention has been illustrated and
described, it will be appreciated that various changes can be made therein without
departing from the spirit and scope of the invention.</p>
    <p num="0038">The embodiments of the invention in which an exclusive property or privilege is claimed are defined as follows:</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A size-adjustable skate having at least one ground engaging member
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a base having a top surface for supporting a skater's foot and a bottom
surface, said base defining a plurality of detents;</claim-text><claim-text>an upper for receiving a skater's foot, said upper defining a toe portion, a heel
portion, and diametrically opposed side wall portions, said upper coupled to said
base;</claim-text><claim-text>a support structure for supporting said upper, said support structure including
a toe member having top and bottom surfaces, said toe member coupled to said toe
portion of said upper and slideably coupled to said base, said toe member slideably
adjustable between a plurality of positions on said base; and</claim-text><claim-text>an actuator coupled to said toe member, said actuator operable to move in a
plane substantially coplaner with said top surface of said base;</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein said toe member is selectively movable on said base to adjust the
shoe size of said skate by operation of a size adjustment mechanism formed between
said detents of said base and a portion of said actuator.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A size-adjustable skate having at least one ground engaging member
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a base having a top surface for supporting a skater's foot and a bottom
surface, said base defining a plurality of detents;</claim-text><claim-text>an upper for receiving a skater's foot, said upper defining a toe portion, a heel
portion, and diametrically opposed side wall portions, said upper coupled to said
base;</claim-text><claim-text>a support structure for supporting said upper, said support structure including
a toe member having top and bottom surfaces, said toe member coupled to said toe
portion of said upper and slideably coupled to said base, said toe member slideably
adjustable between a plurality of positions on said base; and</claim-text><claim-text>an actuator coupled to said toe member, said actuator operable to move in a
plane substantially coplaner with said top surface of said base;</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein said toe member is selectively movable on said base to adjust the
shoe size of said skate.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The skate of Claim 2, wherein said toe member is slideably adjustable
between a plurality of longitudinal positions on said base.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The skate of Claim 2, wherein said toe member slideably coupled to
said base by a fastener.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The skate of Claim 4, wherein said fastener is a permanent fastener.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The skate of Claim 2, wherein said plurality of detents are
horizontally disposed in said top surface of said base.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>The skate of Claim 4, wherein said top surface of said base includes a
slot disposed in the longitudinal dimension of the skate, said detents are formed in a
side of said slot.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The skate of Claim 7, wherein a bottom surface of said toe member
includes a downwardly descending boss, said boss being disposed longitudinally and
mates with said slot.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>The skate of Claim 8, wherein said boss includes a slot, said fastener
translatable within said slot of said boss.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>The skate of Claim 2, wherein said top surface of said base includes
an elongate rib member and said bottom surface of said toe member includes a slot of
corresponding shape with respect to said elongate rib member, said elongate rib
member and said slot mate to form a guide mechanism for preventing the rotation of
said toe member when said toe member slideably adjusts relative to said base.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>The skate of Claim 2, wherein said toe member includes a bottom wall
in slideable relation with said base, said bottom wall having a slot extending
therethrough, said actuator slideably coupled within said slot.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>The skate of Claim 2, wherein said actuator includes horizontally
oriented teeth, said teeth engage and disengage with said detents of said base.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>A size-adjustable skate having at least one ground engaging member
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a base having a top surface for supporting a skater's foot and a bottom
surface, said base defining a plurality of detents;</claim-text><claim-text>and upper for receiving a skater's foot, said upper defining a toe portion, a
heel portion, and diametrically opposed side wall portions;</claim-text><claim-text>a support structure for supporting said upper, said support structure including
a toe member coupled to said toe portion of said upper and slideably coupled to said
base, said toe member slideably adjustable between a plurality of longitudinal
positions; and</claim-text><claim-text>an actuator operably coupled to said toe member, and translatable with said
toe member, that selectively engages one of said plurality of detents of said base;</claim-text><claim-text>said actuator operable to fix said toe member to said base in a desired
longitudinal position relative to said heel portion and operable to adjust said toe
member so that said toe member slides longitudinally to achieve a second desired
longitudinal position relative to said heel portion.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>The skate of Claim 13, wherein said actuator is moved substantially
vertical to permit said toe member to slide longitudinally, to achieve a second
longitudinal position.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>The skate of Claim 13, wherein said actuator is moved substantially
horizontal to permit said toe member to slide longitudinally to achieve a second
longitudinal position.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>The skate of Claim 13, wherein said toe member is slideably coupled
to said base by a fastener.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>The skate of Claim13, wherein said plurality of detents are
horizontally disposed within said base.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="18">
      <claim-text>A size-adjustable in-line skate having at least one ground engaging
member comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a base having a top surface for supporting a skater's foot and a bottom
surface;</claim-text><claim-text>a frame coupled to the bottom surface of said base, said frame including an
aperture positioned between ground engaging members;</claim-text><claim-text>an upper coupled to said base for receiving a skater's foot, said upper defining
a toe portion, a heel portion, and diametrically opposed side wall portions;</claim-text><claim-text>an elongate member coupled to the bottom surface of said toe member and
translatable within said slot;</claim-text><claim-text>a second elongate member cantilevered to said elongate member and
extending through said aperture, said second elongate member including a first
engagement member; and</claim-text><claim-text>a second engagement member having a plurality of detents, said second
engagement member coupled to said frame;</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein said first engagement member engages said one of said plurality of
detents to fix said toe member to said base in a desired longitudinal position relative
to said heel portion and said first engagement member disengaging with said one of
said plurality of said detents to slideably adjust said toe member in a longitudinal
dimension relative to said heel portion.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="19">
      <claim-text>The skate of Claim 18, wherein said second elongate member is
moved vertically to disengage said first engagement member with one of said
plurality of detents.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="20">
      <claim-text>A size-adjustable skate having at least one ground engaging member
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a base having a top surface for supporting a skater's foot and a bottom
surface;</claim-text><claim-text>an upper for receiving a skater's foot, said upper defining a toe portion, a heel
portion, and diametrically opposed side wall portions said upper coupled to said base;</claim-text><claim-text>a support structure for supporting said upper, said support structure including
a toe member coupled to said toe portion of said upper and slideably coupled to said
base, said toe member selectively slideably adjustable between a plurality of
longitudinal positions; and</claim-text><claim-text>an actuator operably coupled to said toe member and slideable with said toe
member, said actuator selectively operable to engage with a portion of said base to
fix said toe member in a desired longitudinal position, and is operable to disengage
with a portion of said base to allow said toe member to slideably translate on said
base to a second desired longitudinal position; said actuator further operable to move
in a plane substantially coplaner with said toe surface of said base.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="21">
      <claim-text>The skate of Claim 20, wherein said toe member is slidably coupled to
said base by a fastener.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="22">
      <claim-text>The skate of Claim 20, where said actuator is biased to engage with a
position of said base to fix said to member in a desired longitudinal position.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="23">
      <claim-text>The skate of Claim 20, wherein said toe member is a toe cup.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="24">
      <claim-text>A size-adjustable skate having at least one ground engaging member
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a base having a top surface for supporting a skater's foot and a bottom
surface, said base defining a plurality of detents;</claim-text><claim-text>an upper for receiving a skater's foot and coupled to said base, said upper
defining a toe portion, a heel portion, and diametrically opposed side wall portions,
said side wall portions defining a vamp opening extending upwardly from said toe
portion of said upper;</claim-text><claim-text>said upper further including a tongue disposed within said upper and having a
lower end fastened to said toe portion of said upper and extending upwardly along
said vamp opening, and an elastic web fastened to said upper on said diametrically
opposed side wall portions and spanning across at least a portion of said vamp
opening over the instep of the skater's foot, compressing said tongue under said vamp
portion;</claim-text><claim-text>a support structure for supporting said upper, said support structure including
a toe member having top and bottom surfaces, said toe member coupled to said toe
portion of said upper and slideably coupled to said base, said toe member slideably
adjustable between a plurality of positions on said base; and</claim-text><claim-text>an actuator coupled to said toe member, said actuator operable to move in a
plane substantially coplaner with said top surface of said base;</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein said toe member is selectively movable on said base to adjust the
shoe size of said skate.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
