<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1264993-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1264993" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="26844869" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021211">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1264993-A2" status="new" fvid="23640522">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1264993</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021211</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02077083-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02077083</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020528</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="US-14737502-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>14737502</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20020516</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
      <priority-claim ucid="US-29665701-P" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>29665701</doc-number>
          <kind>P</kind>
          <date>20010607</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  45/26        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  45/26        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F16B   5/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F16B   5/06        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F16B  19/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F16B  19/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B29C  45/26</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F16B  19/02</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F16B   5/06B3</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L29C509:08</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren und Vorrichtung zur Befestigung von Luftfiltergehäusen</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Method and apparatus for attachment of air cleaner housing</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé et dispositif pour l'attachement du logement de filtre à air</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SIEMENS VDO AUTOMOTIVE INC</name>
            <address>
              <country>CA</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SIEMENS VDO AUTOMOTIVE INC.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Siemens VDO Automotive Inc.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>700 Park Avenue East</street>
              <city>Chatham, Ontario N7M 5M7</city>
              <country>CA</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KEHOE JON DAVIE</name>
            <address>
              <country>CA</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MARCUS BRIAN MAURICE</name>
            <address>
              <country>CA</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KEHOE, JON DAVIE</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MARCUS, BRIAN MAURICE</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>KEHOE, JON DAVIE</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>142 Pierella Drive RR No. 1</street>
              <city>Belle River, Ontario N0R 1A0</city>
              <country>CA</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>MARCUS, BRIAN MAURICE</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>9295 Fairview Lane</street>
              <city>Chatham, Ontario N7M 5J4</city>
              <country>CA</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Payne, Janice Julia</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Siemens AG, Postfach 22 16 34</street>
              <city>80506 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>An injection molded component includes a plurality of integrally formed
push pins that provide a simplified attachment interface for attaching the component
to a vehicle structure. The injection molded component includes a base housing
component with an upper and lower surfaces. Each pin extends out from the lower
surface of the base housing component to a distal end. A plurality of radially
extending flanges is formed about the circumference of the distal end. The flanges
are spaced apart from one another and form a retention feature that is inserted into
an appropriate vehicle structural component to secure the base housing component
to the vehicle. The formation of flanges on the pins eliminates the need for
additional injection mold tooling actions to further form the attachment interface.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="120" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="85"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0001">This invention relates to a method and apparatus for providing an attachment
feature on an injection molded component without requiring any additional injection
mold tooling actions to further form the attachment feature.</p>
    <p num="0002">Injection molded components are used in a variety of different applications
in a vehicle. An example of one injection molded component is an air cleaner
housing. In the past air cleaner housings have been installed into the vehicle by
using separate push pin members and a grommet. The push pins are inserted into
openings in a base portion of the air cleaner housing and are then pushed into a
grommet that is mounted to a vehicle structure. This process is labor intensive and
time consuming.</p>
    <p num="0003">One proposed solution has been to incorporate the details of the push pin
directly into the housing by molding pin attachment features into the base of the air
cleaner housing. This current process requires extensive injection mold tool actions
to form pin attachment features. These mold actions include slide actions and/or
running the parting line around the particular feature to create an undercut that
retains the grommet. Such additional tooling actions increase the overall cost of the
component.</p>
    <p num="0004">Thus, it is desirable to have an attachment feature that can easily be molded
into an injection molded component without requiring extensive injection mold
tooling actions, as well as overcoming the other above mentioned deficiencies with
the prior art.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0005">A retaining assembly is used to attach an injection molded component to a
vehicle structure. The molded component includes a base portion defining a bottom
surface having at least one attachment member for attachment to a vehicle structural
component. The attachment member is integrally formed as one piece with the base
portion such that there is a continuous unbroken surface extending between the base 
portion and attachment member. The attachment member is formed as a cylindrical
body portion that extends to a distal end having a retention member that cooperates
with the vehicle structure component to retain the molded component to the vehicle
structure. The retention member is formed with a plurality flanges spaced apart
from one another and which extend out radially from the cylindrical body portion.</p>
    <p num="0006">Preferably, the injection molded component is an air cleaner housing and the
retention members are integrally formed push pins. The push pins are inserted
through a grommet or other similar component to attach the housing to the
appropriate vehicle structure.</p>
    <p num="0007">In one disclosed embodiment, a pad is formed about at least a portion of the
cylindrical body portion by a lower mold portion. The base portion of the
component further defines a top surface that faces opposite from the bottom surface,
and which includes at least one opening extending through the base portion from the
top surface to the bottom surface adjacent the cylindrical body portion. The opening
receives an upper mold portion, which is positioned at a predetermined distance
apart from the lower mold portion. The flange is formed between the upper and
lower mold portions.</p>
    <p num="0008">The method of forming an air cleaner housing component includes the
following steps. An upper mold defines a top surface of the air cleaner housing
component and includes at least one transversely extending male member defining a
portion of the attachment member. A lower mold defines a bottom surface of the air
cleaner housing component and includes at least one female member defining a
portion of the attachment member. The upper mold is positioned relative to the
lower mold by inserting the male member into the female member. The upper mold
and male member are held at a predetermined distance apart from the lower mold
and female member to define a gap that defines the shape of the air cleaner housing
component. Material is injected into the gap to integrally form the attachment
member and air cleaner housing component as a single piece. Preferably, a plurality
of flanges is formed at a distal end of the attachment members between the upper
and lower molds.</p>
    <p num="0009">The subject apparatus and method provide an attachment interface for an
injection molded component that eliminates the need for additional injection mold 
tool actions, resulting in reduced costs and installation time. These and other
features of the present invention can be best understood from the following
specifications and drawings, the following of which is a brief description.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0010">Figure 1 is an exploded view of an air cleaner housing incorporating the
subject invention.</p>
    <p num="0011">Figure 2 is a perspective view, partially cut-away, of one attachment member
incorporating the subject invention.</p>
    <p num="0012">Figure 3 is a cross-section of the attachment member shown in Figure 2.</p>
    <p num="0013">Figure 4 is a cross-section taken along lines 4-4 in Figure 3.</p>
    <p num="0014">Figure 5 is a bottom view of the attachment member and base component
shown in Figure 2.</p>
    <p num="0015">Figure 6 is a cross-section taken along lines 6-6 of Figure 5.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF A PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0016">An air cleaner housing is shown generally at 10 in Figure 1. The air cleaner
housing includes a main housing portion 12 and a base housing portion 14 that
mounts to a vehicle structure 16, such as a frame member or other vehicle
component. Grommets 18 or other similar members are also preferably included in
mounting the base housing portion 14 to the vehicle structure 16 as is known in the
art. The main 12 and base 14 housing portions are components formed by injection
molding processes.</p>
    <p num="0017">A plurality of attachment members 20 are integrally formed as one piece
with the base housing portion 14 during the injection molding process. This will be
discussed in further detail below. The number of attachment members 20 can vary
depending on the size of the air cleaner housing 10 and the type of vehicle structure
16 that the air cleaner housing is being mounted to. An enlarged view of one of the
attachment members is shown in Figure 2. It should be understood that all
attachment members 20 are formed in a similar manner as that which will be
discussed below. </p>
    <p num="0018">As shown in Figure 2, the attachment member 20 and base housing portion
14 are formed as a single piece. The attachment member 20 includes a cylindrical
body portion 22 that extends from a base end 24 to a distal end 26. A plurality of
radially extending flanges 28 are formed on the distal end 26. Preferably three (3)
flanges are formed that are spaced approximately ninety degrees apart from one
another. While this is the preferred configuration, it should be understood that more
or less flanges 28 could be formed at the distal end 26 with varying spacing patterns.
The flanges 28 form a retainer head portion that is pushed or snapped into the
grommets 18 and/or vehicle structure 16 to retain the air cleaner housing 10 in the
vehicle.</p>
    <p num="0019">The attachment members 20 extend outwardly from a bottom surface 30 on
the bottom housing portion 14. The attachment members 20 are orientated
transversely to the bottom surface 30 and are preferably perpendicular to the bottom
surface 30. This provides for easy installation by applying a single vertical force to
push the attachment members 20 into the vehicle structure 16.</p>
    <p num="0020">A cross-section of the retainer head portion of the attachment member 20 is
shown in Figure 3. The cylindrical body portion 22 defines a center 32 with the
flanges 28 extending out radially away from the center 32. Each of the flanges 28
has a base 34 that extends out to a tip 36. Preferably, the flanges 28 are narrower at
the base 34 than at the tip 36. The tips 36 preferably form an arcuate surface 38.
The arcuate surface 38 facilitates push in force and helps accommodate for any misalignments
between mating components.</p>
    <p num="0021">As shown in Figure 4, each of the flanges 28 is orientated transversely to the
cylindrical body portion 22. Further the cylindrical body portion 22 is preferably
greater in length L1 than the length L2 of the flange 28.</p>
    <p num="0022">As shown in Figure 5, recesses or pockets 40 are formed within the base
housing portion 14 to allow the flanges 28 to be formed between an upper mold half
42 and a lower mold half 44 (Figure 6). A raised pad portion 46 is also integrally
formed about the cylindrical body portion 22 of the attachment member 20 during
the molding process. The pad portion 46 cooperates with the grommets 18 and/or
vehicle structure 16 to accommodate varying grommet heights. </p>
    <p num="0023">The formation of the flanges 28 between the upper 42 and lower 44 molds is
shown in Figure 6. The base housing portion 14 includes a bottom surface 30 and
an opposing top surface 48. The upper mold 42 has a profile that defines the
contours of the top surface 48 of the base housing portion 14. The lower mold 44
has a profile that defines the contours of the bottom surface 30.</p>
    <p num="0024">The upper mold 42 includes a male member 50 that extends from a base 52
to a distal end surface 54 with a male sidewall portion 56 extending between the
base 52 and end surface 54. The lower mold 44 includes a female member 58
defining a bottom face 60 with a female wall portion 62 extending upwardly from
the bottom face 60 of the molds 42, 44. The flanges 28 are formed between the
distal end surface 54 and the bottom face 60.</p>
    <p num="0025">Material, such as plastic, is injected between the upper 42 and lower 44
molds to form the base housing portion 14. Preferably, the male member 50 is non-concentrically
positioned within the female member 58 such that the material does
not completely surround the male member 50. Thus, the cylindrical body portion 22
is formed between the male sidewall portion 56 and the female walled portion 62 at
one side of the male member 50.</p>
    <p num="0026">The lower mold 44 includes a groove 64 or other similar formation that
forms the pad portion 46. As shown in Figure 6, a continuous unbroken surface
extends from the bottom surface 30 of the base housing component 14 to the pad
portion 46, to the cylindrical body portion 22, and finally to the flange 28.</p>
    <p num="0027">An opening 66 that extends through the base housing portion 14 from the top
surface 48 to the bottom surface 30 provides the clearance for the male member 50
of the upper mold 42 to make the undercut flange 28. No further mold tooling
actions are required to form the attachment members 20. Once the mold halves 42,
44 are separated, the attachment members 20 can be pushed into place.</p>
    <p num="0028">The method for forming the attachment members 20 and base housing
portion 14 as a single piece includes the following steps. The upper mold 42 is
positioned relative to the lower mold 44 by inserting the male member 50 into the
female member 58. The upper mold 42 and male member 50 are held at a
predetermined distance apart from the lower mold 44 and female member 58 to
define a gap 68 that defines the shape of the base housing component 14. The 
material is injected into the gap 68 by means well known in the art to integrally form
the attachment member 20 and base housing component 14 as a single piece. The
distal end surface 54 is positioned apart from the bottom face 60 by a first
predetermined distance, and male sidewall 56 is held apart from the female walled
portion 62 by a second predetermined distance. The flanges 28 are formed between
the distal end surface 54 and bottom face 60 to a predetermined thickness defined by
the first predetermined distance and the cylindrical body portion 22 is formed
between the female wall 62 and male 56 sidewall portions.</p>
    <p num="0029">The subject method and apparatus provides an attachment feature that can
easily be molded into an injection molded component without requiring extensive
injection mold tooling actions. This reduces cost and simplifies installation
procedures. Although a preferred embodiment of this invention has been disclosed,
a worker of ordinary skill in this art would recognize that certain modifications
would come within the scope of this invention. For that reason, the following claims
should be studied to determine the true scope and content of this invention.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A retainer apparatus for attaching a component to a vehicle structure
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a molded component including a base portion defining a bottom
surface having at least one attachment member for attachment to a vehicle structural
component, said attachment member being integrally formed as one piece with said
base portion;</claim-text><claim-text>said attachment member including a cylindrical body portion
extending out from said bottom surface to a distal end having a retention member
that cooperates with the vehicle structure component to retain said molded
component to the vehicle structure; and</claim-text><claim-text>said retention member including a plurality flanges spaced apart from
one another and extending out radially from said cylindrical body portion.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as set forth in claim 1 wherein said attachment member
and said base portion are interconnected by at least one continuous unbroken
surface.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as set forth in claim 2 wherein said attachment member
extends in a direction traverse to said bottom surface.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as set forth in claim 1 including a pad formed about at
least a portion of said cylindrical body portion by a lower mold portion and wherein
said base portion defines a top surface facing opposite from said bottom surface and
including at least one opening extending through said base portion from said top
surface to said bottom surface adjacent said cylindrical body portion, said opening
for receiving an upper mold portion at a predetermined distance apart from said
lower mold portion wherein flange thickness is defined by said predetermined
distance.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as set forth in claim 1 wherein said plurality of flanges
comprises three flanges spaced approximately ninety degrees apart from one
another.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>An apparatus as set forth in claim 1 including at least one pad
integrally formed in said bottom surface about at least a portion of the circumference
of said cylindrical body.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>An air cleaner housing assembly comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a main housing component;</claim-text><claim-text>a base component connectible to said main housing component and
defining a bottom surface having at least one attachment member for attachment to a
vehicle structure, said attachment member being integrally formed as one piece with
said base portion;</claim-text><claim-text>said attachment member including a cylindrical body portion with a
base extending to a distal end having a retention member that cooperates with the
vehicle structure to retain said base component to said vehicle structure; and</claim-text><claim-text>said retention member including a plurality flanges spaced apart from
one another and extending out radially from said cylindrical body portion.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A housing assembly as set forth in claim 7 wherein said attachment
member and said base are interconnected by at least one continuous unbroken
surface.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>A housing assembly as set forth in claim 8 wherein said base
component defines a top surface facing opposite from said bottom surface and
including at least one opening extending through said base component from said top
surface to said bottom surface adjacent said base, said opening for receiving a first
mold portion to form said flanges.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>A housing assembly as set forth in claim 9 including a pad portion
extending outwardly from said bottom surface and being integrally formed about at
least a portion of the circumference of said base by a second mold portion, said pad
portion defining an engagement surface that cooperates with said vehicle structure.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>A housing assembly as set forth in claim 10 wherein said vehicle
structure includes a grommet mounted to a vehicle structural component, said
retention member being inserted into said grommet with said engagement surface
cooperating with said grommet to accommodate variable grommet heights.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>A housing assembly as set forth in claim 8 wherein said plurality of
flanges comprises three flanges spaced approximately ninety degrees apart from one
another.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>A method of forming an air cleaner housing component comprising
the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) providing an upper mold defining a top surface of the air
cleaner housing component and including at least one transversely extending male
member defining a portion of an attachment member for attaching the air cleaner
housing component to a vehicle structure;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) providing a lower mold defining a bottom surface of the air
cleaner housing component and including at least one female member defining a
portion of the attachment member;</claim-text><claim-text>(c) positioning the upper mold relative to the lower mold by
inserting the male member into the female member;</claim-text><claim-text>(d) positioning the upper mold and male member at a
predetermined distance apart from the lower mold and female member to define a
gap that defines the shape of the air cleaner housing component;</claim-text><claim-text>(e) injecting material into the gap to integrally form the
attachment member and air cleaner housing component as a single piece.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>A method as set forth in claim 13 further including the step of
positioning the male member in a non-concentric relationship to the female member
such that the material cannot completely surround the male member during step (d).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>A method as set forth in claim 13 wherein the attachment member
includes a cylindrical body portion extending to a distal end and further including
the step of forming a plurality of radially extending flanges on the distal end of the
attachment member.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>A method as set forth in claim 15 further including the step of
forming three flanges spaced apart from each other by approximately ninety degrees.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>A method as set forth in claim 15 wherein the male member includes
a base that extends to a distal end surface with a sidewall portion extending between
the base and distal end surface and wherein the female member includes a female
wall portion that extends downward to a bottom face and further including the steps
of
   positioning the distal end surface apart from the bottom face by a first
predetermined distance,
   positioning the sidewall portion apart from the female wall portion by
a second predetermined distance.
   forming the flanges between the distal end surface and bottom face,
and
   forming the cylindrical body portion between the female wall and
sidewall portions.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="18">
      <claim-text>A method as set forth in claim 15 further including the step of
integrally forming a pad portion about at least a portion of the cylindrical body
portion.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
