<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1253478-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1253478" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="26611706" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021030">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1253478-A2" status="new" fvid="23586626">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1253478</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021030</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02252033-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02252033</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020321</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001081211-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001081211</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010321</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2002060796-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2002060796</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20020306</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41J  29/46        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41J  29/46        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B65H   5/06        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B65H   5/06        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B65H   7/06        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B65H   7/06        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03G  15/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03G  15/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03G  15/16        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03G  15/16        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03G  21/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03G  21/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03G  21/14        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03G  21/14        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G03G  15/16F1</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">S03G215:00C10</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">S03G215:00G3S7</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Bilderzeugungsverfahren und -apparat mit effektiv durchführbarer Blattübergabe</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Method and apparatus for image forming capable of performing a stable sheet transfer operation</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Méthode et appareil de formation d'images pour exécuter des opérations effectifs de transfert de feuilles</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>RICOH KK</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>RICOH COMPANY, LTD.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Ricoh Company, Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>3-6, Nakamagome 1-chome, Ohta-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo 143-8555</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>UEDA KENJI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>UEDA, KENJI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>UEDA, KENJI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>3-6 Nakamagome 1-chome</street>
              <city>Ohta-ku, Tokyo 143-8555</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Senior, Alan Murray</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>J.A. Kemp &amp;amp; Co., 14 South Square, Gray's Inn</street>
              <city>LONDON WC1R 5JJ</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A sheet transferring apparatus for use in an image
forming apparatus includes a sheet transferring mechanism (106)
and a controller. Continuously transporting copy
sheets and with the sheet transferring mechanism
transfering a recording sheet (2) at a transfer speed to an image
forming mechanism (12) in the image forming apparatus, the
controller determines the transfer speed based on the measured
transfer speed used for an immediately previous recording
sheet.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="65" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="133"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a method and
apparatus for image forming, and more particularly to a
method and apparatus for image forming that is capable of
performing a stable sheet transfer operation.</p>
    <p num="0002">A typical background sheet transferring apparatus in
use for an image forming apparatus, such as a laser printer,
a plain paper copying machine, a facsimile machine, etc.,
is illustrated in Fig. 1. The background sheet
transferring apparatus of Fig. 1 has a sheet passage for a
recording sheet traveling from a sheet container 1 through
a photoconductive member 12. In Fig. 1, a stack of
recording sheets 2 stocked in the sheet container 1 are
positioned such that leading edges of the recording sheets
2 are neatly aligned at an initial position A. When a
sheet transfer operation is started, a sheet feed signal is
turned on in an electrical control system (not shown) and
is transmitted to the background sheet transferring 
apparatus. With the sheet feed signal, a pick-up roller 3
is lowered and is rotated so as to move the recording
sheets 2 towards a position B where a sheet separation
mechanism is provided. The sheet separation mechanism,
namely, a friction reverse roller system includes a feed
roller 4 for being rotated to limit and to move one
recording sheet 2 forward and a reverse roller 5 for being
rotated to move back the accompanying recording sheets 2.
The feed roller 4 and the reverse roller 5 are driven at
the same time the pick-up roller 3 is driven so that a
recording sheet 2 is separated and is transferred forward.
In this example, the feed roller 4, the reverse roller 5,
and the pick-up roller 3 are driven with a motor (not
shown).</p>
    <p num="0003">After being separated at the position B by the
friction reverse roller system, the recording sheet 2 is
moved such that the leading edge of the recording sheet 2
reaches a photo sensor 6 located at a position C. Then,
the pick-up roller 3 is lifted and is stopped to be driven
so that the pick-up roller 3 loses a sheet transfer power
for moving the recording sheet 2. After that, the
recording sheet 2 is further moved to a transfer roller 7
located at a position E by a sheet transfer power of the
feed roller 4. The feed roller 4 is stopped to be driven 
in a time period t1 (see Fig. 2) after having been driven
so that the leading edge of the recording sheet 2 is moved
to a position F downstream from the position E. After the
feed roller 4 is stopped to be driven, the recording sheet
2 is further transferred by the transfer roller 7. The
leading edge of the recording sheet 2 is then brought to
pass a photo sensor 8 located at a position H and then to
reach a position I when the trailing edge of the recording
sheet 2 is brought away from the sheet separation mechanism.
After that, the leading edge of the recording sheet 2 is
further moved to a transfer roller 9 located at a position
E'. In the above operations, the transfer rollers 7 and 9
are driven with a transfer roller driving motor (not shown).
The recording sheet 2 is then transferred to a photo sensor
10 (referred to as a registration sensor 10) located at a
position J and to a registration roller 11 located at a
position K. Further, the recording sheet 2 is transferred
to an image transfer section located at a position M and
which is composed of the photoconductive member 12 and an
image transfer roller 13.</p>
    <p num="0004">Fig. 2 is a convenient graph with respect to a sheet
transferring performance of the background sheet
transferring apparatus, which is composed of a performance
characteristic graph 1 to a time chart 1. The performance 
characteristic graph 1 demonstrates a characteristic of a
sheet transfer operation of the background sheet
transferring apparatus by showing successive positions of
leading and trailing edges of a recording sheet in the
sheet passage in response to a time parameter. The time
chart 1 shows the sheet feed signal and the subsequent
actions of the various components in connection with the
movement of the recording sheets shown in the performance
characteristic graph 1. In the performance characteristic
graph 1, the vertical axis represents a distance from the
initial position A to a position after the position K and
the horizontal axis represents time. In the performance
characteristic graph 1, with a time parameter, solid lines
represent actual positions of the leading edge of a
recording sheet 2 and thick broken lines represent actual
positions of the trailing edge of the recording sheet 2.
Thin two-dotted chain lines represent calculated positions
of the leading edge of the recording sheet 2 without
consideration of slippage of the recording sheets 2
relative to the rollers and wearing of the rollers. Thin
broken lines represent calculated positions of the trailing
edge of the recording sheet 2 without consideration of
slippage of the recording sheets 2 relative to the rollers
and wearing of the rollers. In this example, the recording 
sheet 2 has a letter size and is transferred in a direction
of a short edge having a length of 216 mm.</p>
    <p num="0005">In a time period t2 after the leading edge of the
recording sheet 2 is brought to reach the registration
sensor 10 at the position J, the transfer roller driving
motor is stopped so that the transfer rollers 7 and 9 lose
sheet transfer powers for moving the recording sheet 2.
The time period t2 is determined so that the leading edge
of the recording sheet 2 is brought to reach the
registration roller 11. At this time, the registration
roller 11 is not driven. With this determination of the
time period t2, a skew correction is conducted. That is,
the leading edge of the recording sheet 2 is brought to
collide against the registration roller 11 so that the
recording sheet 2 makes a slack before the registration
roller 11 which corrects a skew if it exists. In this
example, the time period t2 is set to 37.5 ms.</p>
    <p num="0006">After that, the transfer roller driving motor is
driven at the same time the registration roller 11 is
driven so that the rotations of the transfer rollers 7 and
9 are restarted. Consequently, the recording sheet 2 is
further transferred to the image transfer section so that
an image formed on the photoconductive member 12 is
transferred onto the recording sheet 2. The registration 
roller 11 is configured to turn on in a time period t3
after the photo sensor 8 at the position H is turned on.
In this example, the time period t3 is set to 400 ms. With
this time period t3, the movement of the recording sheet 2
is timed in synchronism with the rotation of the
photoconductive member 12 so that the position of the image
on the photoconductive member 12 matches the position of
the recording sheet 2.</p>
    <p num="0007">In the performance characteristic graph 1 of Fig. 2,
distances of the various positions with reference to the
initial position A are set as follows:
<sl><li>28 mm between the positions A and B,</li><li>38 mm between the positions A and C,</li><li>123.4 mm between the positions A and E,</li><li>133.4 mm between the positions A and F,</li><li>231.9 mm between the positions A and H,</li><li>244 mm between the positions A and I,</li><li>344 mm between the positions A and J,</li><li>359 mm between the positions A and K, and</li><li>216 mm between the positions B and I.</li></sl>
With the arrangement above, the following time periods t11
- t16 are needed:
<sl><li>979.75 ms for the time period t11 in which the
transfer roller driving motor is driven in synchronism with 
a rise time of the sheet feed signal;</li><li>1048.5 ms for the time period t12 from a rise time of
the sheet feed signal to a time the registration roller 11
is turned on;</li><li>826.09 ms for the time period t13 from a rise time to
the next rise time of the registration roller 11;</li><li>755 ms for the time period t14 between calculated
times the leading edges of a recording sheet and the next
recording sheet are forwarded by the registration roller
11;</li><li>252.5 ms for the time period t15 between calculated
times the trailing edges of a recording sheet and the next
recording sheet are forwarded by the registration roller
11; and</li><li>322.82 ms for the time period t16 between a rise time
to a fall time of the registration sensor 10.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0008">In addition, the time period t1 represents a time the
feed roller 4 is being driven, the time period t2
represents a time from a rise time of the registration
sensor 10 to a time the transfer roller driving motor is
stopped, the time period t3 represents a time from a rise
time of the photo sensor 8 to a time the registration
roller 11 is driven, and the time period t4 represents a
time from a fall time of the registration sensor 10 to a 
time the registration roller 11 is stopped.</p>
    <p num="0009">In the above-described background sheet transferring
apparatus, the transfer rollers are apt to lose the sheet
transfer powers and the diameters due to wear over time and
has a consequent tendency to increasingly cause an excess
slippage against the recording sheet 2. This leads to a
reduction of the sheet transfer linear speed and adversely
affects a printing productivity. More specifically, in the
sheet transfer process, the recording sheet 2 is
transferred forward while being slipped against the rollers
due to a given load such as a load from the reverse roller
5 in the sheet separation mechanism, a load from another
recording sheet in close contact, or the like. Largeness
of the load depends on the nature of the recording sheet 2,
such as a size of the sheet, the surface of the sheet, etc.
That is, there is a tendency that the recording sheet 2
suffering a small load causes a small slippage and the
recording sheet 2 suffering a large load causes a large
slippage. In addition, the recording sheet 2 increasingly
causes such slippage with time due to a reduction of the
sheet transfer power caused by the following phenomena.
This is, the surface of the recording sheet 2 is changed by
deposition of a paper dust or wear. Also, the transfer
rollers have a friction coefficient µ which is reduced due 
to variations of rubber material over time. Furthermore,
the reduction of the roller diameters due to wear with time
causes another problematic reduction of the sheet transfer
linear speed.</p>
    <p num="0010">Figs 3A and 3B show various data associated with the
performance of the background sheet transferring apparatus
that has the sheet transfer linear speed of 400 mm/s. The
data includes a ratio of a sheet slippage, a reduction of a
roller diameter, a reduction of the sheet transfer linear
speed, and an actual sheet transfer linear speed performed
in each part of the sheet passage of the background sheet
transferring apparatus. Figs. 3A and 3B may be read as one
data table having columns AA, BB, CC, DD, EE, FF, and GG.</p>
    <p num="0011">In Figs. 3A and 3B, the sheet passage is divided into
the following passage parts, which are indicated in a
column AA of Figs. 3A and 3B:
<sl><li>A-B represents a passage part between the positions A
and B, that is, from the initial position A to the sheet
separation mechanism;</li><li>B-E represents a passage part between the positions B
and F, that is, from the sheet separation mechanism to the
transfer roller 7;</li><li>E-F represents a passage part between the positions E
and F, that is, from the transfer roller 7 to the position 
F to which the leading edge of the recording sheet 2 is
moved when the feed roller 7 is turned off;</li><li>F-H represents a passage part between the positions F
and H, that is, from the position F to the photo sensor 8;</li><li>H-I represents a passage part between the positions H
and I, that is, from the photo sensor 8 to the position I
to which the leading edge of the recording sheet 2 is moved
when the trailing edge of the recording sheet 2 is brought
away from the sheet separation mechanism;</li><li>I-J represents a passage part between the positions I
and J, that is, from the position I to the registration
sensor 10;</li><li>J-K represents a passage part between the positions J
and K, that is, from the registration sensor 10 to the
registration roller 11; and</li><li>K-M represents a passage part between the positions K
and M, that is, from the registration roller 11 to the
image transfer section.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0012">The components particularly activated and essential
in the sheet transfer operations in each of the above-mentioned
passage parts of column AA of Figs. 3A and 3B are
as follows:
<sl><li>A-B; the pick-up roller 3,</li><li>B-E; the pick-up roller 3 and the feed roller 4, </li><li>E-F; the feed roller 4 and the transfer roller 7,</li><li>F-H; the transfer roller 7,</li><li>H-I; the transfer roller 7,</li><li>I-J; the transfer rollers 7 and 9,</li><li>J-K; the transfer rollers 7 and 9, and</li><li>K-L; the registration roller 11 and the transfer
rollers 7 and 9.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0013">Load factors generated as a reverse force against the
forward force of the sheet transfer operations in each of
the above-mentioned passage parts of column AA of Figs. 3A
and 3B are as follows:
<sl><li>A-B; a close contact power between sheets by friction,</li><li>B-E; a close contact power between sheets by friction
and a repulsive force from the reverse roller 5,</li><li>E-F; a close contact power between sheets by friction
and a repulsive force from the reverse roller 5,</li><li>F-H; a repulsive force from the reverse roller 5,</li><li>H-I; a repulsive force from the reverse roller 5,</li><li>I-J; no particular load factor,</li><li>J-K; no particular load factor, and</li><li>K-L; no particular load factor.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0014">In Fig. 3A, a column BB indicates a distance of each
passage part and a column CC indicates an accumulated
distance from the initial position A to the end of each 
passage part. A column DD is a ratio of a sheet slippage
expressed as a percent and is divided into an initial
condition DD1 and an after-predetermined-time-use condition
DD2. Each of DD1 and DD2 is divided into two cases; MIN
indicating a sheet slippage ratio under a minimum load and
MAX indicating a sheet slippage ratio under a maximum load.
A column EE indicates a diameter of the roller associated
with the sheet transfer operations in each passage part.
The column EE is divided into EE1 - EE3: EE1 is an initial
diameter; EE2 is a radial reduction amount expressed in a
percent due to the wear after a relatively long time use,
and E3 is an amount of reduction in the sheet transfer
linear speed expressed in a percent due to the reduction of
the roller diameter. In Fig. 3B, a column FF indicates an
amount of a total reduction in the sheet transfer linear
speed expressed in a percent, in which wear of the reverse
roller 5 is taken into consideration. The column FF is
divided into an initial condition FF1 and an after-predetermined-time-use
condition FF2. Each of FF1 and FF2
is divided into two cases; MIN indicating a total reduction
in the sheet transfer linear speed expressed in a percent
under a minimum load and MAX indicating a total reduction
in the sheet transfer linear speed expressed in a percent
under a maximum load. A column GG indicates an actual 
sheet transfer linear speed. The column GG is divided into
an initial condition GG1 and an after-predetermined-time-use
condition GG2. Each of GG1 and GG2 is divided into two
cases; MIN indicating the actual sheet transfer linear
speed under a minimum load and MAX indicating the actual
sheet transfer linear speed under a maximum load.</p>
    <p num="0015">The data of the actual sheet transfer linear speed
under the initial condition GG1 is referred to as GG1-MIN
in the case the minimum load is provided and as GG1-MAX in
the case the maximum load is provided. Likewise, the data
of the actual sheet transfer linear speed under the after-predetermined-time-use
condition GG1 is referred to as GG2-MIN
in the case the minimum load is provided and as GG2-MAX
in the case the maximum load is provided. For example, the
solid lines and thick broken lines shown in the performance
characteristic graph 1 of Fig. 2 are based on GG2-MAX.</p>
    <p num="0016">In a similar manner, Fig. 4 demonstrates a linear
speed graph expressing cases Z1, Z2, Z3, and Z4 based on
GG1-MIN, GG1-MAX, GG2-MIN, and GG2-MAX, respectively, of
Figs. 3A and 3B. In Fig. 4, sheet transfer cycles from a
recording sheet 2 to the next recording sheet 2 at the
registration roller 11 in a continuous sheet feeding mode
in the cases Z1, Z2, Z3, and Z4 are referred to as Z1a, Z2a,
Z3a, and Z4a, respectively. Also, time differences from 
the trailing edge of a recording sheet 2 to the leading
edge of the next recording sheet 2 at the registration
roller 11 in the continuous sheet feeding mode in the cases
Z1, Z2, Z3, and Z4 are referred to as Z1b, Z2b, Z3b, and
Z4b, respectively.</p>
    <p num="0017">Based on the above-mentioned sheet transfer cycles
Z1a - Z4a, corresponding copy speeds of the image forming
apparatus employing the sheet transferring apparatus are
calculated in the following manner. In the case Z1, the
sheet transfer cycle Z1a is 784.14 ms per a sheet and
therefore the copy speed is obtained by dividing a minute
by 784.14 ms, that is, 76.52 cpm (copy per minute).
Likewise, in the case Z2, the sheet transfer cycle Z2a is
796.23 ms per a sheet and therefore the copy speed is 75.36
cpm. In the case Z3, the sheet transfer cycle Z3a is
812.60 ms per a sheet and therefore the copy speed is 73.84
cpm. In the case Z4, the sheet transfer cycle Z4a, the
copy speed is 72.63 cpm. From the calculations above, it
should be understood in both the initial condition and the
after-predetermined-time-use condition that the greater the
load against the sheet transfer, the lesser the copy speed.</p>
    <p num="0018">Further, based on the above-mentioned time
differences Z1b - Z4b, corresponding distances from the
trailing edge of a recording sheet 2 to the next recording 
sheet 2 at the registration roller 11 in the continuous
sheet feeding mode in the cases Z1, Z2, Z3, and Z4 are
calculated in the following manner. In the case Z1, the
time difference Z1b is 281.64 ms and therefore the distance
is obtained by multiplying the time difference by the
initial linear speed of the registration roller 11, that is,
0.28164 s multiplied by 400 mm/s which is equal to 112.66.
Likewise, in the case Z2, the time difference Z2b is 293.73
ms and therefore the distance is 0.29373 s multiplied by
400 mm/s which is equal to 117.49 mm. In the case Z3, the
time difference Z3a is 309.34 ms and therefore the distance
is 0.30934 s multiplied by 399.4 mm/s which is equal to
123.55 mm. In the case Z4, the time difference Z4a is
322.82 ms and therefore the distance is 0.32282 s
multiplied by 399.4 mm/s which is equal to 128.93 mm. From
the calculations above, it should be understood in both the
initial condition and the after-predetermined-time-use
condition that the greater the load against the sheet
transfer, the lesser the copy speed.</p>
    <p num="0019">As such, the distance between the adjacent recording
sheets in the continuous sheet feeding mode, which are
worthless for the print operation, is growing. The sheet
transfer linear speed after the registration roller 11 is
predetermined as 400 mm/s in the initial condition and is 
reduced to 399.4 mm/s in the after-predetermined-time-use
condition. That is, a difference between the sheet
transfer linear speeds in the above-mentioned conditions is
relatively small. Therefore, it should be understood that
the growing difference between the adjacent recording
sheets after the registration roller 11 is a major factor
that adversely affects the printing productivity.</p>
    <p num="0020">This patent specification describes a novel sheet
transferring apparatus for use in an image forming
apparatus. In one example, this novel sheet transferring
apparatus includes a sheet transferring mechanism and a
controller. The sheet transferring mechanism is arranged
and configured to transfer a recording sheet at a transfer
speed to an image forming mechanism in the image forming
apparatus. The controller is arranged and configured to
determine the transfer speed based on a transfer speed used
for an immediately previous recording sheet.</p>
    <p num="0021">The sheet transferring mechanism may include a
transfer roller and at least two sensors. The two sensors
are arranged and configured to detect a recording sheet
being transferred. The two sensors are mounted with a
predetermined distance from each other. </p>
    <p num="0022">The controller may determine the transfer speed using
an equation;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">VR (n) ={VR (n-1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>/V(n-1),</st32:df>
wherein n is an integer greater than 1, VR(n) represents a
linear speed of the transfer roller when transferring an
nth recording sheet, VR(n-1) represents a linear speed of
the transfer roller during a transfer of an (n-1)th
recording sheet, and V(n-1) represents a moving speed of
the (n-1)th recording sheet. When the n is equal to 1, the
linear speed VR(1) is set to a predetermined value.</p>
    <p num="0023">The controller may apply a correction tolerance of
±5% to the equation (5) so that the transfer roller is
driven at the linear speed R(n) within a range of;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">[{VR(n-1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>/V(n-1)]x0.95≤R(n)≤<st32:break type="required"/>
[{VR(n-1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>/V(n-1)]x1.05.</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0024">The controller may determine the transfer speed using
an equation;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">VR (n) = [ {VR (n-1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>xT(n-1)]/L,</st32:df>
wherein n is an integer greater than 1, VR(n) represents a
linear speed of the transfer roller when transferring an
nth recording sheet, VR(n-1) represents a linear speed of
the transfer roller during a transfer of an (n-1)th
recording sheet, L represents the predetermined distance,
and T(n-1) represents a time period in which the (n-1)th 
recording sheet is moved the predetermined distance. The n
is equal to 1 the linear speed VR(1) is set to the
predetermined value.</p>
    <p num="0025">This patent specification further describes a novel
image forming apparatus. In one example, this novel image
forming apparatus includes an image forming mechanism, a
sheet transferring mechanism, and a controller. The image
forming mechanism is arranged and configured to form a
visible image on a recording sheet. The sheet transferring
mechanism is arranged and configured to transfer the
recording sheet at a transfer speed to the image forming
mechanism. The controller is arranged and configured to
control a number of revolutions of a motor for driving the
transfer roller to determine said transfer speed based on a
transfer speed used for an immediately previous recording
sheet.</p>
    <p num="0026">This patent specification further describes a novel
image forming system. In one example, this novel image
forming includes an image forming apparatus and an
operation apparatus. The image forming apparatus includes
an image forming mechanism, a sheet transferring mechanism,
and a controller. The image forming mechanism is arranged
and configured to form a visible image on a recording sheet.
The sheet transferring mechanism is arranged and configured 
to transfer the recording sheet at a transfer speed to the
image forming mechanism. The controller is arranged and
configured to determine the transfer speed based on a
transfer speed used for an immediately previous recording
sheet. The operation apparatus includes a display for
indicating a warning that the sheet transfer mechanism is
in a condition asking for an inspection in accordance with
an instruction from the image forming apparatus when the
transfer speed is varied out of predetermined limits.</p>
    <p num="0027">A more complete appreciation of the disclosure and
many of the attendant advantages thereof will be readily
obtained as the same becomes better understood by reference
to the following detailed description when considered in
connection with the accompanying drawings, wherein:
<sl><li>Fig. 1 is an illustration showing a background sheet
transferring apparatus;</li><li>Fig. 2 is a performance chart connected with a time
chart for explaining a sheet transferring operation of the
background sheet transferring apparatus of Fig, 1;</li><li>Figs. 3A and 3B are data tables showing various
performance data of the sheet transferring operation of the
background sheet transferring apparatus of Fig. 1; </li><li>Fig. 4 is a performance chart made based on the data
of Figs. 3A and 3B;</li><li>Fig. 5 is a schematic diagram of an image forming
apparatus according to an embodiment of the present
invention;</li><li>Fig. 6 is an illustration of a sheet transferring
mechanism included in the image forming apparatus of Fig.
5;</li><li>Fig. 7 is a block diagram of an electric system of
the image forming apparatus of Fig. 5;</li><li>Figs. 8A and 8B are data tables showing various
performance data of the sheet transferring operation of the
sheet transferring mechanism of Fig. 6;</li><li>Figs. 9 and 10 are performance charts made based on
the data of Figs. 8A and 8B;</li><li>Fig. 11 an illustration of a sheet transferring
mechanism according to another embodiment of the present
invention;</li><li>Fig. 12 is a block diagram of an electric system
controlling the sheet transferring mechanism of Fig. 11;</li><li>Fig. 13 is a flowchart of the sheet transferring
operation performed by the sheet transferring mechanism of
Fig. 11;</li><li>Figs. 14A and 14B are data tables showing various 
performance data of the sheet transferring operation of the
sheet transferring mechanism of Fig. 11; and</li><li>Figs. 15 and 16 are block diagrams of exemplary
warning systems of the sheet transferring operation.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0028">In describing preferred embodiments illustrated in
the drawings, specific terminology is employed for the sake
of clarity. However, the disclosure of this patent
specification is not intended to be limited to the specific
terminology so selected and it is to be understood that
each specific element includes all technical equivalents
that operate in a similar manner. Referring now to the
drawings, wherein like reference numerals designate
identical or corresponding parts throughout the several
views, particularly to Fig. 5, a description is made for an
electrophotographic image forming apparatus 100 according
to a preferred embodiment of the present invention. The
image forming apparatus 100 of Fig. 5 performs an optical
image reading operation for optically reading an original
document sheet and an image forming operation for forming
an image based on the image reading operation in accordance
with a known electrophotographic method. Therefore, as
shown in Fig. 5, the image forming apparatus 100 includes a 
document feed unit 101, a document reading unit 102, an
optical writing unit 103, an image forming unit 104, a
recording sheet container 105, a sheet transferring
mechanism 106, a fixing unit 107, and a sheet ejection unit
108. The image forming apparatus 100 further includes
optional equipment such as, for example, a duplex print
unit 109 for printing an image on a reverse side of
recording sheets and a large capacity input tray 110
capable of containing a relatively large capacity for
recording sheets. The image forming apparatus 100 further
includes an operation console 111 including various keys
for inputting operator instructions and a display for
indicating various kind of information including machine
statuses.</p>
    <p num="0029">Further, in Fig. 5, the image forming unit 104
includes a photoconductive drum 12. The fixing unit 107
includes fixing rollers 14 and 15 for heat and pressure,
respectively. The recording sheet container 105 includes
sheet cassettes 105a, 105b, 105c, and 105d each of which
contains a stack of recording sheets 2, for example. The
sheet ejection unit 108 includes an ejection roller 16.</p>
    <p num="0030">The document feed unit 101 is an automatic document
feeder (ADF) that automatically inputs an original document
sheet and brings it to pass by an image reading position 
relative to the document reading unit 102 so that the
document reading unit 102 reads an image of the original
document sheet. After inputting, the document feed unit
101 ejects the original document sheet after the reading
process.</p>
    <p num="0031">The document reading unit 102 includes a reading
light source, a movable light reflection mechanism, a lens
system, and a CCD (charge-coupled device), which are not
shown. In the document reading unit 102, the reading light
source is energized to emit light to an original document
sheet, and the movable light reflection mechanism is moved
in a sub-scanning direction to sequentially receive and
deflect the light reflected from the original document
sheet. Via the lens system, the deflected light is brought
into a focus on the CCD which outputs an electrical signal
in response to an input of the light. In this way, image
information of the original document sheet is optically
read and is converted into an electrical signal. Thus, an
image signal is generated.</p>
    <p num="0032">The image signal is subjected to various image
processing operations required before the image forming
operation, and is then used to modulate light emitted from
a writing light source, i.e., a laser diode (LD) 20 (see
Fig. 7), in the optical writing unit 103. The optical 
writing unit 103 includes an optical system that includes
the writing light source, a polygon mirror, lenses, mirrors,
etc., which are not shown. In the optical writing unit 103,
the modulated light is deflected with continuously varying
angles in a main scanning direction to the photoconductive
drum 12 of the image forming unit 104. Thereby, the
surface of the photoconductive drum 12 is scanned with the
light modulated in accordance with the image of the
original document sheet.</p>
    <p num="0033">The image forming unit 104 forms an image according
to electrophotographic and therefore includes various known
components such as the photoconductive drum 12, a charging
member, a development unit, a transfer roller 13 (Fig. 6),
a separation unit, a cleaning unit, a discharging unit,
most of which are not shown. These units are arranged
around the photoconductive drum 12 and act to form an
electrostatic latent image on the surface of the
photoconductive drum 12 based on the scanning operation
with the modulated light and to visualize the electrostatic
latent image into a toner image. While the toner image is
generated in this way, the recording sheet 2 is supplied
from the recording sheet container 105 and is transferred
to the photoconductive drum 12 through the sheet
transferring mechanism 106. After that, the toner image is 
transferred onto the recording sheet 2 by the transfer
roller 13 and is fixed on the recording sheet 2 by the heat
roller 14 and the pressure roller 15 of the fixing unit 107.
Then, the recording sheet 2 having the toner image fixed
thereon is ejected outside the image forming apparatus by
the ejection roller 16 of the sheet ejection unit 108.</p>
    <p num="0034">Fig. 6 shows an exemplary structure of the sheet
transferring mechanism 106 according to a preferred
embodiment of the present invention is explained. The
sheet transferring mechanism 106 is similar to the
background sheet transferring apparatus of Fig. 1, except
for velocity sensors 21 and 22. The sheet transferring
mechanism 106 is provided with the velocity sensor 21 at a
position D and the velocity sensor 22 at a position G, as
shown in Fig. 6. The velocity sensors 21 and 22 are laser
Doppler velocity sensors for detecting linear speed of the
recording sheet being transferred. The sheet transferring
mechanism 106 feeds the recording sheet 2 from the sheet
cassette 105a, for example, and transfers it in a way
similar to that of the background sheet transferring
apparatus of Fig. 1, except for an RPM (revolutions per
minute) control, explained later, for controlling an RPM
(revolutions per minute) of motors associated with in
response to the linear speed of the recording sheet 2 
detected by the velocity sensors 21 and 22. A correction
of the RPM made by the RPM control may be referred to as an
RPM correction.</p>
    <p num="0035">The position D may be anywhere between the positions
C and E but is, in this example, set to a place having a
distance equivalent to a perimeter of the feed roller 4
downstream from the position C in the sheet transferring
direction, for example. The velocity sensor 21 detects the
linear speed of the recording sheet 2 during the time the
leading edge of the recording sheet 2 is fed in an area
between the positions C and E. Also, the position G may be
anywhere between the positions F and H but is, in this
example, set to a place having a distance equivalent to a
perimeter of the transfer roller 7 upstream from the
position H in the sheet transferring direction, for example.
The velocity sensor 22 detects the linear speed of the
recording sheet 2 during the time the leading edge of the
recording sheet 2 is fed in an area between the positions F
and H.</p>
    <p num="0036">Referring to Fig. 7, a block diagram of an exemplary
electric system employed in the above-described image
forming apparatus 100 is explained. As shown in Fig. 7,
the image forming apparatus 100 is provided with a
controller 150 that electrically controls the operations of 
the image forming apparatus 100, including the image
forming operations and the sheet transferring operations.</p>
    <p num="0037">In this example, the image forming apparatus 100 is
provided with driving sources including a main motor 17, a
first feed motor 18, and a second feed motor 19, as shown
in Fig. 7. The main motor 17 drives the photoconductive
drum 12, the image transferring roller 13, the fixing
rollers 14 and 15, and the ejection roller 16. The first
feed motor 18 drives the pick-up roller 3, the feed roller
4, and the reverse roller 5. The second feed motor 19
drives the transfer rollers 7 and 9.</p>
    <p num="0038">Also, the image forming apparatus 100 is provided
with drivers 31 for driving the above-mentioned motors 17 -
19. The image forming apparatus 100 is further provided
with drivers 32 - 36 and clutches 42 - 46 for transmitting
the power of the first and second motors 18 and 19 to the
associated rollers of the sheet transferring mechanism 106.
The image forming apparatus 100 is further provided with a
driver 37 for driving the laser diode 20 with the signal
modulated in accordance with the image of the original
document sheet.</p>
    <p num="0039">The driver 31 controls the main motor 19 that drives
the photoconductive drum 12, the transfer roller 13, the
fixing rollers 14 and 15, and the ejection roller 16. The 
driver 31 further controls the motor 17 that drives the
pick-up roller 3, the feed roller 4, and the reverse roller
5. The driver 31 further controls the motor 18 that drives
the transfer rollers 7 and 9, and the registration roller
11.</p>
    <p num="0040">The driver 32 drives the clutch 42 to transmit the
power of the motor 18 to the pick-up roller 3. The drivers
33 drives the clutch 43 to energize the feed and reverse
rollers 4 and 5 with the power of the motor 17. The
drivers 34 and 35 drive the clutches 44 and 45,
respectively, to rotate the transfer rollers 7 and 9,
respectively, with the power of the motor 18. The driver
36 drives the clutch 46 to rotate the registration roller
11 with the power of the motor 18.</p>
    <p num="0041">In the controller 150, a CPU (central processing
unit) performs various operations, including the image
reading operation and the image forming operation, in
accordance with a program software stored in a ROM (read
only memory) using a RAM (random access memory) as a
working memory in which information required for the
operations performed by the CPU is stored on an as needed
basis.</p>
    <p num="0042">The controller 150 performs the RPM control that
controls an RPM (revolutions per minute) of the first and 
second feed motors 18 and 19 in response to the linear
speed of the recording sheet 2 detected by the velocity
sensors 21 and 22. In a discussion of this RPM control,
several terms are defined as follows. The RPM of the feed
roller 4 is one-xth of the RPM of the first feed motor 18,
and the RPM of the transfer rollers 7 and 9 are one-yth of
the RPM of the second feed motor 19, wherein the x and the
y are any number greater than zero. When a first recording
sheet 2 is fed forward in the sheet passage by the feed
roller 4 driven by the first feed motor 18 under the RPM
control of the controller 150, an RPM of the feed roller 4
that drives the first recording sheet 2 is defined as R1.
Accordingly, the RPM of the first motor 18 is R1 multiplied
by x. Likewise, when the first recording sheet 2 is fed by
the transfer rollers 7 and 9 driven by the second feed
motor 19 under the RPM control of the controller 150, an
RPM of the transfer rollers 7 and 9 that drive the first
recording sheet 2 is defined as R'1. Accordingly, the RPM
of the second motor 19 is R'1 multiplied by y.</p>
    <p num="0043">An actual linear speed of the first recording sheet 2
measured during the time the leading edge thereof is moved
between the positions C and D is defined as V1. An actual
linear speed of the first recording sheet 2 measured during
the time the leading edge thereof is moved between the 
positions F and H is defined as V'1. An outer diameter of
the feed roller 4 is defined as Df. An outer diameter of
the transfer rollers 7 and 9 is defined as De. An ideal
linear speed of the recording sheet 2 being moved between
the positions C and D is defined as V0, given no
consideration of a speed reduction due to slippage or wear
of the rollers. The ideal linear speed V0 satisfies an
equation;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">V0=πxDfxR1.</st32:df>
An ideal linear speed of the recording sheet 2 being moved
between the positions C and D is defined as V'0, given no
consideration of a speed reduction due to slippage or wear
of the rollers. The ideal linear speed V'0 satisfies an
equation;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">V' 0=πxDexR'1.</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0044">The RPM of the feed roller 4 during a transfer of a
second recording sheet 2 following the first recording
sheet 2 is defined as R2. The RPM of the transfer rollers
7 and 9 during a transfer of the second recording sheet 2
following the first recording sheet 2 is defined as R'2.</p>
    <p num="0045">In the RPM control performed by the controller 150,
the RPM R2 and the RPM R'2 are controlled to satisfy the
following equations;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">R2= (πxDfxR1<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>)/V1=(V0/V1)xR1,</st32:df>
and <st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">R'2=(πxDexR'1<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>)/V'1=(V'0/V'1)xR'1.</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0046">On and after a third recording sheet 2 following the
second recording sheet 2, the RPM of the feed roller 4 and
the RPM of the transfer rollers 7 and 9 during a transfer
of the nth recording sheet 2 can be expressed as R(n) and
R'(n), respectively, and the respective equations can be
modified as follows, wherein n is an integer greater than
2;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">R(n)=[πxDfx{R(n-1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>]/V(n-1),</st32:df>
and
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">R' (n)=[πxDex{R'(n-1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>]/V'(n-1).</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0047">That is, a linear speed at which a recording sheet 2
is transferred is defined with a parameter of the linear
speed of the previously transferred recording sheet 2 in a
continuous sheet transferring mode. Therefore, the above
equations can be expressed in the following more generic
equation;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">R(n)=[πxDx{R(n-1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>]/V(n-1),</st32:df>
wherein R(n) represents an RPM of the transfer roller when
transferring the nth recording sheet 2, D represents an
outer diameter of the transfer roller, R(n-1) represents an
RPM of the transfer roller during a transfer of the (n-1) th
recording sheet 2, and V(n-1) represents a linear speed of
the (n-1) th recording sheet 2.</p>
    <p num="0048">Figs. 8A and 8B show various data associated with the 
performance of the sheet transferring mechanism 106 that
has the sheet transfer linear speed of 400 mm/s. Figs. 8A
and 8B may be read as one data table having columns AA, BB,
CC, DD, EE, FF, JJ, KK, and LL.</p>
    <p num="0049">In Figs. 8A and 8B, the sheet passage is divided into
the following passage parts as indicated in a column AA:
<sl><li>A-B represents a passage part between the positions A
and B, that is, from the initial position A to the sheet
separation mechanism;</li><li>B-C represents a passage part between the positions B
and C, that is, from the sheet separation mechanism to the
photo sensor 6;</li><li>C-D represents a passage part between the positions C
and D, that is, from the photo sensor 6 to the velocity
sensor 21;</li><li>D-E represents a passage part between the positions D
and E, that is, from the velocity sensor 21 to the transfer
roller 7;</li><li>E-F represents a passage part between the positions E
and F, that is, from the transfer roller 7 to the position
F to which the leading edge of the recording sheet 2 is
moved when the feed roller 7 is turned off;</li><li>F-G represents a passage part between the positions F
and G, that is, from the position F to which the leading 
edge of the recording sheet 2 is moved when the feed roller
7 is turned off to the velocity sensor 22;</li><li>G-H represents a passage part between the positions G
and H, that is, from the velocity sensor 22 to the photo
sensor 8;</li><li>H-I represents a passage part between the positions H
and I, that is, from the photo sensor 8 to the position I
to which the leading edge of the recording sheet 2 is moved
when the trailing edge of the recording sheet 2 is brought
away from the sheet separation mechanism;</li><li>I-J represents a passage part between the positions I
and J, that is, from the position I to the registration
sensor 10; and</li><li>J-K represents a passage part between the positions J
and K, that is, from the registration sensor 10 to the
registration roller 11.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0050">The components particularly activated and essential
in the sheet transfer operations in each of the above-mentioned
passage parts of the column AA of Fig. Figs. 8A
and 8B are as follows:
<sl><li>A-B; the pick-up roller 3,</li><li>B-C; the pick-up roller 3 and the feed roller 4,</li><li>C-D; the feed roller 4,</li><li>D-E; the feed roller 4, </li><li>E-F; the feed roller 4 and the transfer roller 7,</li><li>F-G; the transfer roller 7,</li><li>G-H; the transfer roller 7,</li><li>H-I; the transfer roller 7,</li><li>I-J; the transfer rollers 7 and 9, and</li><li>J-K; the transfer rollers 7 and 9.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0051">Load factors generated as a reverse force against the
forward force of the sheet transfer operations in each of
the above-mentioned passage parts of column AA of Figs. 8A
and 8B are as follows:
<sl><li>A-B; a close contact power between sheets by friction,</li><li>B-C; a close contact power between sheets by friction
and a repulsive force from the reverse roller 5,</li><li>C-D; a close contact power between sheets by friction
and a repulsive force from the reverse roller 5,</li><li>D-E; a close contact power between sheets by friction
and a repulsive force from the reverse roller 5,</li><li>E-F; a close contact power between sheets by friction
and a repulsive force from the reverse roller 5,</li><li>F-G; a repulsive force from the reverse roller 5,</li><li>G-H; a repulsive force from the reverse roller 5,</li><li>H-I; a repulsive force from the reverse roller 5,</li><li>I-J; no particular load factor, and</li><li>J-K; no particular load factor.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0052">As in the cases of Figs. 3A and 3B, Figs. 8A and 8B
may be read as one data table having columns AA, BB, CC, DD,
EE, FF, JJ, KK, and LL. The columns AA, BB, CC, DD, and EE
in Figs. 8A and 8B are defined in the same manner as those
of Figs. 3A and 3B. The column JJ of Fig. 8B indicates a
corrective increase in percent of the RPMs of the
respective first and second motors 18 and 19 according to
the RPM control based on the measured linear speed of the
recording sheet 2 in each of the passage parts shown in the
column AA. The column JJ is divided into an initial
condition JJ1 and an after-predetermined-time-use condition
JJ2. Each of JJ1 and JJ2 is divided into two cases; MIN
indicating a corrective increase of the RPM in percent
under a minimum load and MAX indicating a corrective
increase of the RPM in percent under a maximum load.</p>
    <p num="0053">The column KK of Fig. 8B indicates a resultant
decrease in percent of the linear speed of the recording
sheet 2 in response to the corrective increase of the RPM
of the first and second motors 18 and 19 in each of the
passage parts shown in the column AA. In this case, wear
of the transfer rollers 7 and 9 are taken into
consideration. The column KK is divided into an initial
condition KK1 and an after-predetermined-time-use condition
KK2. Each of KK1 and KK2 is divided into two cases; MIN 
indicating a resultant decrease of the linear speed of the
recording sheet 2 in percent under a minimum load and MAX
indicating a resultant decrease of the recording sheet 2 in
percent under a maximum load.</p>
    <p num="0054">Although the column LL of Fig. 8B is defined in a
manner similar to the column GG of Fig. 3B, there is a
difference that the column LL indicates an actual sheet
transfer linear speed reflecting the correction according
to the RPM control. As in the case of the column GG of Fig.
3B, the column LL of Fig. 8B is divided into an initial
condition LL1 and an after-predetermined-time-use condition
LL2. Each of LL1 and LL2 is divided into two cases; MIN
indicating the actual corrected sheet transfer linear speed
under a minimum load and MAX indicating the actual
corrected sheet transfer linear speed under a maximum load.</p>
    <p num="0055">Fig. 9 is a graph showing a performance
characteristic of the sheet transferring mechanism 106 with
the horizontal axis of time and the vertical axis of the
positions of the leading and trailing edges of the
recording sheet 2. The graph of Fig. 9 is based on the
sheet transfer during the initial condition LL1 under the
minimum transfer load MIN in the column LL of Fig. 8B. In
Fig. 9, reference numeral i represents the positions of the
leading edge of the first recording sheet 2 with no 
correction, ii represents the positions of the trailing
edge of the first recording sheet 2 with no correction, and
iii represents the positions of the leading edge of the
second recording sheet 2 with the correction. Further,
reference numeral iv represents the positions of the
leading edge of the second recording sheet 2 with no
correction, v represents the positions of the trailing edge
of the second recording sheet 2 with the correction, vi
represents the positions of the leading edge of the third
recording sheet 2 with the correction, and vii represents
the positions of the trailing edge of the third recording
sheet 2 with the correction.</p>
    <p num="0056">In a similar manner, Fig. 10 is a graph showing a
performance characteristic of the sheet transferring
mechanism 106 and is based on the sheet transfer during the
after-predetermined-time-use condition LL2 under the
maximum transfer load MAX in the column LL of Fig. 8B.
Reference numeral i - vii are defined in the same way as
those in Fig. 9.</p>
    <p num="0057">In the graphs of the performance characteristic shown
in Figs. 9 and 10, the controller 150 performs the sheet
transferring operation under the conditions that the RPM
control is performed on and after the second recording
sheet 2 since there is no data with respect to the linear 
speed of the previous recording sheet 2 and therefore the
first recording sheet 2 is transferred without the RPM
control.</p>
    <p num="0058">In Figs. 9 and 10, times α, β, γ, δ, ε, ζ, η, , and
<img id="img-00380001" orientation="unknown" wi="2" img-format="tif" img-content="ff" file="00380001.tif" inline="no" he="2"/> are defined with reference to the position A or K as
follows:
<sl><li>α; a time the first recording sheet 2 is transferred,
wherein the leading edge of the first recording sheet 2 is
at the initial position A,</li><li>β; a time the second recording sheet 2 is transferred,
wherein the leading edge of the second recording sheet 2 is
at the initial position A,</li><li>γ; a time the first recording sheet 2 is transferred,
wherein the leading edge of the first recording sheet 2 is
at the position K,</li><li>δ; a time the second recording sheet 2 is transferred
with the RPM correction, wherein the leading edge of the
second recording sheet 2 is at the position K,</li><li>ε; a time the second recording sheet 2 is transferred
without the RPM correction, wherein the leading edge of the
second recording sheet 2 is at the position K,</li><li>ζ; a time the first recording sheet 2 is transferred,
wherein the leading edge of the first recording sheet 2 is
at the position K, </li><li>η; a time the second recording sheet 2 is transferred
with the RPM correction, wherein the leading edge of the
second recording sheet 2 is at the position K,</li><li>; a time the second recording sheet 2 is transferred
without the RPM correction, wherein the leading edge of the
second recording sheet 2 is at the position K, and</li><li><imgref idrefs="img-00380001"/>; a time the third recording sheet 2 is transferred
with the RPM correction, wherein the leading edge of the
third recording sheet 2 is at the position K.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0059">Using the above times, the graph of Fig. 9 which is
the performance characteristic under the initial condition
with the minimum transfer loads indicates the following
measurements:
<sl><li>γ-α=1007.7 ms, without the RPM correction;</li><li>δ-β=976.41 ms, with the RPM correction;</li><li>ε-β=1007.7 ms, without the RPM correction;</li><li>η-ζ=752.82 ms (=79.70 cpm), with the RPM correction;</li><li>-ζ=784.14 ms (=76.52 cpm), without the RPM
correction; and</li><li><imgref idrefs="img-00380001"/>-η=751.56 ms (=79.83 cpm), with the RPM correction.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0060">From the above measurements, it should be understood
that the time period from the time of starting the sheet
feed to the time of restarting the sheet feed after the
registration by the registration roller 11 is reduced by 
the RPM correction from 1007.7 ms, which is the case of no
RPM correction, to 976.41 ms. Also, it should be
understood that the time period between the times of
restarting the sheet feed after the registration by the
registration roller 11 with respect to the first and second
recording sheets 2 is reduced by the RPM correction from
784.14 ms, which is the case of no RPM correction and is
equivalent to 76.52 cpm, to 752.82 ms which is equivalent
to 79.70 cpm. Also, it should be understood that after the
second recording sheet 2 the time period between the times
of restarting the sheet feed after the registration by the
registration roller 11 with respect to the second and third
recording sheets 2, for example, is further reduced by the
RPM correction down to 751.56 ms which is equivalent to
79.83 cpm since the linear speed of the second recording
sheet 2 has been adjusted by the RPM correction. Therefore,
the reduction of the productivity over time due to the
increasing transfer loads given to the recording sheet 2 is
prevented.</p>
    <p num="0061">In a similar manner, the graph of Fig. 10 which is
the performance characteristic under the after-predetermined-time-use
condition with the maximum transfer
loads indicates the following measurements:
<sl><li>γ-α=1048.5 ms, without the RPM correction; </li><li>δ-β=968.8 ms, with the RPM correction;</li><li>ε-β=1048.5 ms, without the RPM correction;</li><li>η-ζ=746.39 ms (=80.39 cpm), with the RPM correction;</li><li>-ζ=826.09 ms (=72.63 cpm), without the RPM
correction; and</li><li><imgref idrefs="img-00380001"/>-η=744.05 ms (=80.64 cpm), with the RPM correction.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0062">From the above measurements, it is understood that
the time period from the time of starting the sheet feed to
the time of restarting the sheet feed after the
registration by the registration roller 11 is reduced by
the RPM correction from 1048.5 ms, which is the case of no
RPM correction, to 968.8 ms. Also, it is understood that
the time period between the times of restarting the sheet
feed after the registration by the registration roller 11
with respect to the first and second recording sheets 2 is
reduced by the RPM correction from 826.09 ms, which is the
case of no RPM correction and is equivalent to 72.63 cpm,
to 746.39 ms which is equivalent to 80.39 cpm. Also, it is
understood that after the second recording sheet 2 the time
period between the times of restarting the sheet feed after
the registration by the registration roller 11 with respect
to the second and third recording sheets 2, for example, is
further reduced by the RPM correction down to 744.05 ms
which is equivalent to 80.64 cpm since the linear speed of 
the second recording sheet 2 has been adjusted by the RPM
correction. Therefore, the reduction of the productivity
over time due to the increasing transfer loads given to the
recording sheet 2 is prevented.</p>
    <p num="0063">In the discussion above, the sheet transferring
mechanism 106 of the image forming apparatus 100 performs
the sheet transfer operation in an ideal manner. However,
it is more realistic to take a certain tolerance of the RPM
correction into consideration of the sheet transfer
operation. The following discussion describes a case in
which a correction tolerance of ±5%, for example, is
applied.</p>
    <p num="0064">In this case, the controller 150 performs the RPM
control with the correction tolerance of ±5%. In a
discussion of this RPM control, the definitions of the RPM
R1, the RPM R'1, the actual linear speed V1, the actual
linear speed V'1, the outer diameter Df, the outer diameter
De, the ideal linear speed V0, the ideal linear speed V'0,
the RPM R2, and the RPM R'2 remain same as described above.</p>
    <p num="0065">Accordingly, in the RPM control for the RPM
correction with the correction tolerance of ±5% performed
by the controller 150, the RPM R2 and the RPM R'2 are
controlled to satisfy the following equations;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">{(πxDfxR1<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>)/V1)x0.95≤R2≤{(πxDfxR1<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>)/V1)x1.05,</st32:df>
and <st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">{(πxDexR'1<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>)/V'1}x0.95≤R'2≤{(πxDexR'1<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>)/V'1}x1.05.</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0066">On and after a third recording sheet 2 following the
second recording sheet 2, the respective equations can be
modified as follows, wherein n is an integer greater than
2;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">[[πxDfx{R(n-1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>]/V(n-1)]x0.95≤R(n)≤[[πDfx{R(n-<st32:break type="required"/>
1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>]/V(n-1)]x1.05,</st32:df>
and
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">[[πxDex{R<st32:italic>'</st32:italic>(n-1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>] /V'(n-1)]x0.95≤R'(n)≤[ [πxDex{R'(n-<st32:break type="required"/>
1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>]/V<st32:italic>'</st32:italic>(n-1)]x1.05.</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0067">Further, the above equations can be expressed in the
following more generic equation;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">[[πxDx{R(n-1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>]/V(n-1)]x0.95≤R(n)≤<st32:break type="required"/>
[[πxDx{R(n-1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>]/V(n-1)]x1.05.</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0068">With the above arrangement, the performance
characteristic under the initial condition with the minimum
transfer loads, like the one shown in the graph of Fig. 9,
would bring the following measurements:
<sl><li>γ-α=1007.7 ms, without the RPM correction;</li><li>δ-β=1027.80 ms by the RPM correction of -5%, or
929.91 ms by the ROM correction of +5%;</li><li>ε-β=1007.7 ms, without the RPM correction;</li><li>η-ζ=792.44 ms (=75.72 cpm) by the RPM correction of
-5%, or 716.97 ms (=83.69 cpm) by the RPM correction of +5%; </li><li>-ζ=784.14 ms (=76.52 cpm), without the RPM
correction; and</li><li><imgref idrefs="img-00380001"/>-η=791.12 ms (=75.84 cpm) by the RPM correction of
-5%, or 715.77 ms (=83.83 cpm) by the RPM correction of +5%.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0069">In a similar manner, the performance characteristic
under the after-predetermined-time-use condition with the
maximum transfer loads, like the one shown in the graph of
Fig. 10, would bring the following measurements:
<sl><li>γ-α=1048.5 ms, without the RPM correction;</li><li>δ-β=1019.79 ms by the RPM correction of -5%;</li><li>ε-β=1048.5 ms, without the RPM correction;</li><li>η-ζ=785.67 ms (=76.37 cpm) by the ROM correction of
-5%, or 710.85 ms (=84.41 cpm) by the RPM correction of +5%;</li><li>-ζ=826.09 ms (=72.63 cpm), without the RPM
correction; and</li><li><imgref idrefs="img-00380001"/>-η=783.21 ms (=76.61 cpm) by the RPM correction of
-5%, or 708.62 ms (=84.67 cpm) by the RPM correction of +5%.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0070">As indicated above, the RPM correction of -5% adjusts
the copy speed to a level close to the copy speed in the
case of no RPM correction but the RPM correction of +5%
greatly increases the copy speed. The tolerance of the RPM
correction is usually set to a degree smaller than ±5% but
it may be extended to a degree of ±8%, which may be a limit,
without causing adverse unexpected side effect. </p>
    <p num="0071">Next, a sheet transferring mechanism 206 according to
another preferred embodiment of the present invention is
explained with reference to Fig. 11. Fig. 11 shows the
sheet transferring mechanism 206 which is similar to the
sheet transferring mechanism 106 of Fig. 6, except for
photo sensors 31 and 32 for detecting an existence of the
recording sheet 2 at predetermined positions P and Q,
respectively, as shown in Fig. 11.</p>
    <p num="0072">In this example, the linear speed of the feed roller
4 and the transfer roller 7, for example, are measured with
the photo sensors substituting the laser Doppler velocity
sensors. A method of measuring a speed of a moving sheet
with photo sensors is to detect a moving sheet at two
different position having a predetermined distance
therebetween and to divide the predetermined distance by a
time period between the detection at the two different
positions. In this example, the photo sensor 31 is
provided at the position P which has a distance La
downstream from the photo sensor 6 located at the position
C in the sheet transferring direction. The distance La is
defined as;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">La=Dfxπxn,</st32:df>
wherein n represents a number of revolutions of the
transfer roller and is set to 1 in this example, and Df 
represents the outer diameter of the feed roller 4.
Accordingly, the distance La is equivalent to a perimeter
of the feed roller 4. That is, the position P is made
equal to the position D of the sheet transferring mechanism
106, for the sake of simplicity. Thus, the photo sensors 6
and 31 measure a time period in which the recording sheet 2
is transferred from the position C to the position P and
based on which the linear speed of the recording sheet 2
between the positions C and P can be calculated. With this
arrangement, the linear speed is detected without an
adverse affect from variations of the linear speed locally
caused due to an unexpected eccentric rotation axis of or
an unexpected imprecision cylindrical shape of the feed
roller 4.</p>
    <p num="0073">Likewise, the photo sensor 32 is mounted at the
position Q which has a distance Lb upstream from the photo
sensor 8 located at the position H in the sheet
transferring direction. The distance Lb is defined as;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">La=Dexπxn,</st32:df>
wherein n represents a number of revolutions of the
transfer roller and is set to 1 in this example, and De
represents the outer diameter of the transfer roller 7.
Accordingly, the distance Lb is equivalent to a perimeter
of the transfer roller 7. That is, the position Q is made 
equal to the position G of the sheet transferring mechanism
106, for the sake of simplicity. Thus, the photo sensors 8
and 32 measure a time period in which the recording sheet 2
is transferred from the position Q to the position H and
based on which the linear speed of the recording sheet 2
between the positions Q and H can be detected. With this
arrangement, the linear speed is detected without an
adverse affect from variations of the linear speed locally
caused due to an unexpected eccentric rotation axis of or
an unexpected imprecision cylindrical shape of the transfer
roller 7.</p>
    <p num="0074">This sheet transferring mechanism 206 can be employed
in an image forming apparatus (referred to as an image
forming apparatus 200) having a structure similar to the
above-described image forming apparatus 100. Fig. 12 shows
a block diagram of an exemplary electric system of such an
image forming apparatus 200. The image forming apparatus
200 includes a controller (referred to as a controller 250)
which is similar to the controller 150 of Fig. 7, except
for a software stored therein for handling the input
signals from the photo sensors 31 and 32. However, since
differences between the controller 150 and 250 are simply
the software, the details of the controller are not
described. In the image forming apparatus 200, an RPM 
control for controlling the revolutions of the motors is
performed with the sheet transferring mechanism 206. The
RPM control of this case is explained below.</p>
    <p num="0075">The linear speed of the recording sheet 2 at the
leading edge thereof between the positions C and P is
measured with the photo sensors 6 and 31, and the linear
speed between the positions Q and H can be obtained with
the photo sensors 8 and 32.</p>
    <p num="0076">In a discussion of this RPM control performed with
the sheet transferring mechanism 206, the definitions of
the terms remain same as those described in the sheet
transferring mechanism 106, including the RPM R1, the RPM
R'1, the outer diameter Df, the outer diameter De, the RPM
R2, and the RPM R'2. In addition, a measured transfer time
period T1 is defined as a time period in which the leading
edge of the first recording sheet 2 is moved from the
position C to the position P when the first recording sheet
2 is transferred in the sheet passage. A measured transfer
time period T'1 is defined as a time period in which the
leading edge of the first recording sheet 2 is moved from
the position F to the position H when the first recording
sheet 2 is transferred in the sheet passage. An ideal
transfer time period T0 is defined as a time period in
which the leading edge of the recording sheet is moved from 
the position C to the position P under the conditions that
a reduction of the linear speed due to slippage or wear of
the rollers is not taken into consideration. The ideal
linear speed T0 satisfies an equation;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">T0=La/(πxDfxR1).</st32:df>
An ideal transfer time period T'0 is defined as a time
period in which the leading edge of the recording sheet is
moved from the position F to the position H under the
conditions that a reduction of the linear speed due to
slippage or wear of the rollers is not taken into
consideration;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">V'0=Lb/(πxDexR'1).</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0077">With the sheet transferring mechanism 206, the RPM R2
and the RPM R'2 are controlled to satisfy the following
equations;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">R2=(πxDfxR1<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>xT1)/La=(T1/T0)xR1,</st32:df>
and
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">R'2=(πxDexR'1<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>xT'1)/Lb=(T'1/T'0)xR'1.</st32:df>
Here, since the distances La and Lb are;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">La=Dfxπxn,</st32:df>
and
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">Lb=Dexπxn,</st32:df>
Wherein n represents a number of revolutions of the
transfer roller and is set to 1 in this example, and the
RPM R2 and the RPM R'2 are modified as; <st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">R2= R1<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>xT1,</st32:df>
and
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">R'2= R'1<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>xT'1.</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0078">On and after a third recording sheet 2 following the
second recording sheet 2, the RPM of the feed roller 4 and
the RPM of the transfer rollers 7 and 9 during a transfer
of the nth recording sheet 2 can be expressed as R(n) and
R'(n), respectively, and the respective equations can be
modified as follows, wherein n is an integer greater than
2;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">R(n)={R(n-1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>xT(n-1),</st32:df>
and
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">R' (n)={R'(n-1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>xT'(n-1).</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0079">That is, a linear speed at which a recording sheet 2
is transferred is defined with a parameter of the linear
speed of the previously transferred recording sheet 2 in a
continuous sheet transferring mode. Therefore, the above
equations can be expressed in the following more generic
equation;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">R(n)=[πxDx(R(n-1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>xT(n-1)]/L,</st32:df>
wherein R(n) represents an RPM of the transfer roller when
transferring the nth recording sheet 2, D represents an
outer diameter of the transfer roller, R(n-1) represents an
RPM of the transfer roller during a transfer of the (n-1)th
recording sheet 2, T(n-1) represents a transfer time period
of the (n-1)th recording sheet 2 being transferred between 
two predetermined positions, and L represents a distance
between the two predetermined positions.</p>
    <p num="0080">This RPM control is performed along a procedure shown
in Fig. 13. When the sheet transfer operation is started,
the controller 250 starts to drive the first motor 18 and
calculates the RPM R1 of the feed roller 4 based on the rpm
of the first motor 18, in Step S1. The controller 250 then
drives the feed roller 4, in Step S2. In this step, the
controller 250 drives the feed roller 4 at an RPM
calculated on a basis of a measured transfer time period of
the immediately previous recording sheet 2. If there is no
transfer operation of the immediately previous recording
sheet 2, the controller 250 drives the feed roller 4 at a
predetermined RPM.</p>
    <p num="0081">In Step S3, the controller 250 determines whether the
leading edge of the recording sheet 2 reaches the position
C. This step continues until leading edge of the recording
sheet 2 reaches the position C. When the leading edge of
the recording sheet 2 is determined as reaching the
position C and the determination result of Step S3 is YES,
the controller 250 starts counting a time T in Step S4. In
Step S5, the controller 250 determines whether the leading
edge of the recording sheet 2 reaches the position P. This
step continues until leading edge of the recording sheet 2 
reaches the position P. When the leading edge of the
recording sheet 2 is determined as reaching the position P
and the determination result of Step S5 is YES, the
controller 250 stops counting the time T in Step S6. Then,
the controller 250 saves the time T in the RAM, in Step S7,
and calculates the next RPM R1 of the feed roller 4, in
Step S8. After that, in Step S9, the controller 250 stores
the next RPM R1 calculated in Step S8 into the RAM so as to
use it in the transfer of the following recording sheet 2.
This procedure then ends.</p>
    <p num="0082">This procedure is also performed for the RPM R'1 of
the transfer rollers 7 and 9 using the photo sensors 32 and
8.</p>
    <p num="0083">Figs. 14A and 14B show various data associated with
the performance of the sheet transferring mechanism 206
that has the sheet transfer linear speed of 400 mm/s. The
columns of Figs. 14A and 14B are similar to those of Figs.
8A and 8B, except for the positions P and Q in the column
AA, which correspond, as described above, to the positions
D and G in the column AA of Figs. 8A and 8B.</p>
    <p num="0084">The image forming apparatus 200 employing the sheet
transferring mechanism 206 can perform the sheet
transferring operation with the RPM control in a manner
similar to the performance of the image forming apparatus 
100 having the sheet transferring mechanism 106.</p>
    <p num="0085">The equation (3) can be modified by an application of
a correction tolerance of ±5%, for example, and is;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">[[πxDx{R(n-1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>xT(n-1)]/L]x0.95≤R(n)≤<st32:break type="required"/>
[[πxDx{R(n-1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>xT(n-2)]/L]x1.05.</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0086">As in the case of the sheet transferring mechanism
106, the sheet transferring mechanism 206 can obtain
results that the RPM correction of -5% adjusts the copy
speed to a level close to the copy speed in the case of no
RPM correction but that the RPM correction of +5% greatly
increases the copy speed. The tolerance of the RPM
correction is usually set to a degree smaller than ±5% but
it may be extended to a degree of ±8%, which may be a limit,
without causing adverse unexpected side effect.</p>
    <p num="0087">In addition, another method alternative to the
equation (1) applied to the image forming apparatus 100 is
explained. As set forth, the image forming apparatus 100
controls the revolutions of the motors with the equation
(1) to control the revolutions of the feed and transfer
rollers. The alternative method being explained controls a
transfer speed at which the recording sheet 2 is moved, and
this alternative method is expressed in the following
equation;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">VR(n)={VR(n-1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>/V(n-1),</st32:df> 
wherein VR(n) represents a linear speed of the transfer
roller when transferring the nth recording sheet 2, VR(n-1)
represents a linear speed of the transfer roller during a
transfer of the (n-1)th recording sheet 2, and V(n-1)
represents a moving speed of the (n-1)th recording sheet 2.</p>
    <p num="0088">With the above method, the sheet transferring
mechanism 106 can achieve the performance in a manner
similar to the case using on the equation (1).</p>
    <p num="0089">The above equation (5) is obtained in the following
way. That is, in this method, the moving speed Vn is an
actual moving speed of the recording sheet, and a transfer
delay ξ of the recording sheet 2 can be expressed by a
ratio V/VR. For the first recording sheet 2, the roller
linear speed VRn is expressed as VR1=V0 and the delay ξ is
expressed as ξ1=V1/VR1. In this case, V0 means no data
and a predetermined value should be given to V0. For the
second recording sheet 2, the roller linear speed VRn is
expressed as VR2=VR1/ξ1=(VR1)<sup>2</sup>/V1, and the delay ξ is
expressed as ξ2=V2/VR2. For the third recording sheet 2,
the roller linear speed VRn is expressed as VR3=VR2/ξ
2=(VR2)<sup>2</sup>/V2, and the delay ξ is expressed as ξ3=V3/VR3.
Thus, for the nth recording sheet 2, the roller linear
speed VRn is expressed as VRn=VR(n-1)/ξ(n-1)={VR(n-1)}<sup>2</sup>/V(n-1), 
and the delay ξ is expressed as ξn=Vn/VRn.</p>
    <p num="0090">The equation (5) can be modified by an application of
a correction tolerance of ±5%, for example, and is;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">[{VR(n-1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>/V(n-1)]x0.95≤R(n)≤<st32:break type="required"/>
[{VR(n-1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>/V(n-1)]x1.05.</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0091">The tolerance of the RPM correction is usually set to
a degree smaller than ±5% but it may be extended to a
degree of ±8%, which may be a limit, without causing
adverse unexpected side effect.</p>
    <p num="0092">Further, another method alternative to the equation
(3) which is applied to the image forming apparatus 200 is
explained. As set forth, the image forming apparatus 200
controls the revolutions of the motors with the equation
(3) to control the revolutions of the feed and transfer
rollers. The alternative method being explained controls a
transfer speed at which the recording sheet 2 is moved, and
this alternative method is expressed in the following
equation;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">VR(n)=[{VR(n-1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>xT (n-1)]/L,</st32:df>
wherein VR(n) represents a linear speed of the transfer
roller when transferring the nth recording sheet 2, VR(n-1)
represents a linear speed of the transfer roller during a
transfer of the (n-1)th recording sheet 2, and T(n-1)
represents a time period in which the (n-1)th recording 
sheet 2 is moved a predetermined distance.</p>
    <p num="0093">With the above method, the sheet transferring
mechanism 206 can achieve the performance in a manner
similar to the case using the equation (3).</p>
    <p num="0094">The equation (7) can be modified by an application of
a correction tolerance of ±5%, for example, and is;
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">[[{VR(n-1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>xT(n-1)]/L]x0.95≤R(n)≤<st32:break type="required"/>
[[{VR(n-1)}<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>xT(n-1)]/L]x1.05.</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0095">The tolerance of the RPM correction is usually set to
a degree smaller than ±5% but it may be extended to a
degree of ±8%, which may be a limit, without causing
adverse unexpected side effect.</p>
    <p num="0096">Referring to Fig. 15, an exemplary warning system of
the sheet transferring operation provided in the image
forming apparatus 100 of Fig. 5 is explained. As shown in
Fig. 15, the warning system of the sheet transferring
operation is composed of the sheet transferring mechanism
106, the controller 150, and the operation console 111. In
the warning system of the sheet transferring operation, the
controller 150 detects an event that the transfer speed is
varied out of predetermined limits, due to slippage of and
wear of the transfer rollers 7 and 9, for example, based on
the feedback signals from the sheet transferring mechanism
106. In response to this detection, the controller 150 
sends a warning signal to the operation console 111 so that
the operation console 111 indicates through the display
thereof a warning that the sheet transfer mechanism 106 is
in a condition asking for an inspection.</p>
    <p num="0097">Another exemplary warning system of the sheet
transferring operation is explained with reference to Fig.
16. As shown in Fig. 16, an image forming apparatus 300
that includes all the components of the image forming
apparatus 100 and additionally includes a communicator 112
for performing communications with an external system, i.e.,
a data terminal 301, located at a service maintenance
company, for example. The image forming apparatus 300 is
provided with a warning system of the sheet transferring
operation which is composed of the sheet transferring
mechanism 106, the controller 150, the operation console
111, and the communicator 112. In the warning system of
the sheet transferring operation, the controller 150
detects an event that the transfer speed is varied out of
predetermined limits, due to slippage of and wear of the
transfer rollers 7 and 9, for example, based on the
feedback signals sent from the sheet transferring mechanism
106. In response to this detection, the controller 150
sends a request signal for requesting a maintenance service
to the external data terminal 301 via a communications line, 
such as a public switched telephone line, the Internet, a
private telephone line, a mobile telephone, a private
handy-phone system, or the like. At the same time, the
controller 150 sends a status signal to the operation
console 111 which then indicates through the display
thereof a machine status that the sheet transfer mechanism
106 is in a condition asking for an inspection.</p>
    <p num="0098">Numerous additional modifications and variations are
possible in light of the above teachings. It is therefore
to be understood that within the scope of the appended
claims, the disclosure of this patent specification may be
practiced otherwise than as specifically described herein.</p>
    <p num="0099">This paten specification is based on Japanese patent
applications, No. JPAP2001-081211 filed on March 21, 2001
and No. 2002-60796 filed on March 6, 2002, in the Japanese
Patent Office, the entire contents of which are
incorporated by reference herein.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A sheet transfer apparatus for use in an image
forming apparatus, said apparatus comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a sheet transferring mechanism arranged and
configured to transfer a recording sheet at a transfer
speed to an image forming mechanism in said image forming
apparatus; and</claim-text><claim-text>a controller arranged and configured to determine
said transfer speed based on a transfer speed used for an
immediately previous recording sheet.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A sheet transfer apparatus as defined in Claim
1, wherein said sheet transferring mechanism comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a transfer roller; and</claim-text><claim-text>at least two sensors arranged and configured to
detect a recording sheet being transferred, said at least
two sensors being mounted with a predetermined distance
along a sheet transfer path from each other.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A sheet transfer apparatus as defined in Claim
2, wherein said controller determines said transfer speed
using an equation;
VR(n)={VR(n-1)}2/V(n-1),
Wherein n is an integer greater than 1, VR(n) represents a
linear speed of the transfer roller when transferring an
nth recording sheet, VR(n-1) represents a linear speed of
the transfer roller during a transfer of an (n-1)th
recording sheet, and V(n-1) represents a moving speed of
the (n-1)th recording sheet, wherein when the n is equal to
1 the linear speed VR(1) is set to a predetermined value.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A sheet transfer apparatus as defined in Claim
2, wherein said controller determines said transfer speed
using an equation;
VR(n)=[{VR(n-1)}2xT(n-1)]/L,
Wherein n is an integer greater than 1, VR(n) represents a
linear speed of the transfer roller when transferring an
nth recording sheet, VR(n-1) represents a linear speed of
the transfer roller during a transfer of an (n-1)th
recording sheet, L represents the predetermined distance,
and T(n-1) represents a time period in which the (n-1)Lh
recording sheet is moved the predetermined distance,
wherein the n is equal to 1 the linear speed VR(1) is set
to the predetermined value.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A sheet transfer apparatus as defined in Claim
2, wherein said controller determines said transfer speed
using an equation;
R(n)=[πxDx{R(n-1)}2]/V(n-1),
Wherein n is an integer greater than 1, R(n) represents an
angular speed of the transfer roller when transferring an nth
recording sheet, D represents an outer diameter of the
transfer roller, R(n-1) represents an angular speed of the transfer
roller during a transfer of an (n-1)th recording sheet, and
V(n-1) represents a linear speed of the (n-1)th recording
sheet, wherein when n is equal to 1 the angular speed R(1)
is set to a predetermined value.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A sheet transfer apparatus as defined in Claim
2, wherein said controller determines said transfer speed
using an equation;
R(n)=[πxDx{R(n-1)}2xT(n-1)]/L,
Wherein n is an integer greater than 1, R(n) represents an
angular speed of the transfer roller when transferring an nth
recording sheet, D represents an outer diameter of the
transfer roller, R(n-1) represents an angular speed of the transfer
roller during a transfer of an (n-1)th recording sheet, L
represents the predetermined distance, and T(n-1)
represents a transfer time period of the (n-1) th recording
sheet being moved the predetermined distance, wherein whenn
is equal to 1 the angular speed R(1) is set to a
predetermined value.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A sheet transfer apparatus as defined in any one of claims 3 to 6, wherein said
controller apparatus applies a correction tolerance of ± 5% so that the transfer roller
is driven at speed within a range of ± 5% of the value determined by the equation.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A sheet transfer apparatus as defined in any one of claims 2 to 7,
wherein said predetermined distance is defined by an
equation;
L=Dxπxn,
wherein D represents an outer diameter of the transfer
roller, and n is an
integer greater than 1.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>An image forming apparatus, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>an image forming mechanism arranged and configured to
form a visible image on a recording sheet;</claim-text><claim-text>a sheet transferring mechanism arranged and
configured to transfer the recording sheet at a transfer
speed to said image forming mechanism; and</claim-text><claim-text>a controller arranged and configured to determine
said transfer speed based on a transfer speed used for an
immediately previous racording sheet.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>An image forming apparatus as defined in Claim
9 further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a display arranged and configured to indicate a
warning that the sheet transfer mechanism is in a condition
asking for an inspection when said transfer speed deviates
beyond predetermined limits.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>An image forming system, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>an image forming apparatus, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>an image forming mechanism arranged and
configured to form a visible image on a recording sheet;</claim-text><claim-text>a sheet transferring mechanism arranged and
configured to transfer the recording sheet at a transfer
speed to said image forming mechanism; and</claim-text><claim-text>a controller arranged and configured to
determine said transfer speed based on a transfer speed
used for an immediately previous recording sheet, and</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>an operation apparatus comprising a display for
indicating a warning that the sheet transfer mechanism is
in a condition asking for an inspection in accordance with
an instruction from said image forming apparatus when said
transfer speed deviates beyond predetermined limits.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>An image forming system as defined in Claim 11,
further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a communications mechanism arranged and configured to
send a warning that the sheet transfer mechanism is in a
condition asking for an inspection when said transfer speed
deviates beyond predetermined limits to a service
maintenance group through one of a telephone line, Internet,
a mobile communication tool, and a personal handy-phone
system.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>An image forming apparatus, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>an image forming mechanism arranged and configured to
form a visible image on a recording sheet;</claim-text><claim-text>a sheet transferring mechanism arranged and
configured to transfer the recording sheet at a transfer
speed to said image forming mechanism; and</claim-text><claim-text>a controller arranged and configured to control a
number of revolutions of a motor for driving the transfer
roller to determine said transfer speed based on a transfer
speed used for an immediately previous recording sheet.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>An image forming apparatus as defined in Claim
13 further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a display arranged and configured to indicate a
warning that the sheet transfer mechanism is in a condition
asking for an inspection when said number of revolutions of
the motor deviates beyond predetermined limits.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>An image forming system, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>an image forming apparatus, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>an image forming mechanism arranged and
configured to form a visible image on a recording sheet;</claim-text><claim-text>a sheet transferring mechanism arranged and
configured to transfer the recording sheet at a transfer
speed to said image forming mechanism; and</claim-text><claim-text>a controller arranged and configured to
determine said transfer speed based on a transfer speed
used for an immediately previous recording sheet, and</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>an operation apparatus comprising a display for
indicating a warning that the sheet transfer mechanism is
in a condition asking for an inspection in accordance with
an instruction from said image forming apparatus when said
number of revolutions of the motor deviates beyond
predetermined limits.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>An image forming system as defined in Claim 15,
further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a communications mechanism arranged and configured to
send a warning that the sheet transfer mechanism is in a
condition asking for An inspection when said number of
revolutions of the motor deviates beyond predetermined
limits to a service maintenance group through one of a
telephone line, Internet, a mobile communication tool, and
a personal handy-phone system.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
