<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1226990-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1226990" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="18882463" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020731">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1226990-A1" status="new" fvid="23520907">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1226990</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20020731</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02001710-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02001710</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020124</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001016009-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001016009</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010124</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B60H   1/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B60H   1/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F25B  40/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F25B  40/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B60H   1/00A</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B60H   1/00Y6B3B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B60H   1/00Y6B3C</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F25B  40/00</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Fahrzeug-Klimaanlage</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Air conditioner for vehicle</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Climatiseur pour véhicule</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>CALSONIC KANSEI CORP</last-name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>CALSONIC KANSEI CORPORATION</last-name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Calsonic Kansei Corporation</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>24-15, Minamidai 5-chome, Nakano-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>HATAKEYAMA JUN</last-name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>OGIHARA SATOSHI</last-name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>HATAKEYAMA, JUN</last-name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>OGIHARA, SATOSHI</last-name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>HATAKEYAMA, JUN</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Calsonic Kansei Corp., 24-15, Minamidai 5-chome</street>
              <city>Nakano-ku, Tokyo</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>OGIHARA, SATOSHI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Calsonic Kansei Corp., 24-15, Minamidai 5-chome</street>
              <city>Nakano-ku, Tokyo</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Grünecker, Kinkeldey, Stockmair &amp;amp; Schwanhäusser Anwaltssozietät</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Maximilianstrasse 58</street>
              <city>80538 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A sub-condenser 4 is disposed in a
within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1, so that the
sub-condenser is permitted to receive heat from a heater core
21.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="164" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="114"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <heading>1. Field of the Invention</heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to an air conditioner for
a vehicle for air-conditioning a temperature environment within
a vehicle compartment.</p>
    <heading>2. Description of the Related Art</heading>
    <p num="0002">A conventional air conditioner for a vehicle is used to
air-condition a temperature environment within a vehicle
compartment. The conventional air conditioner generally
comprises a refrigeration cycle for circulating a refrigerant
to thereby exchange heat between refrigerant and air, and a
hot water line for exchanging heat using engine cooling water
heated by heat that is exhausted from an engine.</p>
    <p num="0003">In the conventional air conditioner for a vehicle, in an
air passage within a vehicle compartment (which is hereinafter
referred to as a within-vehicle-compartment air passage) into
which the inside air and outside air canbe selectively introduced,
there are disposed an evaporator serving as a heat absorbing
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger to be incorporated
into the refrigeration cycle, and a heater core which serves
as a heat generator and is incorporated into the hot water line.
And, in case where the heat of the air flowing through the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage is absorbed into the 
refrigerant existing within the evaporator, there is produced
the cool air; and, in case where the air flowing through the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage is heated by the heater
core, there is produced the warm air. Also, in case where the
rate between the cool air and warm air is adjusted by an air
mix door, the temperature within the vehicle compartment can
be adjusted.</p>
    <p num="0004">By the way, in the above-structured conventional air
conditioner for a vehicle, since the warm air is produced by
the heater core which uses the engine cooling water as a heat
medium, in a state where the temperature of the engine cooling
water is not yet sufficiently high, for example, just after
the engine is started, or when the running load is small, the
temperature within the vehicle compartment cannot be raised
up to a satisfactory level.</p>
    <p num="0005">In order to cope with the above problem and thus enhance
the heating performance, there are proposed air conditioners
for a vehicle which are respectively disclosed in JP-A-9-175140
and JP-A-10-44742. In these air conditioners for a vehicle,
a sub-condenser serving as a heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger for radiating the
heat of the refrigerant into the air existing within the vehicle
compartment is incorporated into the refrigeration line. And,
the sub-condenser, together with the evaporator and heater core,
is disposed in the above-mentioned within-vehicle-compartment 
air passage.</p>
    <p num="0006">In the thus-structured air conditioners for a vehicle,
since the warm air is produced not only by the heater core using
the engine cooling water as a heat medium but also by the
sub-condenser using the refrigerant as the heat medium, even
in a state where the temperature of the engine cooling water
is not yet sufficiently high, for example, just after the engine
is started, or when the running load is small, the temperature
within the vehicle compartment can be raised relatively rapidly.</p>
    <p num="0007">Recently, the atmosphere of the space within the vehicle
compartment has been made more and more comfortable and, with
the increasing comfort of the vehicle compartment, there has
been raised the need to enhance the performance of the air
conditioner for a vehicle, especially, there has been strongly
raised the need to further enhance the quick heating performance
of the air conditioner for raising the temperature within the
vehicle compartment quickly.</p>
    <p num="0008">In the above-mentioned air conditioners for a vehicle,
as a factor in hindering the further enhancement in the quick
heating performance thereof, there can be pointed out the fact
that, when the air conditioners for a vehicle are started, because
the temperature load of the sub-condenser is low, the discharge
pressure (Pd) of the refrigerant is hard to rise.</p>
    <p num="0009">To enhance the temperature load of the sub-condenser, it
is very effective to transmit heat from another heat source 
to the sub-condenser. According to an air conditioner for a
vehicle disclosed in JP-A-10-44742, since, in a
within-vehicle-compartment air passage, a heater core is disposed
upstream of a sub-condenser, the heat of the heater core can
be transmitted to the sub-condenser through the air flowing
through the within-vehicle-compartment air passage, which makes
it possible to enhance the temperature load of the sub-condenser.</p>
    <p num="0010">However, during the time until the temperature of engine
cooling water rises up to a specified value, in case where the
air is allowed to flow through the within-vehicle-compartment
air passage, the temperature of the air is lowered on the contrary.
For this reason, during this time, preferably, the air may be
prevented from flowing through the within-vehicle-compartment
air passage. That is, in such case, since the heat of the heater
core is not transmitted to the sub-condenser, the temperature
load of the sub-condenser cannot be enhanced. Accordingly, a
state, in which the refrigerant discharge pressure is hard to
rise, continues for a given period of time, which makes it difficult
to enhance the quick heating performance of the vehicle air
conditioner further.</p>
    <p num="0011">Also, in a state where the temperature load of the
sub-condenser is low and the refrigerant discharge pressure
is hard to rise, the efficiency of use of the refrigerant in
the refrigeration cycle is lowered. Therefore, it is necessary
to increase the enclosure amount of the refrigerant to a certain 
degree, and, as a liquid tank for holding therein a liquid-phase
refrigerant temporarily, it is necessary to use a
relatively-large-sized liquid tank, which provides a very great
disadvantage in reducing the size and weight of the whole air
conditioner for a vehicle.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0012">An object of the present invention has been made to solve
the above-mentioned drawbacks found in the conventional air
conditioner for a vehicle. Accordingly, it is an object of the
invention to provide an air conditioner for a vehicle which
is excellent in the rapid heating performance and is able to
realize reduction in the size and weight of the whole air
conditioner for a vehicle.</p>
    <p num="0013">In attaining the above object, according to a first aspect
of the invention, there is provided an air conditioner for a
vehicle, comprising: a compressor for compressing a refrigerant
sucked therein and jetting out the compressed refrigerant
therefrom; an outside-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger for
radiating the heat of the refrigerant to the outside air; a
heat radiating within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger
disposed in a within-vehicle-compartment air passage into which
the inside air and the outside air can be introduced selectively
for radiating the heat of the refrigerant to the air flowing
through the within-vehicle-compartment air passage; an expander 
for expanding the refrigerant the heat of which has been radiated
by at least one of the outside-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger
and heat radiating within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger;
a heat absorbing within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger
disposed upstream of the heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger in the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage for allowing the
refrigerant expanded by the expander to absorb the heat of the
air flowing through the within-vehicle-compartment air passage;
and, a heat generator disposed in the within-vehicle-compartment
air passage, wherein the heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger is disposed at a
position which permits reception of the heat from the heat
generator.</p>
    <p num="0014">According to the first aspect of the invention, the
refrigerant compressed by and jetted out from the compressor
is supplied to at least one of the outside-vehicle-compartment
heat exchanger and heat radiating within-vehicle-compartment
heat exchanger, where the heat of the refrigerant is radiated.
And, the refrigerant, the heat of which is radiated by at least
one of the outside-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger and heat
radiating within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger, is supplied
to and expanded by the expander.</p>
    <p num="0015">The refrigerant expanded by the expander is supplied to
the heat absorbing within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger, 
where the refrigerant absorbs the heat of the air flowing through
the within-vehicle-compartment air passage. And, the
refrigerant, which has absorbed the heat of the air flowing
through the within-vehicle-compartment air passage, is sucked
into the compressor again. This series of cycles are repeated
continuously.</p>
    <p num="0016">In these cycles, in case where the air is introduced into
the within-vehicle-compartment air passage, when the air passes
through the heat absorbing within-vehicle-compartment heat
exchanger disposed in the within-vehicle-compartment air passage,
the heat of the air is absorbed by the refrigerant existing
in the heat absorbing within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger
and the air is thereby dehumidified, so that the air turns
into the cold air. Also, when the air passing through the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage passes through the heat
radiating within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger and a heat
generator respectively disposed in the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage, the present air not
only absorbs the heat of the refrigerant existing in the heat
radiating within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger but also
absorbs the heat from the heat generator to be thereby heated,
so that the air turns into the warm air.</p>
    <p num="0017">Here, in the vehicle air conditioner according to the first
aspect of the invention, since the heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger is disposed at a 
position which permits reception of the heat from the heat
generator, even in a state where the air does not flow in the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage, the heat from the heat
generator is transmitted to the heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger. Due to this, the
temperature load of the heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger can be increased,
which makes it possible to raise the discharge pressure of the
refrigerant rapidly.</p>
    <p num="0018">Now, according to a second aspect of the invention, in
an air conditioner for a vehicle as set forth in the first aspect
of the invention, there are further included a first refrigerant
line for supplying the refrigerant jetted out from the compressor
to the expander through the outside-vehicle-compartment heat
exchanger and allowing the refrigerant to be sucked into the
compressor through heat absorbing within-vehicle-compartment
heat exchanger; a second refrigerant line for supplying the
refrigerant jetted out from the compressor to the expander through
the heat radiating within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger
and allowing the refrigerant to be sucked into the compressor
through the heat absorbing within-vehicle-compartment heat
exchanger; and, a switch capable of selectively switching the
first refrigerant line and second refrigerant line over to each
other.</p>
    <p num="0019">In the vehicle air conditioner according to the second 
aspect of the invention, when the first refrigerant line is
selected by the switch, the refrigerant jetted out from the
compressor is supplied to the outside-vehicle-compartment heat
exchanger but is not supplied to the heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger. And, the
refrigerant, the heat of which has been radiated by the
outside-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger, is supplied to the
expander; and, when the refrigerant passes through the heat
absorbing within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger, the
refrigerant absorbs the heat of the air flowing through the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage and, after then, the
refrigerant is sucked into the compressor again.</p>
    <p num="0020">On the other hand, when the second refrigerant line is
selected by the switch, the refrigerant jetted out from the
compressor is supplied to the heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger but is not supplied
to the outside-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger. And, the
refrigerant, the heat of which has been radiated by the heat
radiating within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger, is supplied
to the expander; and, when the refrigerant passes through the
heat absorbing within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger, the
refrigerant absorbs the heat of the air flowing through the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage and, after then, the
refrigerant is sucked into the compressor again.</p>
    <p num="0021">Now, according to a third aspect of the invention, in an 
air conditioner for a vehicle as set forth in the first or second
aspect of the invention, there are further included a third
refrigerant line for supplying the refrigerant jetted out from
the compressor to a second expander not connected to the heat
absorbing within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger through
the heat radiating within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger
and allowing the refrigerant not only to bypass the heat absorbing
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger but also to be sucked
into the compressor; and, a switch capable of switching the
selection of the third refrigerant line.</p>
    <p num="0022">In the vehicle air conditioner according to the third aspect
of the invention, when the third refrigerant line is selected
by the switch, the refrigerant jetted out from the compressor
is supplied to the heat radiating within-vehicle-compartment
heat exchanger; and, the refrigerant, the heat of which has
been radiated by the heat radiating within-vehicle-compartment
heat exchanger, is supplied to the second expander not connected
to the heat absorbing within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger.
And, the refrigerant, which has been expanded by the second
expander not connected to the heat absorbing
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger, bypasses the heat
absorbing within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger and is then
sucked into the compressor again.</p>
    <p num="0023">Now, according to a fourth aspect of the invention, in
an air conditioner for a vehicle as set forth in the third aspect 
of the invention, in the third refrigerant line, there is disposed
an inter-refrigerant heat exchanger for exchanging heat between
the refrigerant expandedby the second expander and the refrigerant
flowing through the front stage of the second expander.</p>
    <p num="0024">In the vehicle air conditioner according to the fourth
aspect of the invention, when the third refrigerant line is
selected by the switch, the inter-refrigerant heat exchanger
disposed in the third refrigerant line exchanges heat between
the refrigerant expanded by the second expander not connected
to the heat absorbing within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger
and the refrigerant flowing through the front stage of the second
expander. And, the refrigerant, which has absorbed heat through
this heat exchange operation, is sucked into the compressor.</p>
    <p num="0025">Now, according to a fifth aspect of the invention, in an
air conditioner for a vehicle as set forth in the third aspect
of the invention, in the third refrigerant line, there is disposed
an inter-refrigerant heat exchanger for exchanging heat between
the refrigerant expanded by the second expander and the refrigerant
in the front stage of the heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger.</p>
    <p num="0026">In the vehicle air conditioner according to the fifth aspect
of the invention, when the third refrigerant line is selected
by the switch, the inter-refrigerant heat exchanger disposed
in the third refrigerant line exchanges heat between the
refrigerant expanded by the second expander not connected to 
the heat absorbing within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger
and the refrigerant in the front stage of the heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger the second expander.
And, the refrigerant, which has absorbed heat through this heat
exchange operation, is sucked into the compressor.</p>
    <p num="0027">Now, according to a sixth aspect of the invention, in an
air conditioner for a vehicle as set forth in any one of the
first to fifth aspects of the invention, the heat generator
is disposed upstream of the heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger in the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage.</p>
    <p num="0028">In the vehicle air conditioner according to the sixth aspect
of the invention, the air flowing through the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage absorbs the heat from
the heat generator and is thereby heated; and, after then, the
air absorbs the heat of the refrigerant in the heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger and is thereby heated
further.</p>
    <p num="0029">Now, according to a seventh aspect of the invention, in
an air conditioner for a vehicle as set forth in any one of
the first to sixth aspects of the invention, the heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger and a heat generator
are formed as an integral body.</p>
    <p num="0030">In the vehicle air conditioner according to the seventh
aspect of the invention, the heat from the heat generator is 
transmitted directly to the heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger.</p>
    <p num="0031">Now, according to an eighth aspect of the invention, there
is provided an air conditioner for a vehicle, comprising at
least: a compressor for compressing a refrigerant sucked therein
and jetting out the compressed refrigerant to thereby allow
the refrigerant to circulate; a within-vehicle-compartment heat
exchanger disposed in a within-vehicle-compartment air passage,
into which the inside air and the outside air can be introduced
selectively, in such a manner that the circulating refrigerant
can be supplied to the within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger;
a heat generator disposed in the within-vehicle-compartment
air passage; and, an expander for expanding the circulating
refrigerant, wherein the within-vehicle-compartment heat
exchanger is disposed at a position which permits reception
of the heat from the heat generator.</p>
    <p num="0032">In the vehicle air conditioner according to the eighth
aspect of the invention, in case where the air is introduced
into the within-vehicle-compartment air passage while the
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger functions as a heat
radiator, the air flowing through the within-vehicle-compartment
air passage, when passing through the within-vehicle-compartment
heat exchanger and a heat generator, not only absorbs the heat
of the refrigerant in the within-vehicle-compartment heat
exchanger but also absorbs the heat from the heat generator 
to be thereby heated, with the result that the air turns into
the warm air.</p>
    <p num="0033">Here, in the vehicle air conditioner according to the eighth
aspect of the invention, since the within-vehicle-compartment
heat exchanger is disposed at a position permitting reception
of heat from the heat generator, even in a state where the air
does not flow in the within-vehicle-compartment air passage,
the heat from the heat generator is transmitted to a heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger. Thanks to this, the
temperature load of the heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger can be increased,
which makes it possible to raise the discharge pressure of the
refrigerant rapidly.</p>
    <p num="0034">Now, according to a ninth aspect of the invention, in an
air conditioner for a vehicle as set forth in the eighth aspect
of the invention, the heat generator is disposed upstream of
the within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger in the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage.</p>
    <p num="0035">In the vehicle air conditioner according to the ninth aspect
of the invention, the air flowing through the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage absorbs the heat from
the heat generator and is thereby heated and, after then, the
air absorbs the heat of the refrigerant in the
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger functioning as a
radiator and is thereby heated further. </p>
    <p num="0036">Now, according to a tenth aspect of the invention, in an
air conditioner for a vehicle as set forth in the eighth or
ninth aspect of the invention, the within-vehicle-compartment
heat exchanger and a heat generator are formed as an integral
body.</p>
    <p num="0037">In the vehicle air conditioner according to the tenth aspect
of the invention, the heat from the heat generator is transmitted
directly to the within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger.</p>
    <p num="0038">According to the first aspect of the invention, even in
a state where the air does not flow in the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage, the heat from the heat
generator is effectively transmitted to the heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger to thereby be able
to increase the temperature load of the heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger and thus raise the
discharge pressure of the refrigerant rapidly. That is, the
first aspect of the invention allows the present vehicle air
conditioner to fulfill a very excellent quick heating performance.</p>
    <p num="0039">Also, since the temperature load of the heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger can be increased and
the discharge pressure of the refrigerant can be thereby raised
rapidly, the use efficiency of the refrigerant can be enhanced
and thus the quantity of the refrigerant to be enclosed can
be reduced. Therefore, according to the first aspect of the
invention, it is possible to realize reduction in the size and 
weight of the whole vehicle air conditioner.</p>
    <p num="0040">According to the second aspect of the invention, in the
cooling operation time, the first refrigerant line is selected;
whereas, in the heating operation time, the second refrigerant
line is selected. That is, in the cooling operation time, the
heat radiating within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger is
not used. This can avoid an inconvenience that, in the cooling
operation time, the refrigerant, the heat of which has been
radiated by the outside-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger,
can absorb the heat from the heat generator to thereby lower
the cooling efficiency of the vehicle air conditioner.</p>
    <p num="0041">According to the third aspect of the invention, in the
heating operation time, the third refrigerant line is selected;
that is, in the heating operation time, the heat absorbing
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger is not used. This
not only can eliminate the need of execution of complicated
operations such as a high-accuracy inside air and outside air
introduction operation necessary for prevention of the
over-cooling of the heat absorbing within-vehicle-compartment
heat exchanger in the heating operation time, but also allows
the vehicle air conditioner to fulfill an excellent quick heating
performance.</p>
    <p num="0042">According to the fourth aspect of the invention, in case
where the third refrigerant line is selected, since the temperature
of the refrigerant to be sucked into the compressor can be raised 
effectively, the quick heating performance can be enhanced
further.</p>
    <p num="0043">According to the fifth aspect of the invention, in case
where the third refrigerant line is selected, since the temperature
of the refrigerant to be sucked into the compressor can be raised
effectively, the quick heating performance can be enhanced
further.</p>
    <p num="0044">According to the sixth aspect of the invention, the
transmission efficiency of the heat to be transmitted from the
heat generator to the heat radiating within-vehicle-compartment
heat exchanger can be enhanced, which makes it possible to enhance
the quick heating performance still further.</p>
    <p num="0045">According to the seventh aspect of the invention, the
transmission efficiency of the heat to be transmitted from the
heat generator to the heat radiating within-vehicle-compartment
heat exchanger can be enhanced, which makes it possible to enhance
the quick heating performance still further.</p>
    <p num="0046">According to the eighth aspect of the invention, even in
a state where the air does not flow in the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage, the heat from the heat
generator is effectively transmitted to the
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger serving as a heat
radiator to thereby be able to increase the temperature load
of the present within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger and
thus raise the discharge pressure of the refrigerant rapidly. 
That is, the first aspect of the invention allows the present
vehicle air conditioner to fulfill a very excellent quick heating
performance.</p>
    <p num="0047">Also, since the temperature load of the
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger can be increased and
the discharge pressure of the refrigerant can be thereby raised
rapidly, the use efficiency of the refrigerant can be enhanced
and thus the quantity of the refrigerant to be enclosed can
be reduced. Therefore, according to the eighth aspect of the
invention, it is possible to realize reduction in the size and
weight of the whole vehicle air conditioner.</p>
    <p num="0048">According to the ninth aspect of the invention, the
transmission efficiency of the heat to be transmitted from the
heat generator to the within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger
serving as a heat radiator can be enhanced, which makes it possible
to enhance the quick heating performance still further.</p>
    <p num="0049">According to the tenth aspect of the invention, the
transmission efficiency of the heat to be transmitted from the
heat generator to the within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger
serving as a heat radiator can be enhanced further, which makes
it possible to enhance the quick heating performance still further.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0050">
      <sl>
        <li>Fig. 1 is a schematic block diagram of the structure of
a first embodiment of a vehicle air conditioner according to 
the invention.</li>
        <li>Fig. 2 is a schematic block diagram of a first modification
of a vehicle air conditioner according to the first embodiment
of the invention, including a third refrigerant line bypassing
an evaporator.</li>
        <li>Fig. 3 is a schematic block diagram of a second modification
of a vehicle air conditioner according to the first embodiment
of the invention, including a third refrigerant line bypassing
an evaporator.</li>
        <li>Fig. 4 is a typical view of a modification of the third
refrigerant line including an inter-refrigerant heat exchanger
for exchanging heat between a refrigerant expanded by a pressure
reducing valve and a refrigerant flowing through the front stage
of a sub-condenser.</li>
        <li>Fig. 5 is a typical view of a second modification of the
third refrigerant line including an inter-refrigerant heat
exchanger for exchanging heat between a refrigerant expanded
by a pressure reducing valve and a refrigerant flowing through
the front stage of the pressure reducing valve.</li>
        <li>Fig. 6 is a perspective view of an embodiment of an integral
type of pipe member used as the inter-refrigerant heat exchanger.</li>
        <li>Fig. 7 is a perspective view of a second embodiment of
an integral type of pipe member used as the inter-refrigerant
heat exchanger.</li>
        <li>Fig. 8 is a perspective view of an embodiment of a composite 
type of pipe member used as the inter-refrigerant heat exchanger.</li>
        <li>Fig. 9 is a schematic block diagram of the structure of
a third modification of a vehicle air conditioner according
to the first embodiment of the invention, including a refrigerant
collecting line.</li>
        <li>Fig. 10 is a schematic block diagram of the structure of
a fourth modification of a vehicle air conditioner according
to the first embodiment of the invention, in which a main condenser
and a sub-condenser are connected in series with each other.</li>
        <li>Fig. 11 is a schematic block diagram of the structure of
a vehicle air conditioner of a hot gas cycle to which to the
invention is applied.</li>
        <li>Fig. 12 is a schematic block diagram of the structure of
a vehicle air conditioner of a heat pump cycle to which to the
invention is applied.</li>
      </sl>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">DETAIELD DESCRIPTION OF THE PRESENT INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0051">Now, description will be given below in detail of the mode
for carrying out the invention with reference to the accompanying
drawings.</p>
    <p num="0052">Fig. 1 shows schematically the structure of an embodiment
of an air conditioner for a vehicle according to the invention.
The air conditioner for a vehicle shown in Fig. 1 comprises
a refrigeration cycle for circulating a refrigerant and a hot
water line for circulating engine cooling water. </p>
    <p num="0053">In the refrigeration cycle, a compressor 2, a main condenser
3 serving as an outside-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger,
a sub-condenser 4 serving as a heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger, a liquid tank 5,
an expansion valve 6 serving as an expander, and an evaporator
7 serving as a heat absorbing within-vehicle-compartment heat
exchanger are connected to one another through pipe members;
and, a refrigerant, when energy is given thereto by the compressor
2, is allowed to circulate between the above respective components.</p>
    <p num="0054">The compressor 2, which is disposed outside a vehicle
compartment such as an engine room, compresses a vapor-phase
refrigerant having a low pressure absorbed therein and jets
out the compressed refrigerant therefrom as a vapor-phase
refrigerant having a high pressure. The compressor 2 can be
driven, for example, by transmitting the power of a crankshaft
of an engine 10 to the compressor 2 through a belt.</p>
    <p num="0055">By the way, as the compressor 2, preferably, there may
be used a variable-capacity compressor the refrigerant discharge
amount of which can be controlled. In case where a
variable-capacity compressor is used as the compressor 2, the
cooling and heating performance is controlled according to the
refrigerant discharge amount and, therefore, while reducing
the required power of the compressor 2, the temperature within
the vehicle compartment can be adjusted efficiently.</p>
    <p num="0056">The main condenser 3 is used to radiate the heat of the 
high-temperature and high-pressure vapor-phase refrigerant
jetted out from the compressor 2 to the outside. This main
condenser 3 is disposed in such a manner that, when an air blower
11 such as an electric fan is driven, the air can be blown to
the main condenser 3. The main condenser 3 exchanges heat between
the high-temperature and high-pressure vapor-phase refrigerant
passing within the main condenser 3 and the air blown to the
main condenser 3 to thereby radiate the heat of the
high-temperature and high-pressure vapor-phase refrigerant to
the air.</p>
    <p num="0057">The sub-condenser 4 is disposed in a
within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1 (which will be
discussed later) and is used to radiate the heat of the
high-temperature and high-pressure vapor-phase refrigerant
jetted out from the compressor 2 to the air flowing in the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1. The air flowing in
the within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1 absorbs the heat
of the refrigerant radiated by the sub-condenser 4 and thus
turns into the warm air, so that the warm air flows to the downstream
side of the within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1.</p>
    <p num="0058">By the way, in the air conditioner for a vehicle 1 shown
in Fig. 1, the sub-condenser 4 and main condenser 3 are connected
together in parallel, which makes it possible to selectively
use the sub-condenser 4 and main condenser 3. That is, a passage
for the refrigerant jetted out from the compressor 2 branches 
through a three-way connector 12 into a first refrigerant line
L1 which passes through the main condenser 3, and a second
refrigerant line L2 passing through the sub-condenser 4. And,
in the front stage of the liquid tank 5, the first and second
refrigerant lines L1 and L2 join together through another three-way
connector 13.</p>
    <p num="0059">In the case of the first refrigerant line L1, in the front
stage of the main condenser 3, there is disposed an electromagnetic
valve 14; and, in the rear stage of the main condenser 3, there
is disposed a check valve 15. Similarly, in the case of the
second refrigerant line L2 as well, in the front stage of the
sub-condenser 4, there is disposed an electromagnetic valve
16; and, in the rear stage of the sub-condenser 4, there is
disposed a check valve 17. And, in case where the open and closed
states of the electromagnetic valve 14 disposed in the first
refrigerant line L1 and the open and closed states of the
electromagnetic valve 16 disposed in the second refrigerant
line L2 are switched over to each other by a control unit (not
shown) for controlling the operation of the whole vehicle air
conditioner 1, the first refrigerant line L1 or second refrigerant
line L2 can be selected.</p>
    <p num="0060">Specifically, in the cooling operation time of the vehicle
air conditioner 1, the electromagnetic valve 14 disposed in
the first refrigerant line L1 is set in the "open" state, whereas
the electromagnetic valve 16 disposed in the second refrigerant 
line L2 is set in the "closed" state. As a result of this, the
first refrigerant line L1 is selected, so that the refrigerant
jetted out from the compressor 2 is supplied to the main condenser
3. On the other hand, in the heating operation time of the vehicle
air conditioner 1, the electromagnetic valve 14 disposed in
the first refrigerant line L1 is set in the "closed" state,
whereas the electromagnetic valve 16 disposed in the second
refrigerant line L2 is set in the "open" state. As a result
of this, the second refrigerant line L2 is selected, so that
the refrigerant jetted out from the compressor 2 is supplied
to the sub-condenser 3.</p>
    <p num="0061">As described above, in the air conditioner for a vehicle
1, the control unit functions as a switch which is capable of
selectively switching the first and second refrigerant lines
L1 and L2; that is, the passage of the refrigerant jetted out
from the compressor 2 can be switched between the cooling and
heating operations by the control unit, so that the main condenser
3 and sub-condenser 4 can be used selectively.</p>
    <p num="0062">The liquid tank 5 is used to hold therein temporarily a
liquid-phase refrigerant which is obtained when the heat of
the refrigerant is radiated by the main condenser 3 or
sub-condenser 4 and the refrigerant is thereby liquefied. This
liquid tank 5 includes a dust-proof filter and thus has a function
to remove dust mixed into the liquid-phase refrigerant held
therein. By the way, preferably, the liquid tank 5 may be disposed 
in the rear stage of the three-way connector 13. However, when
it is difficult to dispose the liquid tank 5 in the rear stage
of the three-way connector 13 due to the limit of the pipe lay-out
arrangement within the engine room, as shown by a one-dot chained
line in Fig. 1, the liquid tank 5 may be disposed just behind
the main condenser 3 or may be disposed so as to be integral
with the main condenser 3. In this case, the liquid-phase
refrigerant, which is liquefied due to the radiation of the
heat from the refrigerant by the sub-condenser 4, is supplied
directly to the expansion valve 6 not through the liquid tank
5.</p>
    <p num="0063">The expansion valve 6 expands suddenly the liquid-phase
refrigerant, which is obtained when the heat of the refrigerant
is radiated by the main condenser 3 or sub-condenser 4 and is
then held in the liquid tank 5 temporarily, to thereby be able
to supply the liquid-phase refrigerant to the evaporator 7 in
the form of a mist-like refrigerant of low temperature and high
pressure.</p>
    <p num="0064">The evaporator 7 is disposed upstream of the sub-condenser
4 in the within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1 and allows
the heat of the air flowing through the within-vehicle-compartment
air passage P1 to be absorbed by the mist-like refrigerant of
low temperature and high pressure supplied from the expansion
valve 6. The refrigerant supplied to the evaporator 7 as the
mist-like refrigerant of low temperature and high pressure, 
when passing through the evaporator 7, absorbs the heat of the
air flowing through the within-vehicle-compartment air passage
P1 and is thereby vaporized. And, the vapor-phase refrigerant
is sucked into the compressor 2, is compressed again and is
jetted out from the compressor 2. On the other hand, in the
case of the air the heat of which is absorbed by the refrigerant
within the evaporator 7, it is dehumidified to thereby turn
into the cold air, so that the cold air then flows to the downstream
side of the within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1.</p>
    <p num="0065">The refrigeration cycle allows the refrigerant to circulate
in the above-mentioned manner and carries out heat exchange
in the main condenser 3 or sub-condenser 4 and in the evaporator
7, thereby generating the warm air or cold air in the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1.</p>
    <p num="0066">Now, the hot water line carries out heat by allowing the
engine cooling water to circulate, that is, by using the engine
cooling water the temperature of which has been raised up to
a high temperature due to the waste heat of the engine 10; and,
a heater core 21 serving as a heat generator is incorporated
into the hot water line.</p>
    <p num="0067">The heater core 21, together with the sub-condenser 4,
is disposed downstream of the evaporator 7 in the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1; and, using, as its
heat medium, the engine cooling water to be supplied through
a pipe member from the water jacket of the engine 10, that is, 
the engine cooling water the temperature of which has been raised
up to a high temperature due to the waste heat of the engine
10, the heater core 21 generates heat due to the heat of the
high-temperature engine cooling water. And the air flowing in
the within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1 absorbs not only
the heat of the refrigerant the heat of which is radiated by
the above-mentioned sub-condenser 4 but also the heat given
from the heater core 21. In this manner, the warm air can be
produced effectively in the within-vehicle-compartment air
passage P1. By the way, in the pipe member for supplying the
engine cooling water from the water jacket of the engine 10
to the heater core 21, there is disposed a water valve 22; and,
the water valve 22 can be adjusted under the control of the
above-mentioned control unit, whereby the flow rate of the engine
cooling water to be supplied to the heater core 21, that is,
the heating value of the heater core 21 can be adjusted.</p>
    <p num="0068">By the way, in the air conditioner for a vehicle 1 according
to the invention, the sub-condenser 4, which is a heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger, is disposed at a
position where it is able to receive the heat from the heater
core 21 serving as a heat generator. Here, the position permitting
reception of the heat from the heater core 21 means a position
to which the heat from the heater core 21 can be transmitted.
Specifically, for example, in case where the sub-condenser 4
is disposed at a position very near to the heater core 21, or 
in case where the sub-condenser 4 and heater core 21 are formed
as an integral body, the sub-condenser 4 is able to receive
the heat from the heater core 21.</p>
    <p num="0069">In the air conditioner for a vehicle 1 according to the
invention, as described above, since the sub-condenser 4 serving
as a heat radiating within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger,
is disposed at a position where it is able to receive the heat
from the heater core 21 serving as a heat generator, as will
be discussed later in detail, by increasing the temperature
load of the sub-condenser 4, the refrigerant discharge pressure
(Pd) can be increased quickly, which makes it possible to fulfill
its quick heating performance very excellently.</p>
    <p num="0070">By the way, to fulfill the quick heating performance more
excellently, preferably, the heater core 21 serving as a heat
generator may be disposed upstream of the sub-condenser 4 which
serves as a heat radiating within-vehicle-compartment heat
exchanger in the within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1.</p>
    <p num="0071">That is, in case where the heater core 21 is disposed
downstream of the sub-condenser 4, the air, which is introduced
into the within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1 and is passed
through the evaporator 7 to be thereby turn into the cold air,
is contacted directly with the sub-condenser 4 to thereby decrease
the temperature load of the sub-condenser 4 further, which makes
it difficult to raise the refrigerant discharge pressure. On
the other hand, in case where the heater core 21 is disposed 
upstream of the sub-condenser 4, the air, which has been turned
into the cold air by the evaporator 7, is contacted through
the heater core 21 with the sub-condenser 4 and, therefore,
the temperature load of the sub-condenser 4 is not decreased
so much, which makes it possible to raise the refrigerant discharge
pressure further quickly. Also, in this case, since the heat
of the heater core 21 can also be transmitted to the sub-condenser
4 through the air flowing in the within-vehicle-compartment
air passage P1, the transmission efficiency of the heat to be
transmitted from the heater core 21 to the sub-condenser 4 can
enhanced, which makes it possible to fulfill the quick heating
performance more excellently.</p>
    <p num="0072">Also, to enhance the quick heating performance further,
preferably, the sub-condenser 4 serving as a heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger and the heater core
21 serving as a heat generator may be formed as an integral
body. In case where the sub-condenser 4 and heater core 21 are
formed as an integral body, since the heat from the heater core
21 is transmitted directly to the sub-condenser 4, the transmission
efficiency of the heat to be transmitted from the heater core
21 to the sub-condenser 4 can enhanced, which makes it possible
to fulfill the quick heating performance quite excellently.</p>
    <p num="0073">Also, In case where the sub-condenser 4 and heater core
21 are formed as an integral body, there can be provided a great
advantage in reducing the size of the whole vehicle air conditioner 
as well as the manufacturing cost thereof. Here, as a method
of forming the sub-condenser 4 and heater core 21 as an integral
body, for example, the fins of the sub-condenser 4 may be formed
integral with the fins of the heater core 21.</p>
    <p num="0074">On the upstream side of the within-vehicle-compartment
air passage P1, there is disposed a blower fan 31. In the vehicle
air conditioner 1, in case where the blower fan 31 is driven
under the control of the above-mentioned control unit, the outside
air is introduced into the within-vehicle-compartment air passage
P1 from an outside air introduction port, or the inside air
is introduced into the within-vehicle-compartment air passage
P1 from an inside air introduction port, the outside air or
inside air is allowed to flow through the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1. By the way, in the
vicinity of the outside air introduction port or inside air
introduction port, there is disposed an intake door 32 and,
in case where the intake door 32 is driven under the control
of the control unit, the out side air or inside air can be selectively
introduced into the within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1.</p>
    <p num="0075">The air (outside air or inside air) introduced into the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1 from the outside or
inside air introduction port, firstly, passes through the
evaporator 7 disposed on the upstream side of the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1. At the then time,
as described before, the heat of the air passing through the 
evaporator 7 is absorbed by the refrigerant existing in the
evaporator 7, that is, the air is dehumidified and is thereby
turned into the cold air, so that the cold air flows to the
downstream side of the within-vehicle-compartment air passage
P1.</p>
    <p num="0076">In the case of the within-vehicle-compartment air passage
P1, the downstream side of the evaporator 7 branches into a
warm air passage, in which the heater core 21 and sub-condenser
4 are disposed, and a detour passage bypassing the heater core
21 and sub-condenser 4. The air, which is introduced into the
warm air passage, as described above, when passing through the
heater core 21, absorbs the heat from the heater core 21 and,
when passing through the sub-condenser 4, absorbs the heat radiated
from the refrigerant existing within the sub-condenser 4 to
thereby turn into the warm air, so that the warm air flows to
the downstream side. On the other hand, the air, which is
introduced into the detour passage, flows to the downstream
side as it remains the cold air the heat of which has been absorbed
into the evaporator 7.</p>
    <p num="0077">Here, in a branch point, at which the warm air passage
and detour passage are branched, there is disposed an air mix
door 33 which is used to adjust the ratio of the flow rate of
the air to be introduced into the warm air passage and the flow
rate of the air to be introduced into the detour passage. And,
in the vehicle air conditioner 1, in case where the air mix 
door 33 is driven under the control of the control unit to adjust
the ratio of the flow rate of the air to be introduced into
the warm air passage and the flow rate of the air to be introduced
into the detour passage, finally, the temperatures of the air
to be blown out from a defroster blow-out port, a vent blow-out
port and a foot blow-out port can be adjusted.</p>
    <p num="0078">On the further downstream side of the warm air passage
and detour passage in the within-vehicle-compartment air passage
P1, there is disposed an air mix chamber 34 which is used to
mix the warm air from the warm air passage with the cold air
from the detour passage. And, in the air mix chamber 34, there
are formed a defroster blow-out port used to blow out the air,
which is a mixture of the warm air and cold air and thus the
temperature of which has been adjusted due to the mixing thereof,
to a front windshield, a vent blow-out port for blowing out
the air toward the upper body of an occupant, and a foot blow-out
port for blowing out the air toward the foot of the occupant.
In the vicinity of the blow-out port, vent blow-out port and
foot blow-out port, there are disposed a defrost door 35, a
vent door 36, and a foot door 37, respectively. In case where
the defrost door 35, vent door 36 and foot door 37 are respectively
driven under the control of the control unit, the flow rate
of the temperature-controlled air to be blown out from the blow-out
port, vent blow-out port and foot blow-out port can be adjusted.</p>
    <p num="0079">In the above-structured vehicle air conditioner 1, since 
the air, which has passed through the evaporator 7 and has been
thereby dehumidified, is heated by the heater core 21 and
sub-condenser 4 to thereby produce the warm air, in the heating
operation time, dehumidification can also be carried out, thereby
being able to realize a very useful heating operation.</p>
    <p num="0080">Also, in the present vehicle air conditioner 1, not only
the heater core 21 serving as a heat generator, but also the
sub-condenser 4 serving as a heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger are disposed in the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1 and thus, using not
only the heater core 21 but also the sub-condenser 4, the warm
air can be produced. Thanks to this, even in case where the
temperature of the engine cooling water is not sufficiently
high, there can be obtained an excellent heating performance.</p>
    <p num="0081">Especially, in the present vehicle air conditioner 1, since
the sub-condenser 4 serving as a heat radiating
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger is disposed at a
position which permits reception of the heat from the heater
core 21 serving as a heat generator, the heat from the heater
core 21 can be effectively transmitted to the sub-condenser.
Due to this, the temperature load of the sub-condenser 4 can
be increased and thus the refrigerant discharge pressure (Pd)
can be raised quickly, thereby being able to raise the temperature
within the vehicle compartment; that is, the present vehicle
air conditioner 1 is able to fulfill a very excellent quick 
heating performance.</p>
    <p num="0082">Describing in more detail, in the start time of the present
vehicle air conditioner 1, the temperature of the sub-condenser
4 is very low, that is, the temperature load of the sub-condenser
4 is low and thus the refrigerant discharge pressure is low.
In case where the refrigerant discharge pressure is low in this
manner, it is not possible to function the sub-condenser 4
instantaneously as a heating source for generating the warm
air to thereby produce the warm air quickly. Therefore, it is
desired that heat from a heating source such as the heater core
21 is transmitted to the sub-condenser 4 to thereby increase
the temperature load of the sub-condenser 4. However, in case
where the sub-condenser 4 is disposed at a position distant
from the heater core 21, the heat of the heater core 21 cannot
be transmitted to the sub-condenser 4 effectively. Especially,
during the time until the engine cooling water temperature rises
up to a specified value, in case where the air is allowed to
flow into the within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1, the
air is rather cooled against expectation and makes an occupant
feel uncomfortable; and, therefore, the air is prevented from
flowing into the within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1.
For this reason, the heat of the heater core 21 cannot be transmitted
to the sub-condenser 4 effectively. Due to this, the temperature
load of the sub-condenser 4 remains low. In this case, a state,
in which the refrigerant discharge pressure is difficult to 
rise, continues for a given period of time, which makes is difficult
to raise the temperature within the vehicle compartment quickly.</p>
    <p num="0083">On the other hand, in the vehicle air conditioner 1 according
to the invention, since the sub-condenser 4 is disposed at a
position permitting reception of the heat from the heater core
21, even in case where the air does not flow in the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1, the heat from the
heater core 21 can be effectively transmitted to the sub-condenser
4. Therefore, in the vehicle air conditioner 1 according to
the invention, just after the start thereof, the temperature
load of the sub-condenser 4 can be effectively increased and
thus the refrigerant discharge pressure can be raised quickly,
which enables the vehicle air conditioner 1 according to the
invention to fulfill a very excellent quick heating performance.</p>
    <p num="0084">Also, in the vehicle air conditioner 1 according to the
invention, just after the start thereof, the temperature load
of the sub-condenser 4 can be effectively increased and thus
the refrigerant discharge pressure can be raised quickly, so
that the enclosure amount of the refrigerant in the refrigeration
cycle can be reduced. Therefore, it is not necessary to use
a large-sized liquid tank 5, which provides a very great advantage
in reducing the size and weight of the whole vehicle air conditioner
1. Also, because the refrigerant discharge pressure canbe raised
quickly, even in case where a variable-capacity compressor is
used as the compressor 2, the amount of the refrigerant stored 
in a crank room can be reduced to thereby be able to enhance
the response property of the variable-capacity compressor.</p>
    <p num="0085">Also, in the vehicle air conditioner 1 shown in Fig. 1,
as described before, the sub-condenser 4 and main condenser
3 are connected in parallel and thus the sub-condenser 4 and
main condenser 3 can be used selectively. Therefore, in case
where, in the cooling operation time, the refrigerant jetted
out from the compressor 2 is supplied only to the main condenser
3 and, in the heating operation time, the refrigerant jetted
out from the compressor 2 is supplied only to the sub-condenser
4, not only the above-mentioned heating performance can be enhanced
but also the cooling efficiency in the cooling operation time
can be enhanced.</p>
    <p num="0086">That is, in a structure in which, in the cooling operation
time, the refrigerant jetted out from the compressor 2 is supplied
only to the sub-condenser 4, there is a possibility that the
refrigerant within the sub-condenser 4 absorbs the heat from
the heater core 21 and is thereby heated, which lowers the cooling
efficiency. Especially, in the vehicle air conditioner 1
according to the invention, as described above, since the
sub-condenser 4 is disposed at a position permitting reception
of the heat from the heater core 21, in case where the refrigerant,
which is over-cooled because it has passed through the main
condenser 3 in the cooling operation time, is supplied to the
sub-condenser 4, it is difficult to maintain the refrigerant 
in the over-cooled condition, which raises a high possibility
that the cooling efficiency can be lowered.</p>
    <p num="0087">Also, in the case of a structure in which the refrigerant
can be supplied to the sub-condenser 4 in the cooling operation
time, due to the heat from the heater core 21, there is a fear
that the cycle balance in the refrigeration cycle can be
deteriorated in the cooling operation time.</p>
    <p num="0088">On the other hand, in case where the sub-condenser 4 and
main condenser 3 are connected in parallel, in the cooling
operation time, the refrigerant is supplied only to the main
condenser 3, and, in the heating operation time, the refrigerant
is supplied only to the sub-condenser 4, the above-mentioned
problems can be solved: that is, not only the heating performance
can be enhanced but also the cooling efficiency in the cooling
operation time can be enhanced.</p>
    <p num="0089">By the way, in the above-structured vehicle air conditioner
1, assuming that the outside air of low temperature is taken
into the within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1 continuously,
the evaporator 7 can be overcooled by the outside air to thereby
suddenly lower the heat conversion efficiency of the evaporator
7, which makes it difficult to keep the refrigerant pressure
at a proper level, resulting in the lowered in the cooling and
heating efficiency. To prevent such inconvenience, in the above
vehicle air conditioner 1, the temperature of the evaporator
7 is controlled in the following manner: that is, the degree 
of opening of the intake door 32 is finely controlled by the
control unit to thereby adjust the switch-over of the introduction
of the inside air and outside air with high accuracy.</p>
    <p num="0090">However, when much importance is not attached to the
dehumidifying function in the heating operation time, it is
also effective to cope with the above-mentioned problems that
the refrigerant, the heat of which has radiated due to its passage
through the sub-condenser 4 in the heating operation time, is
introduced into the compressor 2 while bypassing the evaporator
7. That is, instead of the second refrigerant line L2 which
is selected in the heating operation time in the vehicle air
condition 1 shown in Fig. 1, or in addition to the second refrigerant
line L2, as shown in Fig. 2 or Fig. 3, there may be disposed
a third refrigerant line L3 which bypasses the evaporator 7
and, in the heating operation time, the third refrigerant line
L3 may be selected. In this case, while eliminating the
above-mentioned high-accuracy control of the intake door 32
by the control unit, a similar quick heating performance to
the vehicle air condition 1 shown in Fig. 1 can be realized.</p>
    <p num="0091">Specifically, in the structure shown in Fig. 2, a passage
for the refrigerant jetted out from the compressor 2 branches
through the three-way connector 12 into a first refrigerant
line L1 in which the refrigerant is guided through the main
condenser 3 to the evaporator 7, and a third refrigerant line
L3 in which the refrigerant passes through the main condenser 
3 but bypasses the evaporator 7. And, in the rear stage of the
evaporator 7, these first and third refrigerant lines L1 and
L3 join together through the three-way connector 13.</p>
    <p num="0092">In the first refrigerant line L1, there is disposed an
electromagnetic valve 14 in the front stage of the main condenser
3 and, in the rear stage of the evaporator 7, there is disposed
a check valve 15. On the other hand, in the third refrigerant
line L3, there is disposed an electromagnetic valve 16 in the
front stage of the main condenser 3 and, in the rear stage of
the sub-condenser 4, there is disposed a pressure reducing valve
40 serving as an expander which is not connected to the evaporator
7. And, in case where the open. and closed states of the
electromagnetic valve 14 disposed in the first refrigerant line
L1 as well as the open and closed states of the electromagnetic
valve 40 disposed in the third refrigerant line L3 are switched
by the control unit, the first refrigerant line L1 or third
refrigerant line L3 can be selected.</p>
    <p num="0093">That is, in the case of the cooling operation time, the
control unit sets the electromagnetic valve 14 disposed in the
first refrigerant line L1 in the "open" state, and sets the
electromagnetic valve 40 disposed in the third refrigerant line
L3 in the "closed" state. As a result of this, the first refrigerant
line L1 is selected; and, the refrigerant jetted out from the
compressor 2 is supplied sequentially to the main condenser
3, liquid tank 5, expansion valve 6 and evaporator 7 in this 
order, and is finally sucked into the compressor 2 again. On
the other hand, in the case of the heating operation time, the
control unit sets the electromagnetic valve 14 disposed in the
first refrigerant line L1 in the "closed" state, and sets the
electromagnetic valve 40 disposed in the third refrigerant line
L3 in the "open" state. As a result of this, the third refrigerant
line L3 is selected; and, the refrigerant jetted out from the
compressor 2 is supplied to the sub-condenser 3 and pressure
reducing valve 40, bypasses the evaporator 7 and is finally
sucked into the compressor 2 again.</p>
    <p num="0094">Also, in the structure shown in Fig. 3, a passage for the
refrigerant jetted out from the compressor 2 branches through
the three-way connector 12 into a first refrigerant line L1
in which the refrigerant passes through main condenser 3, and
a second refrigerant line L2 in which the refrigerant passes
through the sub-condenser 4. And, in the front stage of the
liquid tank 5, these first and second refrigerant lines L1 and
L2 join together through the three-way connector 13. Also, the
refrigerant flow passage, which joined in the front stage of
the liquid tank 5, further branches, through the three-way
connector 41 disposed in the rear stage of the liquid tank 5,
into a refrigerant line (the first refrigerant line L1 or second
refrigerant line L2) in which the refrigerant passes through
the evaporator 7, and a third refrigerant line L3 in which the
refrigerant bypasses the evaporator 7. And, the first 
refrigerant line L1 or second refrigerant line L2 and the third
refrigerant line L3 joins together through a three-way connector
42 in the front stage of the compressor 2.</p>
    <p num="0095">In the first refrigerant line L1, there is disposed an
electromagnetic valve 14 in the front stage of the main condenser
3; and, in the rear stage of the main condenser 3, there is
disposed a check valve 15. Similarly, in the second refrigerant
line L2 as well, there is disposed an electromagnetic valve
16 in the front stage of the sub-condenser 4; and, in the rear
stage of the sub-condenser 4, there is disposed a check valve
17. Further, in the front stage of the expansion valve 6 of
the first refrigerant line L1 or second refrigerant line L2,
there is disposed an electromagnetic valve 43. On the other
hand, in the case of the third refrigerant line L3, there is
disposed a pressure reducing valve 40 serving as an expander
which is not connected to the evaporator 7; and, in the front
stage of the pressure reducing valve 40, there is disposed an
electromagnetic valve 44. And, in case where the open and closed
states of the respective electromagnetic valves 14, 16, 43,
44 are switched by the control unit, the first refrigerant line
L1, or second refrigerant line L2, or third refrigerant line
L3 can be selected.</p>
    <p num="0096">That is, in the cooling operation time, the control unit
sets the electromagnetic valves 14 and 43 respectively in the
"open" states, and sets the electromagnetic valves 16 and 44 
respectively in the "closed" states. In response to this, the
first refrigerant line L1 is selected, and the refrigerant jetted
out from the compressor 2 is supplied to the main condenser
3, liquid tank 5, expansion valve 6 and evaporator 7 in this
order and is finally sucked into the compressor 2 again. On
the other hand, in the heating operation time, the control unit
sets the electromagnetic valves 14 and 43 respectively in the
"closed" states, and sets the electromagnetic valves 16 and
44 respectively in the "open" states. In response to this, the
third refrigerant line L3 is selected, and the refrigerant jetted
out from the compressor 2 is supplied to the sub-condenser 4,
liquid tank 5 and pressure reducing valve 40 in this order,
bypasses the evaporator 7 and is then returned into the compressor
2 again. Also, in case where the control unit is structured
such that, in the heating operation time, it sets the
electromagnetic valves 14 and 44 respectively in the "closed"
states and sets the electromagnetic valves 16 and 43 respectively
in the "open" states, the second refrigerant line L2 is selected,
and the refrigerant jetted out from the compressor 2 is supplied
to the sub-condenser 4, liquid tank 5, expansion valve 6 and
evaporator 7 in this order, and is then sucked into the compressor
2 again.</p>
    <p num="0097">By the way, in the structures shown in Figs. 2 and 3, in
case where, in the heating operation time, the third refrigerant
line L3 is selected, the heat of the refrigerant is radiated 
by the sub-condenser 4 and the refrigerant is then expanded
by the pressure reducing valve 40, so that the temperature of
the refrigerant becomes low; that is, the refrigerant of low
temperature is sucked into the compressor 2 without the heat
of the refrigerant being absorbed by the evaporator 7. Therefore,
in the heating operation time, the temperature of the refrigerant
jetted out from the compressor 2 is apt to be low, which raises
a fear that the low-temperature refrigerent can provide an obstacle
in the way of sufficient fulfillment of the quick heating
performance.</p>
    <p num="0098">In this case, as shown in Fig. 4, preferably, in the third
refrigerant line L3, there may be disposed an inter-refrigerant
heat exchanger 45 which is used to exchange heat between the
refrigerant expanded by the pressure reducing valve 40 and the
refrigerant flowing in the front stage of the sub-condenser
4. Also, as shown in Fig. 5, in the third refrigerant line L3,
there may be disposed an inter-refrigerant heat exchanger 45
which is used to exchange heat between the refrigerant expanded
by the pressure reducing valve 40 and the refrigerant flowing
in the front stage of the pressure reducing valve 40.</p>
    <p num="0099">As the inter-refrigerant heat exchanger 45, for example,
as shown in Figs. 6 and 7, there can be used an integral type
of pipe member structured such that a pipe member in the rear
stage of the pressure reducing valve 40 and a pipe member in
the front stage of the sub-condenser 4 or a pipe member in the 
front stage of the pressure reducing valve 40 are formed as
an integral body; or, as shown in Fig. 8, a composite type of
pipe member structured such that a pipe member in the rear stage
of the pressure reducing valve 40 and a pipe member in the front
stage of the sub-condenser 4 or a pipe member in the front stage
of the pressure reducing valve 40 are closely contacted with
each other. In case where such integral type of pipe member
or such composite type of pipe member is used as the
inter-refrigerant heat exchanger 45, when the refrigerant moving
toward the sub-condenser 4 or the refrigerant moving toward
the pressure reducing valve 40 flows into one pipe and the
refrigerant expanded by the pressure reducing valve 40 flows
into the other pipe, heat can be exchanged effectively between
these refrigerants, so that the refrigerant expanded by the
pressure reducing valve 40 can be heated.</p>
    <p num="0100">As described above, in case where the inter-refrigerant
heat exchanger 45 is disposed in the third refrigerant line
L3 and the refrigerant expanded by the pressure reducing valve
40 is heated due to the heat exchange operation to be executed
by the inter-refrigerant heat exchanger 45, even when the
refrigerant is made to bypass the evaporator 7, the temperature
of the refrigerant jetted out from the compressor 2 can be raised
to thereby be able to obtain an excellent quick heating
performance.</p>
    <p num="0101">By the way, in the vehicle air conditioners 1 respectively 
shown in Figs. 1 to 3, the sub-condenser 4 and main condenser
3 are connected in parallel, while the main condenser 3 is used
only in the cooling operation time but is not used in the heating
operation time. Therefore, in order to enhance the use efficiency
of the main condenser 3, as shown in Fig. 9, preferably, there
may be disposed a refrigerant collecting line L4 which is used
to connect the refrigerant sucking side of the compressor 2
with the main condenser 3 and, when the vehicle air conditioner
1 is switched from the cooling operation to the heating operation,
using the refrigerant collecting line L4, the refrigerant staying
in the main condenser 3 may be collected and sucked into the
compressor 2.</p>
    <p num="0102">In the structure employing the above refrigerant collecting
line L4, in case where, when switching the vehicle air conditioner
1 from the cooling operation to the heating operation, under
the control of the control unit, an electromagnetic valve 46
disposed in the intermediate portion of a pipe member forming
the refrigerant collecting line L4 is set in the "open" state,
the refrigerant staying in the main condenser 3 can be sucked
through three-way connectors 47, 48 into the compressor 2, thereby
being able to enhance the refrigerant use efficiency.</p>
    <p num="0103">However, in the vehicle air conditioner 1 according to
the invention, as described hereinabove, in the heating operation
time, the temperature load of the sub-condenser 4 can be increased
and thus the refrigerant discharge pressure can be increased. 
Therefore, when a sufficient quantity of refrigerant can be
secured even in case where the refrigerant staying in the main
condenser 3 is not collected, the above-mentioned refrigerant
collecting line L4 may not be disposed. In case where the
refrigerant collecting line L4 is not disposed, the size and
weight of the whole of the vehicle air conditioner 1 can be
reduced accordingly.</p>
    <p num="0104">Also, while description has been given heretofore of an
embodiment in which the sub-condenser 4 and main condenser 3
are connected in parallel and thus the sub-condenser 4 and main
condenser 3 can be used selectively, in case where special
importance is attached to the heating performance but much
importance is not attached to the cooling performance, as shown
in Fig. 10, the three-way connector 13 may be disposed in the
front stage of the sub-condenser 4 to thereby connect the
sub-condenser 4 and main condenser 3 in series with each other,
and thus, in the cooling operation time, the refrigerant, which
has passed through the main condenser 3, may be supplied to
the sub-condenser 4.</p>
    <p num="0105">By the way, even in case where the sub-condenser 4 and
main condenser 3 are connected in series with each other, there
may be disposed such a third refrigerant line L3 as shown in
Fig. 2 or Fig. 3 in which the refrigerant bypasses the evaporator
7 and, in the heating operation time, by selecting this third
refrigerant line L3, the refrigerant, the heat of which has 
been radiated by the sub-condenser 4, may bypass the evaporator
7 and may be then sucked into the compressor 7.</p>
    <p num="0106">While description has been given hereinbefore of a specific
embodiment of a vehicle air conditioner according to the invention,
the invention is not limited to the specific embodiment but
the invention can also be widely applied to an air conditioner
for a vehicle in which, in the within-vehicle-compartment air
passage P1, there are disposed at least a
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger serving as a heat
radiator in the heating operation and a heat generator.</p>
    <p num="0107">Specifically, the invention can also be effectively applied
to, for example, a vehicle air conditioner of a so-called hot
gas cycle disclosed in JP-A-5-223357 and a vehicle air conditioner
of a so-called heat pump cycle disclosed in JP-A-2-290475.</p>
    <p num="0108">Now, Fig. 11 shows an embodiment of the structure of a
vehicle air conditioner of a hot gas cycle to which the invention
is applied. In a vehicle air conditioner 50 shown in Fig. 11,
a passage for a refrigerant jetted out from a compressor 51
branches through a three-way connector 52 into a refrigerant
line in which the refrigerant passes through a condenser 53
serving as an outside-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger, and
a refrigerant line in which the refrigerant bypasses the condenser
53. And, these two refrigerant lines join together through a
three-way connector 55 in the front stage of an evaporator 54
serving as a within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger disposed 
in a within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1.</p>
    <p num="0109">In the within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1, in
addition to the evaporator 54, there is disposed a heater core
57 serving as a heat generator which exchanges heat using the
cooling water of an engine 56. And, the evaporator 54 is disposed
at a position which permits reception of the heat from the heater
core 57.</p>
    <p num="0110">In the refrigerant line in which the refrigerant passes
through the condenser 53, there is disposed an electromagnetic
valve 58 in the front stage of the condenser 53 and there are
disposed a liquid tank 59, a check valve 60 and first an expander
61 respectively in the rear stage of the condenser 53. On the
other hand, in the refrigerant line in which the refrigerant
bypasses the condenser 53, there are disposed an electromagnetic
valve 62 and an expander 63. Also, in the passage of the refrigerant
passing through the evaporator 54 and flowing toward the compressor
51, there is disposed an accumulator 64.</p>
    <p num="0111">In the vehicle air conditioner 50 of a hot gas cycle according
to the invention, in case where the open and closed states of
the electromagnetic valves 58 and 62 are switched by a control
unit (not shown) which controls the operation of the whole of
the vehicle air conditioner 50, the refrigerant line passing
through the condenser 53 or the refrigerant line bypassing the
condenser 53 can be selected.</p>
    <p num="0112">That is, in the cooling operation time, the control unit 
sets the electromagnetic valve 58 in the "open" state and sets
the electromagnetic valve 62 in the "closed" state. In response
to this, the refrigerant line passing through the condenser
53 is selected and the refrigerant jetted out from the compressor
51 is supplied to the condenser 53, liquid tank 59, first an
expander 61, evaporator 54 and accumulator 64 in this order,
and is then sucked into the compressor 51 again. In this case,
the evaporator 54 functions as a heat absorber, thereby allowing
the cold air to flow into the within-vehicle-compartment air
passage P1.</p>
    <p num="0113">On the other hand, in the heating operation time, the control
unit sets the electromagnetic valve 58 in the "closed" state
and sets the electromagnetic valve 62 in the "open" state. In
response to this, the refrigerant line bypassing the condenser
53 is selected and the refrigerant jetted out from the compressor
51 is supplied to the second expander 63, evaporator 54 and
accumulator 64 in this order, and is then sucked into the compressor
51 again. In this case, the evaporator 54 functions as a heat
radiator, thereby allowing the warm air to flow into the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1.</p>
    <p num="0114">Here, in the vehicle air conditioner 50 according to the
invention, since the evaporator 54 serving as a
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger is disposed at a
position which permits reception of the heat from the heater
core 57 serving as a heat generator, even in a state where the 
air does not flow through the within-vehicle-compartment air
passage P1, the heat from the heater core 57 can be effectively
transmitted to the evaporator 54. Therefore, in the vehicle
air conditioner 50, just after it is started, the temperature
load of the evaporator 54 can be increased effectively and thus
the refrigerant discharge pressure can be raised rapidly, so
that, similarly to the previously described vehicle air
conditioner 1, a very excellent quick heating performance can
be fulfilled.</p>
    <p num="0115">Especially, as shown in Fig. 11, in case where the heater
core 57 serving as a heat generator is disposed upstream of
the evaporator 54 serving as a within-vehicle-compartment heat
exchanger in the within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1,
even when the cold outside air is introduced into the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1, since the cold outside
air is contacted through the heater core 57 with the evaporator
54, the temperature load of the evaporator 54 is not lowered
so much, which makes it possible to raise the refrigerant discharge
pressure further quickly. Also, in this case, because the heat
of the heater core 57 can also be transmitted to the evaporator
54 through the air flowing through the within-vehicle-compartment
air passage P1, the transmission efficiency of the heat to be
transmitted from the heater core 57 to the evaporator 54 can
be enhanced, which makes it possible to fulfill the quick heating
performance still further. </p>
    <p num="0116">Also, in case where the evaporator 54 serving as a
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger and the heater core
57 serving as a heat generator are formed as an integral body,
the heat from the heater core 57 is transmitted directly to
the evaporator 54. Thanks to this, the transmission efficiency
of the heat to be transmitted from the heater core 57 to the
evaporator 54 can be enhanced still further, thereby being able
to fulfill a very excellent quick heating performance.</p>
    <p num="0117">Further, in the present vehicle air conditioner 50, just
after it is started, the temperature load of the evaporator
54 can be increased effectively and thus the refrigerant discharge
pressure can be raised rapidly, thereby being able to reduce
the quantity of the refrigerant to be enclosed within the
refrigeration cycle. Thanks to this, similarly to the previously
described vehicle air conditioner 1, there can be provided a
great advantage in reducing the size and weight of the whole
of the vehicle air conditioner.</p>
    <p num="0118">Next, Fig. 12 shows an embodiment of the structure of a
vehicle air conditioner of a heat pump cycle according to the
invention. In a vehicle air conditioner 70 shown in Fig. 12,
a passage for a refrigerant jetted out from a compressor 71
can be reversed by a four-way valve 72; and, therefore, the
supply order of the refrigerant to be supplied to a condenser
73 serving as an outside-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger
and to an evaporator 74 disposed in a within-vehicle-compartment 
air passage P1 and serving as a within-vehicle-compartment heat
exchanger can be switched.</p>
    <p num="0119">Also, in the vehicle air conditioner 70, in the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1, in addition to the
evaporator 70, there is disposed a heater core 76 which serves
as a heat generator for exchanging heat using the cooling water
of an engine 75. And, the evaporator 74 is disposed at a position
which permits reception of the heat from the heater core 76.</p>
    <p num="0120">In a refrigerant passage between the condenser 73 and
evaporator 74, there is disposed first an expander 77 in the
vicinity of the condenser 73, while there is disposed a second
expander 78 in the vicinity of the evaporator 74. And, in this
refrigerant passage, there is disposed a detour line in which
the refrigerant bypasses the first an expander 77 through three-way
connectors 79, 80 respectively provided before and behind the
first an expander 77; and, in the detour line, there is disposed
an electromagnetic valve 81. Similarly, there is disposed
another detour line in which the refrigerant bypasses the second
expander 78 through three-way connectors 82, 83 respectively
provided before and behind the second expander 78; and, in this
detour line, there is disposed an electromagnetic valve 84.
Also, on the refrigerant suction side of the compressor 71,
there is disposed an accumulator 85.</p>
    <p num="0121">In the vehicle air conditioner 70 of a heat pump cycle,
in case where the directions of the refrigerant passing through 
the four-way connector 72 as well as the open and closed states
of the electromagnetic valves 81, 84 are switched by a control
unit (not shown) which controls the operation of the whole of
the vehicle air conditioner 70, the passage (the forward-direction
passage or the reversed-direction passage) of the refrigerant
jetted out from the compressor 71 as well as the first an expander
77 or a second expander 78 can be selected.</p>
    <p num="0122">That is, in the cooling operation time, the control unit
sets the direction of the refrigerant passing through the four-way
connector 72 in a direction shown by a solid line in Fig. 12,
sets the electromagnetic valve 81 in the "open" state, and sets
the electromagnetic valve 84 in the "closed" state. In response
to this, the refrigerant jetted out from the compressor 71 is
supplied to the condenser 73, a second expander 78, evaporator
74 and accumulator 85 in this order and is then sucked into
the compressor 71 again. In this case, the condenser 73 functions
as a heat radiator and the evaporator 74 functions as a heat
absorber, so that the cold air is allowed to flow through the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1.</p>
    <p num="0123">On the other hand, in the heating operation time, the control
unit sets the direction of the refrigerant passing through the
four-way connector 72 in a direction shown by a broken line
in Fig. 12, sets the electromagnetic valve 81 in the "closed"
state, and sets the electromagnetic valve 84 in the "open" state.
In response to this, the refrigerant jetted out from the compressor 
71 is supplied to the evaporator 74, first an expander 77, condenser
73 and accumulator 85 in this order and is then sucked into
the compressor 71 again. In this case, the evaporator 74 functions
as a heat radiator and the condenser 73 functions as a heat
absorber, so that the warm air is allowed to flow through the
within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1.</p>
    <p num="0124">Here, in the vehicle air conditioner 70 of a heat pump
cycle according to the invention, since the evaporator 74 serving
as an within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger is disposed
at a position which permits reception of the heat from the heater
core 76 serving as a heat generator, even in case where the
air does not flow through the within-vehicle-compartment air
passage P1, the heat from the heater core 76 can be transmitted
to the evaporator 74 effectively. Therefore, in the present
vehicle air conditioner 70, just after it is started, the
temperature load of the evaporator 74 can be increased effectively
and thus the refrigerant discharge pressure can be raised rapidly,
so that, similarly to the previously described vehicle air
conditioners 1 and 50, the present vehicle air conditioner 70
is able to fulfill a very excellent quick heating performance.</p>
    <p num="0125">Especially, as shown in Fig. 12, in case where the heater
core 76 serving as a heat generator is disposed upstream of
the evaporator 74 which is a within-vehicle-compartment heat
exchanger in the within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1,
even when the cold outside air is introduced into the 
within-vehicle-compartment air passage P1, since the present
cold outside air is contacted through the heater core 76 with
the evaporator 74, the temperature load of the evaporator 74
is not lowered so much, thereby being able to raise the refrigerant
discharge pressure rapidly. Also, in this case, since the heat
of the heater core 76 can also be transmitted to the evaporator
74 through the air flowing in the within-vehicle-compartment
air passage P1, the transmission efficiency of the heat to be
transmitted from the heater core 76 to the evaporator 74 can
be enhanced, which enables the present vehicle air conditioner
70 to fulfill a further excellent quick heating performance.</p>
    <p num="0126">Also, in case where the evaporator 74 serving as a
within-vehicle-compartment heat exchanger and heater core 76
serving as a heat generator are formed as an integral body,
since the heat from the heater core 76 can be transmitted directly
to the evaporator 74, the transmission efficiency of the heat
to be transmitted from the heater core 76 to the evaporator
74 can be enhanced still further, so that the present vehicle
air conditioner 70 is able to fulfill an extremely excellent
quick heating performance.</p>
    <p num="0127">Further, in the present vehicle air conditioner 70, since,
just after it is started, the temperature load of the evaporator
74 can be increased effectively and thus the refrigerant discharge
pressure can be raised rapidly, the quantity of the refrigerant
to be enclosed in the refrigeration cycle can be reduced. Thanks 
to this, similarly to the previously described vehicle air
conditioners 1 and 50, there can be provided a great advantage
in reducing the size and weight of the whole of the vehicle
air conditioner 70.</p>
    <p num="0128">Although a vehicle air conditioner according to the invention
has been described heretofore by way of several specific
embodiments thereof, the structures and specifications of the
respective parts forming the vehicle air conditioner can also
be changed properly according to the performance required and
the kinds of vehicles on which the present vehicle air conditioner
is carried. For example, in the above-described embodiments,
as the heat generator, there is disposed the heater core 21,
57, or 76 using the engine cooling water as a heat source; however,
instead of the heater core 21, 57, or 76, there may be disposed
other types of a heat generator such as a heat transfer heater.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>An air conditioner for a vehicle, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a compressor for compressing a refrigerant sucked therein
and jetting out the compressed refrigerant therefrom;</claim-text><claim-text>a first heat exchanger disposed outside a vehicle compartment,
the first heat exchanger for radiating heat of the refrigerant
to the outside air;</claim-text><claim-text>an air passage defined inside the vehicle compartment,
the air passage for passing an inside air and outside air
selectively introduced thereinto;</claim-text><claim-text>a second heat exchanger disposed in the air passage, the
second heat exchanger for radiating heat of the refrigerant
to the air inside the air passage;</claim-text><claim-text>an expander for expanding the refrigerant after heat of
the refrigerant is radiated by at least one of the first heat
exchanger and the second heat exchanger;</claim-text><claim-text>a third heat exchanger disposed upstream of the second
heat exchanger in the air passage, the third heat exchanger
for absorbing heat from the refrigerant inside the air passage
after expanded by the expander; and</claim-text><claim-text>a heat generator disposed in the air passage,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the second heat exchanger is disposed at a position
to receive heat from the heat generator (21).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The air conditioner as set forth in claim 1, further
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a first refrigerant line for supplying the refrigerant
jetted out from the compressor to the expander through the first
exchanger and allowing the refrigerant to be sucked into the
compressor through the third heat exchanger;</claim-text><claim-text>a second refrigerant line for supplying the refrigerant
jetted out from the compressor to the expander through the second
heat exchanger and allowing the refrigerant to be sucked into
the compressor through the third heat exchanger; and</claim-text><claim-text>a switch for selectively switching the first refrigerant
line and the second refrigerant line over to each other.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The air conditioner as set forth in claim 1, further
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a third refrigerant line for supplying the refrigerant
jetted out from the compressor to a second expander not connected
to the third heat exchanger through the second heat exchanger
and allowing the refrigerant to bypass the third heat exchanger
and to be sucked into the compressor; and</claim-text><claim-text>a switch for switching selection of the third refrigerant
line.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The air conditioner as set forth in claim 3, further
comprising a fourth heat exchanger disposed in the third
refrigerant line, the fourth heat exchanger for exchanging heat
between the refrigerant expanded by the second expander and
the refrigerant flowing through the front stage of the second
expander.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The air conditioner as set forth in claim 3, further
comprising a fifth heat exchanger disposed in the third refrigerant
line, the fifth heat exchanger for exchanging heat between the
refrigerant expanded by the second expander and the refrigerant
flowing through the front stage of the second heat exchanger.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The air conditioner as set forth in claim 1, wherein
the heat generator is disposed upstream of the second heat
exchanger in the air passage.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>The air conditioner as set forth in claim 1, wherein
the second heat exchanger and the heat generator are integrally
formed.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>An air conditioner for a vehicle, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a compressor for compressing a refrigerant sucked therein
and jetting out the compressed refrigerant to allow the refrigerant
to circulate;</claim-text><claim-text>an air passage defined inside a vehicle component, the
air passage for passing an inside air and outside air introduced
selectively;</claim-text><claim-text>a heat exchanger disposed in the air passage to receive
the refrigerant from the air passage;</claim-text><claim-text>a heat generator disposed in the air passage; and,</claim-text><claim-text>an expander for expanding the refrigerant,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the heat exchanger is disposed at a position to
receive heat from the heat generator.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>The air conditioner as set forth in claim 8, wherein
the heat generator is disposed upstream of the heat exchanger
in the air passage.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>The air conditioner as set forth in claim 8, wherein
the heat exchanger and the heat generator are integrally formed.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
