<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1262829-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1262829" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="27346800" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021204">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1262829-A1" status="new" fvid="23606855">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1262829</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20021204</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02011607-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02011607</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020528</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001159059-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001159059</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010528</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001159180-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001159180</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010528</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001159211-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001159211</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010528</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03F   7/029       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03F   7/029       20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G03F   7/029</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Lichtempfindliche Zusammensetzung</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Photosensitive composition</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition photosensible</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>FUJI PHOTO FILM CO LTD</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>FUJI PHOTO FILM CO., LTD.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>FUJI PHOTO FILM CO., LTD.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>210 Nakanuma Minami-Ashigara-shi</street>
              <city>Kanagawa 250-01</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KUNITA KAZUTO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SHIBUYA AKINORI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KUNITA, KAZUTO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SHIBUYA, AKINORI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>KUNITA, KAZUTO</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Fuji Photo Film Co., Ltd., 4000, Kawashiri</street>
              <city>Yoshida-cho, Haibara-gun, Shizuoka</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>SHIBUYA, AKINORI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Fuji Photo Film Co., Ltd., 4000, Kawashiri</street>
              <city>Yoshida-cho, Haibara-gun, Shizuoka</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>HOFFMANN - EITLE</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Patent- und Rechtsanwälte Arabellastrasse 4</street>
              <city>81925 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A photosensitive composition comprising (i) a
sensitizing dye represented by the following formula (I),
(II) or (III) defined in the specification, (ii) a
titanocene compound and (iii) a compound of undergoing a
reaction with at least one of a radical and an acid to
change at least one of its physical and chemical properties
and maintaining the changed physical or chemical property,
and a lithographic printing plate having a photosensitive
layer comprising the photosensitive composition.</p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <u style="single">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a photosensitive
composition containing a novel photo-initiation system,
particularly a photo-initiation system having high
sensitivity and excellent stability. Also, the present
invention relates to a photosensitive composition excellent
as a material for a lithographic printing plate precursor
capable of plate-making by the scanning exposure based on
digital signals. The photosensitive composition of the
present invention can also be used, for example, for image
formation such as optical image-forming, holography and
color hard copy, for production of an electronic material
such as photoresist or for uses as a photocurable resin
material in ink, paint, adhesive or the like.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0002">Conventionally, a PS plate having a construction such
that a lipophilic photosensitive resin layer is provided on
a hydrophilic support has been widely used as a
lithographic printing plate. As for the plate-making
method, a desired printing plate is usually obtained by
performing mask exposure through a lith film and then
dissolving and removing the non-image area.</p>
    <p num="0003">In recent years, digitization techniques of 
electronically processing, accumulating and outputting
image information using a computer have been widespread and
various new image output systems corresponding thereto have
been put into practical use. As a result, a computer-to-plate
(CTP) technique of directly producing a printing
plate without using a lith film but by scanning high
directivity light such as laser light based on the
digitized image information is demanded and it is now an
important technical subject to obtain a printing plate
precursor suitable for such a technique.</p>
    <p num="0004">As one of the means for obtaining such a lithographic
printing plate capable of scanning exposure, a construction
such that a photopolymerizable composition having excellent
photosensitive speed is used as an ink-acceptable
photosensitive resin layer (hereinafter referred to as a
"photosensitive layer") provided on a hydrophilic support
has been heretofore proposed and this is already available
on the market. The printing plate precursor having such a
construction is facilitated in the development processing
and favored with good plate-making and printing
performances of giving excellent resolution, inking
property, press life and scumming resistance.</p>
    <p num="0005">The photopolymerizable composition fundamentally
comprises an ethylenically unsaturated compound, a
photopolymerization initiation system and a binder resin, 
where the photo-initiation system absorbs light to produce
an active radical and the radical induces the addition
polymerization of ethylenically unsaturated compound, as a
result, the photosensitive layer is insolubilized, thereby
effecting the image formation. Most of conventional
proposals regarding the photopolymerizable composition
capable of being subjected to scanning exposure use a
photo-initiation system having excellent photosensitivity
and many compositions therefor are described, for example,
in Bruce M. Monroe et al., <u style="single">Chemical Review,</u> 93, 435 (1993)
and R.S. Davidson, <u style="single">Journal of Photochemistry and Biology A:
Chemistry</u>, 73, 81 (1993).</p>
    <p num="0006">For the purpose of elevating productivity in the
plate-making step, it is demanded to perform the writing at
a higher speed, however, conventional CTP systems using a
photopolymerizable composition comprising the above-described
initiation system and using a long wavelength
visible light source such as Ar laser (488 nm) or FD-YAG
laser (532 nm) as the light source cannot satisfy such a
requirement because the output of light source or the
sensitivity of photosensitive material is not sufficiently
high.</p>
    <p num="0007">On the other hand, a semiconductor laser using, for
example, an InGaN system material and capable of continuous
oscillation in the region from 350 to 450 nm has been 
recently put into practical use. The scanning exposure
system using such a short wavelength light source is
advantageous in that since the semiconductor laser can be
produced at a low cost in view of its structure, an
economical system can be constructed while having
sufficiently high output. Also, as compared with
conventional systems using an FD-YAG or Ar laser, a
photosensitive material having a photosensitive range in
the shorter wavelength region and enabling working under
brighter safe light can be used.</p>
    <p num="0008">In the imaging field, the technique for obtaining a
photo-initiation system having high sensitivity is still
keenly demanded as described, for example, in J.P. Faussier,
<u style="single">Photoinitiated Polymerization-Theory and Applications:
Rapra Review, Vol. 9, Report</u>, Rapra Technology (1998) and M.
Tsunooka et al., <u style="single">Prog. Polym. Sci.,</u><u style="single">21</u>, 1 (1996).</p>
    <p num="0009">However, a photo-initiation system having sensitivity
sufficiently high for the scanning exposure in the short
wavelength region of 350 to 450 nm is not known to date.</p>
    <p num="0010">Conventionally, an initiation system comprising a
combination of a specific dye and a titanocene compound is
known as a relatively high-sensitive photo-initiation
system. A combination of a dye having an oxazolidine
acidic nucleus with a triazine photo-initiator is disclosed
in JP-B-61-9621 (the term "JP-B" as used herein means an 
"examined Japanese patent publication") but this compound
is poor in the storage stability and has a problem in the
production. Also, a combination of a dye having an
oxazolone acidic nucleus with titanocene is disclosed in
JP-A-8-272096 (the term "JP-A" as used herein means an
"unexamined published Japanese patent application") and a
combination of a dye having a 5-membered heterocyclic
acidic nucleus with titanocene is disclosed in JP-A-10-101719.
These compounds have certainly high sensitivity
but the sensitivity is still not satisfied and when a laser
light source having a wavelength of 450 nm or less is used,
a sufficiently high sensitivity cannot be obtained in
practice. Thus, these compounds are not suitable for use
with a short wavelength light source.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0011">An object of the present invention is to provide a
photosensitive composition having excellent workability,
profitability and storage stability, which can be used as a
material of a lithographic printing plate precursor for
scanning exposure suitable for the CTP system or as a
material of a lithographic printing plate precursor highly
sensitive to the oscillation wavelength of an inexpensive
short wavelength semiconductor laser.</p>
    <p num="0012">Another object of the present invention is to provide
a lithographic printing plate precursor having a 
photosensitive layer formed of a photosensitive composition
using a novel photopolymerization initiation system highly
sensitive to a wide wavelength region from 350 to 450 nm.</p>
    <p num="0013">As a result of extensive investigations to achieve
these objects, the present inventors have found that when a
sensitizing dye having a structure represented by formula
(I), (II) or (III) shown below is used, a photosensitive
composition having sufficiently high sensitivity to the
oscillation wavelength of a short wavelength semiconductor
laser and moreover, being excellent in the storage
stability can be obtained. The present invention has been
accomplished based on such findings.</p>
    <p num="0014">The present invention includes the following items.
<sl><li>(1) A photosensitive composition comprising (i) a
sensitizing dye represented by the following formula (I),
(II) or (III), (ii) a titanocene compound and (iii) a
compound of undergoing a reaction with at least one of a
radical and an acid to change at least one of its physical
and chemical properties and maintaining the changed
physical or chemical property:
<img id="img-00060001" orientation="unknown" wi="116" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00060001.tif" inline="no" he="37"/> 
wherein R<sub>1</sub> to R<sub>8</sub> each independently represents a hydrogen
atom, a halogen atom, a substituted or. unsubstituted alkyl,
alkoxy, alkylthio, aryloxy, arylthio, alkenyl, aralkyl,
acyl, aryl, heteroaryl or alkylsulfonic acid group having
20 or less carbon atoms, and X<sub>1</sub> and X<sub>2</sub> each independently
represents an oxygen atom or a sulfur atom;
<img id="img-00070001" orientation="unknown" wi="107" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00070001.tif" inline="no" he="37"/>
wherein R<sub>1</sub> to R<sub>8</sub> each independently represents a hydrogen
atom, a halogen atom, a substituted or unsubstituted alkyl,
alkoxy, alkylthio, aryloxy, arylthio, alkenyl, aralkyl,
acyl, aryl, heteroaryl or alkylsulfonic acid group having
20 or less carbon atoms, X represents an oxygen atom or a
sulfur atom, and A represents a substituted or
unsubstituted aryl or heteroaryl group having 20 or less
carbon atoms;
<img id="img-00070002" orientation="unknown" wi="104" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00070002.tif" inline="no" he="46"/>
wherein Y represents an oxygen atom or a sulfur atom, Q<sub>1</sub> 
represents a hydrogen atom, a methyl group, an ethyl group
or a phenyl group which may have a substituent, Q<sub>2</sub> to Q<sub>11</sub>
each independently represents a hydrogen atom, a halogen
atom, a cyano group, a nitro group, a sulfonic acid group,
or an alkyl group having from 1 to 5 carbon atoms, which
may have a substituent.</li><li>(2) The photosensitive composition as described in
(1) above, wherein the compound of undergoing a reaction
with at least one of a radical and an acid to change at
least one of its physical and chemical properties and
maintaining the changed physical or chemical property and
is an addition-polymerizable compound having an
ethylenically unsaturated double bond.</li><li>(3) The photosensitive composition as described in
(1) above further comprising a binder polymer comprising an
aqueous alkali-soluble or swellablle liner organic polymer.</li><li>(4) The photosensitive composition as described in
(3) above, wherein the aqueous alkali-soluble or swellablle
liner organic polymer is a urethane resin having an alkali-soluble
group.</li><li>(5) The photosensitive composition as described in
(1) above further comprising an oxime ether compound as a
co-sensitizer.</li><li>(6) A photosensitive composition comprising (i) a
sensitizing dye represented by the following formula (I), 
(II) or (III), (ii) a titanocene compound and (iii) a
radical-polymerizable compound having an ethylenically
unsaturated double bond:
<img id="img-00090001" orientation="unknown" wi="111" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00090001.tif" inline="no" he="38"/>
wherein R<sub>1</sub> to R<sub>8</sub> each independently represents a hydrogen
atom, a halogen atom, a substituted or unsubstituted alkyl,
alkoxy, alkylthio, aryloxy, arylthio, alkenyl, aralkyl,
acyl, aryl, heteroaryl or alkylsulfonic acid group having
20 or less carbon atoms, and X<sub>1</sub> and X<sub>2</sub> each independently
represents an oxygen atom or a sulfur atom;
<img id="img-00090002" orientation="unknown" wi="107" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00090002.tif" inline="no" he="36"/>
wherein R<sub>1</sub> to R<sub>8</sub> each independently represents a hydrogen
atom, a halogen atom, a substituted or unsubstituted alkyl,
alkoxy, alkylthio, aryloxy, arylthio, alkenyl, aralkyl,
acyl, aryl, heteroaryl or alkylsulfonic acid group having
20 or less carbon atoms, X represents an oxygen atom or a
sulfur atom, and A represents a substituted or
unsubstituted aryl or heteroaryl group having 20 or less 
carbon atoms;
<img id="img-00100001" orientation="unknown" wi="113" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00100001.tif" inline="no" he="46"/>
wherein Y represents an oxygen atom or a sulfur atom, Q<sub>1</sub>
represents a hydrogen atom, a methyl group, an ethyl group
or a phenyl group which may have a substituent, Q<sub>2</sub> to Q<sub>11</sub>
each independently represents a hydrogen atom, a halogen
atom, a cyano group, a nitro group, a sulfonic acid group,
or an alkyl group having from 1 to 5 carbon atoms, which
may have a substituent.</li><li>(7) The photosensitive composition as described in
(6) above further comprising a binder polymer comprising an
aqueous alkali-soluble or swellablle liner organic polymer.</li><li>(8) A photosensitive lithographic printing plate
comprising a support and a photosensitive layer comprising
(i) a sensitizing dye represented by the following formula
(I), (II) or (III), (ii) a titanocene compound and (iii) a
compound of undergoing a reaction with at least one of a
radical and an acid to change at least one of its physical
and chemical properties and maintaining the changed
physical or chemical property: <img id="img-00110001" orientation="unknown" wi="119" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00110001.tif" inline="no" he="39"/>
wherein R<sub>1</sub> to R<sub>8</sub> each independently represents a hydrogen
atom, a halogen atom, a substituted or unsubstituted alkyl,
alkoxy, alkylthio, aryloxy, arylthio, alkenyl, aralkyl,
acyl, aryl, heteroaryl or alkylsulfonic acid group having
20 or less carbon atoms, and X<sub>1</sub> and X<sub>2</sub> each independently
represents an oxygen atom or a sulfur atom;
<img id="img-00110002" orientation="unknown" wi="109" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00110002.tif" inline="no" he="37"/>
wherein R<sub>1</sub> to R<sub>8</sub> each independently represents a hydrogen
atom, a halogen atom, a substituted or unsubstituted alkyl,
alkoxy, alkylthio, aryloxy, arylthio, alkenyl, aralkyl,
acyl, aryl, heteroaryl or alkylsulfonic acid group having
20 or less carbon atoms, X represents an oxygen atom or a
sulfur atom, and A represents a substituted or
unsubstituted aryl or heteroaryl group having 20 or less
carbon atoms; <img id="img-00120001" orientation="unknown" wi="111" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00120001.tif" inline="no" he="49"/>
wherein Y represents an oxygen atom or a sulfur atom, Q<sub>1</sub>
represents a hydrogen atom, a methyl group, an ethyl group
or a phenyl group which may have a substituent, Q<sub>2</sub> to Q<sub>11</sub>
each independently represents a hydrogen atom, a halogen
atom, a cyano group, a nitro group, a sulfonic acid group,
or an alkyl group having from 1 to 5 carbon atoms, which
may have a substituent.</li><li>(9) The photosensitive lithographic printing plate
as described in (8) above, wherein the compound of
undergoing a reaction with at least one of a radical and an
acid to change at least one of its physical and chemical
properties and maintaining the changed physical or chemical
property and is an addition-polymerizable compound having
an ethylenically unsaturated double bond.</li><li>(10) The photosensitive lithographic printing plate
as described in (8) above, wherein the photosensitive layer
further comprising a binder polymer comprising an aqueous
alkali-soluble or swellablle liner organic polymer.</li><li>(11) The photosensitive lithographic printing plate
as described in (10) above, wherein the aqueous alkali-soluble 
or swellablle liner organic polymer is a urethane
resin having an alkali-soluble group.</li><li>(12) The photosensitive lithographic printing plate
as described in (8) above further comprising a protective
layer containing polyvinyl alcohol.</li><li>(13) A photopolymerization method comprising
exposing the photosensitive composition described in (1)
above with a laser beam having a wavelength of 450 nm or
less.</li><li>(14) A method of preparing a lithographic printing
plate comprising exposing the photosensitive lithographic
printing plate as described in (8) above with a laser beam
having a wavelength of 450 nm or less and developing the
exposed photosensitive lithographic printing plate with an
aqueous alkali developing solution.</li><li>(15) The method of preparing a lithographic printing
plate as described in (14) above, wherein the aqueous
alkali developing solution has a pH of from 9.5 to 14.0.</li><li>(16) The method of preparing a lithographic printing
plate as described in (14) above, wherein the exposure of
the photosensitive lithographic printing plate is conducted
using a laser beam having an exposure wavelength in a range
of from 390 to 430 nm.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0015">The lithographic printing plate precursor using the
photosensitive composition of the present invention has 
sufficiently high sensitivity suitable for the scanning
exposure by a short wavelength semiconductor laser such as
InGaN and gives a lithographic printing plate excellent in
the press life and scumming resistance. The lithographic
printing plate precursor for scanning exposure of the
present invention is remarkably improved in the fogging
under a yellow lamp and therefore, the workability of
handling the plate can be greatly improved. Furthermore,
the photosensitive composition of the present invention has
excellent sensitivity and at the same time, has very
excellent storage stability.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0016">The present invention is described in detail below.</p>
    <p num="0017">The photosensitive composition of the present
invention comprises, as essential components, (A) a
photopolymerization initiation system and (B) a compound of
undergoing a reaction with at least one of a radical and an
acid to change at least one of its physical and chemical
properties and maintaining the changed physical or chemical
property and, if desired, further comprises (C) a binder
polymer. These components are specifically described below.</p>
    <heading>(A) Photopolymerization initiation system</heading>
    <p num="0018">The photopolymerization initiation system as an
essential component of the photosensitive composition of
the present invention contains (I) a sensitizing dye having 
a specific structure and (II) a titanocene compound. In
the initiation system of the present invention, the
sensitizing dye mainly absorbs light to accelerate the
generation of an initiating radical from the titanocene
compound present together (such a process is hereinafter
referred to as "dye sensitization"). One of the reasons
why the sensitizing dye of the present invention is
particularly excellent is in that its absorption wavelength
is present in the region from 350 to 450 nm. Most of
titanocene compounds described later each itself has weak
absorption in the wavelength region from ultraviolet to the
vicinity of 500 nm and has photosensitivity also in that
region. However, the sensitizing dye having a specific
structure of the present invention greatly elevates the
photosensitivity of titanocene. Therefore, for example, by
using a titanocene compound in a relatively small amount,
the photosensitivity in the short wavelength region can be
satisfactorily elevated and at the same time, the
photosensitivity by titanocene itself in the region of
500 nm can be made low, as a result, safelight aptitude can
be improved.</p>
    <p num="0019">The reason why the sensitizing dye having a specific
structure according to the present invention has
particularly excellent dye sensitization property cannot be
specifically described because the mechanism of dye 
sensitization is not clear, but can be considered as
follows. The sensitizing dye of the present invention
exhibits a high-intensity light emission (fluorescence
and/or phosphorescence) spectrum and from the fact it is
considered, as one possibility, that the sensitizing dye
having the above-described partial structure has a
relatively long life in the excited state and thus, acts to
allow the reaction with the activator to efficiently
proceed.</p>
    <p num="0020">It has been also found that the sensitizing dye
having a specific structure according to the present
invention exhibits particularly excellent preservation
stability in case of using together with the titanocene
compound. Although the reason for improvement in the
preservation stability is not definitely understood, it is
presumed that the nitrogen atom included in the
heterocyclic structure of sensitizing dye according to the
present invention may cause some type interaction with the
titanocene compound and as a result, compatibility of these
compounds in the photosensitive layer is increased.</p>
    <heading>(A1) Sensitizing dye</heading>
    <p num="0021">The sensitizing dye for use in the present invention
is represented by the following formula (I), (II) or (III): <img id="img-00170001" orientation="unknown" wi="111" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00170001.tif" inline="no" he="37"/>
wherein R<sub>1</sub> to R<sub>8</sub> each independently represents a hydrogen
atom, a halogen atom, a substituted or unsubstituted alkyl,
alkoxy, alkylthio, aryloxy, arylthio, alkenyl, aralkyl,
acyl, aryl, heteroaryl or alkylsulfonic acid group having
20 or less carbon atoms, and X<sub>1</sub> and X<sub>2</sub> each independently
represents an oxygen atom or a sulfur atom;
<img id="img-00170002" orientation="unknown" wi="109" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00170002.tif" inline="no" he="36"/>
wherein R<sub>1</sub> to R<sub>8</sub> each independently represents a hydrogen
atom, a halogen atom, a substituted or unsubstituted alkyl,
alkoxy, alkylthio, aryloxy, arylthio, alkenyl, aralkyl,
acyl, aryl, heteroaryl or alkylsulfonic acid group having
20 or less carbon atoms, X represents an oxygen atom or a
sulfur atom, and A represents a substituted or
unsubstituted aryl or heteroaryl group having 20 or less
carbon atoms; <img id="img-00180001" orientation="unknown" wi="109" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00180001.tif" inline="no" he="45"/>
wherein Y represents an oxygen atom or a sulfur atom, Q<sub>1</sub>
represents a hydrogen atom, a methyl group, an ethyl group
or a phenyl group which may have a substituent, Q<sub>2</sub> to Q<sub>11</sub>
each independently represents a hydrogen atom, a halogen
atom, a cyano group, a nitro group, a sulfonic acid group,
or an alkyl group having from 1 to 5 carbon atoms, which
may have a substituent.</p>
    <p num="0022">Formula (I) is described in detail below. Specific
examples of R<sub>1</sub> to R<sub>8</sub> are described below.</p>
    <p num="0023">Specific examples of the halogen atom include a
fluorine atom, a chlorine atom, a bromine atom and an
iodine atom.</p>
    <p num="0024">Specific examples of the substituted or unsubstituted
alkyl group include a linear, branched or cyclic alkyl
group, an alkoxyalkyl group, an alkoxyalkoxyalkyl group, an
alkoxyalkoxyalkoxyalkyl group, an alkoxycarbonylalkyl group,
an alkoxycarbonyloxyalkyl group, an alkoxyalkoxycarbonyloxyalkyl
group, a hydroxyalkyl group, a hydroxyalkoxyalkyl
group, a hydroxyalkoxyalkoxyalkyl group, a cyanoalkyl group,
an acyloxyalkyl group, an acyloxyalkoxyalkyl group, an 
acyloxyalkoxyalkoxyalkyl group, a halogenated alkyl group,
a sulfonalkyl group, an alkylcarbonylaminoalkyl group, an
alkylsulfonaminoalkyl group, a sulfonamidoalkyl group, an
alkylaminoalkyl group, an aminoalkyl group and an
alkylsulfonalkyl group.</p>
    <p num="0025">Examples of the linear, branched or cyclic alkyl
group include, on taking account of processability by the
coating on a polycarbonate, acryl, epoxy or polyolefin
substrate, a methyl group, an ethyl group, an n-propyl
group, an iso-propyl group, an n-butyl group, an iso-butyl
group, a sec-butyl group, a tert-butyl group, an n-pentyl
group, an iso-pentyl group, a 2-methylbutyl group, a 1-methylbutyl
group, a neopentyl group, a 1,2-dimethylpropyl
group, a 1,1-dimethylpropyl group, a cyclopentyl group, an
n-hexyl group, 4-methylpentyl group, a 3-methylpentyl group,
a 2-methylpentyl group, a 1-methylpentyl group, a 3,3-dimethylbutyl
group, a 2,3-dimethylbutyl group, a 1,3-dimethylbutyl
group, a 2,2-dimethylbutyl group, a 1,2-dimethylbutyl
group, a 1,1-dimethylbutyl group, a 3-ethylbutyl
group, a 2-ethylbutyl group, a 1-ethylbutyl
group, a 1,2,2-trimethylbutyl group, a 1,1,2-trimethylbutyl
group, a 1-ethyl-2-methylpropyl group, a cyclo-hexyl group,
an n-heptyl group, a 2-methylhexyl group, a 3-methylhexyl
group, a 4-methylhexyl group, a 5-methylhexyl group, a 2,4-dimethylpentyl
group, an n-octyl group, a 2-ethylhexyl 
group, a 2,5-dimethylhexyl group, a 2,5,5-trimethylpentyl
group, a 2,4-dimethylhexyl group, a 2,2,4-trimethylpentyl
group, a 3,5,5-trimethylhexyl group, an n-nonyl group, an
n-decyl group, a 4-ethyloctyl group, a 4-ethyl-4,5-methylhexyl
group, an n-undecyl group, an n-dodecyl group,
a 1,3,5,7-tetraethyloctyl group, 4-butyloctyl group, a 6,6-diethyloctyl
group, an n-tridecyl group, a 6-methyl-4-butyloctyl
group, an n-tetradecyl group, an n-pentadecyl
group, a 3,5-dimethylheptyl group, a 2,6-dimethylheptyl
group, a 2,4-dimethylheptyl group, a 2,2,5,5-tetramethyl-hexyl
group, a 1-cyclopentyl-2,2-dimethylpropyl group and a
1-cyclohexyl-2,2-dimethylpropyl group.</p>
    <p num="0026">Examples of the alkoxyalkyl group include a
methoxymethyl group, an ethoxymethyl group, a propoxymethyl
group, a butoxymethyl group, a methoxyethyl group, an
ethoxyethyl group, a propoxyethyl group, a butoxyethyl
group, an n-hexyloxyethyl group, a 4-methylpentoxyethyl
group, a 1,3-dimethylbutoxyethyl group, a 2-ethylhexyloxy-ethyl
group, an n-octyloxyethyl group, a 3,5,5-trimethyl-hexyloxyethyl
group, a 2-methyl-1-iso-propylpropoxyethyl
group, a 3-methyl-1-iso-propylbutyloxyethyl group, a 2-ethoxy-1-methylethyl
group, a 3-methoxybutyl group, a
3,3,3-trifluoropropoxyethyl group and a 3,3,3-trichloro-propoxyethyl
group.</p>
    <p num="0027">Examples of the alkoxyalkoxyalkyl group include a 
methoxyethoxyethyl group, an ethoxyethoxyethyl group, a
propoxyethoxyethyl group, a butoxyethoxyethyl group, a
hexyloxyethoxyethyl group, a 1,2-dimethylpropoxyethoxyethyl
group, a 3-methyl-1-iso-butylbutoxyethoxyethyl group, a 2-methoxy-1-methylethoxyethyl
group, a 2-butoxy-1-methylethoxyethyl
group, a 2-(2'-ethoxy-1'-methylethoxy)-1-methylethyl
group, a 3,3,3-trifluoropropoxyethoxyethyl
group and a 3,3,3-trichloropropoxyethoxyethyl group.</p>
    <p num="0028">Examples of the alkoxyalkoxyalkoxyalkyl group include
a methoxyethoxyethoxyethyl group, an ethoxyethoxyethoxy-ethyl
group, a butoxyethoxyethoxyethyl group, a 2,2,2-trifluoroethoxyethoxyethoxyethyl
group and a 2,2,2-trichloroethoxyethoxyethoxyethyl
group.</p>
    <p num="0029">Examples of the alkoxycarbonylalkyl group include a
methoxycarbonylmethyl group, an ethoxycarbonylmethyl group,
a butoxycarbonylmethyl group, a 2,2,3,3-tetrafluoro-propoxycarbonylmethyl
group and a 2,2,3,3-tetrachloro-propoxycarbonylmethyl
group.</p>
    <p num="0030">Examples of the alkoxycarbonyloxyalkyl group include
a methoxycarbonyloxyethyl group, an ethoxycarbonyloxyethyl
group, a butoxycarbonyloxyethyl group, a 2,2,2-trifluoro-ethoxycarbonyloxyethyl
group and a 2,2,2-trichloroethoxy-carbonyloxyethyl
group.</p>
    <p num="0031">Examples of the alkoxyalkoxycarbonyloxyalkyl group
include a methoxyethoxycarbonyloxyethyl group, an ethoxy-ethoxycarbonyloxyethyl 
group, a butoxyethoxycarbonyl-oxyethyl
group, a 2,2,2-trifluoroethoxyethoxycarbonyloxy-ethyl
group and a 2,2,2-trichloroethoxyethoxy-carbonyloxyethyl
group.</p>
    <p num="0032">Examples of the hydroxyalkyl group include a 2-hydroxyethyl
group, a 4-hydroxyethyl group, a 2-hydroxy-3-methoxypropyl
group, a 2-hydroxy-3-chloropropyl group, a 2-hydroxy-3-ethoxypropyl
group, a 3-butoxy-2-hydroxypropyl
group, a 2-hydroxy-3-phenoxypropyl group, a 2-hydroxypropyl
group and a 2-hydroxybutyl group.</p>
    <p num="0033">Examples of the hydroxyalkoxyalkyl group include a
hydroxyethoxyethyl group, a 2-(2'-hydroxy-1'-methylethoxy)-1-methylethyl
group, a 2-(3'-fluoro-2'-hydroxypropoxy)ethyl
group and 2-(3'-chloro-2'-hydroxypropoxy)ethyl group.</p>
    <p num="0034">Examples of the hydroxyalkoxyalkoxyalkyl group
include a hydroxyethoxyethoxyethyl group, a [2'-(2'-hydroxy-1'-methylethoxy)-1'-methylethoxy]ethoxyethyl
group,
a [2'-(2'-fluoro-1'-hydroxyethoxy)-1'-methylethoxy]-ethoxyethyl
group and [2'-(2'-chloro-1'-hydroxyethoxy)-1'-methylethoxy]ethoxyethyl
group.</p>
    <p num="0035">Examples of the cyanoalkyl group include a 2-cyanoethyl
group, a 4-cyanobutyl group, a 2-cyano-3-methoxypropyl
group, a 2-cyano-3-chloropropyl group, a 2-cyano-3-ethoxypropyl
group, a 3-butoxy-2-cyanopropyl group,
a 2-cyano-3-phenoxypropyl group, a 2-cyanopropyl group and 
a 2-cyanobutyl group.</p>
    <p num="0036">Examples of the acyloxyalkyl group include an
acetoxyethyl group, a propionyloxyethyl group, a butyryloxyethyl
group, a valeryloxyethyl group, a 1-ethylpentyl-caronyloxyethyl
group, a 2,4,4-trimethylpentylcarbonyl-oxyethyl
group, a 3-fluorobutyryloxyethyl group and a 3-chlorobutyryloxyethyl
group.</p>
    <p num="0037">Examples of the acyloxyalkoxyalkyl group include an
acetoxyethoxyethyl group, a propionyloxyethoxyethyl group,
a valeryloxyethoxyethyl group, a 1-ethylpentylcaronyl-oxyethoxyethyl
group, a 2,4,4-trimethylpentylcarbonyloxy-ethoxyethyl
group, a 2-fluoropropionyloxyethoxyethyl group
and a 2-chloropropionyloxyethoxyethyl group.</p>
    <p num="0038">Examples of the acyloxyalkoxyalkoxyalkyl group
include an acetoxyethoxyethoxyethyl group, a propionyloxy-ethoxyethoxyethyl
group, a valeryloxyethoxyethoxyethyl
group, a 1-ethylpentylcarbonyloxyethoxyethoxyethyl group, a
2,4,4-trimethylpentylcarbonyloxyethoxyethoxyethyl group, a
2-fluoropropionyloxyethoxyethoxyethyl group and a 2-chloropropionyloxyethoxyethoxyethyl
group.</p>
    <p num="0039">Examples of the halogenated alkyl group include a
chloromethyl group, a chloroethyl group, a 2,2,2-trifluoroethyl
group, a trifluoromethyl group, a
bromomethyl group and iodomethyl group.</p>
    <p num="0040">Examples of the sulfone alkyl group include a sulfone 
methyl group, a sulfone ethyl group and a sulfone propyl
group.</p>
    <p num="0041">Examples of the alkylcarbonylaminoalkyl group include
methylcarbonylaminoethyl group, an ethylcarbonylaminoethyl
group, a propylcarbonylaminoethyl group, a cyclohexyl-carbonylaminoethyl
group and a succiniminoethyl group.</p>
    <p num="0042">Examples of the alkylsulfonaminoalkyl group include a
methylsulfonaminoethyl group, an ethylsulfonaminoethyl
group and a propylsulfonaminoethyl group.</p>
    <p num="0043">Examples of the sulfonamidoalkyl group include a
sulfonamidomethyl group, a sulfonamidoethyl group and a
sulfonamidopropyl group.</p>
    <p num="0044">Examples of the alkylaminoalkyl group include an N-methylaminomethyl
group, an N,N-dimethylaminomethyl group,
an N,N-diethylaminomethyl group, an N,N-dipropylaminomethyl
group and an N,N-dibutylaminomethyl group.</p>
    <p num="0045">Examples of the aminoalkyl group include an
aminomethyl group, an aminoethyl group and an aminopropyl
group.</p>
    <p num="0046">Examples of the alkylsulfone alkyl group include a
methylsulfone methyl group, an ethylsulfone methyl group, a
butylsulfone methyl group, a methylsulfone ethyl group, an
ethylsulfone ethyl group, a butylsulfone ethyl group, a
2,2,3,3-tetrafluoropropylsulfone methyl group and a
2,2,3,3-tetrachloropropylsulfone methyl group. </p>
    <p num="0047">Examples of the substituted or unsubstituted alkoxy
group include alkoxy groups having a substituent similar to
those described above for the alkyl group. Preferred
examples thereof include lower alkoxy groups such as a
methoxy group, an ethoxy group, an n-propoxy group, an iso-propoxy
group, an n-butoxy group, an iso-butoxy group, a
sec-butoxy group, a tert-butoxy group, an n-pentoxy group,
an iso-pentoxy group, a neopentoxy group and a 2-methylbutoxy
group.</p>
    <p num="0048">Examples of the substituted or unsubstituted acyl
group include acyl groups having a substituent similar to
those described above for the alkyl group. Preferred
examples thereof include a formyl group, a methylcarbonyl
group, an ethylcarbonyl group, an n-propylcarbonyl group,
an iso-propylcarbonyl group, an n-butylcarbonyl group, an
iso-butylcarbonyl group, a sec-butylcarbonyl group, a tert-butylcarbonyl
group, an n-pentylcarbonyl group, an iso-pentylcarbonyl
group, a neopentylcarbonyl group, a 2-methylbutylcarbonyl
group and a nitrobenzylcarbonyl group.</p>
    <p num="0049">Examples of the substituted or unsubstituted aryl
group include aryl groups having a substituent similar to
those described above for the alkyl group. Preferred
examples thereof include a phenyl group, a nitrophenyl
group, a cyanophenyl group, a hydroxyphenyl group, a
methylphenyl group, a trifluoromethylphenyl group, a 
naphthyl group, a nitronaphthyl group, a cyanonaphthyl
group, a hydroxynaphthyl group, a methylnaphthyl group and
a trifluoromethylnaphthyl group.</p>
    <p num="0050">Examples of the substituted or unsubstituted aralkyl
group include aralkyl groups having a substituent similar
to those described above for the alkyl group. Preferred
examples thereof include a benzyl group, a nitrobenzyl
group, a cyanobenzyl group, a hydroxybenzyl group, a
methylbenzyl group, a trifluoromethylbenzyl group, a
naphthylmethyl group, a nitronaphthylmethyl group, a
cyanonaphthylmethyl group, a hydroxynaphthylmethyl group, a
methylnaphthylmethyl group and a trifluoromethylnaphthyl-methyl
group.</p>
    <p num="0051">Examples of the substituted or unsubstituted alkenyl
group include alkenyl groups having a substituent similar
to those described above for the alkyl group. Preferred
examples thereof include lower alkenyl groups such as
propenyl group, 1-butenyl group, iso-butenyl group, 1-pentenyl
group, 2-pentenyl group, 2-methyl-1-butenyl group,
3-methyl-1-butenyl group, 2-methyl-2-butenyl group, 2,2-dicyanovinyl
group, 2-cyano-2-methylcarboxy vinyl group and
2-cyano-2-methylsulfone vinyl group.</p>
    <p num="0052">Examples of the substituted or unsubstituted
alkylthio group include alkylthio groups having a
substituent similar to those described above for the alkyl 
group. Preferred examples thereof include lower alkylthio
groups such as methylthio group, ethylthio group, an n-propylthio
group, an iso-propylthio group, an n-butylthio
group, an iso-butylthio group, a sec-butylthio group, a
tert-butylthio group, an n-pentylthio group, an iso-pentylthio
group, a neopentylthio group, a 2-methylbutylthio
group and a methylcarboxylethylthio group.</p>
    <p num="0053">Examples of the substituted or unsubstituted aryloxy
group include aryloxy groups having a substituent similar
to those described above for the aryl group. Preferred
examples thereof include a phenoxy group, a 2-methylphenoxy
group, a 4-methylphenoxy group, a 4-tert-butylphenoxy group,
a 2-methoxyphenoxy group and a 4-iso-propylphenoxy group.</p>
    <p num="0054">Examples of the substituted or unsubstituted arylthio
group include arylthio groups having a substituent similar
to those described above for the aryl group. Preferred
examples thereof include a phenylthio group, a 4-methylphenylthio
group, a 2-methoxyphenylthio group and a
4-tert-butylphenylthio group.</p>
    <p num="0055">Examples of the substituted or unsubstituted
heteroaryl group include a pyrrolyl group, a thienyl group,
a furanyl group, an oxazoyl group, an isooxazoyl group, an
oxadiazoyl group, an imidazoyl group, a benzoxazoyl group,
a benzothiazoyl group, a benzimidazoyl group, a
benzofuranyl group and an indoyl group. </p>
    <p num="0056">Examples of the substituted or unsubstituted
alkylsulfone group include alkylsulfone groups having a
substituent similar to those described above for the alkyl
group. Preferred examples thereof include a methylsulfone
group, an ethylsulfone group, an n-propylsulfone group, an
iso-propylsulfone group, an n-butylsulfone group, an iso-butylsulfone
group, a sec-butylsulfone group, a tert-butylsulfone
group, an n-pentylsulfone group, an iso-butylsulfone
group, a neopentylsulfone group, a 2-methylbutylsulfone
group, a 2-hydroxyethylsulfone group and
a 2-cyanoethylsulfone group.</p>
    <p num="0057">The compound represented by formula (I) of the
present invention can be easily produced according to a
known method described, for example, in <u style="single">J. Am. Chem. Soc.,</u>
63, 3203 (1941). More specifically, the compound
represented by formula (I) can be produced by reacting a
compound represented by formula (I-2) with a compound
represented by formula (I-3) using a hydrochloric acid as a
catalyst.
<img id="img-00280001" orientation="unknown" wi="92" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00280001.tif" inline="no" he="39"/><img id="img-00290001" orientation="unknown" wi="95" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00290001.tif" inline="no" he="37"/></p>
    <p num="0058">In formulae (I-2) and (I-3), R<sub>1</sub> to R<sub>8</sub>, X<sub>1</sub> and X<sub>2</sub> have
the same meanings as defined above, respectively.</p>
    <p num="0059">Specific examples of the compound represented by
formula (I) are shown in Table 1A. <img id="img-00300001" orientation="unknown" wi="153" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00300001.tif" inline="no" he="213"/><img id="img-00310001" orientation="unknown" wi="153" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00310001.tif" inline="no" he="213"/><img id="img-00320001" orientation="unknown" wi="73" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00320001.tif" inline="no" he="213"/></p>
    <p num="0060">The compound represented by formula (II) is described
in detail below.</p>
    <p num="0061">Specific examples of each substituent represented by
R<sub>1</sub> to R<sub>8</sub> are the same as the specific examples of R<sub>1</sub> to R<sub>8</sub>
in formula (I).</p>
    <p num="0062">Specific examples of the substituted or unsubstituted
aryl group and the substituted or unsubstituted heteroaryl
group represented by A are the same as the specific
examples of the substituted or unsubstituted aryl group and
the substituted or unsubstituted heteroaryl group
represented by R<sub>1</sub> to R<sub>8</sub>.</p>
    <p num="0063">The compound represented by formula (II) of the
present invention can be easily produced according to a
known method described, for example, in <u style="single">J. Am. Chem. Soc.</u>,
63, 3203 (1941). More specifically, the compound
represented by formula (II) can be produced by reacting a
compound represented by formula (11-2) with a compound
represented by formula (II-3) using a hydrochloric acid as
a catalyst.
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/">A-CHO</st32:che><img id="img-00330001" orientation="unknown" wi="98" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00330001.tif" inline="no" he="37"/></p>
    <p num="0064">In formulae (II-2) and (II-3), R<sub>1</sub> to R<sub>8</sub>, X<sub>1</sub> and X<sub>2</sub> 
have the same meanings as defined above, respectively.</p>
    <p num="0065">Specific examples of the compound represented by
formula (II) are shown in Table 1B. <img id="img-00350001" orientation="unknown" wi="150" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00350001.tif" inline="no" he="209"/><img id="img-00360001" orientation="unknown" wi="151" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00360001.tif" inline="no" he="214"/><img id="img-00370001" orientation="unknown" wi="119" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00370001.tif" inline="no" he="215"/></p>
    <p num="0066">The compound represented by formula (III) is
described in detail below.</p>
    <p num="0067">Examples of the phenyl group having a substituent,
represented by Q<sub>1</sub> include phenyl groups substituted by a
halogen atom (e.g., fluorine, chlorine, bromine, iodine), a
cyano group, a nitro group, a sulfonic acid group or the
like. Examples of the alkyl group having from 1 to 5
carbon atoms which may have a substituent, represented by
Q<sub>2</sub> to Q<sub>11</sub>, include primary alkyl groups such as methyl group,
ethyl group, n-propyl group, n-butyl group, isobutyl group,
n-pentyl group, neopentyl group, isoamyl group and 2-methylbutyl
group, secondary alkyl groups such as isopropyl
group, sec-butyl group, 1-ethylpropyl group, 1-methylbutyl
group and 1,2-dimethylpropyl group, tertiary alkyl groups
such as tert-butyl group, and these alkyl groups
substituted by fluorine, chlorine, bromine, iodine or the
like.</p>
    <p num="0068">Specific preferred examples of the compound
represented by formula (III) include Compounds (D-III-1) to
(D-III-18) shown below, however, the present invention is
not limited thereto. <img id="img-00390001" orientation="unknown" wi="140" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00390001.tif" inline="no" he="42"/><img id="img-00390002" orientation="unknown" wi="141" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00390002.tif" inline="no" he="38"/><img id="img-00390003" orientation="unknown" wi="142" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00390003.tif" inline="no" he="40"/><img id="img-00390004" orientation="unknown" wi="142" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00390004.tif" inline="no" he="54"/><img id="img-00400001" orientation="unknown" wi="136" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00400001.tif" inline="no" he="37"/><img id="img-00400002" orientation="unknown" wi="136" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00400002.tif" inline="no" he="32"/><img id="img-00400003" orientation="unknown" wi="136" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00400003.tif" inline="no" he="32"/><img id="img-00400004" orientation="unknown" wi="135" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00400004.tif" inline="no" he="47"/><img id="img-00400005" orientation="unknown" wi="134" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00400005.tif" inline="no" he="39"/></p>
    <p num="0069">In order to improve the image forming properties, a
compound having absorption maximum in the wavelength region
of 350 to 550 nm and a large refractive index at 400 to 500
nm, other than the above-described compounds, may be mixed.
Specific examples of such compound include cyanine
compounds, squarylium-base compounds, naphthoquinone-base
compounds, anthraquinone-base compounds, tetrapyra-porphyrazine-base
compounds, indophenol-base compounds,
pyrylium-base compounds, thiopyrylium-base compounds,
azulenium-base compounds, triphenylmethane-base compounds,
xanthene-base compounds, indanthrene-base compounds,
indigo-base compounds, thioindigo-base compounds,
merocyanine-base compounds, thiazine-base compounds,
acridine-base compounds, oxazine-base compounds and
dipyrromethene-base compounds. A plurality of these
compounds may be used as a mixture. The mixing ratio of
such compound is approximately from 0.1 to 30%.</p>
    <p num="0070">The sensitizing dye for use in the present invention
may be subjected to various chemical modifications so that
when it is used in a lithographic printing plate precursor,
the properties of the photosensitive layer can be improved.
For example, the sensitizing dye may be bound to an
addition-polymerizable compound structure (e.g., acryloyl
group, methacryloyl group) by a covalent bond, ionic bond,
hydrogen bond or the like, whereby strength of the layer
can be increased and unnecessary deposition of the dye in 
the layer after exposure can be inhibited. Also, the
sensitizing dye may be bound to a titanocene compound
described hereinafter or to other radical generation parts
(for example, a reduction decomposable part such as
halogenated alkyl, onium, peroxide, biimidazole, onium or
biimidazole, or an oxidation cleavable part such as borate,
amine, trimethylsilylmethyl, carboxymethyl, carbonyl or
imine), whereby photosensitivity particularly under a low
concentration condition of the initiation system can be
remarkably increased.</p>
    <p num="0071">Also, in case of using the photosensitive composition
of the present invention for the preparation of a
lithographic printing plate precursor, introduction of a
hydrophilic site (an acidic group or a polar group, for
example, a carboxyl group or an ester thereof, a sulfonic
group or an ester thereof, or an ethylene oxide group) to
the dye is effective for the purpose of enhancing the
processing suitability with an (alkali) aqueous developer,
which is a preferred use mode of the photosensitive layer.
Particularly, an ester-type hydrophilic group has a feature
in that it exhibits excellent compatibility in the
photosensitive layer due to the relatively hydrophobic
structure and in the developer, it is hydrolyzed to
generate an acid radical, thereby increasing solubility.
In addition, a substituent can be appropriately introduced,
for example, for improving the compatibility or inhibiting 
the crystallization in the photosensitive layer. For
example, in a certain kind of photosensitive system, an
unsaturated bond of an aryl group, an allyl group or the
like is sometimes very effective for improving the
compatibility. Furthermore, the formation of a steric
hindrance between π planes of dyes by a method such as
introduction of a branched alkyl structure can
significantly inhibit the crystallization. Also, adhesion
to an inorganic material such as metal or metal oxide can
be improved by the introduction of a phosphonic acid group,
an epoxy group, a trialkoxysilyl group or the like. If
desired, polymerization of the sensitizing dye may also be
used.</p>
    <p num="0072">Details of the use method of the sensitizing dye,
such as selection of the structure, sole or combination use
and amount added, can be appropriately selected in
accordance with the designed performance of the final
photosensitive material. For example, when two or more
sensitizing dyes are used in combination, the compatibility
with the photosensitive composition layer can be increased.
For the selection of sensitizing dye, the molar absorption
coefficient at the emission wavelength of the light source
used is an important factor in addition to the
photosensitivity. Use of a dye having a large molar
absorption coefficient is profitable, because the amount of
dye added can be made relatively small. Also, in case of 
preparing a lithographic printing plate precursor, the use
of such a dye is advantageous in view of the physical
properties of the photosensitive layer. Since the
photosensitivity and resolution of the photosensitive layer
and the physical properties of the exposed layer are
greatly affected by the absorbance at the wavelength of
light source, the amount of the sensitizing dye added is
appropriately selected by taking account of these factors.
For example, the sensitivity decreases in the low
absorbance region of 0.1 or less. Also, the resolution
decreases due to the effect of halation.</p>
    <p num="0073">However, for the purpose of hardening a coating
having a large thickness of 5 µm or more, such low
absorbance is sometimes rather effective in increasing the
hardening degree. On the other hand, in the high
absorbance region of 3 or more, the light is mostly
absorbed on the surface of the photosensitive layer and
hardening in more inner part is inhibited, as a result,
when, for example, a printing plate is manufactured, the
layer strength and the adhesion to substrate become
insufficient. In the case of use as a lithographic
printing plate where the layer has a relatively small
thickness, the amount of the sensitizing dye added is
preferably selected such that the photosensitive layer has
an absorbance of 0.1 to 1.5, preferably from 0.25 to 1. In
the case of use as a lithographic printing plate, the 
amount of the sensitizing dye added is usually from 0.05 to
30 parts by weight, preferably from 0.1 to 20 parts by
weight, and more preferably from 0.2 to 10 parts by weight,
per 100 parts by weight of the photosensitive layer
components.</p>
    <heading>(A2) Titanocene compound</heading>
    <p num="0074">The titanocene compound used as the photopolymerization
initiation system in the present invention may be
any titanocene compound insofar as it can generate an
active radical upon irradiation with light in the
copresence of the above-described sensitizing dye, and may
be appropriately selected from known compounds described,
for example, in JP-A-59-152396, JP-A-61-151197, JP-A-63-41483,
JP-A-63-41484, JP-A-2-249, JP-A-2-291, JP-A-3-27393,
JP-A-3-12403 and JP-A-6-41170.</p>
    <p num="0075">Specific examples thereof include dicyclopentadienyl-Ti-dichloride,
dicyclopentadienyl-Ti-bisphenyl, dicyclo-pentadienyl-Ti-bis-2,3,4,5,6-pentafluorophen-1-yl
(hereinafter
sometimes referred to as "T-1"), dicyclopentadienyl-Ti-bis-2,3,5,6-tetrafluorophen-1-yl,
dicyclopentadienyl-Ti-bis-2,4,6-trifluorophen-1-yl,
dicyclopentadienyl-Ti-bis-2,6-difluorophen-1-yl,
dicyclopentadienyl-Ti-bis-2,4-difluorophen-1-yl,
dimethylcyclopentadienyl-Ti-bis-2,3,4,5,6-pentafluorophen-1-yl,
dimethylcyclopentadienyl-Ti-bis-2,3,5,6-tetrafluorophen-1-yl,
dimethylcyclopenta-dienyl-Ti-bis-2,4-difluorophen-1-yl
and bis (cyclopenta-dienyl)-bis(2,6-difluoro-3-(pir-1-yl)phenyl)titanium 
(hereinafter
sometimes referred to as "T-2").</p>
    <p num="0076">Similarly to the above-described sensitizing dye, the
titanocene compound for use in the present invention may be
subjected to various chemical modifications so that when a
lithographic printing plate precursor is manufactured, the
properties of the photosensitive layer can be improved.
Examples of the method which can be used include binding
with a sensitizing dye, an addition-polymerizable
unsaturated compound or other radical generating part,
introduction of a hydrophilic site, introduction of a
substituent for improving the compatibility or inhibiting
the crystallization, introduction of a substituent for
improving the adhesion, and formation of a polymer.</p>
    <p num="0077">Similarly to the above-described addition-polymerizable
compound and sensitizing dye, the use method
of the titanocene compound can be appropriately and freely
selected according to the designed performance of the
photosensitive material. For example, by using two or more
kinds of titanocene compounds, the compatibility in the
photosensitive composition layer can be improved. In view
of photosensitivity, use of the titanocene compound in a
larger amount is usually more advantageous. Sufficiently
high sensitivity can be obtained by using the titanocene
compound in an amount of 0.5 to 80 parts by weight, and
preferably from 1 to 50 parts by weight, per 100 parts by 
weight of the photosensitive layer components. On the
other hand, for using under a white lamp such as yellow
lamp, the amount of titanocene used is preferably smaller
in view of fogging due to light in the vicinity of 500 nm.
However, when combined with the sensitizing dye of the
present invention, sufficiently high photosensitivity can
be obtained even if the amount of titanocene used is
reduced to 6 parts by weight or less, further to 1.9 parts
by weight or less, even to 1.4 parts by weight or less.</p>
    <heading>(B) Compound of undergoing a reaction with at least one
of a radical and an acid to change at least one of
its physical and chemical properties and maintaining
the changed physical or chemical property</heading>
    <p num="0078">The third essential component (iii) of the present
invention is a compound in which the physical or chemical
property is changed by the action of an active species
generated upon photo-reaction of the above-described photo-initiation
system and maintained. Any compound can be
freely used without any particular limitation insofar as
the compound has such properties. For example, the
compounds described above for the initiation system each
itself has such properties in many cases. The
characteristics of the component (iii), which are changed
by the action of a radical, an acid and/or a base generated
from the photo-initiation system, include molecular
physical properties such as absorption spectrum (color), 
chemical structure and polarizability, and physical
properties of the material such as solubility, strength,
refractive index, fluidity and adhesive property.</p>
    <p num="0079">For example, when a compound of changing the
absorption spectrum by pH, such as pH indicator, is used as
the component (iii) and an acid or a base is generated from
the initiation system, the color tone can be changed only
in the exposed area. Such a composition is useful as an
image forming material. Similarly, when a compound of
changing in the absorption spectrum by oxidation-reduction
or nucleophilic addition reaction is used as the component
(iii), oxidation, reduction or the like is induced by a
radical generated from the initiation system and thereby
image formation can be effected. These are disclosed, for
example, in <u style="single">J. Am. Chem. Soc.</u>, <u style="single">108,</u> 128 (1986), <u style="single">J. Imaging
Sci.</u>, <u style="single">30</u>, 215 (1986) and <u style="single">Israel. J. Chem.</u>, <u style="single">25</u>, 264 (1986).</p>
    <p num="0080">Also, a photocurable resin or a negative working
photopolymer can be formed by combining an addition-polymerizable
or condensation-polymerizable compound as the
component (iii) and the initiation system.</p>
    <p num="0081">As the component (iii), a radical polymerizable
compound (e.g., compound having an ethylenically
unsaturated bond), a cationic polymerizable compound (e.g.,
epoxy compound, vinyl ether compound, methylol compound) or
an anionic polymerizable compound (e.g., epoxy compound) is
used. These are described, for example, in <u style="single">Photopolymer</u><u style="single">Handbook</u>, edited by Photopolymer Konwa Kai, published by
Kogyo Chosa Kai (1989), and <u style="single">Kobunshi (Polymer),</u> 45, 786
(1996). A composition in which a thiol compound is used as
the component (iii) and combined with a photo-radical
generation system is also well known.</p>
    <p num="0082">It is also effective to use an acid-decomposable
compound as the component (iii) and combine it with a
photoacid generator. For example, a material which uses a
polymer having a side chain or main chain decomposable by
an acid and changes in the solubility or hydro-philic/hydrophobic
property by light is broadly used in
practice as a photodecomposable photosensitive resin or a
positive working photopolymer. Specific examples thereof
include those described, for example, in <u style="single">ACS. Symp. Ser.,
242,</u> 11 (1984), JP-A-60-3625, U.S. Patents 5,102,771,
5,206,317 and 5,212,047, JP-A-4-26850, JP-A-3-1921731, JP-A-60-10247
and JP-A-62-40450.</p>
    <p num="0083">The addition-polymerizable compound as a component
(iii) particularly useful for obtaining a high-sensitive
lithographic printing plate precursor which is one of the
objects of the present invention is described in detail
below.</p>
    <heading>(B-1) Addition-polymerizable compound</heading>
    <p num="0084">The addition-polymerizable compound having at least
one ethylenically unsaturated double bond, as a preferred
component (iii) for use in the present invention, is 
selected from compounds having at least one, preferably two
or more, terminal ethylenically unsaturated double bonds.
Such compounds are widely known in the field of art and can
be used in the present invention without any particular
limitation. These compounds have a chemical form such as
monomer, prepolymer, namely dimer, trimer or oligomer or a
mixture thereof, or copolymer thereof. Examples of the
monomer and the copolymer thereof include unsaturated
carboxylic acids (e.g., acrylic acid, methacrylic acid,
itaconic acid, crotonic acid, isocrotonic acid, maleic
acid) and esters or amides thereof. Among these, preferred
are esters of an unsaturated carboxylic acid with an
aliphatic polyhydric alcohol compound, and amides of an
unsaturated carboxylic acid with an aliphatic polyvalent
amine compound. An addition reaction product of an
unsaturated carboxylic acid ester or amide having a
nucleophilic substituent such as hydroxyl group, amino
group or mercapto group with a monofunctional or
polyfunctional isocyanate or epoxy, or a dehydration
condensation reaction product of the unsaturated carboxylic
acid ester or amide with a monofunctional or polyfunctional
carboxylic acid is also suitably used.</p>
    <p num="0085">Furthermore, an addition reaction product of an
unsaturated carboxylic acid ester or amide having an
electrophilic substituent such as isocyanato group or epoxy
group with a monofunctional or polyfunctional alcohol, 
amine or thiol, or a substitution reaction product of an
unsaturated carboxylic acid ester or amide having a
releasable substituent such as halogen group or tosyloxy
group with a monofunctional or polyfunctional alcohol,
amine or thiol is also suitably used. Additionally,
compounds in which the unsaturated carboxylic acid is
replaced by an unsaturated phosphonic acid, styrene, vinyl
ether or the like can also be used.</p>
    <p num="0086">Specific examples of the monomer, which is an ester
of an aliphatic polyhydric alcohol compound with an
unsaturated carboxylic acid, include acrylic acid esters
such as ethylene glycol diacrylate, triethylene glycol
diacrylate, 1,3-butanediol diacrylate, tetramethylene
glycol diacrylate, propylene glycol diacrylate, neopentyl
glycol diacrylate, trimethylolpropane triacrylate,
trimethylolpropane tri(acryloyloxypropyl) ether,
trimethylolethane triacrylate, hexanediol diacrylate, 1,4-cyclohexanediol
diacrylate, tetraethylene glycol diacrylate,
pentaerythritol diacrylate, pentaerythritol triacrylate,
pentaerythritol tetraacrylate, dipentaerythritol diacrylate,
dipentaerythritol hexaacrylate, sorbitol triacrylate,
sorbitol tetraacrylate, sorbitol pentaacrylate, sorbitol
hexaacrylate, tri(acryloyloxyethyl) isocyanurate and
polyester acrylate oligomer; methacrylic acid esters such
as tetramethylene glycol dimethacrylate, triethylene glycol
dimethacrylate, neopentyl glycol dimethacrylate, 
trimethylolpropane trimethacrylate, trimethylolethane
trimethacrylate, ethylene glycol dimethacrylate, 1,3-butanediol
dimethacrylate, hexanediol dimethacrylate,
pentaerythritol dimethacrylate, pentaerythritol
trimethacrylate, pentaerythritol tetramethacrylate,
dipentaerythritol dimethacrylate, dipentaerythritol
hexamethacrylate, sorbitol trimethacrylate, sorbitol
tetramethacrylate, bis [p-(3-methacryloxy-2-hydroxypropoxy)-phenyl]dimethylmethane
and bis[p-(methacryloxyethoxy)-phenyl]dimethylmethane;
itaconic acid esters such as
ethylene glycol diitaconate, propylene glycol diitaconate,
1,3-butenediol diitaconate, 1,4-butanediol diitaconate,
tetramethylene glycol diitaconate, pentaerythritol
diitaconate and sorbitol tetraitaconate; crotonic acid
esters such as ethylene glycol dicrotonate, tetramethylene
glycol dicrotonate, pentaerythritol dicrotonate and
sorbitol tetradicrotonate; isocrotonic acid esters such as
ethylene glycol diisocrotonate, pentaerythritol
diisocrotonate and sorbitol tetraisocrotonate; and maleic
acid esters such as ethylene glycol dimaleate, triethylene
glycol dimaleate, pentaerythritol dimaleate and sorbitol
tetramaleate.</p>
    <p num="0087">Other examples of the ester, which can be suitably
used, include aliphatic alcohol-base esters described in
JP-B-46-27926, JP-B-51-47334 and JP-A-57-196231, those
having an aromatic skeleton described in JP-A-59-5240, JP-A-59-5241 
and JP-A-2-226149, and those containing an amino
group described in JP-A-1-165613.</p>
    <p num="0088">The above-described ester monomers can also be used
as a mixture.</p>
    <p num="0089">Specific examples of the monomer, which forms an
amide of an aliphatic polyvalent amine compound with an
unsaturated carboxylic acid, include methylene bis-acrylamide,
methylene bis-methacrylamide, 1,6-hexamethylene
bis-acrylamide, 1,6-hexamethylene bis-methacrylamide,
diethylenetriamine tris-acrylamide, xylylene bis-acrylamide
and xylylene bis-methacrylamide.</p>
    <p num="0090">Other preferred examples of the amide-base monomer
include those having a cyclohexylene structure described in
JP-B-54-21726.</p>
    <p num="0091">A urethane-base addition polymerizable compound
produced using an addition reaction between an isocyanate
and a hydroxyl group is also suitably used and specific
examples thereof include vinylurethane compounds having two
or more polymerizable vinyl groups within one molecule
obtained by adding a vinyl monomer containing a hydroxyl
group represented by the following formula (6) to a
polyisocyanate compound having two or more isocyanate
groups within one molecule, described in JP-B-48-41708.
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/">CH<sub>2</sub>=C(R)COOCH<sub>2</sub>CH(R')OH</st32:che>
wherein R and R' each represents H or CH<sub>3</sub>.</p>
    <p num="0092">Also, urethane acrylates described in JP-A-51-37193, 
JP-B-2-32293 and JP-B-2-16765, and urethane compounds
having an ethylene oxide-base skeleton described in JP-B-58-49860,
JP-B-56-17654, JP-B-62-39417 and JP-B-62-39418
may be suitably used.</p>
    <p num="0093">Furthermore, a photosensitive composition having
remarkably excellent sensitizing speed can be obtained by
using an addition-polymerizable compound having an amino
structure or a sulfide structure within the molecule,
described in JP-A-63-277653, JP-A-63-260909 and JP-A-1-105238.</p>
    <p num="0094">Other examples include polyfunctional acrylates and
methacrylates such as polyester acrylates and epoxy
acrylates obtained by reacting an epoxy resin with a
(meth)acrylic acid, described in JP-A-48-64183, JP-B-49-43191
and JP-B-52-30490. Specific unsaturated compounds
described in JP-B-46-43946, JP-B-1-40337 and JP-B-1-40336,
and vinylphosphonic acid-base compounds described in JP-A-2-25493
can also be used. In some cases, the structure
containing a perfluoroalkyl group described in JP-A-61-22048
can be suitably used. Also, those described as a
photocurable monomer or oligomer in <u style="single">Nippon Secchaku Kyokai
Shi (Journal of Japan Adhesion Society)</u>, Vol. 20, No. 7, pp.
300-308 (1984) can be used.</p>
    <p num="0095">Details of the use method of the addition-polymerizable
compound, such as selection of the structure,
sole or combination use and amount added, can be freely 
selected in accordance with the designed performance of
final sensitive material. For example, the compound is
selected from the following standpoints. In view of
sensitizing speed, a structure having a large unsaturated
group content per one molecule is preferred and in most
cases, a bifunctional or greater functional group is
preferred. For increasing the strength of image portion,
namely, hardened layer, a trifunctional or greater
functional group is preferred. A combination use of
compounds different in the functional number and in the
polymerizable group (for example, an acrylic acid ester, a
methacrylic acid ester, a styrene-base compound or a vinyl
ether-base compound) is an effective method for controlling
both the photosensitivity and the strength. A compound
having a large molecular weight or a compound having high
hydrophobicity is excellent in the sensitizing speed and
layer strength but is not preferred in some cases in view
of developing speed and precipitation in the developer.</p>
    <p num="0096">The selection and use method of the addition
polymerization compound are important factors for the
compatibility and dispersibility with other components
(e.g., binder polymer, initiator, coloring agent) in the
photosensitive composition. For example, the compatibility
may be improved in some cases by using a low purity
compound or using two or more compounds in combination. In
the case of manufacturing a lithographic printing plate 
precursor, a specific structure may be selected for the
purpose of improving the adhesive property to a support or
overcoat layer described hereinafter. As for the blending
ratio of the addition-polymerizable compound in the
photosensitive composition, a larger ratio is advantageous
in view of sensitivity but if the blending ratio is too
large, undesired phase separation may occur, a problem may
arise in the production step due to adhesive property of
the photosensitive composition (e.g., production failure
due to transfer or adhesion of the photosensitive
components), and when a lithographic printing plate
precursor is manufactured, precipitation in the developer
may be disadvantageously generated. In view of these
points, the blending ratio is in most cases preferably from
5 to 80 wt%, more preferably from 25 to 75 wt%, based on
all components of the composition. The addition-polymerizable
compounds may be used individually or in
combination of two or more thereof. As for the use method
of the addition-polymerizable compound, appropriate
structure, blending and amount added can be freely selected
by taking account of the degree of polymerization
inhibition due to oxygen, resolution, fogging, change in
refractive index, surface adhesive property and the like.
Depending on the case, a layer construction and a coating
method, such as undercoat and overcoat, can also be
employed. </p>
    <heading>(C) Binder polymer</heading>
    <p num="0097">In the application to a lithographic printing plate
precursor as a preferred embodiment of the present
invention, a binder polymer is preferably further used in
the photosensitive layer. The binder is preferably a
linear organic high molecular polymer. The "linear organic
high molecular polymer" may be any linear organic high
molecular polymer. Preferably, a linear organic high
molecular polymer soluble or swellable in water or
alkalescent water, which enables water development or
alkalescent water development, is selected. The linear
organic high molecular polymer is selected not only as a
film forming agent of the composition but also considering
the use of water, alkalescent water or organic solvent as
developer. For example, when a water-soluble organic high
molecular polymer is used, water development can be
performed. Examples of the linear organic high molecular
polymer include addition polymers having a carboxylic acid
group on the side chain, for example, methacrylic acid
copolymers, acrylic acid copolymers, itaconic acid
copolymers, crotonic acid copolymers, maleic acid
copolymers and partially esterified maleic acid copolymers
described in JP-A-59-44615, JP-B-54-34327, JP-B-58-12577,
JP-B-54-25957, JP-A-54-92723, JP-A-59-53836 and JP-A-59-71048.
Furthermore, acidic cellulose derivatives having a
carboxylic acid group on the side chain may also be used. 
In addition, polymers obtained by adding a cyclic acid
anhydride to the above-described addition polymers having a
hydroxyl group are also useful.</p>
    <p num="0098">Among these, [benzyl (meth)acrylate/(meth)acrylic
acid/another addition polymerizable vinyl monomer, if
desired] copolymers and [allyl (meth)acrylate/(meth)acrylic
acid/another addition polymerizable vinyl monomer, if
desired] copolymers are preferred because of their
excellent balance in the film strength, sensitivity and
developability.</p>
    <p num="0099">Also, the acid group-containing urethane-base binder
polymers described in JP-B-7-120040, JP-B-7-120041, JP-B-7-120042,
JP-B-8-12424, JP-A-63-287944, JP-A-63-287947, JP-A-1-271741
and Japanese Patent Application No. 10-116232 are
advantageous in view of press life and low exposure
suitability because of their very excellent strength.</p>
    <p num="0100">When the acid group-containing urethane-base binder
is used in the photosensitive composition of the present
invention, the sensitivity thereof is preferably increased.
Although the reason for increasing the sensitivity is not
completely clear, it is presumed that the nitrogen atom in
the heterocyclic ring included in the skeleton of the
sensitizing dye interacts with the urethane bond in the
urethane-base binder to increase in compatibility in the
photosensitive layer, whereby the sensitivity increases.</p>
    <p num="0101">The binder having an amido group described in JP-A-11-171909 
has both excellent developability and film
strength and therefore, is suitably used.</p>
    <p num="0102">Other than these, polyvinyl pyrrolidone, polyethylene
oxide and the like are useful as a water-soluble linear
organic polymer. Also, an alcohol-soluble nylon and a
polyether of 2,2-bis-(4-hydroxyphenyl)-propane with
epichlorohydrin are useful for the purpose of increasing
the strength of hardened film. The linear organic high
molecular polymer can be mixed in an arbitrary amount based
on the entire composition. However, if the amount exceeds
90 wt%, an undesired effect may result in view of image
strength or the like. The amount added is preferably from
30 to 85 wt%. Also, the photopolymerizable compound having
an ethylenically unsaturated double bond and the linear
organic high molecular polymer are preferably used at a
weight ratio of 1/9 to 7/3.</p>
    <p num="0103">In a preferred embodiment, the binder polymer is
substantially insoluble in water and soluble in alkali. By
using such a binder, use of an organic solvent which is
preferably not used in the developer from the environmental
concern can be avoided or limited to a very small amount.
In such a case, the acid value (acid content per 1 g of
polymer, expressed by the chemical equivalent number) and
molecular weight of the binder polymer are appropriately
selected by taking account of the image strength and the
developability. The acid value is preferably from 0.4 to 
3.0 meq/g, more preferably from 0.6 to 2.0 meq/g, and the
molecular weight is preferably from 3,000 to 500,000, more
preferably from 10,000 to 300,000.</p>
    <heading>(D) Other components</heading>
    <p num="0104">The photosensitive composition of the present
invention may further appropriately contain other
components suitable for use, production method and the like.
Preferred additives are described below,</p>
    <heading>(D1) Co-sensitizer</heading>
    <p num="0105">The sensitivity can be further elevated by using a
certain additive (hereinafter referred to as a "co-sensitizer").
The operation mechanism is not clearly known
but considered to be mostly based on the following chemical
process. That is, the co-sensitizer reacts with various
intermediate active species (e.g., radical, peroxide,
oxidizing agent and reducing agent) generated during the
process of photo-reaction initiated upon light absorption
of the above-described initiation system and subsequent
addition-polymerization reaction, to produce new active
radicals. Such compounds are roughly classified into (a)
compound which is reduced to produce an active radical, (b)
compound which is oxidized to produce an active radical and
(c) compound which react with a radical having low activity
to convert it into a more highly active radical or act as a
chain transfer agent. However, in many cases, a common
view is not present about which compound belongs to which 
type.</p>
    <heading>(a) Compound which is reduced to produce an active
radical</heading>
    <heading>Compound having carbon-halogen bond:</heading>
    <p num="0106">An active radical is considered to be generated by
the reductive cleavage of carbon-halogen bond. Specific
examples of the compound which can be suitably used include
trihalomethyl-s-triazines and trihalomethyloxadiazoles.</p>
    <heading>Compound having nitrogen-nitrogen bond:</heading>
    <p num="0107">An active radical is considered to be generated by
the reductive cleavage of nitrogen-nitrogen bond. Specific
examples of the compound which can be suitably used include
hexaarylbiimidazoles.</p>
    <heading>Compound having oxygen-oxygen bond:</heading>
    <p num="0108">An active radical is considered to be generated by
the reductive cleavage of oxygen-oxygen bond. Specific
examples of the compound which can be suitably used include
organic peroxides.</p>
    <heading>Onium compound:</heading>
    <p num="0109">An active radical is considered to be generated by
the reductive cleavage of carbon-hetero bond or oxygen-nitrogen
bond. Specific examples of the compound which can
be suitably used include diaryliodonium salts,
triarylsulfonium salts and N-alkoxypyridinium (azinium)
salts. </p>
    <heading>Ferrocene and iron allene complexes:</heading>
    <p num="0110">An active radical can be reductively produced.</p>
    <heading>(b) Compound which is oxidized to produce an active radical
Alkylate complex:</heading>
    <p num="0111">An active radical is considered to be generated by
the oxidative cleavage of carbon-hetero bond. Specific
examples of the compound which can be suitably used include
triaryl alkylborates.</p>
    <heading>Alkylamine compound:</heading>
    <p num="0112">An active radical is considered to be generated by
the oxidative cleavage of C-X bond on the carbon adjacent
to nitrogen, where X is preferably a hydrogen atom, a
carboxyl group, a trimethylsilyl group or a benzyl group.
Specific examples of the compound include ethanolamines, N-phenylglycines
and N-trimethylsilylmethylanilines.</p>
    <heading>Sulfur- or tin-containing compound:</heading>
    <p num="0113">This is a compound in which the nitrogen atom of the
above-described amines is replaced by a sulfur atom or a
tin atom. An active radical is produced by the same action.
Also, a compound having an S-S bond is known to effect
sensitization by the cleavage of S-S.</p>
    <heading>α-Substituted methylcarbonyl compound:</heading>
    <p num="0114">An active radical is produced by the oxidative
cleavage of carbonyl-α carbon bond. The compound in which
the carbonyl is converted into an oxime ether also shows
the similar function. Specific examples of the compound 
include 2-alkyl-1-[4-(alkylthio)phenyl]-2-morpholinopronone-1
and oxime ethers thereof obtained by
the reaction with a hydroxyamine and subsequent
etherification of N-OH.</p>
    <heading>Sulfinic acid salts:</heading>
    <p num="0115">An active radical is reductively produced. Specific
examples of the compound include sodium arylsulfinate.</p>
    <heading>(c) Compound which reacts with a radical to convert it into
a more highly active radical or acts as a chain transfer
agent:</heading>
    <p num="0116">For example, compounds having SH, PH, SiH or GeH
within the molecule are used. These compounds donate
hydrogen to a low activity radical species to produce a
radical or are oxidized and deprotonized to produce a
radical. Specific examples of the compound include 2-mercaptobenzimidazoles.</p>
    <p num="0117">A large number of examples of the co-sensitizers are
more specifically described, for example, in JP-A-9-236913
as an additive for improving sensitivity. Some of these
are set forth below, however, the present invention is not
limited thereto.
<img id="img-00630001" orientation="unknown" wi="149" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00630001.tif" inline="no" he="26"/><img id="img-00640001" orientation="unknown" wi="117" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00640001.tif" inline="no" he="37"/><img id="img-00640002" orientation="unknown" wi="140" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00640002.tif" inline="no" he="26"/><img id="img-00640003" orientation="unknown" wi="90" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00640003.tif" inline="no" he="23"/></p>
    <p num="0118">Similarly to the above-described sensitizing dye, the
co-sensitizer can be subjected to various chemical
modifications so as to improve the characteristics of the
photosensitive layer. For example, methods such as binding
to the sensitizing dye, activator, addition-polymerizable
unsaturated compound or other parts, introduction of a
hydrophilic site, introduction of a substituent for
improving compatibility, inhibiting crystallization or
improving adhesion, and formation of a polymer, may be used. </p>
    <p num="0119">Of the co-sensitizers, the compound which is oxidized
to produce an active radical is preferably employed in the
photosensitive composition of the present invention in view
of increase in sensitivity. The α-substituted
methylcarbonyl compound is more preferably used and the
oxime ether compound is still more preferably used.
Although the reason for increasing the sensitivity by using
the compound which is oxidized to produce an active radical
together with the sensitizing dye having the specific
structure according to the present invention, it is
presumed that an efficiency of generating a novel active
species during the process of addition-polymerization
reaction subsequent to the light absorption increases.</p>
    <p num="0120">These co-sensitizers can be used individually or in
combination of two or more thereof. The amount of the co-sensitizer
used is from 0.05 to 100 parts by weight,
preferably from 1 to 80 parts by weight, more preferably
from 3 to 50 parts by weight, per 100 parts by weight of
the compound having an ethylenically unsaturated double
bond.</p>
    <heading>(D2) Polymerization inhibitor</heading>
    <p num="0121">In the present invention, a small amount of a thermal
polymerization inhibitor is preferably added in addition to
the above-described basic components, so as to prevent the
polymerizable compound having an ethylenically unsaturated
double bond from undergoing undesirable thermal 
polymerization during the production or storage of the
photosensitive composition. Examples of suitable thermal
polymerization inhibitors include hydroquinone, p-methoxyphenol,
di-tert-butyl-p-cresol, pyrogallol, tert-butylcatechol,
benzoquinone, 4,4'-thiobis(3-methyl-6-tert-butylphenol),
2,2'-methylenebis(4-methyl-6-tert-butyl-phenol)
and N-nitrosophenylhydroxyamine cerium(III) salt.
The amount of the thermal polymerization inhibitor added is
preferably from about 0.01 to about 5 wt%, based on the
weight of the entire composition. If desired, in order to
prevent polymerization inhibition by oxygen, a higher fatty
acid derivative such as behenic acid or behenic acid amide
may be added and when a lithographic printing plate
precursor is manufactured, allowed to localize on the
photosensitive layer surface during the drying step after
the coating on a support or the like. The amount of the
higher fatty acid derivative added is preferably from about
0.5 to about 10 wt% based on the entire composition.</p>
    <heading>(D3) Coloring agent and the like</heading>
    <p num="0122">In the case of using the photosensitive composition
of the present invention for a lithographic printing plate
precursor, a dye or a pigment may be added for the purpose
of coloring the photosensitive layer. By such a coloring,
so-called plate inspection such as visibility of the
printing plate after the plate-making or suitability for an
image density meter can be improved. Since many dyes cause 
reduction in the sensitivity of photosensitive layer, a
pigment is preferably used as the coloring agent. Specific
examples include pigments such as phthalocyanine-base
pigment, azo-base pigment, carbon black and titanium oxide,
and dyes such as Ethyl Violet, Crystal Violet, azo-base dye,
anthraquinone-base dye and cyanine-base dye. The amount of
the dye or pigment added is preferably from about 0.5 to
about 5 wt% based on the entire composition.</p>
    <heading>(D4) Other additives</heading>
    <p num="0123">In the case of using the photosensitive composition
of the present invention for a lithographic printing plate
precursor, other known additives may be further added, such
as inorganic filler and plasticizer for improving physical
properties of the hardened film, and oil-sensitizer capable
of improving the inking property on the photosensitive
layer surface.</p>
    <p num="0124">Examples of the plasticizer include dioctyl phthalate,
didodecyl phthalate, triethylene glycol dicaprylate,
dimethyl glycol phthalate, tricresyl phosphate, dioctyl
adipate, dibutyl sebacate and triacetylglycerol. In the
case of using a binder, the plasticizer can be added in an
amount of 10 wt% or less based on the total weight of the
compound having an ethylenically unsaturated double bond
and the binder.</p>
    <p num="0125">Also, a UV initiator, a heat crosslinking agent and
the like may be added for elevating the effect of heating 
and exposure after the development and thereby improving
the film strength (press life) which will be described
later.</p>
    <p num="0126">In addition, for improving the adhesion between the
photosensitive layer and a support or elevating the
developing and removing property of unexposed photosensitive
layer, an additive may be added or an interlayer
may be provided. For example, a compound showing a
relatively strong interaction with the substrate, such as
compound having a diazonium structure or phosphone compound
may be added or undercoated, whereby the adhesive property
and the press life can be enhanced. Also, by the addition
or undercoating of a hydrophilic polymer such as
polyacrylic acid or polysulfonic acid, the developability
of non-image area is improved and resistance to stain can
be improved.</p>
    <p num="0127">In the case of coating the photopolymerizable
composition of the present invention on a support to
provide a lithographic printing plate, the composition is
used after dissolving it in various organic solvents.
Examples of the solvent used here include acetone, methyl
ethyl ketone, cyclohexane, ethyl acetate, ethylene
dichloride, tetrahydrofuran, toluene, ethylene glycol
monomethyl ether, ethylene glycol monoethyl ether, ethylene
glycol dimethyl ether, propylene glycol monomethyl ether,
propylene glycol monoethyl ether, acetylacetone, 
cyclohexanone, diacetone alcohol, ethylene glycol
monomethyl ether acetate, ethylene glycol ethyl ether
acetate, ethylene glycol monoisopropyl ether, ethylene
glycol monobutyl ether acetate, 3-methoxypropanol,
methoxymethoxyethanol, diethylene glycol monomethyl ether,
diethylene glycol monoethyl ether, diethylene glycol
dimethyl ether, diethylene glycol diethyl ether, propylene
glycol monomethyl ether acetate, propylene glycol monoethyl
ether acetate, 3-methoxypropyl acetate, N,N-dimethylformamide,
dimethyl sulfoxide, γ-butyrolactone,
methyl lactate and ethyl lactate. The solvents may be used
individually or as a mixture. The concentration of solid
content in the coating solution is suitably from 2 to 50
wt%.</p>
    <p num="0128">The coverage of the photosensitive layer on the
support affects mainly the sensitivity and developability
of photosensitive layer and the strength and press life of
exposed layer and therefore, an appropriate coverage is
preferably selected according to the use end. If the
coverage is too small, press life is not sufficient,
whereas if it is excessively large, the sensitivity
decreases, as a result, not only the exposure but also the
development processing disadvantageously take a longer time.
In the case of a lithographic printing plate for scanning
exposure, which is a main object of the present invention,
the coverage is suitably, in terms of the weight after 
drying, from about 0.1 to about 10 g/m<sup>2</sup>, more preferably
from 0.5 to 5 g/m<sup>2</sup>.</p>
    <heading>[Support]</heading>
    <p num="0129">In order to obtain a lithographic printing plate as a
main object of the present invention, the above-described
photosensitive layer is preferably provided on a support
having a hydrophilic surface. As for the hydrophilic
support, conventionally known hydrophilic supports used for
lithographic printing plates can be used without any
limitation. The support used is preferably a dimensionally
stable plate-like material, such as paper, paper laminated
with plastic (e.g., polyethylene, polypropylene,
polystyrene), metal plate (e.g., aluminum, zinc, copper),
plastic film (e.g., cellulose diacetate, cellulose
triacetate, cellulose propionate, cellulose butyrate,
cellulose acetate butyrate, cellulose nitrate, polyethylene
terephthalate, polyethylene, polystyrene, polypropylene,
polycarbonate, polyvinyl acetal) and paper or plastic film
having laminated or vapor-deposited thereon the above-described
metal. If desired, the surface of the support
may be subjected to an appropriate known physical or
chemical treatment for the purpose of imparting
hydrophilicity, improving the strength or the like.</p>
    <p num="0130">Among these supports, preferred are paper, polyester
film and aluminum plate. In particular, aluminum plate is
preferred, because it has good dimensional stability, is 
relatively inexpensive and can provide a surface having
excellent hydrophilicity and strength, if desired, by a
surface treatment. Also, the composite sheet comprising an
aluminum sheet having bonded thereon a polyethylene
terephthalate film described in JP-B-48-18327 is preferred.</p>
    <p num="0131">The aluminum plate is preferably a pure aluminum
plate or an alloy plate mainly comprising aluminum and
containing trace hetero-elements. A plastic film laminated
or vapor-deposited with aluminum may also be used.
Examples of the hetero-element contained in the aluminum
alloy include silicon, iron, manganese, copper, magnesium,
chromium, zinc, bismuth, nickel and titanium. The hetero-element
content in the alloy is at most 10 wt%. The
aluminum particularly preferred in the present invention is
pure aluminum, however, since perfect pure aluminum is
difficult to produce in view of the refining technique, the
aluminum may contain trace hetero-elements. The
composition of the aluminum plate for use in the present
invention is not specified and conventionally known
aluminum plates in common use can be appropriately used.
The thickness of the aluminum plate for use in the present
invention is approximately from 0.1 to 0.6 mm, preferably
from 0.15 to 0.4 mm, more preferably from 0.2 to 0.3 mm.</p>
    <p num="0132">In the case of a support having a metal surface,
particularly an aluminum surface, the support is preferably
subjected to a surface treatment such as surface roughening 
(graining), dipping in an aqueous solution of sodium
silicate, potassium fluorozirconate or phosphate, or
anodization.</p>
    <p num="0133">The surface roughening treatment of the aluminum
plate may be performed by various methods such as a method
of mechanically roughening the surface, a method of
electrochemically dissolving and roughening the surface or
a method of selectively dissolving the surface by chemical
means. Examples of the mechanical method which can be used
include known methods such as ball graining, brush graining,
blast graining and buff graining. Examples of the
electrochemical surface roughing method include a method of
performing the surface roughening in an electrolytic
solution such as hydrochloric acid or nitric acid by
passing an alternating current or a direct current. A
combination of these two kinds of methods disclosed in JP-A-54-63902
may also be used. If desired, in order to
remove rolling oil on the surface, a degreasing treatment
with a surfactant, an organic solvent, an alkaline aqueous
solution or the like is performed in advance of the surface
roughening of the aluminum plate.</p>
    <p num="0134">An aluminum plate which is roughened and then dipped
in an aqueous sodium silicate solution may also be
preferably used. An aluminum plate subjected to an
anodization treatment and then to a dipping treatment in an
aqueous alkali metal silicate solution described in JP-B-47-5125 
is suitably used. The anodization treatment is
performed by passing a current using the aluminum plate as
anode in an aqueous or non-aqueous electrolytic solution of
an inorganic acid such as phosphoric acid, chromic acid,
sulfuric acid or boric acid, an organic acid such as oxalic
acid or sulfamic acid, or a salt thereof. These aqueous or
non-aqueous electrolytic solutions may be used individually
or in combination of two or more thereof.</p>
    <p num="0135">The silicate electrodeposition method described in
U.S. Patent 3,658,662 is also effective.</p>
    <p num="0136">Furthermore, a surface treatment in which a support
subjected to electrolytic graining is combined with the
above-described anodization treatment and sodium silicate
treatment, disclosed in JP-B-46-27481, JP-A-52-58602 and
JF-A-52-30503 is also useful.</p>
    <p num="0137">Also, a support subjected to mechanical roughening,
chemical etching, electrolytic graining, anodization and
sodium silicate treatment in this order, disclosed in JP-A-56-28893,
is suitably used.</p>
    <p num="0138">A support which is subjected to, after these
treatments, undercoating with a water-soluble resin such as
polyvinylphosphonic acid, polymer or copolymer having a
sulfonic acid group on the side chain, polyacrylic acid,
water-soluble metal salt (e.g., zinc borate), yellow dye,
amine salt or the like, is also suitably used.</p>
    <p num="0139">In addition, a substrate subjected to a sol-gel 
treatment, where a functional group capable of undergoing
an addition reaction by a radical is covalently bonded,
disclosed in JP-A-7-159983 may also be suitably used.</p>
    <p num="0140">Other preferred examples include those obtained by
providing a water-resistant hydrophilic layer as a surface
layer on an optional support. Examples of the surface
layer include a layer comprising an inorganic pigment and a
binder described in U.S. Patent 3,055,295 and JP-A-56-13168,
a hydrophilic swelling layer described in JP-A-9-80744 and
a sol-gel film comprising titanium oxide, polyvinyl alcohol
and silicic acids described in JP-W-8-507727 (the term "JP-W"
as used herein means an "unexamined published Japanese
international patent application").</p>
    <p num="0141">The hydrophilization treatment is performed not only
to render the support surface hydrophilic but also to
prevent a harmful reaction of the photopolymerizable
composition provided thereon and at the same time, to
improve adhesive property of the photosensitive layer.</p>
    <heading>[Protective layer]</heading>
    <p num="0142">In the case of a lithographic printing plate for
scanning exposure as a preferred embodiment of the present
invention, the exposure is generally performed in air and
therefore, a protective layer is preferably provided
further on the photopolymerizable composition layer. The
protective layer prevents oxygen or low molecular weight
compounds such as basic substance present in air, which 
inhibit the image forming reaction generated upon exposure
in the photosensitive layer, from permeating into the
photosensitive layer and enables exposure in air.
Accordingly, the protective layer is demanded to have the
following properties, that is, to have low permeability to
oxygen or low molecular weight compounds, not to
substantially inhibit the transmission of light used for
exposure, to exhibit good adhesion to the photosensitive
layer and to be easily removable in the development step
after exposure.</p>
    <p num="0143">Various investigations on the protective layer have
been made and are described in detail, for example, in U.S.
Patent 3,458,311 and JP-A-55-49729. The material which can
be used for the protective layer is suitably, for example,
a water-soluble polymer compound having relatively
excellent crystallinity. Specifically, water-soluble
polymers such as polyvinyl alcohol, polyvinyl pyrrolidone,
acidic celluloses, gelatin, gum arabic and polyacrylic acid
are known. Among these, when polyvinyl alcohol is used as
the main component, most excellent results can be obtained
in view of fundamental properties such as oxygen blocking
property and removability by development. The polyvinyl
alcohol used for the protective layer may be partially
substituted with an ester, an ether or an acetal insofar as
it contains an unsubstituted vinyl alcohol unit for giving
necessary oxygen blocking property and water solubility. 
Similarly, a part may have another copolymer component.</p>
    <p num="0144">Examples of the polyvinyl alcohol include those
having a hydrolysis degree of 71 to 100% and a molecular
weight of 300 to 2,400. Specific examples thereof include
PVA-105, PVA-110, PVA-117, PVA-117H, PVA-120, PVA-124, PVA-124H,
PVA-CS, PVA-CST, PVA-HC, PVA-203, PVA-204, PVA-205,
PVA-210, PVA-217, PVA-220, PVA-224, PVA-217EE, PVA-217E,
PVA-220E, PVA-224E, PVA-405, PVA-420, PVA-613 and L-8
produced by Kuraray Co., Ltd.</p>
    <p num="0145">The components (selection of PVA, use of additives)
and coating amount of the protective layer are determined
by taking account of the oxygen blocking property,
development removability, fogging, adhesive property and
scratch resistance. In general, as the hydrolysis degree
of PVA is higher (as the unsubstituted vinyl alcohol unit
content in the protective layer is higher) and as the layer
thickness is larger, the oxygen blocking property becomes
higher, which is advantageous in view of sensitivity.
However, if the oxygen blocking property is excessively
elevated, there arise problems, for example, an unnecessary
polymerization reaction takes place during the production
or stock storage, or undesirable fogging or thickening of
image lines is caused at the time of image exposure. The
adhesion to the image area and scratch resistance are also
important factors in view of handling of the plate. More
specifically, when a hydrophilic layer comprising a water-soluble 
polymer is laminated on a lipophilic polymerization
layer, delamination is liable to occur due to insufficient
adhesive strength and the delaminated part causes a defect
such as hardening failure due to polymerization inhibition
by oxygen.</p>
    <p num="0146">To overcome such a problem, various proposals have
been made with an attempt to improve the adhesive property
between these two layers. For example, U.S. Patents
292,501 and 44,563 describe a technique of mixing from 20
to 60 wt% of an acrylic emulsion or a water-insoluble vinyl
pyrrolidone-vinyl acetate copolymer in a hydrophilic
polymer mainly comprising a polyvinyl alcohol and
laminating the mixture on the polymerization layer, thereby
obtaining sufficient adhesive property. These known
techniques all can be applied to the protective layer of
the present invention. The coating method of such a
protective layer is described in detail, for example, in
U.S. Patent 3,458,311 and JP-A-55-49729.</p>
    <p num="0147">Furthermore, other functions may also be imparted to
the protective layer. For example, when a coloring agent
(e.g., water-soluble dye) having excellent transmittance of
light at 350 to 450 nm used for the exposure and capable of
efficiently absorbing light of 500 nm or more is added, the
safe light aptitude can be more improved without causing
reduction in the sensitivity.</p>
    <p num="0148">In the case where a photosensitive material using the 
photosensitive composition of the present invention is used
as an image-forming material, an image is usually obtained
by performing image exposure and then removing unexposed
area of the photosensitive layer with a developer.
Examples of the developer preferably employed for the
manufacture of a lithographic printing plate using the
photosensitive composition include a developer described in
JP-B-57-7427. The developer is suitably an aqueous
solution of an inorganic alkali agent such as sodium
silicate, potassium silicate, sodium hydroxide, potassium
hydroxide, lithium hydroxide, sodium tertiary phosphate,
sodium secondary phosphate, ammonium tertiary phosphate,
ammonium secondary phosphate, sodium metasilicate, sodium
bicarbonate and aqueous ammonia, or an aqueous solution of
an organic alkali agent such as monoethanolamine and
diethanolamine. The concentration of the alkali solution
is from 0.1 to 10 wt%, preferably from 0.5 to 5 wt%.</p>
    <p num="0149">If desired, the alkaline aqueous solution may contain
a small amount of a surface active agent or an organic
solvent such as benzyl alcohol, 2-phenoxyethanol and 2-butoxyethanol.
Examples thereof include those described in
U.S. Patents 3,375,171 and 3,615,480.</p>
    <p num="0150">The developers described in JP-A-50-26601, JP-A-58-54341,
JP-B-56-39464 and JP-B-56-42860 are also excellent.</p>
    <p num="0151">In another plate-making process of a lithographic
printing plate precursor using the photosensitive 
composition of the present invention, the entire surface
may be heated, if desired, before or during exposure or
between exposure and development. By the heating, the
image forming reaction in the photosensitive layer is
accelerated and effects such as improvement in the
sensitivity and press life and stabilization of the
sensitivity are achieved. For the purpose of improving the
image strength and press life, it is also effective to
perform entire after-heating or entire exposure of the
image after development. In general, the heating before
development is preferably performed under a mild condition
of 150°C or less. If the temperature is too high, there
arise problems such as fogging of the non-image area. The
heating after development uses a very strong condition,
usually from 200 to 500°C. If the temperature is too low,
a sufficiently high effect of strengthening the image may
not be obtained, whereas if it is excessively high, there
arise problems such as deterioration of the support and
thermal decomposition of the image area.</p>
    <p num="0152">As for the exposure method of a lithographic printing
plate for scanning exposure using the photosensitive
composition of the present invention, known methods can be
used without limitation. The light source preferably has a
wavelength of 350 to 450 nm and, specifically, an InGaN
semiconductor laser is suitably used. The exposure
mechanism may be any of internal drum system, external drum 
system and flat bed system. When the photosensitive
composition of the present invention used has high water
solubility, the photosensitive layer can be made soluble in
neutral water or alkalescent water and a lithographic
printing plate precursor having such a construction can be
loaded on a printing machine and then subjected to exposure
and development on the machine.</p>
    <p num="0153">As for the available laser light source of 350 to
450 nm, the followings can be used.</p>
    <p num="0154">A gas laser such as Ar ion laser (364 nm, 351 nm,
10 mW to 1 W), Kr ion laser (356 nm, 351 nm, 10 mW to 1 W)
and He-Cd laser (441 nm, 325 nm, 1 mW to 100 mW) may be
used.</p>
    <p num="0155">A solid laser such as a combination of Nd:YAG (YVO<sub>4</sub>)
with SHG crystals×twice (355 nm, 5 mW to 1 W) and a
combination of Cr:LiSAF with SHG crystal (430 nm, 10 mW)
may be used.</p>
    <p num="0156">A semiconductor laser system such as a KNBOb<sub>3</sub> ring
resonator (430 nm, 30 mW), a combination of a waveguide-type
wavelength conversion element with an AlGaAs or InGaAs
semiconductor (380 nm to 450 nm, 5 mW-100 mW), a
combination of a waveguide-type wavelength conversion
element with an AlGaInP or AlGaAs semiconductor (300 nm to
350 nm, 5 mW to 100 mW), and AlGaInN (350 nm to 450 nm, 5
mW to 30 mW) may be used.</p>
    <p num="0157">A pulse laser such as N<sub>2</sub> laser (337 nm, pulse 0.1 to 
10 mJ) and XeF (351 nm, pulse 10-250 mJ) may be used.</p>
    <p num="0158">Among these light sources, the AlGaInN semiconductor
laser (commercially available InGaN semiconductor laser,
400 to 410 nm, 5 to 30 mW) is particularly suitable in view
of the wavelength property and cost.</p>
    <p num="0159">As for the exposure apparatus for a lithographic
printing plate of scanning exposure system, the exposure
mechanism includes an internal drum system, an external
drum system and a flat bed system. The light source is
preferably a light source capable of continuous oscillation
among the above-described light sources. In practice, the
following exposure apparatuses are particularly preferred
in view of the relationship between the sensitivity of
photosensitive material and the plate-making time.</p>
    <p num="0160">A single to triple beam exposure apparatus of
internal drum system, using one or more gas or solid laser
light source to give a semiconductor laser having a total
output of 20 mW or more.</p>
    <p num="0161">A multi-beam (from 1 to 10 beams) exposure apparatus
of flat bed system, using one or more semiconductor, gas or
solid laser to give a total output of 20 mW or more.</p>
    <p num="0162">A multi-beam (from 1 to 9 beams) exposure apparatus
of external drum system, using a semiconductor, gas or
solid laser to give a total output of 20 mW or more.</p>
    <p num="0163">A multi-beam (10 or more beams) exposure apparatus of
external drum system, using a semiconductor or solid laser 
to give a total output of 20 mW or more.</p>
    <p num="0164">In the laser direct drawing-type lithographic
printing plates, the following equation (eq 1) is
ordinarily established among the sensitivity X (J/cm<sup>2</sup>) of
photosensitive material, the exposure area S (cm<sup>2</sup>) of
photosensitive material, the power q (w) of one laser light
source, the number n of lasers and the total exposure time
t (s) :
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">X·S=n·q·t</st32:df><sl><li>i) In the case of internal drum (single beam) system
The following equation (eq 2) is ordinarily
established among the laser revolution number f (radian/s),
the sub-scanning length Lx (cm) of photosensitive material,
the resolution Z (dot/cm) and the total exposure time t
(s) :
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">f·Z·t=Lx</st32:df></li><li>ii) In the case of external drum (multi-beam) system
The following equation (eq 3) is ordinarily
established among the drum revolution number F (radian/s),
the sub-scanning length Lx (cm) of photosensitive material,
the resolution Z (dot/cm), the total exposure time t (s)
and the number (n) of beams:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">F·Z·n·t=Lx</st32:df></li><li>iii) In the case of flat bed (multi-beam) system
The following equation (eq 4) is ordinarily 
established among the revolution number H (radian/s)
polygon mirror, the sub-scanning length Lx (cm) of
photosensitive material, the resolution Z (dot/cm), the
total exposure time t (s) and the number (n) of beams:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">F·Z·n·t=Lx</st32:df></li></sl></p>
    <p num="0165">When the resolution (2,560 dpi) required for
practical printing plate, the plate size (A1/B1, sub-scanning
length: 42 inch), the exposure condition of about
20 sheets/1 hour and the photosensitive characteristics
(photosensitive wavelength, sensitivity: about 0.1 mJ/cm<sup>2</sup>)
of the photosensitive composition of the present invention
are substituted for the above equations, it can be
understood that a photosensitive material using the
photosensitive composition of the present invention is
preferably combined with a multi-beam exposure system using
a semiconductor laser to give a total output of 20 mW or
more and on taking account of operability, cost and the
like, most preferably combined with an external drum system
semiconductor laser multi-beam (10 or more beams) exposure
apparatus.</p>
    <p num="0166">Other exposure light beams which can be used for the
photosensitive composition of the present invention include
an ultra-high pressure mercury lamp, a high pressure
mercury lamp, a medium pressure mercury lamp, a low
pressure mercury lamp, a chemical lamp, a carbon arc lamp,
a xenon lamp, a metal halide lamp, various visible or 
ultraviolet laser lamps, a fluorescent lamp, a tungsten
lamp and sunlight. As for uses, the photosensitive
composition of the present invention can be applied not
only to the lithographic printing plate for scanning
exposure but also to uses over a wide range known as uses
of photocurable resin without limitation. For example,
when applied to a liquid photopolymerizable composition
using, if desired, a cation-polymerizable compound in
combination, a high-sensitivity material for rapid
prototyping can be obtained. A hologram material may also
be prepared by making use of change in the refraction index
accompanying the photopolymerization. The photosensitive
composition of the present invention can also be applied to
various transfer materials (e.g., peelable photosensitive
material, toner development photosensitive material) by
making use of change in the adhesive property on the
surface accompanied with the photopolymerization; to photocuring
of microcapsules; to the production of electronic
materials such as photoresists; and to photocurable resin
materials such as ink, paint and adhesive.</p>
    <p num="0167">The present invention is described in greater detail
below by referring to Examples, however, the present
invention should not be construed as being limited thereto.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLES 1 TO 10 AND COMPARATIVE EXAMPLES 1 TO 6</u>
    </heading>
    <heading>(Preparation of support)</heading>
    <p num="0168">A 0.3 mm-thick aluminum plate was etched by dipping 
it in an aqueous 10 wt% sodium hydroxide solution at 60°C
for 25 seconds, washed with running water, neutralized and
cleaned with an aqueous 20 wt% nitric acid solution and
then washed with water. The aluminum plate was then
subjected to an electrolytic graining treatment in an
aqueous 1 wt% nitric acid solution using an alternating
current with a sinusoidal waveform at an anode time
electricity of 300 coulomb/dm<sup>2</sup>. Subsequently, the aluminum
plate was dipped in an aqueous 1 wt% sodium hydroxide
solution at 40°C for 5 seconds, dipped in an aqueous 30 wt%
sulfuric acid solution at 60°C for 40 seconds to effect a
desmutting treatment, and then subjected to an anodization
treatment in an aqueous 20 wt% sulfuric acid solution for 2
minutes at a current density of 2 A/dm<sup>2</sup> to form an anodic
oxide film having a thickness of 2.7 g/m<sup>2</sup>. The surface
roughness was measured and found to be 0.3 µm (Ra value
according to JIS B0601).</p>
    <p num="0169">On the back surface of the thus-treated plate, the
sol-gel reaction solution shown below was coated by a bar
coater and dried at 100°C for 1 minute, thereby preparing a
support having provided thereon a backcoat layer having a
dry coating amount of 70 mg/m<sup>2</sup>.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">Sol-gel reaction solution</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tetraethyl silicate</entry><entry align="left">50 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water</entry><entry align="left">20 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Methanol</entry><entry align="left">15 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Phosphoric acid</entry><entry align="left">0.05 parts by weight</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0170">The above components were mixed and stirred, and heat generation was started within 5 minutes. After reacting the mixture for 60 minutes, the following solution was added to prepare a coating solution for backcoat layer. <tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Pyrogallol formaldehyde condensed resin (molecular weight: 2,000)</entry><entry align="left">4 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dimethyl phthalate</entry><entry align="left">5 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fluorine-containing surfactant (N-butylperfluorooctane sulfonamidoethyl acrylate/ polyoxyethylene acrylate copolymer, molecular weight: 20,000)</entry><entry align="left">0.7 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Methanol silica sol (produced by Nissan Chemical Industries, Ltd., methanol: 30 wt%)</entry><entry align="left">50 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Methanol</entry><entry align="left">800 parts by weight</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <heading>(Preparation of photosensitive layer)</heading>
    <p num="0171">On the thus-treated aluminum plate, a photosensitive
composition having the following composition was coated to
have a dry coating amount of 1.0 g/m<sup>2</sup> and dried at 80°C for
2 minutes to form a photosensitive layer.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">(Photosensitive composition)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Pentaerythritol tetraacrylate</entry><entry align="left">1.5 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Allyl methacrylate/methacrylic acid copolymer (copolymerization molar ratio: 83/17)</entry><entry align="left">2.0 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Photopolymerization initiation system (shown in Table 2A) </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sensitizing dye</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Titanocene compound</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Co-sensitizer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fluorine-containing nonionic surfactant (F-177P)</entry><entry align="left">0.02 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Thermal polymerization inhibitor (N-nitrosophenylhydroxylamine aluminum salt)</entry><entry align="left">0.01 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coloring pigment dispersion</entry><entry align="left">2.0 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">(Composition of pigment dispersion)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Pigment Blue 15:6</entry><entry align="right">15 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Allyl methacrylate/methacrylic acid copolymer (copolymeriza tion molar ratio: 83/17)</entry><entry align="right">10 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Cyclohexanone</entry><entry align="right">15 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Methoxypropyl acetate</entry><entry align="right">20 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Propylene glycol monomethyl ether</entry><entry align="right">40 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Methyl ethyl ketone</entry><entry align="right">20.0 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Propylene glycol monomethyl ether</entry><entry align="right">20.0 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <heading>(Preparation of protective layer)</heading>
    <p num="0172">On the photosensitive layer, an aqueous solution
containing 3 wt% of polyvinyl alcohol (saponification
degree: 98 mol%, polymerization degree: 550) was coated to
have a dry coating weight of 2 g/m<sup>2</sup> and dried at 100°C for
2 minutes.</p>
    <heading>(Evaluation of photosensitivity and storage stability)</heading>
    <p num="0173">A Fuji Step Guide (a gray scale discontinuously
changing in the transmission optical density at ΔD=0.15)
manufactured by Fuji Photo Film Co., Ltd. was brought into 
close contact with the thus-obtained photosensitive
material and exposure was performed using a xenon lamp
through an optical filter. For the purpose of estimating
the exposure aptitude for a short wavelength semiconductor
laser, KENKO BP-40 capable of exposure with monochromic
light of 400 nm was used as the optical filter. Thereafter,
development was performed by dipping the photosensitive
material in a developer having the following composition at
25°C for 10 seconds, and the sensitivity (clear
sensitivity) was calculated from the highest step number
where the image was completely removed (see Table 2A). The
clear sensitivity as used herein means a minimum energy
necessary for the formation of an image and as the value is
lower, the sensitivity is higher.</p>
    <p num="0174">Separately, the photosensitive material was stored
under high temperature condition of 60°C for 3 days and
then exposed in the same manner as above so as to obtain
the same clear sensitivity as above, and energy necessary
for the formation of image was determined. A ratio of
energy (energy necessary for the formation of image after
the high temperature storage/energy necessary for the
formation of image before the high temperature storage) was
calculated. It is preferred that the ratio of energy is
1.1 or less in view of storage stability. The results of
storage stability obtained are also shown in Table 2A. <tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry nameend="6" namest="1">&lt;Examples Using Bisbenzothiazole Dye&gt;</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry nameend="4" align="center" namest="2">Photopolymerization Initiation System (amount added: g)</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">Clear Sensitivity (mJ/cm<sup>2</sup>)</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">Storage Stability (ratio of energy)</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Sensitizing Dye</entry><entry align="center">Titanocene Compound</entry><entry align="center">Co-Sensitizer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 1</entry><entry align="center">D7 (0.05)</entry><entry align="center">T-1 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">H1 (0.2)</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 2</entry><entry align="center">D13 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.12)</entry><entry align="center">H5 (0.2)</entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 3</entry><entry align="center">D16 (0.05)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry><entry align="center">1.05</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 4</entry><entry align="center">D23 (0.05)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.12)</entry><entry align="center">H1 (0.2)</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 5</entry><entry align="center">D30 (0.08)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.12)</entry><entry align="center">H5 (0.5)</entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry><entry align="center">1.05</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 6</entry><entry align="center">D1 (0.05)</entry><entry align="center">T-1 (0.10)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="center">1.05</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 7</entry><entry align="center">D7 (0.10)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">H1 (0.2)</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 8</entry><entry align="center">D23 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">T-1 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 9</entry><entry align="center">D2 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.03)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="center">1.05</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 10</entry><entry align="center">D30 (0.05)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.12)</entry><entry align="center">H1 (0.2)</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">1.05</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 1</entry><entry align="center">D7 (0.08)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">Image could not be formed</entry><entry align="center">Could not be evaluated</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 2</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">T-1 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">comparative Example 3</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.12)</entry><entry align="center">H1 (0.2)</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry><entry align="center">1.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 4</entry><entry align="center">DR-2 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 5</entry><entry align="center">DR-2 (0.12)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry><entry align="center">1.6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 6</entry><entry align="center">DR-1 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">H-3 (0.12)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">1.6</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0175">As seen from Table 2A, the lithographic printing
plate precursor according to the present invention has very
high sensitivity and exhibits sufficiently high sensitivity
for the scanning exposure system.</p>
    <p num="0176">The photopolymerization initiation system according 
to the present invention has high sensitivity as compared
with the case of using no sensitizing dye and even in the
case where the amount of titanocene added is small,
exhibits sufficiently high sensitivity.</p>
    <p num="0177">Further, the lithographic printing plate precursor of
the present invention exhibits excellent storage stability
that is sufficient for the production.</p>
    <heading>(Developer)</heading>
    <p num="0178"><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">Aqueous solution of pH 13 having the following composition:</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1K Potassium silicate</entry><entry align="right">3.0 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Potassium hydroxide</entry><entry align="right">1.5 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound of formula (7)</entry><entry align="right">0.2 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water</entry><entry align="right">95.3 parts by weight</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><img id="img-00900001" orientation="unknown" wi="90" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00900001.tif" inline="no" he="25"/>
   Pelex NBL, produced by Kao Atlas Co., Ltd.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLES 11 TO 19 AND COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 7</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0179">Lithographic printing plates were manufactured as
follows and evaluated on the printing performance. The
results are shown in Table 3A.</p>
    <heading>[Pretreatment of support]</heading>
    <p num="0180">The surface of a 0.3 mm-thick 1S aluminum plate was
grained using No. 8 nylon brush and a water suspension of
800-mesh pumice stone and then thoroughly washed with water.
Then, the aluminum plate was etched by dipping it in an 
aqueous 10 wt% sodium hydroxide solution at 70°C for 60
seconds, washed with running water, neutralized and cleaned
with an aqueous 20 wt% nitric acid solution and then washed
with water. The plate was subjected to an electrolytic
surface roughening treatment in an aqueous 1 wt% nitric
acid solution using an alternating current with a
sinusoidal waveform at an anode time electricity of
300 coulomb/dm<sup>2</sup> under the condition of V<sub>A</sub>=12.7 V. The
surface roughness was measured and found to be 0.45 µm (Ra
value according to JIS B 0601).</p>
    <heading>[Hydrophilization treatment of support surface]</heading>
    <p num="0181">The thus-treated support was dipped in an aqueous
solution containing 2.5 wt% of No. 3 sodium silicate (SiO<sub>2</sub>
= 28 to 30%, Na<sub>2</sub>O = 9 to 10%, Fe = 0.02% or less) at a pH
of 11.2 and 70°C for 13 seconds and then washed with water.
From the amount of Si element measured by fluorescent X-ray
analysis of the surface, the amount of silicate on the
surface was determined as 10 mg/m<sup>2</sup>.</p>
    <heading>[Coating of interlayer]</heading>
    <p num="0182">A coating solution having the following composition
(A) was prepared, coated on the surface of the
hydrophilized support using a whirler under the condition
of 180 rpm such that the amount of phenylphosphonic acid
coated became 20 mg/m<sup>2</sup>, and then dried at 80°C for 30
seconds. <tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">(Interlayer Coating Solution A)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Phenylphosphonic acid</entry><entry align="left">0.07 to 1.4 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Methanol</entry><entry align="left">200 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <heading>[Coating of photosensitive layer]</heading>
    <p num="0183">A photosensitive solution having the following
composition was prepared, coated on the support having
provided thereon the interlayer using a whirler to have a
coating amount of 1.0 to 2.0 g/m<sup>2</sup>, and then dried at 100°C
for 1 minute.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">(Photosensitive solution)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Addition-polymerizable compound (compound shown in Table 3A)</entry><entry align="left">1.5 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Binder polymer (compound shown in Table 3A)</entry><entry align="left">2.0 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sensitizing dye (compound shown in Table 3A)</entry><entry align="left">0.1 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Activator (compound shown in Table 3A)</entry><entry align="left">0.1 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Co-sensitizer (compound shown in Table 3A)</entry><entry align="left">0.3 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coloring pigment dispersion</entry><entry align="left">2.0 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">(Composition of pigment dispersion)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Pigment Blue 15:6</entry><entry align="right">15 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Allyl methacrylate/methacrylic acid copolymer (copolymeriza tion molar ratio: 83/17)</entry><entry align="right">10 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Cyclohexanone</entry><entry align="right">15 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Methoxypropyl acetate</entry><entry align="right">20 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Propylene glycol monomethyl ether</entry><entry align="right">40 parts by weight</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Thermal polymerization inhibitor (N-nitrosophenylhydroxylamine aluminum salt)</entry><entry align="right">0.01 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Surfactant (Megafac F-177, produced by Dainippon Ink &amp; Chemicals, Inc.)</entry><entry align="right">0.02 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Methyl ethyl ketone</entry><entry align="right">20.0 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Propylene glycol monomethyl ether</entry><entry align="right">20.0 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <heading>[Coating of protective layer]</heading>
    <p num="0184">An aqueous solution containing 3 wt% of polyvinyl
alcohol (saponification degree: 98 mol%, polymerization
degree: 550) was coated on the photosensitive layer to have
a dry coating weight of 2 g/m<sup>2</sup> and dried at 100°C for 2
minutes.</p>
    <heading>[Exposure of lithographic printing plate precursor]</heading>
    <p num="0185">The thus-obtained lithographic printing plate
precursor was subjected to solid image exposure or dot
image exposure at 175 lines/inch increasing from 1 to 99%
in 1% steps, using monochromatic light of 400 nm by
adjusting the exposure power to give an exposure energy
density of 200 µJ/cm<sup>2</sup> on the plate surface.</p>
    <heading>[Development/Plate-making]</heading>
    <p num="0186">A predetermined developer (shown in Table 3A) and
Finisher FP-2W produced by Fuji Photo Film Co., Ltd. were
charged into an automatic developing machine LP-850
manufactured by Fuji Photo Film Co., Ltd., and then the
exposed plate was subjected to development/plate-making at
a developer temperature of 30°C for a development time of
1B seconds to obtain a lithographic printing plate. </p>
    <heading>[Press life test]</heading>
    <p num="0187">Printing was conducted using R201 manufactured by
Roland Co. as a printing machine and GEOS-G (N) produced by
Dainippon Ink &amp; Chemicals, Inc. as ink. The solid image
area of the printed matter was observed and the press life
was examined by the number of prints when the image started
to become thin. As the numeral is larger, the press life
is better.</p>
    <heading>[Dot image press life test under forced condition]</heading>
    <p num="0188">Printing was conducted using R201 manufactured by
Roland Co. as a printing machine and GEOS-G (N) produced by
Dainippon Ink &amp; Chemicals, Inc. as ink. After printing of
5,000 sheets, the ink on the plate surface was cleaned by
wiping the dot image area with a sponge for printing
impregnated with PS Plate Cleaner CL-2 produced by Fuji
Photo Film Co., Ltd. Thereafter, printing of 10,000 sheets
was performed and the presence or absence of cutting of
dots on the printed matter was visually observed.</p>
    <heading>[Staining test]</heading>
    <p num="0189">Printing was conducted using R201 manufactured by
Roland Co. as a printing machine and GEOS-G (S) produced by
Dainippon Ink &amp; Chemicals, Inc. as ink. The stain was
evaluated by observing the non-image area (unexposed area)
of the printed matter. <img id="img-00950001" orientation="unknown" wi="119" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00950001.tif" inline="no" he="230"/></p>
    <heading>(Addition-polymerizable compounds)</heading>
    <p num="0190">
      <dl compact="compact" tsize="5">
        <dt>(M-1)</dt>
        <dd>Pentaerythritol tetraacrylate (NK Ester A-YMMT,
produced by Shin-Nakamura Chemical Co., Ltd.)</dd>
        <dt>(M-2)</dt>
        <dd>Glycerin dimethacrylate hexamethylene diisocyanate
urethane prepolymer (UA101H, produced by Kyoeisha
Chemical Co., Ltd.)</dd>
      </dl>
    </p>
    <heading>(Binder polymers)</heading>
    <p num="0191">
      <dl compact="compact" tsize="5">
        <dt>(B-1)</dt>
        <dd>Allyl methacrylate/methacrylic acid/N-isopropyl-acrylamide
(copolymerization molar ratio: 67/13/20)

Acid value measured by NaOH titration: 1.15 meq/g

Weight average molecular weight measured by GPC:
130,000</dd>
        <dt>(B-2)</dt>
        <dd>Allyl methacrylate/methacrylic acid copolymer
(copolymerization molar ratio 83/17)

Acid value measured by NaOH titration: 1.55 meq/g

Weight average molecular weight measured by GPC:
125,000</dd>
        <dt>(B-3)</dt>
        <dd>Polyurethane resin of a condensation polymerization
product of the following diisocyanates and diols

4,4'-Diphenylmethane diisocyanate (MDI)

Hexamethylene diisocyanate (HMDI)

Polypropylene glycol (weight average molecular
weight: 1,000) (PPG 1000)

2,2-Bis (hydroxymethyl)propionic acid (DMPA)

Copolymerization molar ratio (MDI/HMDI/PPG 1000/DMPA):
40/10/15/35
 
Acid value measured by NaOH titration: 1.05 meq/g

Weight average molecular weight measured by GPC:
45,000</dd>
      </dl>
    </p>
    <heading>(Developer)</heading>
    <heading>(DV-1)</heading>
    <p num="0192">An aqueous solution of pH 10 having the following
composition:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Monoethanolamine</entry><entry align="left">0.1 part by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Triethanolamine</entry><entry align="left">1.5 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound of the following formula (7) (Pelex NBL, produced by Kao Atlas Co., Ltd.)</entry><entry align="left">4.0 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound of the following formula (8) (Nukol B4SN, manufactured by Nippon Nyukazai Co., Ltd.)</entry><entry align="left">2.5 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound of the following formula (9)</entry><entry align="left">0.2 part by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water</entry><entry align="left">91.7 parts by weight</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><img id="img-00970001" orientation="unknown" wi="88" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00970001.tif" inline="no" he="24"/>
   Pelex NBL, produced by Kao Atlas Co., Ltd.
<img id="img-00970002" orientation="unknown" wi="96" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00970002.tif" inline="no" he="18"/>
   Nukol B4SN, produced by Nippon Nyukazai Co., Ltd. <img id="img-00980001" orientation="unknown" wi="104" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00980001.tif" inline="no" he="30"/></p>
    <heading>(DV-2)</heading>
    <p num="0193">An aqueous solution of pH 10 having the following
composition:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Sodium hydrogencarbonate</entry><entry align="right">1.2 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sodium carbonate</entry><entry align="right">0.8 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound of formula (7) (Pelex NBL, produced by Kao Atlas Co., Ltd.)</entry><entry align="right">3.0 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound of formula (8) (Nukol B4SN, produced by Nippon Nyukazai Co., Ltd.)</entry><entry align="right">2.0 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound of formula (9)</entry><entry align="right">0.2 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water</entry><entry align="right">92.8 parts by weight</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <heading>(DV-3)</heading>
    <p num="0194">An aqueous solution of pH 13 having the following
composition:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">1K Potassium silicate</entry><entry align="right">3.0 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Potassium hydroxide</entry><entry align="right">1.5 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound of formula (9)</entry><entry align="right">0.2 parts by weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water</entry><entry align="right">95.3 parts by weight</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0195">As is apparent from Table 3A, according to the
present invention, an excellent lithographic printing plate
is provided even under the condition such that plate-making
can be performed with high productivity by scanning
exposure, namely, under the very low energy exposure 
condition. On the other hand, in Comparative Example 7
wherein the initiation system of the present invention is
not used, a practically usable lithographic printing plate
cannot be obtained.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLE 20</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0196">A lithographic printing plate precursor was prepared
in the same manner as in Examples 1 to 6 except that the
initiation system was changed to the following composition
and the thickness of photopolymerization layer was changed
to 1.5 g/m<sup>2</sup>.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Initiation system</entry><entry align="center">Content based on total solid content of photopolymerizable layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sensitizing dye   D7</entry><entry align="center">1.3 wt%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Titanocene compound   T-2</entry><entry align="center">1.5 wt%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Co-sensitizer   H-1</entry><entry align="center">7.0 wt%</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0197">The resulting lithographic printing plate precursor
was subjected to scanning exposure using an InGaN
semiconductor laser having an oscillation wavelength of
400 nm under the conditions of giving a beam diameter of
25 µm and an exposure energy density of 0.2 mJ/cm<sup>2</sup> on the
plate surface. Subsequently, the plate was heated at 100°C
for 10 seconds and then developed in the same manner as in
Examples 1 to 6 above.</p>
    <p num="0198">A lithographic printing plate having a blue image
with excellent visibility was obtained. Using the thus-obtained
plate, offset printing was performed in a printing 
machine KOR-D manufactured by Heidelberg. As a result,
50,000 sheets or more of printed matters having excellent
image density and stain resistance could be obtained.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLE 21</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0199">The printing plate precursor of Example 20 was stored
for 3 days under forced storage conditions of a humidity of
65% and 45°C and then, the plate-making and printing were
performed in the same manner as in Example 20. Similarly
to Example 20, good results were obtained.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLE 22</u>
    </heading>
    <heading>(Evaluation of safelight aptitude)</heading>
    <p num="0200">Safelights commonly used were measured on the
emission intensity distribution, and the position where the
emission intensity distribution in the short-wavelength
side rose (short-wavelength end) was determined.
Furthermore, the workability under each safelight was
evaluated. The results are shown in Table 4A.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Safelight</entry><entry align="center">Short-wavelength End of Emission</entry><entry align="center">Workability</entry></row><row><entry align="left">White lamp</entry><entry align="center">400 nm</entry><entry align="left">Good.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Yellow lamp</entry><entry align="center">520 nm</entry><entry align="left">Sufficiently bright for plate-making work.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Orange lamp</entry><entry align="center">570 nm</entry><entry align="left">Considerably dark and difficult to work. Time was spent until getting accustomed to work.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Red lamp</entry><entry align="center">600 nm</entry><entry align="left">Very dark. Skill was necessary for work.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0201">On taking account of workability, a yellow lamp is
preferred. The photosensitive material capable of handling
under a yellow lamp must have low photosensitivity at least
at a wavelength of 520 nm, preferably 490 nm or more and
from this point of view, the dyes according to the present
invention are advantageous because they have the absorption
maximum in the vicinity of 400 nm.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLE 23</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0202">A lithographic printing plate precursor was prepared
in the same manner as in Example 20 except that the
initiation system was changed to the following composition
and the thickness of the photosensitive layer was changed
to 2.0 g/m<sup>2</sup>.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Initiation system</entry><entry align="center">Content based on total solid content of photopolymerizable layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sensitizing dye   D12</entry><entry align="center">1.6 wt%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Titanocene compound   T-2</entry><entry align="center">1.5 wt%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Co-sensitizer   H-1</entry><entry align="center">5.0 wt%</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0203">The resulting lithographic printing plate precursor
was subjected to scanning exposure using an InGaN
semiconductor laser having an oscillation wavelength of
400 nm under the conditions of giving a beam diameter of
25 µm and an exposure energy density of 0.15 mJ/cm<sup>2</sup> on the
plate surface. Subsequently, the plate was heated at 100°C
for 10 seconds and then developed in the same manner as in
Example 20 above. A lithographic printing plate having a 
blue image with excellent visibility was obtained. The
thus-obtained printing plate was further heated at 300°C
for 5 minutes and then, offset printing was performed in a
printing machine KOR-D manufactured by Heidelberg. As a
result, 200,000 sheets or more of printed matters having
excellent image density and stain resistance could be
obtained.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLE 24</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0204">The printing plate precursor of Example 23 was
irradiated with a yellow lamp for 30 minutes before the
exposure and using the resulting printing plate precursor,
print-making and printing were performed thoroughly in the
same manner as in Example 23. Similarly to Example 23,
good results were obtained.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 8</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0205">A lithographic printing plate precursor was prepared
in the same manner as in Example 23 except that Sensitizing
Dye D12 (absorption maximum wavelength: 415 nm) was changed
to DR-4 (absorption maximum wavelength: 500 nm). The
lithographic printing plate precursor was subjected to
plate-making in the same manner as in Example 23 using an
InGaN semiconductor laser having an oscillation wavelength
of 400 nm. As a result, the image could not be formed.
Separately, the lithographic printing plate precursor was
irradiated with a yellow lamp for 30 minutes before the
exposure in the same manner as in Example 24 and then the 
plate-making and printing were performed thoroughly in the
same manner as in Example 23. As a result, the entire
surface was fogged.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 9</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0206">A printing plate was manufactured in the same manner
as in Example 23 except that the laser was changed to FD-YAG
(532 nm). As a result, an image having a clear
sensitivity of 1.8 mJ/cm<sup>2</sup> was obtained. However, when the
lithographic printing plate precursor prepared was
irradiated with a yellow lamp for 30 minutes before the
exposure in the same manner as in Example 24 and then,
plate-making and printing were performed thoroughly in the
same manner as in Example 23, the entire surface was fogged.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLES 101 TO 110 AND COMPARATIVE EXAMPLES 101 TO 106</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0207">Photosensitive materials were prepared and evaluated
in the same manner as in Examples 1 to 10 and Comparative
Examples 1 to 6 except that the photopolymerization
initiation system in the photosensitive composition of the
photosensitive layer was changed as shown in Table 2B below.
The results obtained are shown in Table 2B. <tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry nameend="6" namest="1">&lt;Examples Using Stilbene Dye&gt;</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry nameend="4" align="center" namest="2">Photopolymerization Initiation System (amount added: g)</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">Clear Sensitivity (mJ/cm<sup>2</sup>)</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">Storage stability (ratio of energy)</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Sensitizing Dye</entry><entry align="center">Titanocene Compound</entry><entry align="center">Co-Sensitizer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 101</entry><entry align="center">D-II-5

(0.06)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">HI (0.2)</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">1.05</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 102</entry><entry align="center">D-II-12

(0.08)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.12)</entry><entry align="center">H5 (0.2)</entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 103</entry><entry align="center">D-II-3

(0.05)</entry><entry align="center">T-1 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 104</entry><entry align="center">D-II-6

(0.05)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry><entry align="center">1.05</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 105</entry><entry align="center">D-II-6

(0.06)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.12)</entry><entry align="center">H5 (0.2)</entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry><entry align="center">1.05</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 106</entry><entry align="center">D-II-8

(0.06)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.15)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry><entry align="center">1.05</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 107</entry><entry align="center">D-II-15

(0.10)</entry><entry align="center">T-1 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">H2 (0.2)</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">1.05</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 108</entry><entry align="center">D-II-8

(0.06)</entry><entry align="center">T-1 (0.03)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 109</entry><entry align="center">D-II-16

(0.06)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 110</entry><entry align="center">D-II-18

(0.06)</entry><entry align="center">T-1 (0.12)</entry><entry align="center">H1 (0.2)</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 101</entry><entry align="center">D-II-6

(0.07)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">Image could not be formed</entry><entry align="center">Could not be evaluated</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 102</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">T-1 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">none</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="center">1.6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 103</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.12)</entry><entry align="center">H1 (0.2)</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 104</entry><entry align="center">DR-2

(0.06)</entry><entry align="center">T-1 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 105</entry><entry align="center">DR-2

(0.12)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.12)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">0.9</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 106</entry><entry align="center">DR-1

(0.06)</entry><entry align="center">H-3 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="center">1.6</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0208">As seen from Table 2B, the lithographic printing
plate precursor according to the present invention has very
high sensitivity and exhibits sufficiently high sensitivity
for the scanning exposure system.</p>
    <p num="0209">The photopolymerization initiation system according
to the present invention has high sensitivity as compared
with the case of using no sensitizing dye and even in the
case where the amount of titanocene added is small,
exhibits sufficiently high sensitivity.</p>
    <p num="0210">Further, the lithographic printing plate precursor of
the present invention exhibits excellent storage stability
that is sufficient for the production.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLES 111 TO 119 AND COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 107</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0211">Lithographic printing plates were manufactured in the
same manner as in Examples 11 to 19 and Comparative Example
7 except for changing the photosensitive composition of the
photosensitive layer and the developer composition as shown
in Table 3B below, and evaluated on the printing
performance. The results obtained are shown in Table 3B.
In Table 3B, Addition-Polymerizable Compounds M-1 and M-2,
Binder Polymers B-1 to B-3 and Developer Compositions DV-1
to DV-3 were the same as those in Table 3A. <img id="img-01060001" orientation="unknown" wi="118" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="01060001.tif" inline="no" he="230"/></p>
    <p num="0212">As is apparent from Table 3B, according to the
present invention, an excellent lithographic printing plate
is provided even under the condition such that plate-making
can be performed with high productivity by scanning
exposure, namely, under the very low energy exposure
condition. On the other hand, in Comparative Example 107
wherein the initiation system of the present invention is
not used, a practically usable lithographic printing plate
cannot be obtained.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLE 120</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0213">A lithographic printing plate precursor was prepared
in the same manner as in Examples 111 to 116 except that
the initiation system was changed to the following
composition and the thickness of photopolymerization layer
was changed to 1.5 g/m<sup>2</sup>.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Initiation system</entry><entry align="center">Content based on total solid contents of photopolymerizable layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sensitizing dye   D-II-7</entry><entry align="center">1.3 wt%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Titanocene compound   T-2</entry><entry align="center">1.5 wt%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Co-sensitizer   H-1</entry><entry align="center">7.0 wt%</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0214">The obtained lithographic printing plate precursor
was subjected to scanning exposure using an InGaN
semiconductor laser having an oscillation wavelength of
400 nm under the conditions of giving a beam diameter of
25 µm and an exposure energy density of 0.2 mJ/cm<sup>2</sup> on the
plate surface. Subsequently, the plate was heated at 100°C 
for 10 seconds and then developed in the same manner as in
Examples 101 to 106 above.</p>
    <p num="0215">A lithographic printing plate having a blue image
with excellent visibility was obtained. Using the thus-obtained
plate, offset printing was performed in a printing
machine KOR-D manufactured by Heidelberg. As a result,
50,000 sheets or more of printed matters having excellent
image density and stain resistance could be obtained.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLE 121</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0216">The printing plate precursor of Example 120 was
stored for 3 days under forced storage conditions of a
humidity of 65% and 45°C and then, the plate-making and
printing were performed in the same manner as in Example
120. Similarly to Example 120, good results were obtained.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLE 122</u>
    </heading>
    <heading>(Evaluation of safelight aptitude)</heading>
    <p num="0217">Safelights commonly used were measured on the
emission intensity distribution and the position where the
emission intensity distribution in the short-wavelength
side arose (short-wavelength end) was determined.
Furthermore, the workability under each safelight was
evaluated. The results are shown in Table 4B. <tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Safelight</entry><entry align="center">Short-Wavelength End of Emission</entry><entry align="center">Workability</entry></row><row><entry align="left">White lamp</entry><entry align="center">400 nm</entry><entry align="left">Good.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Yellow lamp</entry><entry align="center">520 nm</entry><entry align="left">Sufficiently bright for plate-making work.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Orange lamp</entry><entry align="center">570 nm</entry><entry align="left">Considerably dark and difficult to work. Time was spent until getting accustomed to work.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Red lamp</entry><entry align="center">600 nm</entry><entry align="left">Very dark. Skill was necessary for work.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0218">On taking account of workability, a yellow lamp is
preferred. The photosensitive material capable of handling
under a yellow lamp must have low photosensitivity at least
at a wavelength of 520 nm, preferably 490 nm or more and
from this point of view, the dyes according to the present
invention are advantageous because they have the absorption
maximum in the vicinity of 400 nm.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLE 123</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0219">A lithographic printing plate precursor was prepared
in the same manner as in Example 120 except that the
initiation system was changed to the following composition
and the thickness of the photosensitive layer was changed
to 2.0 g/m<sup>2</sup>.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Initiation system</entry><entry align="center">Content based on total solid content of photopolymerizable layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sensitizing dye   D-II-7</entry><entry align="center">1.4 wt%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Titanocene compound   T-2</entry><entry align="center">1.5 wt% </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Co-sensitizer   H-1</entry><entry align="center">5.0 wt%</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0220">The resulting lithographic printing plate precursor
was subjected to scanning exposure using an InGaN
semiconductor laser having an oscillation wavelength of
400 nm under the conditions of giving a beam diameter of
25 µm and an exposure energy density of 0.15 mJ/cm<sup>2</sup> on the
plate surface. Subsequently, the plate was heated at 100°C
for 10 seconds and then developed in the same manner as in
Example 120 above. A lithographic printing plate having a
blue image with excellent visibility was obtained. The
thus-obtained printing plate was further heated at 300°C
for 5 minutes and then, offset printing was performed in a
printing machine KOR-D manufactured by Heidelberg. As a
result, 200,000 sheets or more of printed matters having
excellent image density and stain resistance could be
obtained.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLE 124</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0221">The printing plate precursor of Example 123 was
irradiated with a yellow lamp for 30 minutes before the
exposure and using the resulting printing plate precursor,
print-making and printing were performed thoroughly in the
same manner as in Example 123. Similarly to Example 123,
good results were obtained.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 108</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0222">A lithographic printing plate precursor was prepared
in the same manner as in Example 123 except that 
Sensitizing Dye D-II-7 (absorption maximum wavelength:
390 nm) was changed to DR-4 (absorption maximum wavelength:
500 nm). The lithographic printing plate precursor was
subjected to plate-making in the same manner as in Example
123 using an InGaN semiconductor laser having an
oscillation wavelength of 400 nm. As a result, the image
could not be formed. Separately, the lithographic printing
plate precursor was irradiated with a yellow lamp for 30
minutes before the exposure in the same manner as in
Example 124 and then the plate-making and printing were
performed thoroughly in the same manner as in Example 123.
As a result, the entire surface was fogged.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 109</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0223">A printing plate was manufactured in the same manner
as in Example 123 except that the laser was changed to FD-YAG
(532 nm). As a result, an image having a clear
sensitivity of 1.8 mJ/cm<sup>2</sup> was obtained. However, when the
lithographic printing plate precursor prepared was
irradiated with a yellow lamp for 30 minutes before the
exposure in the same manner as in Example 124 and then,
plate-making and printing were performed thoroughly in the
same manner as in Example 123, the entire surface was
fogged.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLES 201 TO 210 AND COMPARATIVE EXAMPLES 201 TO 206</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0224">Photosensitive materials were prepared and evaluated
in the same manner as in Examples 1 to 10 and Comparative 
Examples 1 to 6 except that the photopolymerization
initiation system in the photosensitive composition of the
photosensitive layer was changed as shown in Table 1C below,
The results obtained are shown in Table 1C.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry nameend="6" namest="1">&lt;Examples Using Pyrrolopyrrole Dye&gt;</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry nameend="4" align="center" namest="2">Photopolymerization Initiation System (amount added: g)</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">Clear Sensitivity (mJ/cm<sup>2</sup>)</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">Storage Stabllity (ratio of energy)</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Sensitizing Dye</entry><entry align="center">Titanocene Compound</entry><entry align="center">Co-Sensitizer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 201</entry><entry align="center">D-III-2 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">T-1 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">H1 (0.2)</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 202</entry><entry align="center">D-III-2 (0.05)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.12)</entry><entry align="center">H1 (0.2)</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">1.05</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 203</entry><entry align="center">D-III-12 (0.08)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry><entry align="center">1.05</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 204</entry><entry align="center">D-III-6 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">T-1 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">H5 (0.2)</entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 205</entry><entry align="center">D-III-18 (0.05)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.12)</entry><entry align="center">H1 (0.5)</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 206</entry><entry align="center">D-III-2 (0.05)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.15)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry><entry align="center">1.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 207</entry><entry align="center">D-III-12 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">H5 (0.2)</entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 208</entry><entry align="center">D-III-2 (0.10)</entry><entry align="center">T-1 (0.03)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="center">1.05</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 209</entry><entry align="center">D-III-3 (0.08)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 210</entry><entry align="center">D-III-1 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">T-1 (0.12)</entry><entry align="center">H1 (0.2)</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 201</entry><entry align="center">D-III-2 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">Image could not be formed</entry><entry align="center">Could not be evaluated</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 202</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">1.9</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 203</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">H1 (0.2)</entry><entry align="center">1.2</entry><entry align="center">1.6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 204</entry><entry align="center">DR-2 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">T-1 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 205</entry><entry align="center">DR-2 (0.12)</entry><entry align="center">T-2 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">1.1</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 206</entry><entry align="center">DR-1 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">H-3 (0.06)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="center">1.7</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0225">As seen from Table 1C, the lithographic printing 
plate precursor according to the present invention has very
high sensitivity and exhibits sufficiently high sensitivity
for the scanning exposure system.</p>
    <p num="0226">The photopolymerization initiation system according
to the present invention has high sensitivity as compared
with the case of using no sensitizing dye and even in the
case where the amount of titanocene added is small,
exhibits sufficiently high sensitivity.</p>
    <p num="0227">Further, the lithographic printing plate precursor of
the present invention exhibits excellent storage stability
that is sufficient for the production.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLES 211 TO 219 AND COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 207</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0228">Lithographic printing plates were manufactured in the
same manner as in Examples 11 to 19 and Comparative Example
7 except for changing the photosensitive composition of the
photosensitive layer and the developer composition as shown
in Table 2C below, and evaluated on the printing
performance. The results obtained are shown in Table 2C.
In Table 2C, Addition-Polymerizable Compounds M-1 and M-2,
Binder Polymers B-1 to B-3 and Developer Compositions DV-1
to DV-3 were the same as those in Table 3A. <img id="img-01140001" orientation="unknown" wi="109" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="01140001.tif" inline="no" he="230"/></p>
    <p num="0229">As is apparent from Table 2C, according to the
present invention, an excellent lithographic printing plate
is provided even under the condition such that plate-making
can be performed with high productivity by scanning
exposure, namely, under the very low energy exposure
condition. On the other hand, in Comparative Example 207
wherein the initiation system of the present invention is
not used, a practically usable lithographic printing plate
cannot be obtained.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLE 220</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0230">A lithographic printing plate precursor was prepared
in the same manner as in Examples 201 to 206 except that
the initiation system was changed to the following
composition and the thickness of photopolymerization layer
was changed to 1.5 g/m<sup>2</sup>.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Initiation system</entry><entry align="center">Content based on total solid contents of photopolymerizable layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sensitizing dye   D-III-3</entry><entry align="center">1.4 wt%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Titanocene compound   T-2</entry><entry align="center">1.5 wt%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Co-sensitizer   H-1</entry><entry align="center">7.0 wt%</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0231">The resulting lithographic printing plate precursor
was subjected to scanning exposure using an InGaN
semiconductor laser having an oscillation wavelength of
400 nm under the conditions of giving a beam diameter of
25 µm and an exposure energy density of 0.2 mJ/cm<sup>2</sup> on the 
plate surface. Subsequently, the plate was heated at 100°C
for 10 seconds and then developed in the same manner as in
Examples 201 to 206 above.</p>
    <p num="0232">A lithographic printing plate having a blue image
with excellent visibility was obtained. Using the thus-obtained
plate, offset printing was performed in a printing
machine KOR-D manufactured by Heidelberg. As a result,
50,000 sheets or more of printed matters having excellent
image density and stain resistance could be obtained.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLE 221</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0233">The printing plate precursor of Example 220 was
stored for 3 days under forced storage conditions of a
humidity of 65% and 45°C and then, the plate-making and
printing were performed in the same manner as in Example
220. Similarly to Example 220, good results were obtained.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLE 222</u>
    </heading>
    <heading>(Evaluation of safelight aptitude)</heading>
    <p num="0234">Safelights commonly used were measured on the
emission intensity distribution, and the position where the
emission intensity distribution in the short-wavelength
side rose (short-wavelength end) was determined.
Furthermore, the workability under each safelight was
evaluated. The results are shown in Table 3C. <tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Safelight</entry><entry align="center">Short-wavelength End of Emission</entry><entry align="center">Workability</entry></row><row><entry align="left">White lamp</entry><entry align="center">400 nm</entry><entry align="left">Good.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Yellow lamp</entry><entry align="center">520 nm</entry><entry align="left">Sufficiently bright for plate-making work.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Orange lamp</entry><entry align="center">570 nm</entry><entry align="left">Considerably dark and difficult to work. Time was spent until getting accustomed to work.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Red lamp</entry><entry align="center">600 nm</entry><entry align="left">Very dark. Skill was necessary for work.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0235">On taking account of workability, a yellow lamp is
preferred. The photosensitive material capable of handling
under a yellow lamp must have low photosensitivity at least
at a wavelength of 520 nm, preferably 490 nm or more and
from this point of view, the dyes according to the present
invention are advantageous because they have the absorption
maximum in the vicinity of 400 nm.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLE 223</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0236">A lithographic printing plate precursor was prepared
in the same manner as in Example 220 except that the
initiation system was changed to the following composition
and the thickness of the photosensitive layer was changed
to 2.0 g/m<sup>2</sup>.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Initiation system</entry><entry align="center">Content based on total solid content of photopolymerizable layer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sensitizing dye   D-III-12</entry><entry align="center">1.4 wt%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Titanocene compound   T-2</entry><entry align="center">1.5 wt% </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Co-sensitizer   H-1</entry><entry align="center">5.0 wt%</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0237">The resulting lithographic printing plate precursor
was subjected to scanning exposure using an InGaN
semiconductor laser having an oscillation wavelength of
400 nm under the conditions of giving a beam system of
25 µm and an exposure energy density of 0.15 mJ/cm<sup>2</sup> on the
plate surface. Subsequently, the plate was heated at 100°C
for 10 seconds and then developed in the same manner as in
Example 22C above. A lithographic printing plate having a
blue image with excellent visibility was obtained. The
thus-obtained printing plate was further heated at 300°C
for 5 minutes and then, offset printing was performed in a
printing machine KOR-D manufactured by Heidelberg, as a
result, 200,000 sheets or more of printed matters having
excellent image density and stain resistance could be
obtained.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">EXAMPLE 224</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0238">The printing plate precursor of Example 223 was
irradiated with a yellow lamp for 30 minutes before the
exposure and using the resulting printing plate precursor,
print-making and printing were performed thoroughly in the
same manner as in Example 223. Similarly to Example 223,
good results were obtained.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 208</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0239">A lithographic printing plate precursor was prepared 
in the same manner as in Example 223 except that
Sensitizing Dye D-III-12 (absorption maximum wavelength:
395 nm) was changed to DR-4 (absorption maximum wavelength:
500 nm). The lithographic printing plate precursor was
subjected to plate-making in the same manner as in Example
223 using an InGaN semiconductor laser having an
oscillation wavelength of 400 nm. As a result, the image
formed had streaks. Separately, the lithographic printing
plate precursor was irradiated with a yellow lamp for 30
minutes before the exposure in the same manner as in
Example 224 and then the plate-making and printing were
performed thoroughly in the same manner as in Example 223.
As a result, the entire surface was fogged.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 209</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0240">A printing plate was manufactured in the same manner
as in Example 223 except that the laser was changed to FD-YAG
(532 nm). As a result, an image having a clear
sensitivity of 1.8 mJ/cm<sup>2</sup> was obtained. However, when the
lithographic printing plate precursor prepared was
irradiated with a yellow lamp for 30 minutes before the
exposure in the same manner as in Example 224 and then,
plate-making and printing were performed thoroughly in the
same manner as in Example 223, the entire surface was
fogged.</p>
    <p num="0241">The sensitizing dyes used in Examples are described 
hereinbefore in the specification and structures of other
compounds are shown below.
<img id="img-01200001" orientation="unknown" wi="125" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01200001.tif" inline="no" he="32"/><img id="img-01200002" orientation="unknown" wi="130" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01200002.tif" inline="no" he="44"/><img id="img-01200003" orientation="unknown" wi="132" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01200003.tif" inline="no" he="34"/><img id="img-01200004" orientation="unknown" wi="79" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01200004.tif" inline="no" he="37"/></p>
    <p num="0242">As described above, the photosensitive composition of
the present invention comprises (i) a sensitizing dye
having a structure represented by formula (I), (II) or
(III), (ii) a titanocene compound and (iii) a compound of
undergoing a reaction with at least one of a radical and an
acid to change at least one of its physical and chemical
properties and maintaining the changed physical or chemical
property, whereby a lithographic printing plate precursor
using the photosensitive composition can have sufficiently
high sensitivity suitable for the scanning exposure by a
short wavelength semiconductor laser such as InGaN and
provide a lithographic printing plate excellent in the
press life and stain resistance. The lithographic printing
plate precursor for scanning exposure of the present
invention is remarkably improved in the fogging under a
yellow lamp, so that the workability of handling the
printing plate precursor can be greatly improved.
Furthermore, the photosensitive composition of the present
invention has not only excellent sensitivity but also very
excellent storage stability.</p>
    <p num="0243">The entire disclosure of each and every foreign
patent application from which the benefit of foreign
priority has been claimed in the present application is
incorporated herein by reference, as if fully set forth
herein. </p>
    <p num="0244">While the invention has been described in detail and
with reference to specific embodiments thereof, it will be
apparent to one skilled in the art that various changes and
modifications can be made therein without departing from
the spirit and scope thereof.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A photosensitive composition comprising (i) a
sensitizing dye represented by the following formula (I),
(II) or (III), (ii) a titanocene compound and (iii) a
compound of undergoing a reaction with at least one of a
radical and an acid to change at least one of its physical
and chemical properties and maintaining the changed
physical or chemical property:

wherein R1 to R8 each independently represents a hydrogen
atom, a halogen atom, a substituted or unsubstituted alkyl,
alkoxy, alkylthio, aryloxy, arylthio, alkenyl, aralkyl,
acyl, aryl, heteroaryl or alkylsulfonic acid group having
20 or less carbon atoms, and X1 and X2 each independently
represents an oxygen atom or a sulfur atom;

wherein R1 to R8 each independently represents a hydrogen
atom, a halogen atom, a substituted or unsubstituted alkyl,
alkoxy, alkylthio, aryloxy, arylthio, alkenyl, aralkyl,
acyl, aryl, heteroaryl or alkylsulfonic acid group having
20 or less carbon atoms, X represents an oxygen atom or a
sulfur atom, and A represents a substituted or
unsubstituted aryl or heteroaryl group having 20 or less
carbon atoms;

wherein Y represents an oxygen atom or a sulfur atom, Q1
represents a hydrogen atom, a methyl group, an ethyl group
or a phenyl group which may have a substituent, Q2 to Q11
each independently represents a hydrogen atom, a halogen
atom, a cyano group, a nitro group, a sulfonic acid group,
or an alkyl group having from 1 to 5 carbon atoms, which
may have a substituent.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The photosensitive composition as claimed in
Claim 1, wherein the compound of undergoing a reaction with
at least one of a radical and an acid to change at least
one of its physical and chemical properties and maintaining
the changed physical or chemical property and is an
addition-polymerizable compound having an ethylenically
unsaturated double bond.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The photosensitive composition as claimed in
Claim 1 further comprising a binder polymer comprising an
aqueous alkali-soluble or swellablle liner organic polymer.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The photosensitive composition as claimed in
Claim 1, wherein the aqueous alkali-soluble or swellablle
liner organic polymer is a urethane resin having an alkali-soluble
group.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The photosensitive composition as claimed in
Claim 1 further comprising an oxime ether compound as a co-sensitizer.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A photosensitive composition comprising (i) a
sensitizing dye represented by the following formula (I),
(II) or (III), (ii) a titanocene compound and (iii) a
radical-polymerizable compound having an ethylenically
unsaturated double bond:

wherein R1 to R8 each independently represents a hydrogen
atom, a halogen atom, a substituted or unsubstituted alkyl,
alkoxy, alkylthio, aryloxy, arylthio, alkenyl, aralkyl,
acyl, aryl, heteroaryl or alkylsulfonic acid group having
20 or less carbon atoms, and X1 and X2 each independently
represents an oxygen atom or a sulfur atom;

wherein R1 to R8 each independently represents a hydrogen
atom, a halogen atom, a substituted or unsubstituted alkyl,
alkoxy, alkylthio, aryloxy, arylthio, alkenyl, aralkyl,
acyl, aryl, heteroaryl or alkylsulfonic acid group having
20 or less carbon atoms, X represents an oxygen atom or a
sulfur atom, and A represents a substituted or
unsubstituted aryl or heteroaryl group having 20 or less
carbon atoms;

wherein Y represents an oxygen atom or a sulfur atom, Q1
represents a hydrogen atom, a methyl group, an ethyl group
or a phenyl group which may have a substituent, Q2 to Q11
each independently represents a hydrogen atom, a halogen
atom, a cyano group, a nitro group, a sulfonic acid group,
or an alkyl group having from 1 to 5 carbon atoms, which
may have a substituent.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>The photosensitive composition as claimed in
Claim 6 above further comprising a binder polymer
comprising an aqueous alkali-soluble or swellablle liner
organic polymer.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A photosensitive lithographic printing plate
comprising a support and a photosensitive layer comprising
(i) a sensitizing dye represented by the following formula
(I), (II) or (III), (ii) a titanocene compound and (iii) a
compound of undergoing a reaction with at least one of a
radical and an acid to change at least one of its physical
and chemical properties and maintaining the changed
physical or chemical property:

wherein R1 to R8 each independently represents a hydrogen
atom, a halogen atom, a substituted or unsubstituted alkyl,
alkoxy, alkylthio, aryloxy, arylthio, alkenyl, aralkyl,
acyl, aryl, heteroaryl or alkylsulfonic acid group having
20 or less carbon atoms, and X1 and X2 each independently
represents an oxygen atom or a sulfur atom;
wherein R1 to R8 each independently represents a hydrogen
atom, a halogen atom, a substituted or unsubstituted alkyl,
alkoxy, alkylthio, aryloxy, arylthio, alkenyl, aralkyl,
acyl, aryl, heteroaryl or alkylsulfonic acid group having
20 or less carbon atoms, X represents an oxygen atom or a
sulfur atom, and A represents a substituted or
unsubstituted aryl or heteroaryl group having 20 or less
carbon atoms;

wherein Y represents an oxygen atom or a sulfur atom, Q1
represents a hydrogen atom, a methyl group, an ethyl group
or a phenyl group which may have a substituent, Q2 to Q11
each independently represents a hydrogen atom, a halogen
atom, a cyano group, a nitro group, a sulfonic acid group,
or an alkyl group having from 1 to 5 carbon atoms, which
may have a substituent.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>The photosensitive lithographic printing plate
as claimed in Claim 8, wherein the compound of undergoing a
reaction with at least one of a radical and an acid to
change at least one of its physical and chemical properties
and maintaining the changed physical or chemical property
and is an addition-polymerizable compound having an
ethylenically unsaturated double bond.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>The photosensitive lithographic printing plate
as claimed in Claim 8, wherein the photosensitive layer
further comprising a binder polymer comprising an aqueous
alkali-soluble or swellablle liner organic polymer.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>The photosensitive lithographic printing plate
as claimed in Claim 10, wherein the aqueous alkali-soluble
or swellablle liner organic polymer is a urethane resin
having an alkali-soluble group.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>The photosensitive lithographic printing plate
as claimed in Claim 8 further comprising a protective layer
containing polyvinyl alcohol.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>A photopolymerization method comprising
exposing the photosensitive composition as claimed in Claim
1 with a laser beam having a wavelength of 450 nm or less.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>A method of preparing a lithographic printing
plate comprising exposing the photosensitive lithographic
printing plate as claimed in Claim 8 with a laser beam
having a wavelength of 450 nm or less and developing the
exposed photosensitive lithographic printing plate with an
aqueous alkali developing solution.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>The method of preparing a lithographic printing
plate as claimed in Claim 14, wherein the aqueous alkali
developing solution has a pH of from 9.5 to 14.0.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>The method of preparing a lithographic printing
plate as claimed in Claim 15, wherein the exposure of the
photosensitive lithographic printing plate is conducted
using a laser beam having an exposure wavelength in a range
of from 390 to 430 nm.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
