<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1246386-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1246386" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="19707407" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021002">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1246386-A1" status="new" fvid="23560954">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1246386</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20021002</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02251843-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02251843</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020314</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="KR-20010015641-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>KR</country>
          <doc-number>20010015641</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010326</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04L   5/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04L   5/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04L  27/26        20060101AFI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04L  27/26        20060101CFI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H04L   5/02Q</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Vorrichtung und Verfahren zur Datenkommunikation basierend auf OFDM</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Data communication apparatus and method based on orthogonal frequency division multiple access</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Dispositif et procédé pour la communication de données fondée sur le multiplexage par division en fréquences orthogonales</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SAMSUNG ELECTRONICS CO LTD</name>
            <address>
              <country>KR</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SAMSUNG ELECTRONICS CO., LTD.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Samsung Electronics Co., Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>416, Maetan-dong, Paldal-gu</street>
              <city>Suwon-city, Kyungki-do</city>
              <country>KR</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KIM YUNG-SOO</name>
            <address>
              <country>KR</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KIM, YUNG-SOO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>KIM, YUNG-SOO</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>109-2401 Kachi Maeul Apt. Gumi-dong Bundang-gu</street>
              <city>Seongnam-city Kyungki-do</city>
              <country>KR</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Ertl, Nicholas Justin</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Elkington and Fife, Prospect House, 8 Pembroke Road</street>
              <city>Sevenoaks, Kent TN13 1XR</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A data communication apparatus and method based on orthogonally frequency
division multiple access (OFDMA) are provided. The system comprises at
least one base station and several users. In the user transmitting unit
an encoder encodes the user information and outputs the result of encoding as user symbols.
An user signal generator generates an user signal in the time
domain from the user symbol received from the encoder. A cyclic extension
symbol inserter inserts a cyclic extension symbol into the user signal. A
signal transmitter converts the result of insertion into a symbol block signal
and transmits the symbol block signal to the base station.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="63"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to data communication, and more particularly, to
a data communication apparatus and method based on orthogonal frequency
division multiple access (OFDMA).</p>
    <p num="0002">In conventional data communication based on OFDMA, information is
transmitted from a base station to a user part in units of data symbol blocks as
follows. First, N-point inverse discrete Fourier transform (IDFT) or N-point inverse
fast Fourier transform (IFFT) is performed on information to be transmitted (N
denotes a total number of symbols to be allocated to users). A symbol block
generated by adding a cyclic prefix to the front of a sequence of main symbols
having transformed information is transmitted. As a result, in conventional data
communication based on OFDMA, an entire frequency band is divided into N small
frequency bands (or sub-carriers), and a single data symbol is transmitted through
each sub-carrier.</p>
    <p num="0003">In conventional data communication based on OFDMA, a base station
deduces user symbols from a signal received from a user part as follows. First, the
start point of each symbol block is found, and a cyclic prefix is removed. Then,
N-point DFT or N-point FFT is performed on N samples to convert the N samples
into a signal in a frequency domain. Next, signal distortion occurring in each
frequency due to a channel is compensated for, and data is detected. Here, a
cyclic prefix is added to prevent inter-block interference from occurring due to a
channel and needs to be longer than an impulse response of the channel. Here,
the value of N needs to be as large as possible in order to increase the efficiency of
conventional data communication based on OFDMA. However, with an increase in
the value of N, the size of hardware for FFT/IFFT also increases, so it is difficult to
realize conventional data communication based OFDMA.</p>
    <p num="0004">In normal data communication based on OFDMA, when a plurality of users
communicate simultaneously, as many frequencies or sub-carriers as needed are
allocated to each user to establish multiple access. Accordingly, each user part
transmits data symbols using only some frequencies, and the remaining frequencies
are not used for data transmission. Even in this case where data is transmitted at 
only some frequencies, a user part in conventional data communication based on
OFDMA must perform N-point IFFT and N-point FFT, which results in unnecessary
waste of hardware.</p>
    <p num="0005">In a multimedia wireless communication environment in which various speeds
and characteristics from a low-speed voice service to a high-speed data service exist
together, a user part, that is, a user terminal, including a user transmitting unit and a
user receiving unit provides only limited services according to its price or purpose.
For example, a low-priced terminal can provide only a low-speed data service such
as a voice service, and a high-priced terminal can provide a high-speed data service
and a video service. Accordingly, although N should be set to be large in order to
increase communication efficiency in the multimedia wireless communication
environment, N can be set to be small for a low-speed terminal. However,
conventional data communication based on OFDMA complicates the hardware and
designs of terminals.</p>
    <p num="0006">According to a first aspect of the invention, there is provided a data
communication apparatus based on OFDMA including a base station transmitting
unit which transmits user information for at least one user. The base station
transmitting unit includes first through U-th encoders among which a u-th encoder
(where 1 ≤ u ≤ U, and U indicates the number of users) encodes the user information
and outputs the result of encoding as N<sub>u</sub> u-th user symbols (where N<sub>u</sub> is the number
of symbols allocated to a u-th user); a frequency allocator for allocating different
frequencies to the user symbols received from each of the first through U-th
encoders and outputting the results of allocation; a first inverse Fourier transformer
for performing N-point inverse Fourier transform on the results of allocation received
from the frequency allocator (where N is a total number of symbols which can be
allocated to the U users); a first cyclic extension symbol inserter for inserting a cyclic
extension symbol into the result of inverse Fourier transform; and a first signal
transmitter for converting the result of insertion into a symbol block signal and
transmitting the symbol block signal to the user. The sum of N<sub>1</sub> through N<sub>U</sub> is no
greater than N.</p>
    <p num="0007">The data communication apparatus preferably further includes a user
receiving unit which receives the symbol block signal transmitted from the base
station transmitting units and estimates the u-th user symbol from the received 
symbol block signal. The user receiving unit includes a second signal receiver for
converting the received symbol block signal into a symbol block and outputting the
symbol block; a second pre-processor for finding a start point of the symbol block
received from the second signal receiver, removing the cyclic extension symbol from
the symbol block on the basis of the start point, and outputting the result r<sub>k</sub> (where "k"
indicates a time index and satisfies 0 ≤ k ≤ N-1) of removal; a user signal extractor
for extracting a signal R<sub>n</sub><sup>(u)</sup> in a frequency domain for a u-th user from the result r<sub>k</sub>
received from the second pre-processor according to the formula,
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">R<st32:sup pos="post">(u)</st32:sup><st32:sub pos="post">n</st32:sub> = BA<st32:sup pos="post">(u)</st32:sup><st32:sub pos="post">m</st32:sub>H<st32:sup pos="post">(u)</st32:sup><st32:sub pos="post">n</st32:sub> + N<st32:sup pos="post">'</st32:sup><st32:sub pos="post">n</st32:sub> ,</st32:df>
   where n is a frequency index and satisfies 0 ≤ n ≤ N<sub>n</sub>-1, B indicates a size
control factor, H<sub>n</sub><sup>(u)</sup> indicates a channel characteristic in a frequency domain, and N'<sub>u</sub>
indicates a noise characteristic in a frequency domain; a second equalizer for
removing inter-channel interference from the signal R<sub>n</sub><sup>(u)</sup> received from the user
signal extractor; and a second estimate value detector for detecting an estimate
value Â (u) / m of the u-th user symbol A<sub>m</sub><sup>(u)</sup> from the result of removal received from the
second equalizer.</p>
    <p num="0008">The first aspect of the invention also provides a data communication
apparatus based on OFDMA including U user transmitting units each of which
transmits user information to a base station part. A u-th user transmitting unit (1 ≤ u
≤ U) among the U user transmitting units includes a (U+1)-th encoder for encoding
the user information and outputting the result of encoding as N<sub>u</sub> u-th user symbols
(where N<sub>u</sub> is the number of symbols allocated to a u-th user); a user signal generator
for generating a u-th user signal x<sub>k</sub><sup>(u)</sup> in a time domain from the u-th user symbol A<sub>m</sub><sup>(u)</sup>
(where 0 ≤ m &lt; N<sub>u</sub>) received from the (U+1)-th encoder according to the formula,
x (u) / k = a (u) / k%Nu exp(j2πkn<sub>u</sub> /N), and outputting the generated u-th user signal x<sub>k</sub><sup>(u)</sup> where
0 ≤ k ≤ N-1, N is a total number of symbols which can be allocated to the U users
and is at least the sum of N<sub>1</sub> through N<sub>u</sub>, k%N<sub>u</sub> indicates the remainder when "k" is
divided by N<sub>u</sub>, a<sub>k</sub><sup>(u)</sup> indicates the result of performing inverse Fourier transform on the
N<sub>u</sub> user symbols A<sub>m</sub><sup>(u)</sup>, and n<sub>u</sub> indicates a frequency offset number allocated to a u-th
user; a second cyclic extension symbol inserter for inserting a cyclic extension
symbol into the u-th user signal; and a second signal transmitter for converting the
result of insertion into a symbol block signal and transmitting the symbol block signal
to the base station part. Here, 1 ≤ N<sub>u</sub> ≤ N. </p>
    <p num="0009">The data communication apparatus preferably further includes a base station
receiving unit which receives the symbol block signal transmitted from each of the U
user transmitting units and estimates the u-th user symbol from the received symbol
block signal. The base station receiving unit includes a first signal receiver for
converting the received symbol block signal into a symbol block and outputting the
symbol block; a first pre-processor for finding a start point of the symbol block
received from the first signal receiver, removing the cyclic extension symbol from the
symbol block on the basis of the start point, and outputting the result r<sub>k</sub> of removal; a
first Fourier transformer for performing N-point Fourier transform on the result r<sub>k</sub> of
removal received from the first pre-processor; a first equalizer for removing
inter-channel interference from the result of Fourier transform received from the first
Fourier transformer; and a first estimate value detector for detecting an estimate
value of the u-th user symbol Am(U) from the result of removal received from the first
equalizer.</p>
    <p num="0010">This first aspect of the invention provides a data communication apparatus
based on orthogonal frequency division multiple access (OFDMA), which allows a
user transmitting unit and a user receiving unit to be variably and simply realized
according to an information transmission speed.</p>
    <p num="0011">According to a second aspect of the invention, there is provided a data
communication method based on OFDMA through which the base station
transmitting unit of the data communication apparatus transmits user information to
one or more users. The data communication method includes the steps of
encoding each of U pieces of user information to obtain N<sub>u</sub> user symbols for each of
the users; allocating different frequencies to the respective user symbols for each of
the users; performing inverse Fourier transform on the results of frequency
allocation; inserting a cyclic extension symbol into the result of inverse Fourier
transform; and converting the result of insertion into a symbol block signal and
transmitting the symbol block signal to the user.</p>
    <p num="0012">The second aspect of the invention also provides a data communication
method based on OFDMA through which the u-th user transmitting unit of the data
communication apparatus transmits the user information to the base station part.
The data communication method includes the steps of encoding the user information
to obtain N<sub>u</sub> u-th user symbols; generating a u-th user signal x<sub>k</sub><sup>(u)</sup> in a time domain 
from the u-th user symbols A<sub>m</sub><sup>(u)</sup> according to the formula,
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">x<st32:sup pos="post">(u)</st32:sup><st32:sub pos="post">k</st32:sub> = a<st32:sup pos="post">(u)</st32:sup><st32:sub pos="post">k%Nu</st32:sub> exp(j2πkn<st32:sub pos="post">u</st32:sub> /N);</st32:df>
   inserting the cyclic extension symbol into the u-th user signal; and transmitting
the result of insertion to the base station part as the symbol block signal.</p>
    <p num="0013">The second aspect of the invention also provides a data communication
method based on OFDMA through which the base station receiving unit of the data
communication apparatus estimates the u-th user symbol from the received symbol
block signal. The data communication method includes the steps of converting the
received symbol block signal into the symbol block; finding the start point of the
symbol block and removing the cyclic extension symbol from the symbol block on the
basis of the start point; performing N-point Fourier transform on the result r<sub>k</sub> of
removal of the cyclic extension symbol; removing the inter-channel interference from
the result of Fourier transform; and detecting the estimate value of the u-th user
symbol A<sub>m</sub><sup>(u)</sup> from the result of removal of the inter-channel interference.</p>
    <p num="0014">The second aspect of the invention also provides a data communication
method based on OFDMA through which the user receiving unit of the data
communication apparatus estimates the u-th user symbol from the received symbol
block signal. The data communication method includes the steps of converting the
received symbol block signal into the symbol block; finding the start point of the
symbol block and removing the cyclic extension symbol from the symbol block on the
basis of the start point; extracting the signal R<sub>n</sub><sup>(u)</sup> from the result r<sub>k</sub> of removal of the
cyclic extension symbol; removing the inter-channel interference from the signal
R<sub>n</sub><sup>(u)</sup>; and detecting the estimate value Â<sup>(u)</sup><sub>m</sub> of the u-th user symbol A<sub>m</sub><sup>(u)</sup> from the
result of removal of the inter-channel interference.</p>
    <p num="0015">The second aspect of the invention also provides a data communication
method based on OFDMA through which the frequency offset number is obtained in
the data communication apparatus. The data communication method includes the
steps of (a) arranging users in order of ascending L<sub>u</sub>; (b) initializing the user index "u"
and the frequency offset number; (c) increasing the user index "u" by 1, obtaining a
value of b<sub>l</sub>0{0, 1} satisfying
<img id="img-00050001" orientation="unknown" wi="31" img-format="tif" img-content="mf" file="00050001.tif" inline="no" he="12"/>
and obtaining the frequency offset
number using
<img id="img-00050002" orientation="unknown" wi="18" img-format="tif" img-content="mf" file="00050002.tif" inline="no" he="11"/>
and (d) determining whether the user index "u" is less than 
the number of users and going to the step (c) if it is determined that the user index
"u" is less than the number of users.</p>
    <p num="0016">The second aspect of the invention provides a data communication method
based on OFDMA, which is performed by the data communication apparatus of the
first aspect of the invention, based on OFDMA.</p>
    <p num="0017">Examples of the invention will now be described in detail with reference to the
accompanying drawings, in which:
<sl><li>FIG. 1 is a schematic block diagram of a data communication apparatus
based on orthogonal frequency division multiple access (OFDMA) according to the
present invention;</li><li>FIG. 2 is a diagram of a data format illustrating relationship among a frame, a
time slot, and a symbol block;</li><li>FIG. 3 is a diagram of the format of the symbol block shown in FIG. 2;</li><li>FIG. 4 is a block diagram of a base station transmitting unit according to the
present invention;</li><li>FIG. 5 is a flowchart of a data communication method performed by the base
station transmitting unit shown in FIG. 4 according to the present invention;</li><li>FIG. 6 is a block diagram of a user transmitting unit according to the present
invention;</li><li>FIG. 7 is a flowchart of a data communication method performed by the user
transmitting unit shown in FIG. 6 according to the present invention;</li><li>FIG. 8 is a block diagram of the general example of each of the first and
second signal transmitters shown in FIGS. 4 and 6;</li><li>FIG. 9 is a block diagram of a base station receiving unit according to the
present invention;</li><li>FIG. 10 is a flowchart of a data communication method performed by the base
station receiving unit shown in FIG. 9 according to the present invention;</li><li>FIG. 11 is a block diagram of a user receiving unit according to the present
invention;</li><li>FIG. 12 is a flowchart of a data communication method performed by the user
receiving unit shown in FIG. 11 according to the present invention;</li><li>FIG. 13 is a block diagram of the general example of each of the first and
second signal receivers shown in FIGS. 9 and 11; </li><li>FIG. 14 is a flowchart of a data communication method for obtaining a
frequency offset number according to the present invention;</li><li>FIG. 15 is a diagram illustrating symbols in a frequency domain when four
users simultaneously transmit information at the same speed; and</li><li>FIG. 16 is a diagram illustrating symbols in a frequency domain when four
users simultaneously transmit information at different speeds.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0018">Hereinafter, the configuration and operations of a data communication
apparatus based on orthogonal frequency division multiple access (OFDMA)
according to the present invention will be described with reference to the attached
drawings.</p>
    <p num="0019">FIG. 1 is a schematic block diagram of a data communication apparatus
based on OFDMA according to the present invention. The data communication
apparatus includes a user part 10 having a user transmitting unit 12 and a user
receiving unit 14 and a base station part 20 having a base station receiving unit 22
and a base station transmitting unit 24.</p>
    <p num="0020">There may be as many user parts 10 communicating with the base station
part 20 as the number of users. Each of all user parts 10 communicates with the
base station part 20 as follows.</p>
    <p num="0021">Referring to FIG. 1, the user transmitting unit 12 of the data communication
apparatus according to the present invention transmits user information, which is
encoded in the form of user symbols, to the base station receiving unit 22 in symbol
block units composed of at least one main symbol and at least one additional cyclic
extension symbol. The base station receiving unit 22 receives user information
from each of the one or more user transmitting units 12 in symbol block units and
estimates a user symbol transmitted from the user part 10 using the received user
information.</p>
    <p num="0022">The base station transmitting unit 24 of the data communication apparatus of
the present invention transmits information for a certain user to the corresponding
user receiving unit 14 in symbol block units including at least one main symbol and
at least one cyclic extension symbol. Here, the user receiving unit 14 receives the
information transmitted from the base station transmitting unit 24 in symbol block
units and estimates a symbol with respect to the certain user from the received
information. </p>
    <p num="0023">Hereinafter, the format of information transmitted and received between the
user part 10 and the base station part 20 shown in FIG. 1 will be described with
reference to the attached drawings.</p>
    <p num="0024">FIG. 2 is a diagram of a data format illustrating relationship among a frame, a
time slot, and a symbol block. Referring to FIG. 2, a unit frame 30 is composed of
at least one time slot. A unit time slot 32 is composed of at least one symbol block.
When information is transmitted and received between the user part 10 and the base
station part 20 according to a data communication apparatus and method of the
present invention, a symbol block 34 can be allocated to a single user or to a
plurality of users at a time. In other words, according to the present invention, the
scheme of allocation of the symbol block 34 is not fixed within one frame but is
different among symbol slots.</p>
    <p num="0025">FIG. 3 is a diagram of the format of the symbol block 34 shown in FIG. 2.
The symbol block 34 is composed of cyclic extension symbols 40 and 44 and main
symbols 42.</p>
    <p num="0026">Referring to FIG. 3, the symbol block 34 is composed of N main symbol(s) (N
is a total number of symbols which can be allocated to all users, that is, the number
of subcarriers) 42 and N<sub>p</sub> cyclic extension symbol(s) (N<sub>p</sub> is 1 or an integer greater
than 1) 40. The symbol block 34 can additionally include N<sub>q</sub> cyclic extension
symbol(s) (N<sub>q</sub> is 1 or an integer greater than 1) 44. In other words, the cyclic
extension symbol(s) 40 is usually necessarily added at the front of the symbol block
34, but the cyclic extension symbol(s) 44 added at the rear of the symbol block 34
can be omitted. The last N<sub>p</sub> main symbol(s) of the N main symbol(s) 42 is copied to
the front of the symbol block 34 to form the cyclic extension symbol(s) 40, as
indicated by an arrow 46, and the first N<sub>q</sub> main symbol(s) of the N main symbol(s) 42
is copied to the rear of the symbol block 34 to form the cyclic extension symbol(s) 44,
as indicated by an arrow 48. Here, if N indicating the number of main symbols 42 is
set to a value of an exponential with base 2 (i.e., N ∈ {2<sup>n'</sup>|n' = 1,2,3,...}), a data
communication apparatus according to the present invention can be much more
easily realized. Here, the length N<sub>p</sub> or N<sub>q</sub> of the cyclic extension symbol(s) 40 or 44
is set to be equal to or greater than the length of a channel impulse response.
When a plurality of pieces of user information transmitted from a plurality of user
parties do not reach a base station part exactly at the same time, an arrival time
difference is included in the cyclic extension symbol(s) 40 or 44. </p>
    <p num="0027">Hereinafter, the configuration and the operations of a preferred embodiment
of the base station transmitting unit 24 according to the present invention and a data
communication method of the present invention through which the base station
transmitting unit 24 transmits corresponding user information to the user receiving
unit 14 will be described with reference to the attached drawings.</p>
    <p num="0028">FIG. 4 is a block diagram of the base station transmitting unit 24 according to
the present invention. The base station transmitting unit 24 includes first through
U-th encoders 60 through 62, a frequency allocator 64, a first inverse Fourier
transformer 66, a first cyclic extension symbol inserter 68, and a first signal
transmitter 70.</p>
    <p num="0029">FIG. 5 is a flowchart of a data communication method performed by the base
station transmitting unit 24 shown in FIG. 4 for transmission of user information
according to the present invention. In steps 90 and 92, a frequency is allocated to
each of user symbols obtained by encoding user information. In steps 94 through
98, a symbol block completed by inserting a cyclic extension symbol into the result of
performing inverse Fourier transform on the user symbols allocated frequencies is
transmitted.</p>
    <p num="0030">The base station transmitting unit 24 shown in FIG. 4 serves to transmit
corresponding user information to the at least one user receiving unit 14. For this,
in step 90, the first through U-th encoders 60 through 62 encode U pieces of user
information received through respective input terminals IN<sub>1</sub> through IN<sub>U</sub>, and each of
the first through U-th encoders 60 through 62 outputs the result of encoding to the
frequency allocator 64 as N<sub>u</sub> user symbols A<sub>m</sub><sup>(u)</sup> for each user. Here, N<sub>u</sub> is the
number of symbols allocated to a u-th user, and "u" is a user index satisfying 1 ≤ u ≤
U and 0 ≤ m &lt; N<sub>u</sub>. Here, when 1 ≤ N<sub>u</sub> ≤ N, the sum of N<sub>1</sub> through N<sub>U</sub> is no greater
than N, and N is set to a value of an exponential with base 2, as shown in Formula
(1), a data communication apparatus according to the present invention can be much
more easily realized. In addition, N<sub>u</sub> can be set to a value of an exponential with
base 2, as shown in Formula (1).
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">N∈{2<st32:sup pos="post">n'</st32:sup>|n' =1,2,3,...},  N<st32:sub pos="post">u</st32:sub>∈{2<st32:sup pos="post">n'</st32:sup>|n' = 1,2,3,...}</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0031">For example, a u-th encoder, one of the encoders 60 through 62, encodes
user information received in the form of bits through an input terminal IN<sub>u</sub> and 
outputs the result of encoding as N<sub>u</sub> user symbols A<sub>m</sub><sup>(u)</sup> for a u-th user to the
frequency allocator 64.</p>
    <p num="0032">After step 90, the frequency allocator 64 allocates different frequencies S<sub>u</sub> to
the N<sub>u</sub> user symbols A<sub>m</sub><sup>(1)</sup> through N<sub>u</sub> user symbols A<sub>m</sub><sup>(U)</sup> output from the first through
U-th encoders 60 through 62 for all of the users according to Formula (2) and
outputs the results of allocation to the first inverse Fourier Transformer 66 in step 92.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">S<st32:sub pos="post">u</st32:sub> = {n|n = mL<st32:sub pos="post">u</st32:sub> + n<st32:sub pos="post">u</st32:sub>}</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0033">Here, L<sub>u</sub> is N/ N<sub>u</sub>, and n<sub>u</sub> indicates a frequency offset number allocated to the
u-th user.</p>
    <p num="0034">To perform the step 92, the frequency allocator 64 can include a first
switching unit 80 and a first controller 82. The first switching unit 80 selects one out
of the results of encoding received from the first through U-th encoders 60 through
62 in response to a first control signal C1 received from the first controller 82, and
outputs the selected one as the result X<sub>n</sub> of frequency allocation, which is expressed
by Formula (3), to the first inverse Fourier transformer 66.
<img id="img-00100001" orientation="unknown" wi="140" img-format="tif" img-content="mf" file="00100001.tif" inline="no" he="20"/></p>
    <p num="0035">Here, "n" is a frequency index and satisfies 0 ≤ n &lt; N-1. In Formula (3), X<sub>n</sub><sup>(u)</sup>
is A<sub>m</sub><sup>(u)</sup> only when n=mL<sub>u</sub>+n<sub>u</sub>, and is otherwise 0. The first controller 82 generates
the first control signal C1 in response to L<sub>u</sub> and n<sub>u</sub> and outputs the first control signal
C1 to the first switching unit 80.</p>
    <p num="0036">After step 92, the first inverse Fourier transformer 66 performs N-point inverse
Fourier transform on the result X<sub>n</sub> of frequency allocation received from the
frequency allocator 64 and outputs the result of N-point inverse Fourier transform to
the first cyclic extension symbol inserter 68 in step 94.</p>
    <p num="0037">After step 94, the first cyclic extension symbol inserter 68 inserts the cyclic
extension symbol 40 or the cyclic extension symbols 40 and 44 into the result of
N-point inverse Fourier transform received from the first inverse Fourier transformer
66 and outputs the result of insertion to the first signal transmitter 70 in step 96. </p>
    <p num="0038">After step 96, the first signal transmitter 70 converts the result of insertion
received from the first cyclic extension symbol inserter 68 into a symbol block signal
and transmits the symbol block signal to the user receiving unit 14 in step 98.</p>
    <p num="0039">Hereinafter, the configuration and the operations of a preferred embodiment
of the user transmitting unit 12 according to the present invention and a data
communication method of the present invention through which the user transmitting
unit 12 transmits user information to the base station receiving unit 22 will be
described with reference to the attached drawings.</p>
    <p num="0040">FIG. 6 is a block diagram of the user transmitting unit 12 according to the
present invention. The user transmitting unit 12 includes a (U+1)-th encoder 100, a
user signal generator 102, a second cyclic extension symbol inserter 104, and a
second signal transmitter 106.</p>
    <p num="0041">FIG. 7 is a flowchart of a data communication method performed by the user
transmitting unit 12 shown in FIG. 6 transmitting user information to the base station
receiving unit 22 according to the present invention. In steps 120 and 122, a user
signal is generated from a user symbol obtained by encoding user information. In
steps 124 and 126, a symbol block completed by inserting a cyclic extension symbol
into the generated user signal is transmitted.</p>
    <p num="0042">The user transmitting unit 12 of FIG. 6 included in a u-th user part 10 among
the U user parts transmits corresponding user information to the base station
receiving unit 22. For this, the (U+1)-th encoder 100 encodes corresponding user
information received through an input terminal IN<sub>U+1</sub> to form a quadrature amplitude
modulation (QAM) symbol or a phase shift keying (PSK) symbol and outputs the
result of encoding to the user signal generator 102 as N<sub>u</sub> user symbols A<sub>m</sub><sup>(u)</sup> for the
u-th user in step 120.</p>
    <p num="0043">After step 120, the user signal generator 102 generates a u-th user signal x<sub>k</sub> <sup>(u)</sup>
in a time domain from the N<sub>u</sub> user symbols A<sub>m</sub><sup>(u)</sup> for the u-th user received from the
(U+1)-th encoder 100, under the condition of frequency allocation expressed by
Formula (2), as expressed by Formula (4), and outputs the generated u-th user
signal x<sub>k</sub><sup>(u)</sup> to the second cyclic extension symbol inserter 104 in step 122.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">x<st32:sup pos="post">(u)</st32:sup><st32:sub pos="post">k</st32:sub> = a<st32:sup pos="post">(u)</st32:sup><st32:sub pos="post">k%Nu</st32:sub> exp(j2πkn<st32:sub pos="post">u</st32:sub> /N)</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0044">Here, 0 ≤ k ≤ N-1, k%N<sub>u</sub> indicates the remainder when "k" is divided by N<sub>u</sub>,
a<sub>k</sub><sup>(u)</sup> (0 ≤ k &lt; N<sub>u</sub>-1) indicates the result of performing inverse Fourier transform on the
N<sub>u</sub> user symbols A<sub>m</sub> <sup>(u)</sup>, and x<sub>k</sub> <sup>(u)</sup> indicates the result of performing inverse Fourier
transform on X<sub>n</sub> <sup>(u)</sup>.</p>
    <p num="0045">For performing the step 122, the user signal generator 102 can include a
second inverse Fourier transformer 110, a block repeater 112, and a multiplier 114.
The second inverse Fourier transformer 110 performs N<sub>u</sub>-point inverse Fourier
transform on the N<sub>u</sub> user symbols A<sub>m</sub><sup>(u)</sup> for the u-th user received from the (U+1)-th
encoder 100 and outputs the N<sub>u</sub> results a<sub>k</sub><sup>(u)</sup> of N<sub>u</sub>-point inverse Fourier transform to
the block repeater 112. The block repeater 112 defines the N<sub>u</sub> results a<sub>k</sub><sup>(u)</sup> of
N<sub>u</sub>-point inverse Fourier transform received from the second inverse Fourier
transformer 110 as a single sub-block, repeats the single sub-block L<sub>u</sub> times to
generate N symbols a <sup>(u)</sup> / <sub>k'</sub>, and outputs the N symbols a <sup>(u)</sup> / <sub>k'</sub>to the multiplier 114.
Here, k' = k%N<sub>u</sub> and indicates the remainder when "k" is divided by N<sub>u</sub>. The
multiplier 114 multiplies the N symbols a<sup>(u)</sup><sub>k'</sub> received from the block repeater 112 by
γ<sub>u</sub> exp(j2πkn<sub>u</sub> / N) and outputs the result x<sub>k</sub><sup>(u)</sup> of multiplication expressed by Formula
(5) as a u-th user signal in a time domain to the second cyclic extension symbol
inserter 104.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">x<st32:sup pos="post">(u)</st32:sup><st32:sub pos="post">k</st32:sub> = a<st32:sup pos="post">(u)</st32:sup><st32:sub pos="post">k'</st32:sub> · γ<st32:sub pos="post">u</st32:sub> exp(j2πkm<st32:sub pos="post">u</st32:sub> / M)</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0046">Here, 1 ≤ k ≤ N-1, and γ<sub>u</sub> indicates a magnitude control factor for the u-th user
signal x<sub>k</sub><sup>(u)</sup>, for example, L <sup>-0.5</sup> / <sub>u</sub>.</p>
    <p num="0047">After step 122, the second cyclic extension symbol inserter 104 inserts a
cyclic extension symbol into the u-th user signal x<sub>k</sub><sup>(u)</sup> received from the user signal
generator 102 and outputs the result of insertion to the second signal transmitter 106
as a symbol block in step 124.</p>
    <p num="0048">After step 124, the second signal transmitter 106 converts the symbol block
received from the second cyclic extension symbol inserter 104 into a symbol block
signal and transmits the symbol block signal to the base station receiving unit 22 in
step 126.</p>
    <p num="0049">FIG. 8 is a block diagram of the general example of each of the first and
second signal transmitters 70 and 106 shown in FIGS. 4 and 6. Each of the first
and second signal transmitters 70 and 106 includes a digital-to-analog converter 130 
(DAC), a first low-pass filter (LPF) 132, a first local oscillator 134, a multiplier 136, a
high power amplifier (HPA) 138, and an antenna 140.</p>
    <p num="0050">Referring to FIG. 8, the DAC 130 of the first or second signal transmitter 70 or
106 converts a symbol block received from the first or second cyclic extension
symbol inserter 68 or 104 through an input terminal IN<sub>U+2</sub> into an analog signal and
outputs the analog signal to the first LPF 132. Then, the first LPF 132 performs
low-pass filtering on the analog signal received from the DAC 130 and outputs the
result of low-pass filtering to the multiplier 136. The multiplier 136 multiplies the
output of the first LPF 132 by a carrier signal having a frequency fc, which is output
from the first local oscillator 134, to thus modulate the output of the first LPF 132 to
form a signal having a center frequency of fc and outputs the result of modulation to
the HPA 138. Then, the HPA 138 amplifies the output of the multiplier 136. The
result of amplification is transmitted to the user receiving unit 14 or the base station
receiving unit 22 through the antenna 140.</p>
    <p num="0051">Hereinafter, the configuration and the operations of a preferred embodiment
of the base station receiving unit 22 according to the present invention and a data
communication method of the present invention through which the base station
receiving unit 22 estimates a user symbol will be described with reference to the
attached drawings.</p>
    <p num="0052">FIG. 9 is a block diagram of the base station receiving unit 22 according to the
present invention. The base station receiving unit 22 includes a first signal receiver
140, a first pre-processor 142, a first Fourier transformer 144, a first equalizer 146,
and a first estimate value detector 148.</p>
    <p num="0053">FIG. 10 is a flowchart of a data communication method performed by the base
station receiving unit 22 shown in FIG. 9 estimating a user symbol according to the
present invention. Fourier transform is performed on the result of removing a cyclic
extension symbol from a received symbol block in steps 160 through 164.
Inter-channel interference is removed from the result of Fourier conversion, and an
estimate value of a user symbol is detected in steps 166 and 168.</p>
    <p num="0054">The base station receiving unit 22 shown in FIG. 9 receives a symbol block
signal transmitted from the user transmitting unit 12 included in the u-th user part 10
among U user parts and estimates a u-th user symbol from the received symbol
block signal. For this, the first signal receiver 140 converts the symbol block signal 
received from the user transmitting unit 12 into a symbol block and outputs the
symbol block to the first pre-processor 142 in step 160.</p>
    <p num="0055">After step 160, the first pre-processor 142 finds the start point of the symbol
block received from the first signal receiver 140, removes a cyclic extension symbol
from the symbol block on the basis of the start point, and outputs the result r<sub>k</sub> of
removing a cyclic extension symbol to the first Fourier transformer 144 in step 162.</p>
    <p num="0056">After step 162, the first Fourier transformer 144 performs N-point Fourier
transform on the result r<sub>k</sub> received from the first pre-processor 142 and outputs the
result of N-point Fourier transform to the first equalizer 146 in step 164.</p>
    <p num="0057">After step 164, the first equalizer 146 removes inter-channel interference from
the result of N-point Fourier transform received from the first Fourier transformer 144
and outputs the result of removal to the first estimate value detector 148 in step 166.
Here, inter-channel interference indicates interference occurring when a symbol
block signal is transmitted from the user transmitting unit 12 to the base station
receiving unit 22 through a channel.</p>
    <p num="0058">After step 166, the first estimate value detector 148 detects an estimate value
Â <sup>(u)</sup> / <sub>m</sub> of a u-th user symbol A<sub>m</sub><sup>(u)</sup> from the result of removing inter-channel
interference received from the first equalizer 146 in step 168. For this, the first
estimate value detector 148 may include a detector 150, a second switching unit 152,
and a second controller 154.</p>
    <p num="0059">The detector 150 detects an estimate value X and<sub>n</sub> of X<sub>n</sub> expressed by Formula
(3) from the result of removing inter-channel interference received from the equalizer
146 and outputs the detected estimate value X and<sub>n</sub> to the second switching unit 152.
The second switching unit 152 outputs the estimate value X and<sub>n</sub> received from the
detector 150 as the estimate value Â <sup>(u)</sup> / <sub>m</sub> of the u-th user symbol in response to a
second control signal C2 received from the second controller 154. For this, like the
first controller 82, the second controller 154 generates the second control signal C2
using L<sub>u</sub> and n<sub>u</sub> and output it to the second switching unit 152.</p>
    <p num="0060">Hereinafter, the configuration and the operations of a preferred embodiment
of the user receiving unit 14 according to the present invention and a data
communication method of the present invention through which the user receiving unit
14 estimates a user symbol will be described with reference to the attached
drawings. </p>
    <p num="0061">FIG. 11 is a block diagram of the user receiving unit 14 according to the
present invention. The user receiving unit 14 includes a second signal receiver 170,
a second pre-processor 172, a user signal extractor 174, a second equalizer 176,
and a second estimate value detector 178.</p>
    <p num="0062">FIG. 12 is a flowchart of a data communication method performed by the user
receiving unit 14 shown in FIG. 11 estimating a user symbol according to the present
invention. A user signal in a frequency domain is extracted from the result of
removing a cyclic extension symbol from a received symbol block in steps 190
through 194. Inter-channel interference is removed from the user signal in a
frequency domain, and an estimate value of a user symbol is detected in steps 196
and 198.</p>
    <p num="0063">The user receiving unit 14 shown in FIG. 11 receives a symbol block signal
transmitted from the base station transmitting unit 24 and estimates a u-th user
symbol from the received symbol block signal. For this, the second signal receiver
170 converts the received symbol block signal into a symbol block and outputs the
symbol block to the second pre-processor 172 in step 190.</p>
    <p num="0064">After step 190, the second pre-processor 172 finds the start point of the
symbol block received from the second signal receiver 170, removes a cyclic
extension symbol from the symbol block on the basis of the start point, and outputs
the result r<sub>k</sub> of removing a cyclic extension symbol to the user signal extractor 174 in
step 192. The result r<sub>k</sub> is expressed by Formula (6).
<img id="img-00150001" orientation="unknown" wi="132" img-format="tif" img-content="mf" file="00150001.tif" inline="no" he="16"/></p>
    <p num="0065">Here, k=0, 1, ..., or N-1, and x<sub>k</sub> indicates a user signal before a cyclic
extension symbol is inserted by the base station transmitting unit 24. For example,
x<sub>k</sub> corresponds to the output of the first inverse Fourier transformer 66 shown in FIG.
4. In addition, (k-I+N)%N indicates the remainder when (k-I+N) is divided by N, ⊗
indicates circular convolution, and n<sub>k</sub> indicates a noise characteristic in a time
domain. In other words, for each block of r<sub>k</sub>, circular convolution is performed on a
user signal x<sub>k</sub> and a channel impulse response h<sub>k</sub>.</p>
    <p num="0066">After step 192, the user signal extractor 174 extracts a signal R<sub>n</sub><sup>(u)</sup> in a
frequency domain for a u-th user from the r<sub>k</sub>, which is received from the second 
pre-processor 172 and expressed by Formula (6), and outputs the signal R<sub>n</sub><sup>(u)</sup>
expressed by Formula (7) to the second equalizer 176 in step 194.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">R<st32:sup pos="post">(u)</st32:sup><st32:sub pos="post">n</st32:sub> = BA<st32:sup pos="post">(u)</st32:sup><st32:sub pos="post">m</st32:sub>H<st32:sup pos="post">(u)</st32:sup><st32:sub pos="post">n</st32:sub> + N'<st32:sub pos="post">n</st32:sub></st32:df></p>
    <p num="0067">Here, 0 ≤ n ≤ N<sub>n</sub>-1, B indicates a size control factor, H<sub>n</sub><sup>(u)</sup> indicates a channel
characteristic in a frequency domain, i.e., a value obtained by performing N<sub>u</sub>-point
Fourier transform on exp(-j2πkn<sub>u</sub>/N)·h<sub>k</sub>, and N'<sub>u</sub> indicates a noise characteristic in a
frequency domain.</p>
    <p num="0068">For performing the step 194, the user signal extractor 174 may include a
multiplier 180, a post-processor 182, and a second Fourier transformer 184. The
multiplier 180 multiplies the result r<sub>k</sub>, which is received from the second
pre-processor 172 and expressed by Formula (6), by α<sub>u</sub>exp(-j2πkn<sub>u</sub>/N) and outputs
the result <img id="img-00160001" orientation="unknown" wi="4" img-format="tif" img-content="ff" file="00160001.tif" inline="no" he="4"/> of multiplication expressed by Formula (8) to the post-processor 182.
<img id="img-00160002" orientation="unknown" wi="127" img-format="tif" img-content="mf" file="00160002.tif" inline="no" he="11"/></p>
    <p num="0069">Here, 0 ≤ k ≤ N-1, and α<sub>u</sub> indicates a size control factor for the result <imgref idrefs="img-00160001"/> of
multiplication. For example, α<sub>u</sub> can be set to L<sup>-0.5</sup><sub>u</sub>.</p>
    <p num="0070">Then, the post-processor 182 folds and adds the results <imgref idrefs="img-00160001"/> of multiplication
received from the multiplier 180 with a period of N<sub>v</sub> and outputs the result r<sup>(u)</sup><sub>k</sub> of
folding and addition expressed by Formula (9) to the second Fourier transformer
184.
<img id="img-00160003" orientation="unknown" wi="133" img-format="tif" img-content="mf" file="00160003.tif" inline="no" he="17"/></p>
    <p num="0071">Here, 0 ≤ k ≤ N <sub>u</sub>-1. If the result of combining Formula (6) with Formula (8) is
combined with Formula (9), r<sub>k</sub><sup>(u)</sup> expressed by Formula (9) is expressed by Formula
(10).
<img id="img-00160004" orientation="unknown" wi="144" img-format="tif" img-content="mf" file="00160004.tif" inline="no" he="20"/></p>
    <p num="0072">Here, k=0, 1, ..., or M<sub>u</sub>-1, and (k+N-I)%N<sub>u</sub> indicates the remainder when
(k+N-I) is divided by N<sub>u</sub>. If α<sub>u</sub>γ<sub>u</sub>=1/L<sub>u</sub> is set, Formula (10) can be simplified.</p>
    <p num="0073">The second Fourier transformer 184 performs N<sub>v</sub>-point Fourier transform on
the result r<sub>k</sub><sup>(u)</sup> of folding and addition, which is received from the post-processor 182
and expressed by Formula (10), and outputs the result R <sup>(u)</sup> / <sub>n</sub> of Fourier transform,
which is expressed by Formula (7), to the second equalizer 176. Accordingly, the
size control factor B in Formula (7) is a<sub>u</sub>γ<sub>u</sub>L<sub>u</sub>.</p>
    <p num="0074">After step 194, the second equalizer 176 removes inter-channel interference
from the signal R <sup>(u)</sup> / <sub>n</sub>, which is received from the user signal extractor 174 and
expressed by Formula (7), and outputs the result of removal to the second estimate
value detector 178 in step 196.</p>
    <p num="0075">After step 196, the second estimate value detector 178 detects an estimate
value Â <sup>(u)</sup> / <sub>m</sub> of a u-th user symbol A<sub>m</sub><sup>(u)</sup> from the result of removing inter-channel
interference received from the second equalizer 176 in step 198.</p>
    <p num="0076">Inverse Fourier transform performed by each of the first and second inverse
Fourier transformers 66 and 110 shown in FIGS. 4 and 6 may be inverse discrete
Fourier transform (IDFT) or inverse fast Fourier transform (IFFT). In this case,
Fourier transform performed by each of the first and second Fourier transformers
144 and 184 shown in FIGS. 9 and 11 may be DFT or FFT.</p>
    <p num="0077">FIG. 13 is a block diagram of the general example of each of the first and
second signal receivers 140 and 170. Each of the first and second signal receivers
140 and 170 includes an antenna 200, a low noise amplifier (LNA) 202, a band-pass
filter (BPF) 204, a second local oscillator 206, a multiplier 208, a second LPF 210,
and an analog-to-digital converter (ADC) 212.</p>
    <p num="0078">Referring to FIG. 13, the LNA 202 amplifies a symbol block signal received
through the antenna 200 and outputs the result of amplification to the BPF 204.
The BPF 204 performs band-pass filtering on the result of amplification received
from the LNA 202 and outputs the result of band-pass filtering to the multiplier 208.
The multiplier 208 multiplies the result of band-pass filtering received from the BPF
204 by a carrier signal having a frequency -fc received from the second local
oscillator 206 and outputs the result of multiplication as a baseband signal to the
second LPF 210. The LPF 210 performs low-pass filtering on the baseband signal
and outputs the result of low-pass filtering to the ADC 212. The ADC 212 converts
an analog signal resulting from low-pass filtering in the second LPF into a digital 
signal and outputs the digital signal as a symbol block to the first or second
pre-processor 142 or 172 through an output terminal OUT.</p>
    <p num="0079">Meanwhile, if a frequency S<sub>u</sub> allocated to each user is set as shown in
Formula (2), a frequency offset number n<sub>u</sub> must be set to satisfy Formula (11) so that
frequencies allocated to user symbols do not overlap.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">S<st32:sub pos="post">i</st32:sub> ∩ S<st32:sub pos="post">j</st32:sub> ≠ 0</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0080">Here, i≠j.</p>
    <p num="0081">Hereinafter, a data communication method for obtaining a frequency offset
number n<sub>u</sub> satisfying the condition of Formula (11) according to the present invention
will be described with reference to the attached drawings.</p>
    <p num="0082">FIG. 14 is a flowchart of a data communication method for obtaining a
frequency offset number n<sub>u</sub> according to the present invention. In steps 220
through 226, a frequency offset number n<sub>u</sub> is obtained using the value of L<sub>u</sub>.</p>
    <p num="0083">Referring to FIG. 14, a data communication method based on OFDMA
according to the present invention includes arranging U users in order of ascending
L<sub>u</sub> in step 220. After step 220, a user index "u" and a frequency offset number n<sub>u</sub>
are initialized in step 222.</p>
    <p num="0084">After step 222, the user index "u" is increased by 1, the value of b<sub>l</sub>∈{0, 1}
satisfying Formula (12) is obtained, and the frequency offset number n<sub>u</sub> expressed
by Formula (13) is obtained using b<sub>l</sub> obtained from Formula (12), in step 224.
<img id="img-00180001" orientation="unknown" wi="132" img-format="tif" img-content="mf" file="00180001.tif" inline="no" he="16"/><img id="img-00180002" orientation="unknown" wi="134" img-format="tif" img-content="mf" file="00180002.tif" inline="no" he="13"/></p>
    <p num="0085">After step 224, it is determined whether the user index "u" is less than the
number U of users in step 226. If it is determined that the user index "u" is less than
the number U of users, the procedure goes to step 224. However, if it is
determined that the user index "u" is not less than the number U of users, the
procedure shown in FIG. 14 ends. </p>
    <p num="0086">According to an embodiment of the present invention, the user index "u" and
the frequency offset number n<sub>u</sub> can be initialized to 1 and 0, respectively, in step 222.
In this case, the frequency offset number n<sub>u</sub> is obtained from Formula (13) in step
224.</p>
    <p num="0087">According to another embodiment of the present invention, the user index "u"
and the frequency offset number n<sub>u</sub> can be initialized to 1 and L<sub>1</sub>-1, respectively, in
step 222. In this case, the frequency offset number n<sub>u</sub> is obtained from Formula
(14) in step 224.
<img id="img-00190001" orientation="unknown" wi="138" img-format="tif" img-content="mf" file="00190001.tif" inline="no" he="19"/></p>
    <p num="0088">Hereinafter, the fact that a plurality of users can share a single symbol block
using the frequency offset number n<sub>u</sub> obtained as described above will be described
with reference to the attached drawings. Here, it is assumed that the number U of
users is 4.</p>
    <p num="0089">FIG. 15 is a diagram illustrating symbols X<sub>n</sub><sup>(1)</sup>, X<sub>n</sub><sup>(2)</sup>, X<sub>n</sub><sup>(3)</sup>, and X<sub>n</sub><sup>(4)</sup> in a
frequency domain when four users simultaneously transmit information at the same
speed. Referring to FIG. 15, when four users share N main symbols, that is, each
of the users transmits N<sub>u</sub> (=N/4) user symbols (L<sub>1</sub>=4, L<sub>2</sub>=4, L<sub>3</sub>=4, and L<sub>4</sub>=4),
frequency offset numbers n<sub>u</sub>, i.e., n<sub>1</sub>, n<sub>2</sub>, n<sub>3</sub>, and n<sub>4</sub>, allocated to the respective four
users are 0, 2, 1, and 3, respectively. Here, the N/4 symbols allocated to a u-th
user are repeated four times to form main symbols having a size of N. The main
symbols having a size of N have a frequency characteristic that a symbol X<sub>n</sub><sup>(1)</sup>, X<sub>n</sub><sup>(2)</sup>,
X<sub>n</sub><sup>(3)</sup>, or X<sub>n</sub><sup>(4)</sup> is non-zero only at a frequency of 4n (n=0, 1, ..., (N/4)-1) and is 0 at all
other frequencies, as shown in FIG. 15.</p>
    <p num="0090">If the frequencies of the main symbols having a size of N are shifted by the
frequency offset number n<sub>u</sub> due to multiplication of the main symbols having a size of
N by exp(j2πkn<sub>u</sub>/N), the symbol X<sub>n</sub><sup>(1)</sup>, X<sub>n</sub><sup>(2)</sup>, X<sub>n</sub><sup>(3)</sup>, or X<sub>n</sub><sup>(4)</sup> is not 0 only at a frequency
of 4n'+n<sub>u</sub> and is 0 at the other frequencies. Consequently, as shown in FIG. 15, the
symbols X<sub>n</sub><sup>(1)</sup>, X<sub>n</sub><sup>(2)</sup>, X<sub>n</sub><sup>(3)</sup>, and X<sub>n</sub><sup>(4)</sup> in a frequency domain for the four users occupy
different frequency ranges so that signals do not interfere with one another in a
frequency domain. </p>
    <p num="0091">FIG. 16 is a diagram illustrating symbols X<sub>n</sub><sup>(1)</sup>, X<sub>n</sub><sup>(2)</sup>, X<sub>n</sub><sup>(3)</sup>, and X<sub>n</sub><sup>(4)</sup> in a
frequency domain when four users simultaneously transmit information at different
speeds. Referring to FIG. 16, when four users share N main symbols in different
manners, that is, the four users transmit N/2 user symbols (L<sub>1</sub>=2), N/4 user symbols
(L<sub>2</sub>=4), N/8 user symbols (L<sub>3</sub>=8), and N/8 user symbols (L<sub>4</sub>=8), respectively,
frequency offset numbers n<sub>u</sub>, i.e., n<sub>1</sub>, n<sub>2</sub>, n<sub>3</sub>, and n<sub>4</sub>, allocated to the respective four
users are 0, 1, 3, and 7, respectively. Here, N/2 symbols are repeated two times to
form main symbols having a size of N for a first user, N/4 symbols are repeated four
times to form main symbols having a size of N for a second user, N/8 symbols are
repeated eight times to form main symbols having a size of N for a third user, and
N/8 symbols are repeated eight times to form main symbols having a size of N for a
fourth user.</p>
    <p num="0092">Next, if main symbols having a size of N are multiplied by exp(j2πkn<sub>u</sub>/N), as
shown in FIG. 16, the symbols X<sub>n</sub><sup>(1)</sup>, X<sub>n</sub><sup>(2)</sup>, X<sub>n</sub><sup>(3)</sup>, and X<sub>n</sub><sup>(4)</sup> in a frequency domain for
the four users occupy different frequency ranges so that signals do not interfere with
one another in a frequency domain.</p>
    <p num="0093">Unlike a conventional user transmitting unit using an N-point inverse Fourier
transformer, the user transmitting unit 12 shown in FIG. 6 according to the present
invention uses a single multiplier and an N<sub>u</sub>-point inverse Fourier transformer to
transmit a symbol block signal to the base station receiving unit 22. Unlike a
conventional user receiving unit using an N-point Fourier transformer, the user
receiving unit 14 shown in FIG. 11 according to the present invention uses a single
multiplier and an N<sub>u</sub>-point Fourier transformer to estimate a user symbol transmitted
from the base station transmitting unit 24.</p>
    <p num="0094">As described above, according to a data communication apparatus and
method based on OFDMA of the present invention, a user part uses an N<sub>u</sub>-point
inverse Fourier transformer and an N<sub>u</sub>-point Fourier transformer which are much
simpler in hardware than an N-point inverse Fourier transformer and an N-point
Fourier transformer when transmitting information and receiving information in units
of symbol blocks each having N main symbols. Therefore, the hardware of a user
part can be optionally simplified by appropriately determining the value of N<sub>u</sub>. Since
the hardware of a user part is not complicated, a data communication apparatus can
be easily implemented. In addition, the present invention greatly increases
communication efficiency compared to conventional data communication based on 
OFDMA in a given channel environment. According to the present invention,
different types of user parts having different complexities due to different values of N<sub>u</sub>
can communicate with a base station part using a single data format.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A data communication apparatus based on orthogonal frequency
division multiple access (OFDMA) comprising a base station transmitting unit which
transmits user information for at least one user, the base station transmitting unit
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>first through U-th encoders among which a u-th encoder (where 1 ≤ u ≤ U, and
U indicates the number of users) encodes the user information and outputs the result
of encoding as Nu u-th user symbols (where Nu is the number of symbols allocated to
a u-th user);</claim-text><claim-text>a frequency allocator for allocating different frequencies to the user symbols
received from each of the first through U-th encoders and outputting the results of
allocation;</claim-text><claim-text>a first inverse Fourier transformer for performing N-point inverse Fourier
transform on the results of allocation received from the frequency allocator (where N
is a total number of symbols which can be allocated to the U users);</claim-text><claim-text>a first cyclic extension symbol inserter for inserting a cyclic extension symbol
into the result of inverse Fourier transform; and</claim-text><claim-text>a first signal transmitter for converting the result of insertion into a symbol
block signal and transmitting the symbol block signal to the user,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the sum of N1 through NU is no greater than N.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The data communication apparatus of claim 1, wherein the frequency
allocator comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a first switching unit for selecting one out of the results of encoding received
from the first through U-th encoders in response to a first control signal and
outputting the selected one as the results Xn of allocation, which is expressed by the
following formula, to the first inverse Fourier transformer,

   where "n" is a frequency index and satisfies 0 ≤ n &lt; N, Am(U) indicates the u-th
user symbol, 0 ≤ m &lt; Nu, and if_Lu is N/ Nu and nu indicates a frequency offset
number allocated to the u-th user, Xn(u) = Am(u) only when n=mLu+nu, and, Xn(u) = 0
when n≠mLu+nu; and</claim-text><claim-text>a first controller for generating the first control signal using Lu and nu.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A data communication apparatus based on orthogonal frequency
division multiple access (OFDMA) comprising U user transmitting units each of which
transmits user information to a base station part, a u-th user transmitting unit (1 ≤ u ≤
U) among the U user transmitting units comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a (U+1)-th encoder for encoding the user information and outputting the result
of encoding as Nu u-th user symbols (where Nu is the number of symbols allocated to
a u-th user);</claim-text><claim-text>a user signal generator for generating a u-th user signal xk(u) in a time domain
from the u-th user symbol Am(u) (where 0 ≤ m &lt; Nu) received from the (U+1)-th
encoder according to the following formula and outputting the generated u-th user
signal xk(u),
x(u)k = a(u)k%Nu exp(j2πknu /N)
   where 0 ≤ k &lt; N-1, N is a total number of symbols which can be allocated to
the U users and is at least the sum of N1 through Nu, k%Nu indicates the remainder
when "k" is divided by Nu, ak(u) indicates the result of performing inverse Fourier
transform on the Nu user symbols Am(u), and nu indicates a frequency offset number
allocated to a u-th user;</claim-text><claim-text>a second cyclic extension symbol inserter for inserting a cyclic extension
symbol into the u-th user signal; and</claim-text><claim-text>a second signal transmitter for converting the result of insertion into a symbol
block signal and transmitting the symbol block signal to the base station part,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein 1 ≤ NU ≤ N.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The data communication apparatus of claim 3, wherein the user signal
generator comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a second inverse Fourier transformer for performing Nu-point inverse Fourier
transform on the Nu u-th user symbols Am(u) received from the (U+1)-th encoder and
outputting the result ak(u) of inverse Fourier transform;</claim-text><claim-text>a block repeater for repeating the result ak(u) of inverse Fourier transform Lu
(Lu = N/Nu) times to generate N symbols; and</claim-text><claim-text>a multiplier for multiplying the N symbols by γu exp(j2πknu / N) and outputting
the result of multiplication as the u-th user signal xk(u) to the second cyclic extension
symbol inserter.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The data communication apparatus of claim 4, further comprising a
base station receiving unit which receives the symbol block signal transmitted from
each of the U user transmitting units and estimates the u-th user symbol from the
received symbol block signal, the base station receiving unit comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a first signal receiver for converting the received symbol block signal into a
symbol block and outputting the symbol block;</claim-text><claim-text>a first pre-processor for finding a start point of the symbol block received from
the first signal receiver, removing the cyclic extension symbol from the symbol block
on the basis of the start point, and outputting the result rk of removal;</claim-text><claim-text>a first Fourier transformer for performing N-point Fourier transform on the
result rk of removal received from the first pre-processor;</claim-text><claim-text>a first equalizer for removing inter-channel interference from the result of
Fourier transform received from the first Fourier transformer; and</claim-text><claim-text>a first estimate value detector for detecting an estimate value of the u-th user
symbol Am(U) from the result of removal received from the first equalizer.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The data communication apparatus of claim 5, wherein the first
estimate value detector comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a detector for detecting an estimate value Xandn of Xn (where "n" is a frequency
index and satisfies 0 ≤ n ≤ N), which is expressed by the formula, from the result of
removing inter-channel interference received from the first equalizer,

   where Xn(u) indicates the u-th user signal in a frequency domain with respect to
xk(u);</claim-text><claim-text>a second switching unit for outputting the estimate value Xandn as the estimate
value of the u-th user symbol in response to a second control signal; and</claim-text><claim-text>a second controller for generating the second control signal using Lu and nu.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>The data communication apparatus of claim 1, further comprising a
user receiving unit which receives the symbol block signal transmitted from the base
station transmitting units and estimates the u-th user symbol from the received
symbol block signal, the user receiving unit comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a second signal receiver for converting the received symbol block signal into a
symbol block and outputting the symbol block;</claim-text><claim-text>a second pre-processor for finding a start point of the symbol block received
from the second signal receiver, removing the cyclic extension symbol from the
symbol block on the basis of the start point, and outputting the result rk (where "k"
indicates a time index and satisfies 0 ≤ k ≤ N-1) of removal;</claim-text><claim-text>a user signal extractor for extracting a signal Rn(u) in a frequency domain for a
u-th user from the result rk received from the second pre-processor according to the
following formula,
R(u)n = BA(u)mH(u)n + N'n
   where n is a frequency index and satisfies 0 ≤ n ≤ Nn-1, B indicates a size
control factor, Hn(u) indicates a channel characteristic in a frequency domain, and N'u
indicates a noise characteristic in a frequency domain;</claim-text><claim-text>a second equalizer for removing inter-channel interference from the signal
Rn(u) received from the user signal extractor; and</claim-text><claim-text>a second estimate value detector for detecting an estimate value Â(u)mof the
u-th user symbol Am(U) from the result of removal received from the second equalizer.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The data communication apparatus of claim 7, wherein the user signal
extractor comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a second multiplier for multiplying the result rk received from the second
pre-processor by αuexp(-j2πknu/N) (where αu indicates a size control factor) and
outputting the result of multiplication;</claim-text><claim-text>a post-processor for folding and adding the results of multiplication received
from the second multiplier with a period of Nv and outputting the result of folding and
addition; and</claim-text><claim-text>a second Fourier transformer for performing Nv-point Fourier transform on the
result of folding and addition received from the post-processor and outputting the
result of Fourier transform as the signal R(u)n.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>A data communication method based on orthogonal frequency division
multiple access (OFDMA) through which the base station transmitting unit of the data
communication apparatus of claim 1 transmits user information to one or more users,
the data communication method comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>encoding each of U pieces of user information to obtain Nu user symbols for
each of the users;</claim-text><claim-text>allocating different frequencies to the respective user symbols for each of the
users;</claim-text><claim-text>performing inverse Fourier transform on the results of frequency allocation;</claim-text><claim-text>inserting a cyclic extension symbol into the result of inverse Fourier transform;
and</claim-text><claim-text>converting the result of insertion into a symbol block signal and transmitting
the symbol block signal to the user.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>A data communication method based on orthogonal frequency division
multiple access (OFDMA) through which the u-th user transmitting unit of the data
communication apparatus of claim 3 transmits the user information to the base
station part, the data communication method comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>encoding the user information to obtain Nu u-th user symbols;</claim-text><claim-text>generating a u-th user signal xk(u) in a time domain from the u-th user symbols
Am(u) according to the following formula,
x(u)k = a(u)k%Nu exp(j2πknu / N) ;</claim-text><claim-text>inserting the cyclic extension symbol into the u-th user signal; and</claim-text><claim-text>transmitting the result of insertion to the base station part as the symbol block
signal.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>A data communication method based on orthogonal frequency division
multiple access (OFDMA) through which the base station receiving unit of the data
communication apparatus of claim 5 estimates the u-th user symbol from the
received symbol block signal, the data communication method comprising the steps
of:
<claim-text><claim-text>converting the received symbol block signal into the symbol block;</claim-text><claim-text>finding the start point of the symbol block and removing the cyclic extension
symbol from the symbol block on the basis of the start point;</claim-text><claim-text>performing N-point Fourier transform on the result rk of removal of the cyclic
extension symbol;</claim-text><claim-text>removing the inter-channel interference from the result of Fourier transform;
and</claim-text><claim-text>detecting the estimate value of the u-th user symbol Am(u) from the result of
removal of the inter-channel interference.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>A data communication method based on orthogonal frequency division
multiple access (OFDMA) through which the user receiving unit of the data
communication apparatus of claim 7 estimates the u-th user symbol from the
received symbol block signal, the data communication method comprising the steps
of:
<claim-text><claim-text>converting the received symbol block signal into the symbol block;</claim-text><claim-text>finding the start point of the symbol block and removing the cyclic extension
symbol from the symbol block on the basis of the start point;</claim-text><claim-text>extracting the signal Rn(u) from the result rk of removal of the cyclic extension
symbol;</claim-text><claim-text>removing the inter-channel interference from the signal Rn(u); and</claim-text><claim-text>detecting the estimate value Â(u)m of the u-th user symbol Am(u) from the result
of removal of the inter-channel interference.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>A data communication method based on orthogonal frequency division
multiple access (OFDMA) through which the frequency offset number is obtained in
the data communication apparatus of claim 2, the data communication method
comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) arranging users in order of ascending Lu;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) initializing the user index "u" and the frequency offset number;</claim-text><claim-text>(c) increasing the user index "u" by 1, obtaining a value of bl0{0, 1} satisfying

and obtaining the frequency offset number using

and</claim-text><claim-text>(d) determining whether the user index "u" is less than the number of users
and going to the step (c) if it is determined that the user index "u" is less than the
number of users.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>The data communication method of claim 13, wherein the step (b)
comprises initializing the user index "u" and the frequency offset number to 1 and 0,
respectively, and the step (c) comprises determining

as the frequency
offset number.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>The data communication method of claim 13, wherein the step (b)
comprises initializing the user index "u" and the frequency offset number to 1 and
L1-1, respectively, and the step (c) comprises determining

as the
frequency offset number.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
