<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1231495-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1231495" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="18898247" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020814">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1231495-A2" status="new" fvid="23512667">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1231495</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20020814</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02250844-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02250844</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020207</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001034690-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001034690</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010209</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G02B  13/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G02B  13/06        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G02B  17/08        20060101AFI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G02B  17/08        20060101CFI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03B  15/00        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03B  15/00        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03B  17/17        20060101ALI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03B  17/17        20060101CLI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03B  37/00        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03B  37/00        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04N   5/225       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H04N   5/225       20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G02B  13/06</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H04N   5/225C4</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Abbildungsvorrichtung und Verfahren zu deren Herstellung</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Imaging device and method for producing the same</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Dispositif d'imagerie et procédé pour sa fabrication</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SHARP KK</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SHARP KABUSHIKI KAISHA</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Sharp Kabushiki Kaisha</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>22-22, Nagaike-cho, Abeno-ku</street>
              <city>Osaka 545-8522</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KAKO NORITOSHI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KUMATA KIYOSHI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KURIYAMA AKIHIKO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KAKO, NORITOSHI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KUMATA, KIYOSHI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KURIYAMA, AKIHIKO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>KAKO, NORITOSHI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>2-6-47, Chiyogaoka</street>
              <city>Nara-shi, Nara</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>KUMATA, KIYOSHI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>125-10, Miyazu Sagagaito</street>
              <city>Kyotanabe-shi, Kyoto</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>KURIYAMA, AKIHIKO</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>10-57, Nakacho</street>
              <city>Tenri-shi, Nara</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Brown, Kenneth Richard</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>R.G.C. Jenkins &amp;amp; Co. 26 Caxton Street</street>
              <city>London SW1H 0RJ</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>An imaging device includes a convex mirror for
reflecting incident light representing an object, the
convex mirror having a shape of solid of revolution; an
imaging mechanism for taking an image represented by
reflected light from the convex mirror; and an optical
member for guiding the incident light toward the convex
mirror and guiding the reflected light toward the imaging
mechanism, the optical member being in close-contact with
the convex mirror.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="127" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="110"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <heading>1. FIELD OF THE INVENTION:</heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to an imaging device
capable of imaging objects in the omniazimuthal angle of
360 degrees and used in the fields of visual systems such
as, for example, surveillance cameras; and a method for
producing the same.</p>
    <heading>2. DESCRIPTION OF THE RELATED ART:</heading>
    <p num="0002">Recently in the fields of visual systems, such as,
for example, surveillance cameras, various attempts have
been made to allow a camera to perform monitoring
operations conventionally conducted by the human eye, by
combining the camera with a computer.</p>
    <p num="0003">A generally used camera, which has a limited
viewing angle, is not suitable for such applications.
Therefore, cameras using fish-eye lenses or other
wide-angle lenses have been developed. For example, in
the field of movable robots, the use of convex mirrors
having a shape of solid of revolution (such as conical
mirrors), spherical mirrors or the like, have been
actively studied. (Hereinafter, such convex mirrors 
will be referred to as "convex rotatable mirrors".)
According to systems studied in this field, an optical
image of a viewing angle of 360 degrees is taken by a convex
rotatable mirror, then the optical image is converted into
a video image, and the video image is further converted
into a desirable image by a computer.</p>
    <p num="0004">Figure <b>8A</b> shows a schematic structure of an
imaging device <b>80</b> using a conventional convex rotational
mirror, and Figure <b>8B</b> is a cross-sectional view thereof
taken along a plane including the rotation axis of a convex
rotational mirror <b>93</b> described below.</p>
    <p num="0005">The imaging device <b>80</b> includes a convex rotational
mirror unit <b>91.</b> The convex rotational mirror unit <b>91</b>
includes a generally disc-shaped base <b>92</b> and the generally
conical convex rotational mirror <b>93.</b> The imaging device
<b>80</b> further includes a generally cup-shaped, spherical
optical member <b>94.</b> The optical member <b>94</b> is open toward
the convex rotational mirror unit <b>91</b> and covers a surface
of the base <b>92</b> and the convex rotational mirror <b>93.</b> The
optical member <b>94</b> holds the convex rotational mirror unit
<b>91</b> and is formed of a light-transmissive material. An
inner circumferential surface of the optical member <b>94</b> 
and the convex rotational mirror <b>93</b> interpose a hollow
space therebetween. The optical member <b>94</b> has a thickness
which is sufficiently thin to allow light which is
incident on an outer circumferential surface of the
optical member <b>94</b> to be transmitted through the optical
member <b>94,</b> so that it is proximately parallel to light
which is directed toward the convex rotational mirror <b>93</b>
from the inner circumferential surface of the optical
member <b>94.</b> </p>
    <p num="0006">A generally cylindrical imaging mechanism <b>98</b> is
provided on the opposite side to the convex rotational
mirror unit <b>91,</b> with the optical member <b>94</b> interposed
therebetween. The imaging mechanism <b>98</b> is able to be
engaged with the optical member <b>94.</b> The imaging mechanism
<b>98</b> includes a lens <b>99</b> facing an opening of the optical
member <b>94,</b> which is formed on the opposite side to the
convex rotational mirror unit <b>91,</b> and an imaging section
<b>90</b> provided on the opposite side to the optical member
<b>94,</b> with the lens <b>99</b> interposed therebetween. The imaging
section <b>90</b> is connected to a signal processing section
<b>88</b> provided for adjusting the distortion of an image taken
by the imaging mechanism <b>98.</b> </p>
    <p num="0007">As described above, the light-transmissive
optical member <b>94</b> is used for holding the convex
rotational mirror unit <b>91,</b> and thus a separate holding
member is not provided. The reason is that if a separate
holding member is provided for holding the convex
rotational mirror unit <b>91,</b> an image of the holding member
itself would be taken and so would be a part of an image
taken by the imaging mechanism <b>98.</b></p>
    <p num="0008">As the convex rotational mirror <b>93,</b> a mirror which
reflects incident light at a surface thereof is used so
that an image formed by the reflection does not overlap
the image that is intended to be taken. The convex
rotational mirror <b>93</b> is formed of a metal material.
Alternatively, the convex rotational mirror <b>93</b> may have
a metal material, for example, vapor-deposited or plated
onto an outer circumferential surface thereof.</p>
    <p num="0009">The imaging device <b>80</b> having the above-described
structure operates as follows.</p>
    <p num="0010">Light <b>71</b> is incident on the outer circumferential
surface of the light-transmissive optical member <b>94</b> and
is transmitted through the optical member <b>94.</b> While being 
transmitted through the optical member <b>94,</b> the incident
light <b>71</b> is refracted twice (not shown) so as to become
light <b>72.</b> The light <b>72</b> is directed from the inner
circumferential surface of the optical member <b>94</b> toward
the convex rotational mirror <b>93</b> through the hollow space
between the optical member <b>94</b> and the convex rotational
mirror <b>93.</b> Then, the light <b>72</b> is reflected by the convex
rotational mirror <b>93</b> and is directed toward the imaging
mechanism <b>98</b> as reflected light <b>81.</b> The reflected light
<b>81</b> is transmitted through the lens <b>99</b> of the imaging
mechanism <b>98</b> and incident on the imaging section <b>90.</b> The
imaging section <b>90</b> transforms the reflected light <b>81</b> into
an image signal representing an image and outputs the
image signal to the signal processing section <b>88.</b> The
signal processing section <b>88</b> processes the received image
signal so as to adjust the distortion of the image.</p>
    <p num="0011">The conventional imaging device <b>80</b> has the
following problems.
<sl><li>(1) An outer surface of the convex rotational
mirror <b>93</b> is exposed to the air filling the hollow space
between the optical member <b>94</b> and the convex rotational
mirror <b>93.</b> Therefore, the metal on the surface of the 
convex rotational mirror <b>93</b> is oxidized, or the metal
material vapor-deposited or plated onto the surface of
the convex rotational mirror <b>93</b> is exfoliated. As a
result, the reflectance of the light incident on the
convex rotational mirror <b>93</b> is lowered.</li><li>(2) Dust, moisture or the like which invades into
the hollow space between the optical member <b>94</b> and the
convex rotational mirror <b>93</b> through the gap between the
base <b>92</b> and the optical member <b>94,</b> causes noise to the
light <b>72</b> and the reflected light <b>81.</b> Therefore, the
quality of the image taken by the imaging mechanism <b>98</b>
is degraded.
When the imaging device <b>80</b> having the above-described
problem is used outdoors or the like for an
extended period of time, external factors such as
temperature, moisture, ultraviolet rays or the like cause
the following problems. The metal material of the convex
rotational mirror <b>93</b> is oxidized and thus corroded. When
the metal material is vapor-deposited or plated onto the
surface of the convex rotational mirror <b>93,</b> such metal
material is exfoliated or corroded. It is necessary to
prevent exfoliation and corrosion of the metal material 
and also to prevent dust or moisture from entering the
connection part of the optical member <b>94</b> and the convex
rotational mirror <b>93.</b></li><li>(3) The optical member <b>94</b> is hollow and therefore
is mechanically weak and easy to break. In actual use,
specific care needs to be taken to avoid breakage.</li></sl></p>
    <heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0012">According to one aspect of the invention, an
imaging device includes a convex mirror for reflecting
incident light representing an object, the convex mirror
having a shape of solid of revolution; an imaging
mechanism for taking an image represented by reflected
light from the convex mirror; and an optical member for
guiding the incident light toward the convex mirror and
guiding the reflected light toward the imaging mechanism,
the optical member being in close-contact with the convex
mirror.</p>
    <p num="0013">In one embodiment of the invention, the optical
member has a concave portion which is in close-contact
with the convex mirror so as to cover the convex mirror. </p>
    <p num="0014">In one embodiment of the invention, the convex
mirror is formed of a thin layer of a material having a
mirror-surface effect, the thin layer being provided on
the concave portion.</p>
    <p num="0015">In one embodiment of the invention, the convex
mirror is formed of a metal material.</p>
    <p num="0016">In one embodiment of the invention, the convex
mirror is formed of aluminum.</p>
    <p num="0017">In one embodiment of the invention, the convex
mirror is formed as a result of vapor-deposition,
sputtering or plating of a material having a mirror-surface
effect.</p>
    <p num="0018">In one embodiment of the invention, the imaging
mechanism includes a lens for converging the reflected
light, and an imaging section for taking an image
represented by the reflected light converged by the lens;
and the lens is integrally formed with the optical member.</p>
    <p num="0019">In one embodiment of the invention, the imaging 
mechanism includes a lens for converging the reflected
light, and an imaging section for taking an image
represented by the reflected light converged by the lens;
and the lens is in close-contact with the optical member.</p>
    <p num="0020">In one embodiment of the invention, the optical
member has a refractive index which is smaller than the
refractive index of the lens.</p>
    <p num="0021">In one embodiment of the invention, the optical
member has an outer circumferential surface formed so as
to cause the incident light to be incident thereon in a
direction normal to the outer circumferential surface.</p>
    <p num="0022">In one embodiment of the invention, the optical
member has a reflected light releasing face formed so as
to cause the reflected light directed toward the imaging
mechanism to be incident thereon in a direction normal
to the reflected light releasing face.</p>
    <p num="0023">In one embodiment of the invention, the reflected
light releasing face is a part of a surface of a circle
having, as the center, a focal point at which the reflected
light is converged. </p>
    <p num="0024">According to another aspect of the invention, a
method for producing the above-described imaging device
includes the steps of causing the optical member to be
in close-contact with the convex mirror so that the
optical member covers the convex mirror; and attaching
the imaging mechanism to the optical member so that the
reflected light is incident on the imaging mechanism.</p>
    <p num="0025">Hereinafter, the function of the present
invention will be described.</p>
    <p num="0026">According to the present invention, the optical
member formed of a light-transmissive material is
provided in close-contact with a surface of the convex
rotational mirror, so as to cover the convex rotational
mirror. Therefore, even when the imaging device is
subjected to external heat, ultraviolet rays or the like,
the surface of the convex rotational mirror is not
deteriorated due to oxidation or the like, nor is the
vapor-deposited or plated metal material exfoliated.
Thus, the reflectance of the convex rotational mirror is
not reduced. Since the optical member is provided in
close-contact with the convex rotational mirror so as to 
cover the convex rotational mirror, dust, moisture or the
like can be prevented from entering between the convex
rotational mirror and the optical member. As a result,
noise to the light incident on the convex rotational
mirror or noise to the light reflected by the convex
rotational mirror is not generated. The structure of the
optical member in close-contact with the convex
rotational mirror also increases the mechanical strength
of the optical member compared to the conventional
structure having the hollow optical member, thus
providing a wider viewing angle.</p>
    <p num="0027">In a structure where the optical member is formed
of a material having a smaller refractive index than that
of the lens, the optical member need not be formed of a
material having a large refractive index and thus need
not be expensive, as described below in a second example
of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0028">In a structure where the optical member and the
lens are formed of the same material, the optical member
and the lens can be integrally formed. Therefore, the
adjustment of the lens with respect to the optical member
is not necessary and the number of components of the 
optical system can be reduced, as described below in a
first example of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0029">In a structure where the reflected light releasing
face of the optical member is formed so as to cause the
reflected light directed toward the imaging mechanism to
be incident thereon in a direction normal to the reflected
light releasing face, the optical system can be easily
designed as described below in a third example of the
present invention (Figures <b>5</b> and <b>6</b>). In the case where
the reflected light is designed to be converged on a
prescribed focal point, the reflected light releasing
face may be formed so as to be a part of the surface of
a circle having the focal point as the center.</p>
    <p num="0030">In a structure where a thin layer of a material
having a mirror-surface effect is provided on the concave
portion of the optical member, the thin layer acts as a
convex rotational mirror. In this case, the convex
rotational mirror and the optical member can be integrally
produced and the size of the imaging device is reduced.
The production process of the imaging device is also
simplified. </p>
    <p num="0031">The convex rotational mirror may be formed of a
convex surface of a member formed of a metal material.</p>
    <p num="0032">Aluminum, silver, platinum, a nickel-chromium
alloy, gold and the like are suitable metal materials for
producing a mirror-surface effect. Aluminum is optimum
to reduce the cost of the imaging device.</p>
    <p num="0033">Thus, the invention described herein makes
possible the advantages of providing (1) an imaging
device for preventing reduction in the reflectance of
light incident on a convex rotational mirror, and a method
for producing the same; and (2) an imaging device for
preventing dust, moisture or the like from entering
between a convex rotational mirror and an optical member,
and a method for producing the same.</p>
    <p num="0034">These and other advantages of the present
invention will become apparent to those skilled in the
art upon reading and understanding the following detailed
description with reference to the accompanying figures. </p>
    <heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
    <p num="0035">
      <sl>
        <li>Figure <b>1A</b> shows a schematic structure of an
imaging device according to a first example of the present
invention, and Figure <b>1B</b> is a cross-sectional view
thereof;</li>
        <li>Figure <b>2A</b> shows a schematic structure of another
imaging device according to the first example of the
present invention, and Figure <b>2B</b> is a cross-sectional view
thereof;</li>
        <li>Figure <b>3A</b> shows a schematic structure of still
another imaging device according to the first example of
the present invention, and Figure <b>3B</b> is a cross-sectional
view thereof;</li>
        <li>Figure <b>4A</b> shows a schematic structure of an
imaging device according to a second example of the
present invention, and Figure <b>4B</b> is a cross-sectional view
thereof ;</li>
        <li>Figure <b>5</b> shows a schematic structure of an imaging
device according to a third example of the present 
invention;</li>
        <li>Figure <b>6</b> shows a structure of the imaging device
according to the third example of the present invention;</li>
        <li>Figure <b>7</b> shows a schematic structure of another
imaging device according to the third example of the
present invention; and</li>
        <li>Figure <b>8A</b> shows a schematic structure of a
conventional imaging device, and Figure <b>8B</b> is a
cross-sectional view thereof.</li>
      </sl>
    </p>
    <heading>DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
    <p num="0036">Hereinafter, the present invention will be
described by way of illustrative examples with reference
to the accompanying drawings.</p>
    <heading>(Example 1)</heading>
    <p num="0037">Figure <b>1A</b> shows a schematic structure of an
imaging device <b>100</b> according to a first example of the
present invention, and Figure <b>1B</b> is a cross-sectional view
thereof taken along a plane including the rotation axis 
of a convex rotational mirror <b>3</b> described below.</p>
    <p num="0038">The imaging device <b>100</b> includes a convex
rotational mirror unit <b>1.</b> The convex rotational mirror
unit <b>1</b> includes a generally disc-shaped base <b>2</b> and the
convex rotational mirror <b>3</b> provided on a surface of the
base <b>2.</b> The convex rotational mirror <b>3</b> has a rotational
shape having a rotation axis which is vertical to the
surface of the base <b>2.</b> A surface of the convex rotational
mirror <b>3</b> is, for example, hyperboloidal. Alternatively,
the surface of the convex rotational mirror <b>3</b> may be
hemispherical or conical.</p>
    <p num="0039">The convex rotational mirror <b>3</b> is formed of a metal
material such as, for example, aluminum or stainless steel.
Alternatively, the convex rotational mirror <b>3</b> may have
a material having a mirror-surface effect such as, for
example, aluminum, silver, platinum, a nickel-chromium
alloy or gold, vapor-deposited, sputtered or plated onto
the surface thereof.</p>
    <p num="0040">The imaging device <b>100</b> further includes an optical
member <b>4</b> so as to cover the surface of the base <b>2</b> and the
convex rotational mirror <b>3.</b> A surface of the optical 
member <b>4</b> facing the convex rotational mirror unit <b>1</b> has
a concave portion <b>5</b> having a curved surface projecting
in an opposite direction to the base <b>2.</b> The optical member
<b>4</b> is formed of, for example, a light-transmissive and
non-moisture permeable resin such as an acrylic resin,
polycarbonate, or the like, or glass. The optical member
<b>4</b> is formed so as to be in close-contact with the convex
rotational mirror <b>3</b> along the concave portion <b>5,</b> unlike
in the conventional imaging device <b>80</b> described above with
reference to Figures <b>8A</b> and <b>8B</b> which have a hollow space
between the optical member <b>94</b> and the convex rotational
mirror <b>93.</b></p>
    <p num="0041">The optical member <b>4</b> preferably has a rotational
shape with a rotation axis that matches the rotation axis
of the convex rotational mirror <b>3.</b> The reason for this
is because where the optical member <b>4</b> and the convex
rotational mirror <b>3</b> have matching rotation axes, the
optical path length from an outer circumferential surface
of the optical member <b>4</b> to a surface of the convex
rotational mirror <b>3</b> is equal over the omniazimuthal angle
of 360 degrees. This facilitates a processing operation
of an image signal obtained based on light which is
reflected by the convex rotational mirror <b>3</b> and represents 
an image of an object.</p>
    <p num="0042">The imaging device <b>100</b> further includes a
generally cylindrical imaging mechanism <b>8</b> on the opposite
side to the convex rotational mirror unit <b>1,</b> with the
optical member <b>4</b> interposed therebetween. The imaging
mechanism <b>8</b> includes a lens <b>9</b> facing a reflected light
releasing face <b>7</b> of the optical member <b>4,</b> which is formed
on the opposite side to the convex rotational mirror unit
<b>1.</b> The lens <b>9</b> is located so that an optical axis thereof
matches the rotation axis of the convex rotational mirror
<b>3.</b> The lens <b>9</b> converges light which is reflected by the
convex rotational mirror <b>3.</b> The imaging mechanism 8 also
includes an imaging section <b>10</b> provided on the opposite
side to the optical member <b>4</b> with the lens <b>9</b> interposed
therebetween. The imaging section <b>10</b> is formed of a CCD
or the like. The imaging section <b>10</b> generates an image
signal representing an image based on the reflected light
converged by the lens <b>9,</b> and outputs the image signal to
a signal processing section (not shown). The signal
processing section adjusts the distortion of the image
signal which is output from the imaging section <b>10.</b></p>
    <p num="0043">The imaging device <b>100,</b> having the above-described 
structure, operates as follows.</p>
    <p num="0044">Light <b>21</b> is incident on the outer circumferential
surface of the optical member <b>4.</b> The incident light <b>21</b>
is refracted by the outer circumferential surface of the
optical member <b>4</b> so as to become light <b>22.</b> The light <b>22</b>
passes through the optical member <b>4</b> and reaches the convex
rotational mirror <b>3</b> which is in close-contact with the
optical member <b>4.</b></p>
    <p num="0045">The light-transmissive resin, such as an acrylic
resin, polycarbonate or the like, or glass that is used
to form the optical member <b>4,</b> has a refractive index which
is larger than that of air at room temperature. For
example, a light-transmissive resin has a refractive
index of 1.49 to 1.71, and glass has a refractive index
of 1.52 to 1.90. Therefore, the viewing angle of the
imaging device <b>100</b> is wider than that of the conventional
imaging device <b>80</b> (Figures <b>8A</b> and <b>8B</b>) having a hollow space
filled with air between the optical member <b>94</b> and the
convex rotational mirror <b>93.</b></p>
    <p num="0046">The light <b>22</b> incident on the convex rotational
mirror <b>3</b> is reflected by the surface of the convex 
rotational mirror <b>3</b> so as to become reflected light <b>41.</b>
The reflected light <b>41</b> passes through the reflected light
releasing face <b>7</b> of the optical member <b>4</b> and is converged
by the lens <b>9</b> of the imaging mechanism <b>8.</b> The imaging
section <b>10</b> generates an image signal which represents an
image based on the reflected light <b>41</b> converged by the
lens <b>9,</b> and outputs the image signal to the signal
processing section (not shown). The signal processing
section adjusts the distortion of the image signal which
is output from the imaging section <b>10.</b></p>
    <p num="0047">As described above, in the first example of the
present invention, the optical member <b>4</b> is in close-contact
with the convex rotational mirror <b>3.</b> Therefore,
there is no air or moisture existing between the optical
member <b>4</b> and the convex rotational mirror <b>3,</b> unlike the
conventional imaging device <b>80</b> described above with
reference to Figures <b>8A</b> and <b>8B.</b> Due to such a structure,
the surface of the convex rotational mirror 3 is prevented
from being corroded by moisture or air.</p>
    <p num="0048">In an alternative structure, a thin layer of a
material having a mirror-surface effect may be formed on
a surface of the concave portion <b>5</b> of the optical member <b>4,</b> instead of the convex rotational mirror unit <b>1</b> being
provided. The light <b>22</b> is reflected by the thin layer.
Such an alternative structure can reduce the size of the
imaging device and simplify the production process of the
imaging device. In addition, a layer of a resin or other
light-transmissive materials may be formed on a surface
of the thin layer opposite to the surface reflecting the
light <b>22.</b> Thus, the deterioration of the optical member
<b>4</b> caused by oxidation or the like can be avoided. The
convex rotational mirror <b>3</b> and the optical member <b>4</b> may
be produced separately.</p>
    <p num="0049">Figure <b>2A</b> shows a schematic structure of another
imaging device <b>200</b> according to the first example of the
present invention, and Figure <b>2B</b> is a cross-sectional view
thereof taken along a plane including the rotation axis
of the convex rotation mirror <b>3.</b> Identical elements
described above referring to Figures <b>1A</b> and <b>1B</b> bear
identical reference numerals therewith and detailed
descriptions thereof will be omitted.</p>
    <p num="0050">As shown in Figures <b>2A</b> and <b>2B,</b> the imaging device
200 includes an optical member <b>4A</b> which is generally
cylindrical. Such a structure provides an effect 
substantially the same as that of the imaging device <b>100.</b></p>
    <p num="0051">Figure <b>3A</b> shows a schematic structure of still
another imaging device <b>300</b> according to the first example
of the present invention, and Figure 3B is a cross-sectional
view thereof taken along a plane including the
rotation axis of the convex rotation mirror 3. Identical
elements described above referring to Figures <b>1A</b> and <b>1B</b>
bear identical reference numerals therewith and detailed
descriptions thereof will be omitted.</p>
    <p num="0052">As shown in Figures <b>3A</b> and <b>3B,</b> the imaging device
<b>300</b> includes an optical member <b>4B</b> which is integrally
formed with a lens <b>9B</b> included in an imaging mechanism
<b>8B.</b></p>
    <p num="0053">Where the optical member <b>4B</b> is integrally formed
with the lens <b>9B,</b> the following advantages are provided.
By designing and producing the lens <b>9B</b> in terms of shape
and position with respect to the optical member <b>4B</b> in
advance, the production process can exclude the step of
adjusting the position of the lens <b>9B</b> with respect to the
optical member <b>4,</b> and also the number of components of
the optical system can be reduced. Thus, the production 
efficiency is improved.</p>
    <p num="0054">The imaging devices <b>100, 200</b> and <b>300</b> also have the
advantage of a higher mechanical strength since the
optical members <b>4, 4A</b> and <b>4B</b> are solid inside.</p>
    <heading>(Example 2)</heading>
    <p num="0055">Figure <b>4A</b> shows a schematic structure of an
imaging device <b>400</b> according to a second example of the
present invention, and Figure <b>4B</b> is a cross-sectional view
thereof taken along a plane including the rotation axis
of a convex rotational mirror <b>3.</b> Identical elements
described above referring to Figures <b>1A</b> and <b>1B</b> bear
identical reference numerals therewith and detailed
descriptions thereof will be omitted.</p>
    <p num="0056">An imaging device <b>400</b> includes an optical member
<b>4C.</b> The optical member <b>4C</b> has a reflected light releasing
face <b>7C</b> on the opposite side to the convex rotational
mirror unit <b>1.</b> The reflected light releasing face <b>7C</b> has
a curved surface which projects toward the convex
rotational mirror <b>3.</b> The optical member <b>4C</b> is formed of
a light-transmissive material. </p>
    <p num="0057">A generally cylindrical imaging mechanism <b>8C</b> is
provided on the opposite side to the convex rotational
mirror unit 1 with the optical member <b>4C</b> interposed
therebetween. The imaging mechanism <b>8C</b> covers the
reflected light releasing face <b>7C</b> of the optical member
<b>4C.</b> The imaging mechanism <b>8</b> includes a lens <b>9C.</b> The lens
<b>9C</b> is in close-contact with the reflected light releasing
face <b>7C.</b> The lens <b>9C</b> is formed of a light-transmissive
material. The light-transmissive material used to form
the lens <b>9C</b> has a refractive index which is larger than
that of the light-transmissive material used to form the
optical member <b>4C.</b> The light-transmissive material used
to form the lens <b>9C</b> is, for example, lead glass having
a refractive index of 1.92 or diamond having a refractive
index of 2.42.</p>
    <p num="0058">The imaging device <b>400,</b> having the above-described
structure, operates as follows.</p>
    <p num="0059">Light, which is incident on an outer
circumferential surface of the optical member <b>4C</b>, is
refracted by the outer circumferential surface, passes
through the optical member <b>4C</b> and is directed to the convex
rotational mirror <b>3</b> which is in close-contact with the 
optical member <b>4C.</b> The light incident on the convex
rotational mirror <b>3</b> is reflected by a surface of the convex
rotational mirror <b>3</b> and passes through the reflected light
releasing face <b>7C</b> of the optical member <b>4C</b> as reflected
light, so as to be directly incident on the lens <b>9C,</b> which
is in close-contact with the reflected light releasing
face <b>7C.</b> The reflected light is then converged by the
lens <b>9C.</b></p>
    <p num="0060">The imaging section <b>10</b> generates an image signal
which represents an image based on the reflected light
converged by the lens <b>9C,</b> and outputs the image signal
to the signal processing section (not shown). The signal
processing section adjusts the distortion of the image
signal which is output from the imaging section <b>10.</b></p>
    <p num="0061">As described above, the lens <b>9C</b> is in close-contact
with the optical member <b>4C.</b> Therefore, the light
reflected by the convex rotational mirror <b>3</b> is incident
on the lens <b>9C</b> from the reflected light releasing face
<b>7C</b> directly, instead of through the air layer, as in the
imaging device <b>100</b> (Figures <b>1A</b> and <b>1B</b>), formed between
the reflected light releasing face <b>7</b> and the lens <b>9.</b> The
refractive index of the optical member <b>4C,</b> having the 
reflected light releasing face <b>7C</b> in the imaging device
<b>400,</b> is larger than the refractive index of the air layer
in the imaging device <b>100.</b> Therefore, the curvature of
the lens <b>9C</b> directly receiving the incident light from
the reflected light releasing face <b>7C</b> needs to be larger
than that of the lens <b>9</b> receiving the incident light
through the air layer. This is why the lens <b>9C</b> is formed
of lead glass, diamond or the like, which have a relatively
large refractive index. Since a material possessing a
larger refractive index is relatively expensive, the
optical member <b>4C</b> is formed of a material having a small
refractive index and thus is relatively inexpensive.</p>
    <p num="0062">Where the reflected light releasing face <b>7C</b> of the
optical member <b>4C</b> is in close-contact with the lens <b>9C</b>
of the imaging mechanism <b>8C,</b> the following advantages are
provided, which are similar to those of the imaging device
<b>300,</b> described above with reference to Figures <b>3A</b> and <b>3B.</b>
By designing and producing the lens <b>9C</b> in terms of shape
and position, with respect to the optical member <b>4C</b> in
advance, the production process can exclude the step of
adjusting the position of the lens <b>9C</b> with respect to the
optical member <b>4C,</b> and also the number of components of
the optical system can be reduced. Thus, the production 
efficiency is improved.</p>
    <heading>(Example 3)</heading>
    <p num="0063">Figures <b>5</b> and <b>6</b> show a schematic structure of an
imaging device <b>500</b> according to a third example of the
present invention. Identical elements described above
referring to Figures <b>1A</b> and <b>1B</b> bear identical reference
numerals therewith and detailed descriptions thereof will
be omitted. The imaging device <b>500</b> is different from the
imaging device <b>100</b> (Figures <b>1A</b> and <b>1B</b>) in that the imaging
device <b>500</b> includes an optical member <b>4D</b> instead of the
optical member <b>4.</b></p>
    <p num="0064">The optical member <b>4D</b> has an outer circumferential
surface formed so as to cause light to be incident thereon
in a direction normal thereto (Figure <b>5</b>). The optical
member <b>4D</b> includes a reflected light releasing face <b>7D</b>
formed so as to cause the light reflected by the convex
rotational mirror <b>3</b> to pass therethrough in a direction
normal thereto (Figure <b>6</b>).</p>
    <p num="0065">The imaging device <b>500,</b> having the above-described
structure, operates as follows. </p>
    <p num="0066">Light <b>23,</b> incident on the outer circumferential
surface of the optical member <b>4D,</b> advances straight
without being refracted by the outer circumferential
surface, passes through the optical member <b>4D</b> and is
directed to the convex rotational mirror <b>3</b> which is in
close-contact with the optical member <b>4D.</b> The incident
light <b>23</b> is then reflected by a surface of the convex
rotational mirror <b>3</b> so as to become reflected light <b>42.</b>
The reflected light <b>42</b> passes straight through the
reflected light releasing face <b>7D</b> without being refracted
and is converged by a lens (not shown) included in the
imaging mechanism <b>8.</b> An imaging section (not shown) of
the imaging mechanism <b>8</b> generates an image signal
representing an image based on the reflected light <b>42</b>
converged by the lens, and outputs the image signal to
a signal processing section (not shown). The signal
processing section adjusts the distortion of the image
signal which is output from the imaging section.</p>
    <p num="0067">As described above, the outer circumferential
surface of the optical member <b>4D</b> is formed so as to cause
the light to be incident in a direction normal thereto.
Therefore, the incident light <b>23</b> advances straight
without being refracted by the outer circumferential 
surface, regardless of the refractive index of the
material used to form the optical member <b>4D.</b> The
reflected light releasing face <b>7D</b> is formed so as to cause
light to pass therethrough in a direction normal thereto.
Therefore, the reflected light <b>42</b> passes straight through
the reflected light releasing face <b>7D</b> without being
refracted, regardless of the refractive index of the
material used to form the optical member <b>4D.</b> Accordingly,
the optical system can be designed without considering
the refractive index of the optical member <b>4D,</b> with
respect to the incident light or the reflected light.
Since the material for the optical member <b>4D</b> can be
selected regardless of the refractive index, the optical
system can be designed more easily.</p>
    <p num="0068">In the example shown in Figures <b>5</b> and <b>6,</b> the convex
rotational mirror <b>3</b> is designed so as to converge the
reflected light <b>42</b> on a prescribed focal point. In this
case, the reflected light releasing face <b>7D</b> may be formed
so as to be a part of the surface of a circle having the
focal point as the center.</p>
    <p num="0069">Figure <b>7</b> is a cross-sectional view of another
imaging device <b>600</b> according to the third example of the 
present invention. Identical elements described above
referring to Figures <b>5</b> and <b>6</b> bear identical reference
numerals therewith and detailed descriptions thereof will
be omitted. The imaging device <b>600</b> is different from the
imaging device <b>500</b> in that the imaging device <b>600</b> includes
an optical member <b>4E</b> instead of the optical member <b>4D.</b></p>
    <p num="0070">The optical member <b>4E</b> has an outer circumferential
surface formed to refract light incident thereon. The
optical member <b>4E</b> includes a reflected light releasing
face <b>7E</b> formed to refract the light reflected by the convex
rotational mirror <b>3.</b></p>
    <p num="0071">The imaging device <b>600,</b> having the above-described
structure, operates as follows.</p>
    <p num="0072">Light <b>26,</b> incident on the outer circumferential
surface of the optical member <b>4E,</b> is refracted by the outer
circumferential surface so as to become light <b>28.</b> The
light <b>28</b> passes through the optical member <b>4E</b> and is
directed to the convex rotational mirror <b>3</b> which is in
close-contact with the optical member <b>4E.</b> The light <b>28</b>
is then reflected by a surface of the convex rotational
mirror <b>3</b> so as to become reflected light <b>47.</b> The reflected 
light <b>47</b> is refracted by the reflected light releasing
face <b>7E,</b> is transmitted through the air layer between the
reflected light releasing face <b>7E</b> and the imaging
mechanism <b>8</b> and is converged by a lens (not shown) included
in the imaging mechanism <b>8.</b> An imaging section (not
shown) of the imaging mechanism <b>8</b> generates an image
signal representing an image based on the reflected light
<b>47</b> converged by the lens, and outputs the image signal
to a signal processing section (not shown). The signal
processing section adjusts the distortion of the image
signal which is output from the imaging section.</p>
    <p num="0073">In Figure <b>7,</b> dashed line <b>27</b> represents incident
light in the conventional imaging device <b>80</b> described
above with reference to Figures <b>8A</b> and <b>8B.</b> In the
conventional imaging device <b>80,</b> the light incident on the
optical member <b>94</b> and the light directed from the optical
member <b>94</b> toward the convex rotational mirror <b>93</b> are
proximately parallel to each other due to the thinness
of the hollow optical member <b>94.</b> Thus, the incident light
<b>27</b> becomes the light <b>28.</b> In the imaging device <b>600</b> in
the third example of the present invention, the light <b>26</b>
is incident on the optical member <b>4E</b> reaches the optical
member <b>4E</b> along a path above the path of the light <b>27.</b> 
Therefore, the viewing angle of the imaging device <b>600</b>
is wider than that of the conventional imaging device <b>80.</b></p>
    <p num="0074">Thus, in the structure where the light is
refracted by the outer circumferential surface of the
optical member <b>4E,</b> the viewing angle of the imaging device
can be enlarged.</p>
    <p num="0075">In the structure where an outer circumferential
surface of the optical member is spherical, i.e.,
cup-shaped, the influence of the reflected light inside
the optical member is eliminated. As a result, a clearer
image can be obtained. In the structure where the convex
rotational mirror 3 has a hyperboloidal shape, the image
data representing the image taken by the imaging mechanism
can be easily converted into image data representing a
perspective view or a panoramic view.</p>
    <p num="0076">As described above, the present invention
provides an imaging device for preventing reduction in
the reflectance of light incident on a convex rotational
mirror, and a method for producing the same; and an imaging
device for preventing dust, moisture or the like from
entering between a convex rotational mirror and an optical 
member, and a method for producing the same.</p>
    <p num="0077">Various other modifications will be apparent to
and can be readily made by those skilled in the art without
departing from the scope and spirit of this invention.
Accordingly, it is not intended that the scope of the
claims appended hereto be limited to the description as
set forth herein, but rather that the claims be broadly
construed.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>An imaging device, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a convex mirror for reflecting incident light
representing an object, the convex mirror having a shape
of solid of revolution;</claim-text><claim-text>an imaging mechanism for taking an image
represented by reflected light from the convex mirror;
and</claim-text><claim-text>an optical member for guiding the incident light
toward the convex mirror and guiding the reflected light
toward the imaging mechanism, the optical member being
in close-contact with the convex mirror.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>An imaging device according to claim 1, wherein the
optical member has a concave portion which is in
close-contact with the convex mirror so as to cover the
convex mirror.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>An imaging device according to claim 2, wherein the
convex mirror is formed of a thin layer of a material having
a mirror-surface effect, the thin layer being provided
on the concave portion.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>An imaging device according to claim 1, wherein the
convex mirror is formed of a metal material.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>An imaging device according to claim 1, wherein the
convex mirror is formed of aluminum.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>An imaging device according to claim 1, wherein the
convex mirror is formed as a result of vapor-deposition,
sputtering or plating of a material having a mirror-surface
effect.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>An imaging device according to claim 1, wherein the
imaging mechanism includes a lens for converging the
reflected light, and an imaging section for taking an
image represented by the reflected light converged by the
lens; and the lens is integrally formed with the optical
member.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>An imaging device according to claim 1, wherein the
imaging mechanism includes a lens for converging the
reflected light, and an imaging section for taking an
image represented by the reflected light converged by the
lens; and the lens is in close-contact with the optical
member.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>An imaging device according to claim 8, wherein the
optical member has a refractive index which is smaller
than the refractive index of the lens.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>An imaging device according to claim 1, wherein the
optical member has an outer circumferential surface
formed so as to cause the incident light to be incident
thereon in a direction normal to the outer circumferential
surface.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>An imaging device according to claim 1, wherein the
optical member has a reflected light releasing face formed
so as to cause the reflected light directed toward the
imaging mechanism to be incident thereon in a direction
normal to the reflected light releasing face.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>An imaging device according to claim 11, wherein the
reflected light releasing face is a part of a surface of
a circle having, as the center, a focal point at which
the reflected light is converged.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>A method for producing an imaging device according
to claim 1, the method comprising the steps of:<claim-text><claim-text>causing the optical member to be in close-contact
with the convex mirror so that the optical member covers
the convex mirror; and</claim-text><claim-text>attaching the imaging mechanism to the optical
member so that the reflected light is incident on the
imaging mechanism.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>An imaging device comprising
   means providing a convex reflection surface having a shape of solid
revolution for reflecting incident light, and
   an image sensor for receiving the reflected light, wherein there is
provided an optical member for conducting the incident light toward the
reflection surface and for conducting the reflected light toward the image
sensor, and wherein said reflection surface is contiguous with the body of
the optical member.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>An imaging device including a convex mirror and an optical
element which conducts incident light right up to a reflection surface and
conducts the reflected light toward an optical sensor.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>An imaging device according to claim 14 or claim 15 wherein said
optical member comprises a solid body formed with a concave surface at
which the reflection surface is provided, or with which the reflection
surface is in contact.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
