<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1247811-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1247811" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="25244938" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021009">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1247811-A1" status="new" fvid="23558838">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1247811</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20021009</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02252129-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02252129</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020325</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="US-82579501-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>82579501</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010404</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C07F   7/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C07F   7/08        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  77/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  77/08        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  77/12        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07F   7/08D4K2</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur Herstellung linearer Organohydrosiloxanen</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Process for the production of linear organohydrogensiloxanes</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé de préparation des organohydrosiloxanes linéaires</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GEN ELECTRIC</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1 River Road</street>
              <city>Schenectady, NY 12345</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KHANSHAB AKBER ALI</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TOLENTINO LUISITO A</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KHANSHAB, AKBER ALI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TOLENTINO, LUISITO A.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>KHANSHAB, AKBER ALI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>4116 Stonefield Way</street>
              <city>Schenectady, New York 12188</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>TOLENTINO, LUISITO A.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>4 Cherry Hills Court</street>
              <city>Clifton Park, New York 12065</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Szary, Anne Catherine, Dr.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>GE London Patent Operation, Essex House, 12-13 Essex Street</street>
              <city>London WC2R 3AA</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>NL</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A process for preparing linear organohydrogensiloxanes comprises
contacting an organohydrogendichlorosilane in the presence of
trimethylchlorosilane with water to form an M-stopped hydrolyzate. The
hydrolyzate is optionally preheated prior to being contacted with an acidic
rearrangement catalyst to effect formation of linear organohydrogensiloxanes.
The linear organohydrogensiloxanes are separated from cyclic
organohydrogensiloxanes and recovered. The cyclic
organohydrogensiloxanes may then be recycled to the process for further
contact with the acidic rearrangement catalyst for maximum overall
conversion rate.</p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a process for the production of linear
organohydrogenpolysiloxanes.</p>
    <p num="0002">Linear organohydrogenpolysiloxanes are used in coatings, textiles and
paper release applications. They are also used as source of SiH for catalyzed
silicone addition cure with vinyl functional silicones.</p>
    <p num="0003">Organohydrogenpolysiloxanes are typically prepared by hydrolysis of
organohydogenpolysiloxane (RSiHCl<sub>2</sub>) with or without a chainstopper such
as trimethylchlorosilane. The product is a mixture of linear and cyclic silicone
hydride with the latter as the minor component. U.S. Patent No. 5,396,956
discloses a continuous process of preparing cyclic organohydrogensiloxanes
by contacting an organohydrogendichlorosilane with about a stoichiometric
equivalent of water to form a hydrolyzate, an equilibrium mixture containing
cyclic and linear organohydrogensiloxanes. The hydrolyzate is then
rearranged by contact with an acidic rearrangement catalyst to effect
formation of cyclic organohydrogensiloxanes. In U.S. Patent No. 5,698,654, the
ring opening polymerization of cyclic organosiloxanes is done in the presence
of a basic catalyst and by the neutralization of the basic catalyst with an excess
of a catalytic Lewis acid compound.</p>
    <p num="0004">Since the majority of applications require materials containing mostly
linear species, it is common in the art to flash strip or distill the hydrolyzate to
remove the cyclic species. As the demand for linear
organohydrogenpolysiloxanes grows, the amount of cyclic species also
grows. There is still a need for an improved method for recycling the cyclic
species and converting them to linear species. </p>
    <p num="0005">The present invention relates to a process for preparing linear
organopolysiloxanes, which comprises contacting organodichlorosilane in the
presence of trimethylchlorosilane with water to form M-stopped hydrolyzate.
The hydrolyzate is contacted with an acidic rearrangement catalyst at a
temperature of about 65°C or lower to effect the formation of linear
organopolysiloxanes. The linear organopolysiloxanes are separated from the
cyclic organopolysiloxanes and recovered.</p>
    <p num="0006">The present invention is a process for preparing linear
organohydrogensiloxanes by converting volatile cyclic
organohydrogensiloxanes in hydride hydrolyzates into linear
organohydrogensiloxanes.</p>
    <p num="0007"><u style="single">Preparing hydride hydrolyzate feed</u>. The feed to the process of the
present invention, hydride hydrolyzates or organomethyl-hydrosiloxanes are
well-known in the silicone art and may be prepared by any suitable
technique. In this step, halosilanes exemplified by the formula of RHSiCl<sub>2</sub> (1)
are placed in contact with water in the presence of a chain stopper to form a
hydrolyzate comprising cyclic organohydrogensiloxanes and linear
organohydrogensiloxanes.</p>
    <p num="0008">The silanes may be a single species of silane or may be a mixture of
such silanes. The substituent R in formula (1) R is selected from a group
consisting of saturated monovalent hydrocarbon radicals comprising one to
12 carbon atoms and aryl radicals. R can be, for example, methyl, ethyl,
propyl, isopropyl, butyl, tertiary butyl, sec-butyl, hexyl, cyclohexyl, dodecyl,
phenyl, tolyl, and naphthyl. In one embodiment, R is selected from a group
consisting of methyl and phenyl. In another embodiment, R is methyl and
methyldichlorosilane is used. In yet another embodiment, 
trimethylchlorosilane (CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub> SiCl is added in less than 5 wt. % as a chain
stopper to stop polymerization and control the viscosity of the finished fluid.</p>
    <p num="0009">The ratio of cyclic to linear in the M-stopped hydrolyzate in the present
invention, as well as the chain length of the linear siloxane, varies depending
on the conditions of the hydrolysis, such as the ratio of halosilane to water,
temperature, contact, time, and solvents. M-stopped hereby, as commonly
known in the art, refers to the tri-functional organosilane end groups
R<sub>1,2,3</sub>SiO<sub>1/2</sub> at the end of the chain, wherein each of the R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>2</sub>, and R<sub>3</sub> is
independently selected from one to forty carbon atom monovalent
hydrocarbon radicals. In one embodiment, M is trimethylsilyl.</p>
    <p num="0010">In one embodiment of this hydrolysis reaction, the silane is contacted
with excess water, where a stoichiometric equivalent of water is defined as 0.5
mole of water per mole of halogen provided to the process by the silane. In
another embodiment, the mole ratio of water to silane is 100 to 200 % of
stoichiometric equivalence.</p>
    <p num="0011">Contact of the silane with the water can be conducted in standard
reactors for hydrolyzing halosilanes. In one embodiment, the process is at a
pressure at which the silane is present as a liquid phase. The hydrolysis
process can be conducted at a temperature at about -15°C to about 50°C. In
one embodiment, the hydrolysis process is conducted at a temperature within
a range of about 5°C to 30°C.</p>
    <p num="0012">The M-stopped hydrolyzate feed to the process of the present
invention typically has a weight ratio of about 0.5:1 to 4:1 of cyclic
organohydrogensiloxanes to linear organohydrogensiloxanes.</p>
    <p num="0013">In one embodiment, the hydrolyzate formed in the hydrolysis process
prior to being fed to the rearrangement process of the present invention is 
flash distilled to separate the cyclic organohydrogensiloxanes from the linear
organohydrogensiloxanes. The flash distillation is typically a known
standard method for separating cyclic siloxanes from mixtures for a feed
stream with primarily cyclic. In one embodiment, the hydrolyzate is stripped
at about 150°C at 5mm Hg to give an overhead stream comprising primarily
trace hexamethyl disiloxane, mixed cyclics D<sub>4</sub> - D<sub>5</sub> and low-boiling linear
species. The overhead stream is then fed to the rearrangement process to
convert the cyclic species into linears.</p>
    <p num="0014">In one embodiment of the invention, the M-stopped hydrolyzate feed
to the rearrangement process of the present invention is in the form of being
diluted in an inert solvent. By the term "inert" it is meant a solvent which can
serves as a diluent and does not otherwise react in the process. In one
embodiment, the inert solvents are those alkanes and mixtures of alkanes
having a boiling point above that of the cyclic heptamer of the
organohydrogensiloxane</p>
    <p num="0015"><u style="single">Optional preheating step.</u> In one embodiment, the M-stopped
hydrolyzate feed is preheated to a temperature of about 35°C to 55°C in a heat
exchanger prior to the rearrangement step comprising passing the
hydrolyzate through an acid rearrangement catalyst. The preheating is
optional to cut down on the residence time in the acid rearrangement reactor.</p>
    <p num="0016"><u style="single">Rearranging the hydrolyzate feed</u>. In this process, the M-stopped
hydrolyzate feed, after the optional pre-heating step if desired, is passed
through an acid rearrangement catalyst. Acid rearrangement catalysts can be
any acid which facilitates rearrangement of cyclic organohydrogensiloxanes
to linear organohydrogensiloxanes. The acidic rearrangement catalyst can be
an Arhennius, Bronsted, or a Lewis acid. The acidic rearrangement catalyst
can be a homogeneous catalyst such as hydrogen chloride, sulfuric acid, or 
chlorosulfonic acid. It can be a heterogeneous acid such as bentonite clays
such as Super Filtrol F-I O (Engelhard Corporation, Jackson, Miss.). In one
embodiment, the acidic rearrangement catalyst is a porous solid such as
carbon, a clay, or a zeolite having absorbed thereto a protic acid such as
sulfuric or phosphoric acid. Alternatives to acidic polymerization medium
including art-known strong acid cationic ion exchange resins can be used, an
example of which is Nafion™ (Aldrich Chemical Company, Milwaukee, Wis.),
a sulfonic acid functionalized fluoropolymer. Others include standard
sulfonic acid functionalized styrene-divinylbenzene (H) ion exchange resins
(sulfonated divinylbenzene styrene copolymer resin).</p>
    <p num="0017">The temperature at which the rearrangement can be run is about 65°C
or lower. In one embodiment, the temperature is within a range of about
18°C to 65°C. In another embodiment, the temperature is within a range of
about 40°C to 55°C.</p>
    <p num="0018">In one embodiment of the invention, the pressure of the rearrangement
process is at or about ambient pressure.</p>
    <p num="0019">The rearrangement process of the present invention is carried out in a
fixed-bed or stirred-bed. It can be run as a continuous, semi-continuous, or
batch process. In one embodiment, the process is run as a continuous process
using a fixed-bed of the acidic rearrangement catalyst.</p>
    <p num="0020">The residence time in the rearrangement reactor is about two hours or
less. In one embodiment, the residence time is within a range of about five to
an hour. In another embodiment, the residence time for a continuous process
is about five to thirty minutes.</p>
    <p num="0021">The conversion rate of cyclic to linear in rearrangement step as well as
the chain length of the linear siloxane varies depending on the feed 
composition, the residence time in the preheater as well as the conditions of
the rearrangement reaction.</p>
    <p num="0022"><u style="single">Recovering linear organohydrogensiloxanes</u>. The linear
organohydrogensiloxanes (from rearrangement of cyclic
organohydrogensiloxanes) are described by formula: MD<sub>n</sub>M, wherein:
<sl><li>M: as previously described, refers to the tri-functional organosilane
end groups R<sub>1,2,3</sub>SiO<sub>1/2</sub> at the end of the chain D.</li><li>D: R<sub>4</sub>HSiO<sub>2/2</sub></li></sl>
   and wherein n is an integer of 1 or higher, and each of R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>2</sub>, R<sub>3</sub>, and R<sub>4</sub>
is independently selected from one to forty carbon atom monovalent
hydrocarbon radicals. In one embodiment, the linear
organohydrogensiloxanes recovered from the present process are those where
R is methyl and n is 1 or higher, and mostly in the range of 20 to 80.</p>
    <p num="0023">The method for recovering the linear organohydrogensiloxanes from
the present process is not critical and can be standard methods known in the
art for separating linear and cyclic siloxanes mixtures. For example, the
rearranged hydrolyzate can be flash distilled to separate the volatile cyclic
organohydrogensiloxanes and recover the linear organohydrogensiloxanes.</p>
    <p num="0024">In one embodiment, the volatile cyclic siloxanes are recycled and sent
back to the rearrangement reactor as a separate feed stream by themselves for
further rearrangement or optionally mixed with the incoming M-stopped
hydrolyzate feed. Continuous runs of the rearrangement process of the
present invention with continuous recycled of the recovered cyclics provide a
theoretical yield of greater than 99 percent of the chlorosilane feed being
converted to linear organohydrogen siloxanes. </p>
    <heading>EXAMPLES</heading>
    <p num="0025">The following examples are provided to illustrate the present
invention. They are not intended to limit the present claims.</p>
    <p num="0026"><u style="single">Comparative example 1.</u> A mixture of 96.5 wt. % methyldichlorosilane
and 3.5 wt. % trimethylchlorosilane was mixed with 200% excess of
stoichiometric equivalent of water in a hydrolysis reactor i.e. 0.5 mole of
water per mole of silicon bonded chlorine added to the reactor. The
hydrolysis reactor was maintained at 60 psig and the temperature of the
reactor was controlled such that the hydrolyzate exiting the reactor was at a
temperature of about 33°C. The organohydrogen siloxane hydrolyzate
exiting the reactor was analyzed by gas chromatography (GC) using a thermal
conductivity detector (TCD) and found to comprise about 80 weight percent
M-stopped linear organohydrogensiloxane species and about 20 weight
percent cyclic organohydrogensiloxane species. The viscosity of the
hydrolyzate is about 10-20 centistokes and a % weight loss (at 150°C / hour)
of about 15 - 20%.</p>
    <p num="0027">The hydrolyzate from the hydrolysis reactor was vacuum flash
distilled at about 150°C at 5mm Hg and the cyclic species and low-boiling
linear species taken overhead. The bottom linear fraction was cooled and
recovered. The overhead fraction was analyzed by gas chromatography (GC)
and found to contain about 20 wt.% linears and 80 wt. % mixed cyclics of
primarily D<sub>4</sub>-D<sub>5</sub>, with the rest of the cyclics being primarily D<sub>6</sub>-D<sub>7</sub>. The
overhead stream with 79.8 % "volatiles," a mixture of primarily cyclics and
some linears was used as the feed stream for examples 2-10.</p>
    <p num="0028"><u style="single">Examples 2 -10</u>. The M-stopped hydrolyzate feed from example 1 was
pumped at the rate of 1.3 to 5.4 g/min. through a preheater maintained at
about 35 to 55°C, followed by a single pass through a packed bed reactor 
containing about 100 grams of Filtrol 25 bentonite acid leached granules
catalyst at a bed temperature of either 35, 45, or 55°C. The residence time of
the rearrangement reactor was controlled by the pump rate. The product
exiting the reactor was analyzed by gas chromatography (GC) using a thermal
conductivity detector (TCD) for volatile content (i.e., indicator of cyclic
presence), viscosity, and % weight loss (at 150°C / hour).</p>
    <p num="0029"><u style="single">Examples 11 - 17</u>. In these examples, the product exiting the reactor
was stripped at about 150°C at 5mm Hg to reduce the volatiles (cyclics)
content to less than or about 3 wt. %. The material recovered from the
receiver was re-used as feed to the rearrangement reactor by blending with
the hydrolyzate feed of example 1 at a ratio of 15 wt. % volatile and 85 wt. %
original hydrolyzate feed. For example 11 (comparative), the feed stream
bypassed the rearrangement reactor and was analyzed for volatile content,
viscosity, and % weight loss (at 150°C / hour). The percent of "volatiles," a
mixture of primarily cyclics and some linears was found to be at 39.26 wt. %.</p>
    <p num="0030">For examples 12-17, the "mixed" hydrolyzate feed was pumped at the
rate of 1.3 to 5.4 g/min. through a preheater maintained at about 35 to 55°C,
followed by a single pass through a packed bed reactor containing about 100
grams of Filtrol 25 bentonite acid leached granules catalyst at a bed
temperature of either 35, 45, or 55°C with the residence time being controlled
by the pump rate. The product was analyzed for volatile content, viscosity,
and % weight loss (at 150°C / hour).</p>
    <p num="0031">The results of examples are as follows: <tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Examples</entry><entry align="left">Feed Material</entry><entry align="center">Temp. °C</entry><entry align="center">Residence Time (min)</entry><entry align="center">Viscosity@ 25°C cstks</entry><entry align="center">% weight loss</entry><entry align="center">% volatiles</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative 1</entry><entry align="left">Volatile hydride</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">65</entry><entry align="center">79.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2</entry><entry align="left">Volatile hydride</entry><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">8</entry><entry align="center">11.5</entry><entry align="center">15.06</entry><entry align="center">26.63</entry></row><row><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">Volatile hydride</entry><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">18</entry><entry align="center">16.4</entry><entry align="center">9.25</entry><entry align="center">14.98</entry></row><row><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">Volatile hydride</entry><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">16.3</entry><entry align="center">8.62</entry><entry align="center">13.16</entry></row><row><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="left">Volatile hydride</entry><entry align="center">45</entry><entry align="center">8</entry><entry align="center">14</entry><entry align="center">10.01</entry><entry align="center">16.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">6</entry><entry align="left">Volatile hydride</entry><entry align="center">45</entry><entry align="center">18</entry><entry align="center">15.7</entry><entry align="center">8.99</entry><entry align="center">14.16</entry></row><row><entry align="left">7</entry><entry align="left">Volatile hydride</entry><entry align="center">55</entry><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">17</entry><entry align="center">8.75</entry><entry align="center">13.27</entry></row><row><entry align="left">8</entry><entry align="left">Volatile hydride</entry><entry align="center">55</entry><entry align="center">8</entry><entry align="center">15.6</entry><entry align="center">9.22</entry><entry align="center">13.93</entry></row><row><entry align="left">9</entry><entry align="left">Volatile hydride</entry><entry align="center">55</entry><entry align="center">18</entry><entry align="center">16.7</entry><entry align="center">8.8</entry><entry align="center">14.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="left">Volatile hydride</entry><entry align="center">55</entry><entry align="center">38</entry><entry align="center">19.6</entry><entry align="center">8.24</entry><entry align="center">13.03</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative 11</entry><entry align="left">Hydride mix.</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="center">28.88</entry><entry align="center">39.25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">12</entry><entry align="left">Hydride mix.</entry><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">9</entry><entry align="center">14.2</entry><entry align="center">8.68</entry><entry align="center">21.82</entry></row><row><entry align="left">13</entry><entry align="left">Hydride mix.</entry><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">17</entry><entry align="center">14.75</entry><entry align="center">8.58</entry><entry align="center">15.86</entry></row><row><entry align="left">14</entry><entry align="left">Hydride mix.</entry><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">14.45</entry><entry align="center">8.47</entry><entry align="center">16.16</entry></row><row><entry align="left">15</entry><entry align="left">Hydride mix.</entry><entry align="center">55</entry><entry align="center">9</entry><entry align="center">15.65</entry><entry align="center">8.56</entry><entry align="center">16.09</entry></row><row><entry align="left">16</entry><entry align="left">Hydride mix.</entry><entry align="center">55</entry><entry align="center">17</entry><entry align="center">15.4</entry><entry align="center">8.56</entry><entry align="center">13.90</entry></row><row><entry align="left">17</entry><entry align="left">Hydride mix.</entry><entry align="center">55</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">16.5</entry><entry align="center">8.57</entry><entry align="center">13.97</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A process for preparing linear organohydrogensiloxanes, the
process comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>(A) contacting a silane of the formula RHSiCl2 with water in
the presence of trimethylchlorosilane to form an M-stopped hydrolyzate
comprising cyclic organohydrogensiloxanes and linear
organohydrogensiloxanes,</claim-text><claim-text>(B) contacting the hydrolyzate with an acidic rearrangement
catalyst at a temperature of about 65°C or less thereby increasing the ratio of
the linear organohydrogensiloxanes to the cyclic organohydrogensiloxanes,
and</claim-text><claim-text>(C) separating the linear organohydrogensiloxanes from the
cyclic organohydrogensiloxanes;</claim-text></claim-text>
where R is selected from a group consisting of saturated monovalent
hydrocarbon radicals comprising one to 12 carbon atoms and aryl radicals.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A process according to claim 1, further including preheating the
hydrolyzate at a temperature of about 35°C to 55°C prior to contacting said
hydrolyzate with an acidic rearrangement catalyst.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A process according to claim 1, wherein the mole ratio of water
to silane is about 100 to 200% of stoichiometric equivalence</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A process according to claim 1, wherein the hydrolyzate is in
contact with the acidic rearrangement catalyst for about at least about five
minutes.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A process according to claim 1, wherein the hydrolyzate is in
contact with the acidic rearrangement catalyst at atmospheric pressure.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A process according to claim 1, wherein the hydrolyzate is a
distillate of product from a process comprising the reaction of a silane of the
formula RHSiCl2 with water in the presence of trimethylchlorosilane.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A process according to claim 1, wherein said hydrolyzate is in
contact with the acidic rearrangement catalyst in a fixed bed reactor.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A process according to claim 1, wherein the process is run as a
continuous process.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>A process according to claim 8, wherein the cyclic
organohydrogensiloxanes are recovered and recycled to the continuous
process.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>A process according to claim 1, wherein the acidic
rearrangement catalyst is a heterogeneous catalyst.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
