<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1236400-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1236400" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="19772972" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020904">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1236400-A2" status="new" fvid="23541353">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1236400</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20020904</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02075798-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02075798</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020228</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="NL-1017461-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>NL</country>
          <doc-number>1017461</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010228</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A21D   2/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A21D   2/16        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A21D   2/18        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A21D   2/36        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A21D   8/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A21D   8/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A21D  10/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A21D  10/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">A21D  10/00B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">A21D   2/16D</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">A21D   2/18E</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">A21D   2/36</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">A21D   8/04B</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Pumpfähiges Brotverbesserungsmittel und Verfahren zur Herstellung</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Pumpable bread improver and a method for preparation thereof</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition pompable d'amélioration du pain et procédé pour sa fabrication</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SONNEVELD BV</name>
            <address>
              <country>NL</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SONNEVELD B.V.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>SONNEVELD B.V.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Rietgorsweg 1-3</street>
              <city>NL-3356 LJ Papendrecht</city>
              <country>NL</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SONNEVELD, GERRIT CORNELIS</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>The designation of the inventor has not yet been filed</last-name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Van Someren, Petronella F. H. M.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Arnold &amp;amp; Siedsma, Advocaten en Octrooigemachtigden, Sweelinckplein 1</street>
              <city>2517 GK Den Haag</city>
              <country>NL</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>The invention relates to a pumpable bread improver
which consists of an oil fraction and a powder fraction and
is obtainable by means of a method which the mixing of the
liquid oil fraction and means for preventing sedimentation of
the powder fraction are performed at a temperature at which
the means for preventing sedimentation of the powder fraction
are liquid. Cooling down of the obtained mixture and adding
and mixing of the powder fraction which contains at least one
or more emulsifiers. The viscosity of the bread improver is
between 80 and 3000 mPa.s.</p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a pumpable bread
improver and a method for the preparation thereof.</p>
    <p num="0002">A bread improver is a mixture of ingredients that,
next to flour, water, yeast and salt, are used as improver.
Bread improvers have an important function during the process
of making bread because they counterbalance the changes in
the quality of the flour and process variations. They play a
role in the improvement of the characteristic properties of
bread and the realization of a broad assortment of bread
products.</p>
    <p num="0003">A bread improver is a combination of basic
ingredients, additives and technological resources. Besides
this, also other foods can also be added as an ingredient.
The basic ingredients are ingredients, which are added in
quantities from about 0.3 percent (calculated in relation to
the flour). These ingredients include milk components, wheat
gluten, soya flour, malt flour or malt extract, sugars, oils
and fats. The additives consist of emulsifiers, acid
regulators, colorings and conservatives. Finally, the
technical resources include flour improvers and enzymes.</p>
    <p num="0004">Bread improvers are known in different forms, like
powders, pastes or liquids. They can contain more or less of
the above mentioned types of ingredients, depending on the
sort of bread for which they are used. In some cases,
combinations of dosage means are used to obtain a broadly
applicable bread improver. It is known to use a separate
liquid fat phase next to a powder product, which contains the
other ingredients. A disadvantage of this is that one has to
dose twice. </p>
    <p num="0005">In bakeries, process automation plays an ever
increasing role. Additionally, the demand for automatic
dosable basic ingredients also increases. Already, it has
been a custom for a long time to automatically dose flour and
water. During the last few years, also liquid yeast has
entered the industrial bakeries. Because of the broad
assortment in bakeries, the automated dosing of bread
improvers has been delayed until now. Already used today are
large scale charge packages with salt. Nevertheless, the
demand for automated dosing of concentrated bread improvers
remains. As a consequence, this also implies that the
transport has to take place in bulk packages or containers
and the storage in silos.</p>
    <p num="0006">Nevertheless, when already existing bread improvers
are concentrated, they turn out to be no longer pumpable.
Especially bread improvers, which use as an emulsifier
stearoyllactylate and mono-/ diglycerides of fatty acids, are
already at an amount of 6 percent emulsifier unpumpable. Such
an amount of stearoyllactylate and mono-/ diglycerides of
fatty acids is much too low to be used in a concentrated
bread improver.</p>
    <p num="0007">Finally, it is desired that, prior to dosage, the
bread improver does not need to be to be preprocessed, like
for example heating in order to liquidize the improver.</p>
    <p num="0008">It is therefor the aim of the invention to provide
a concentrated bread improver which is still pumpable,
without requiring heating or other preprocessing steps.</p>
    <p num="0009">This is achieved by the invention by providing a
bread improver which contains an oil fraction and a powder
fraction obtainable by a method, which comprises the
following steps:
<sl><li>(a) mixing the liquid oil fraction and means for 
preventing the sedimentation of the powder fraction at a
temperature at which the means for preventing sedimentation
of the powder fraction are fluid;</li><li>(b) cooling the obtained mixture; and</li><li>(c) adding and mixing of a powder fraction which
contains at least one or more emulsifiers.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0010">It has been found that when the above mentioned
sequential of steps is used, a bread improver is obtained
which is pumpable at room temperatures and which can, by
means of pumping, be dosed into the dough. The powder
fraction can be present in the end product between 5 to 55
percent, in which case the powder fraction can contain
stearoyllactylate and mono-/ diglycerides of fatty acids, as
emulsifiers, even up to 30 to 50 percent thereof without
negatively affecting the pumpability of the product.</p>
    <p num="0011">According to the invention, the viscosity of the
pumpable bread improver is between 80 and 3000, preferably
between 400 and 1500 and more preferably between 600 and 1000
mPa.s.</p>
    <p num="0012">The means for preventing the sedimentation of the
powder fraction (also called the "hard fraction") are
important to prevent the powder fraction from sedimentation
after a certain period of time and thus again needs to be
mixed with the oil fraction. Because of these means, an
homogenous end product is obtained. Means which prevent
sedimentation of the powder fraction are preferably chosen
from the group consisting of hardened fats and hardened
monoglycerides.</p>
    <p num="0013">When hardened fats are used, they can be of plant
or animal origin and they are preferably chosen from the
group consisting of hardened palm oil, hardened fractions of
palm oil, hardened soya oil and hardened turnip oil. With 
fractions of palm oil is meant (hard) fractions obtained
through the fractioning of palm oil.</p>
    <p num="0014">To ensure the pumpability of the end product, it is
also important that traditional fat fractions, an oil
fraction of plant or animal origin, are liquid, at room
temperature. Suitable oils are plant oils chosen from the
group which consists of sunflower oil, soya oil, turnip oil,
safflower oil and arachide oil.</p>
    <p num="0015">Emulsifiers are fatty substances that have an
emulsifying through which they interact with the gluten,
proteins and oils, in other word lipids, which are present in
the flour. They provide a more flexible dough, a dough, which
is more tolerant during rising, a more delicate crumb and a
longer tenderness of the bread. Because of their emulsifying
properties, emulsifiers are more active than oils and fats.
In addition, the optimal effect is obtained at lower
concentrations. The optimal addition of and emulsifier is
usually between 0.25 and 0.5 percent in relation to the flour
while usually fat is used in amounts of 1 percent and higher.</p>
    <p num="0016">The emulsifiers, which can be applied to the bread
improver according to the invention, are preferably chosen
from the group consisting of stearoyllactylate and mono-/diglycerides
of fatty acids and the diacetyl tartaric acids
esters of mono and diglycerides (DATEs). The DATEs are
usually applied to bread species which do not originate from
the Netherlands. Stearoyllactylates can be used in the form
of a powder. The mono and diglycerides of fatty acids are
usually also in powder form. When they have a melting point
above 35 degrees, they can also serve as the "hard fraction".
DATES are usually used in a liquid form and are, in this
form, already added to the oil fraction. Nevertheless, they
can also be used as powder and are then part of the powder 
fraction.</p>
    <p num="0017">Besides emulsifiers, the powder fraction can
further contain one or more of the usual micro components.
These micro components are the above mentioned additives and
technological resources, like oxidation and reduction means,
enzymes and flourings.</p>
    <p num="0018">The powder fraction can further contain one or more
basic ingredients, which preferably are chosen from sugars,
grains and/or legumes, vital gluten, starches, milk
derivatives and malt flour.</p>
    <p num="0019">According to the invention, the powder fraction in
the bread improver can be between 5 and 55 percent,
preferably between 10 and 50 percent, and more preferably
between 30 and 50 percent. Because of this, an important
concentration of the important ingredients is possible, while
the bread improver remains pumpable.</p>
    <p num="0020">The invention further relates to a method for the
preparation of a pumpable bread improver comprising:
<sl><li>(a) mixing a liquid oil fraction and means for
preventing sedimentation of the powder fraction at a
temperature at which the means for preventing the
sedimentation of the powder fraction are liquid;</li><li>(b) cooling the obtained mixture; and</li><li>(c) adding and mixing of the powder fraction, which
contains at least one or more emulsifiers.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0021">The mixing of the different fractions can very
simple be done in a mixing apparatus. The means for
preventing the sedimentation of the powder fraction, also
referred to as the "hard fraction", are melted into the oil
fraction. Preferably, the powder fraction will be added when
the temperature of the mixture of the oil fraction and the
hard fraction is lowered under the melting point of the used 
emulsifiers which are present in the powder fraction.</p>
    <p num="0022">The viscosity limits of the pumpable bread
improver, which renders them suitable for use by the general
dosage pumps in the bakeries, is between 80 mPa.s. and 3000
mPa.s. at 20 degrees (determined with a rotoviscometer with a
shifting velocity of 600 per second) with a maximal yield
stress of 100 Pa.s.</p>
    <p num="0023">The invention will further be illustrated by the
following example.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>EXAMPLE</b>
    </heading>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Pumpable bread improver according to the invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0024">For the preparation of a bread improver according
to the invention the following ingredients were used:
<sl><li>Oil fraction:
<sl><li>52% turnip oil</li></sl></li><li>Hard fraction:
<sl><li>1% fully hardened palm oil</li><li>2% mono-/diglycerides of fatty acids</li></sl></li><li>Powder fraction:
<sl><li>30% stearoyllactylate</li><li>11.4% bean flour</li><li>3% ascorbic acid</li><li>0.6% enzymes</li></sl></li></sl></p>
    <p num="0025">The palm oil and the mono-/diglycerides were added
to the turnip oil at a temperature of 80 degrees. After
cooling down of the mixture, the powder fraction was mixed by
using a static mixer. The, in this way, obtained bread 
improver was homogenous and remained homogenous even after
two months of storage at room temperature.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A pumpable bread improver consisting of an oil
fraction and a powder fraction and obtainable by a method
which comprises the following steps:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) mixing the liquid oil fraction and means for
preventing sedimentation of the powder fraction at a
temperature at which the means for preventing of the
sedimentation of the powder fraction are liquid;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) cooling down of the obtained mixture; and</claim-text><claim-text>(c) adding and mixing of the powder fraction, which
contains at least one or more emulsifiers.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A bread improver according to claim 1,
characterized in that the viscosity is between a 80 and 3000
mPa.s.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A bread improver according to claim 2,
characterized in that the viscosity is preferably between 400
and 1500, more preferably between 600 and 1000 mPa.s.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A bread improver according to the claims 1 to 3,
characterized in that the means for preventing the
sedimentation of the powder fraction are chosen from the
group consisting of hardened fats and mono-/diglycerides.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A bread improver according to claim 4,
characterized in that the hardened fats are of plant and/or
animal origin.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A bread improver according to claim 5,
characterized in that the hardened fats are chosen from the
group consisting of hardened palm oil, hardened fractions of
palm oil, hardened soya oil or hardened turnip oil.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A bread improver according to one or more of the
claims 1 to 6, characterized in that the oil fraction is of
plant and/or animal origin.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A bread improver according to claim 7,
characterized in that the oil fraction is chosen from the
group consisting of sunflower oil, soya oil, turnip oil,
safflower oil and arachide oil.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>A bread improver according to one or more of the
claims 1 to 8, characterized in that the emulsifiers are
chosen from the group consisting of stearoyllactylates, mono- and
diglycerides of fatty acids, diacetyl tartaric acid
esters of mono- and diglycerides (DATEs).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>A bread improver according to one or more of
the claims 1 to 9, characterized in that the powder fraction
further contains one or more micro components which are
chosen from the group consisting of oxidation and reduction
means, enzymes, aromas and flourings.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>A bread improver according to one or more of
the claims 1 to 10, characterized in that the powder fraction
further comprises one or more basic ingredients which are
chosen from the group consisting of sugars, flour of grains
and/or legumes, vital glutes, starches, physically modified
starches, salt, milk derivatives and malt flour.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>A bread improver according to one or more of
the claims 1 to 11, characterized in that the powder
fraction forms 5 to 55 percent, preferably 10 to 50 percent
and more preferably between 30 to 50 percent of the bread
improver.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>A method for preparation of a pumpable bread
improver comprising
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) mixing the liquid oil fraction and means for
preventing sedimentation of the powder fraction at a
temperature at which the means for preventing the
sedimentation of the powder fraction are liquid;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) cooling down of the obtained mixture; and</claim-text><claim-text>(c) adding and mixing of the powder fraction which
contains at least one or more emulsifiers.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>A method according to claim 13, characterized
in that the oil fraction, the powder fraction and means for
preventing sedimentation of the powder fraction are defined
as in claims 2 to 12.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
