<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1258680-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1258680" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="32715152" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021120">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1258680-A2" status="new" fvid="23614375">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1258680</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021120</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02253449-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02253449</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020515</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="GB-0111971-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>GB</country>
          <doc-number>0111971</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010516</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
      <priority-claim ucid="US-15774602-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>15774602</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20020529</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23N   5/00        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23N   5/00        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23N   5/24        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23N   5/24        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23N   5/26        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23N   5/26        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F23N   5/24B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F23N   5/26B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">R23N31:20</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">R23N5:00B</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Sicherheitsmodul für einen Brenner und Gerät mit solchem Modul</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Safety module for fuel-burning appliance, and appliance using such a module</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Module de sécurité pour un brûleur et un appareil utilisant un tel module</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MONOX LTD</name>
            <address>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MONOX LIMITED</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Monox Limited</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Dawley Road</street>
              <city>Hayes, Middlesex UB3 1HH</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>PERRYMAN CHARLES</name>
            <address>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>PERRYMAN, CHARLES</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>PERRYMAN, CHARLES</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Little Acres 16 Shiphay Park Road</street>
              <city>Torquay Devon TQ2 7DJ</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Sharp, Alan Cooper</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>QED I.P. Services Limited, Dawley Road</street>
              <city>Hayes, Middlesex UB3 1HH</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>The invention provides a safety module (1) for connection to a fuel-burning appliance
(11). The safety module connects to the existing circuitry of the appliance and triggers
an alarm response when certain predetermined conditions are met. The safety
module includes a CO sensor (3) and processing means (4) and can respond not only
to acutely high CO levels but also to chronically high CO levels and lack of adherence
to service schedules amongst other conditions. Means (7) are provided whereby the
safety module (1) can be programmed/reset.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="151" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="104"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">The invention relates to a safety module for a fuel-burning appliance, and to an
appliance using such a safety module. In particular, the invention relates to a safety
module which provides an alarm response (such as shutting off the fuel supply or
sounding an alarm) when predetermined conditions are reached.</p>
    <p num="0002">Fuel-burning appliances are of many types. Fuels used include gas, kerosene, solid
fuel and many others. Fuel-burning appliances are commonly used for e.g. heating in
both domestic and commercial applications. A well-known and dangerous by-product
of such appliances, however, is carbon monoxide. Carbon monoxide is an odourless,
tasteless, poisonous gas, which cannot readily be detected. In conjunction with fuel-burning
appliances, therefore, some form of CO detector is frequently supplied, either
as a separate detector or as an integral part of the appliance.</p>
    <p num="0003">One type of device used to sense the presence of CO is an Oxygen Depletion Sensor
(ODS), which responds to a drop in the oxygen concentration of the surrounding air.
ODS sensors commonly produce an alarm response when the oxygen level drops to,
say, 95% of the normal level. A typical alarm response might be, for example, the
cutting off of the fuel supply and/or the sounding of an alarm signal. It is well known,
however, that concentrations of CO which are not low enough to trigger an ODS may
still be high enough to cause ill effects, particularly over a long period. It has therefore 
been suggested to use a detector which reacts to the presence of carbon monoxide
(as opposed to the absence of oxygen), either instead of or as well as an ODS.</p>
    <p num="0004">The provision of both a carbon monoxide sensor and an ODS in a fuel-burning
appliance has hitherto required the provision of two separate circuits in the appliance,
bringing with it increased complexity and costs. The absence of both types of sensor,
however, can lead to ill health and possibly fatal effects.</p>
    <p num="0005">It is an object of the present invention to provide a safety module for a fuel-burning
appliance which avoids the above problems. In particular, it is an object of the present
invention to provide a safety module for a fuel-burning appliance which is simple,
economical, easily maintained &amp; replaced and which provides early detection of high
levels of carbon monoxide. It is a further object of the invention to provide a safety
module which responds not only to acutely high levels of CO but also to chronically
high levels of CO and provides a means to ensure adherence to servicing
requirements etc. It is a yet further object of the present invention to provide such a
safety module which responds to certain predetermined conditions, the said
predetermined conditions being easily programmable and alterable. It is a still further
object of the present invention to provide a fuel-burning appliance using such a safety
module.</p>
    <p num="0006">In accordance with the above objects the invention provides a safety module for a
fuel-burning appliance, the said safety module being adapted and arranged for 
connection to a fuel-burning appliance so that an alarm response of the fuel-burning
appliance is triggered by an alarm signal of the said safety module, the safety module
comprising processing means adapted so as to initiate a said safety module alarm
signal when one or more predetermined conditions have been reached.</p>
    <p num="0007">Preferably the said processing means includes a suitably programmed integrated
circuit chip. Advantageously, programming means are provided whereby
programming of the said processing means may be effected.</p>
    <p num="0008">Preferably the said safety module includes a carbon monoxide sensor connected to
the said processing means. Particularly preferably, the said safety module is adapted
to be connected to the existing alarm circuitry of a fuel-burning appliance.
Advantageously, the said existing alarm circuitry includes an oxygen depletion
sensor.</p>
    <p num="0009">Advantageously, the said predetermined conditions include one or more of the
following; the detection of a CO level by the said CO sensor over a predetermined
first threshold value at any one time; the detection of a CO level by the said CO
sensor over a predetermined second threshold value over a predetermined time
period; a predetermined time interval having elapsed and/or, where the said safety
module is provided with reset means, the safety module having been reset a
predetermined number of times. Particularly preferably, the programming means may
be used to program the processing means with a value for one or more of the said 
first threshold value, second threshold value, predetermined time interval and / or
predetermined number of times. Preferably, means are provided to provide a
permanent alarm signal when any or all of the said predetermined conditions have
been met.</p>
    <p num="0010">According to a preferred realisation of the invention the components thereof are
provided on a printed circuit board so as to provide an integrated safety module.</p>
    <p num="0011">According to another aspect, the invention provides a fuel-burning appliance having a
safety module as described above.</p>
    <p num="0012">For a better understanding of the present invention and to show more clearly how it
may be carried into effect, reference will now be made, by way of example, to the
accompanying drawings which show schematically various embodiments of the
present invention. The figures are not to scale.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="8"><dt>Figure 1</dt><dd>shows a safety module according to one embodiment of the present
invention; and</dd><dt>Figure 2</dt><dd>shows the module of Figure 1 installed in an appliance.</dd></dl></p>
    <p num="0013">Figure 1 shows a safety module (1) which comprises a printed circuit board (2) upon
which is mounted a carbon monoxide sensor (3) such as a Monox Compact sensor
manufactured by Monox Ltd., UK. An Integrated Circuit (IC) chip (4) is also provided 
on the circuit board. The IC (4) has a two-way connection (5) to the sensor (3). The IC
(4) also has an alarm line (6) for outputting an alarm signal. A socket (7) is also
connected to the IC (4) by means of a second two-way connection (8). During
assembly and commissioning/servicing of the safety module (1), the plug (9) of a
control device (not shown) can be inserted into the socket (7) so that signals can be
input to/read from the IC (4). The module (1) can thereby be calibrated/reset. This
plug-and-socket arrangement provides readily accessible means to perform
sophisticated programming/resetting functions. The IC (4) has been pre-programmed
with software which uses signals from the CO sensor (3) to calculate and monitor the
amblent carbon monoxide level and provide an appropriate signal on the alarm line
(6) depending on the detected conditions. A power supply (10) typically a dry cell
battery, provides power for the module. The IC (4) has an integral clock, which is
used to help determine the maintenance requirements and servicing frequency.</p>
    <p num="0014">In Figure 2 a gas appliance (shown partially as 11) has a safety module (1) installed.
The gas appliance is provided with an oxygen depletion sensor (12) which has an
ODS alarm line (13). The ODS alarm line (13) is used to trigger an alarm response of
the gas appliance when low oxygen levels are detected. A particular signal appearing
on the alarm line (13) may, for example, trigger the sounding of an audible alarm
and/or cut off the gas supply to the appliance. The safety module (1) is adapted and
arranged for connection to the ODS alarm line (13) by means of a connector (14) in
such a way that a suitable alarm signal output by either the ODS (12) or the safety
module (1) will trigger the alarm response. In this way, a separate wiring system is not 
required for the safety module (1) of the invention. The carbon monoxide level at
which the safety module (1) can provide a warning is several orders of magnitude
below required to trigger the ODS (12) on its own.</p>
    <p num="0015">The integral safety module (1) is preferably self-contained. The battery (10) and
sensor (3) are replaceable. The module is connected to the alarm line (13) of an
existing ODS (12) to fulfil its intended role. The module (1) is designed to be securely
and permanently attached to e.g. the base of a fuel-burning appliance such as a gas-fired
heater. The CO sensor (3) may be positioned so as to monitor the air in the
environment of the gas appliance, or may be positioned so as to monitor air in a
particular area of the appliance such as an inlet duct or outlet duct.</p>
    <p num="0016">The software installed on the IC (4) can be configured to activate an alarm signal at
varying (predetermined) levels of CO. These can be a single set point or averaged
over time, or set so as to comply with any existing standard such as any statutory
British, European, or North American residential carbon monoxide detector standard
as appropriate. Alternatively, the safety module could be programmed so as to
comply with commercial or industrial boiler applications and their requisite standards
using an appropriate relay.</p>
    <p num="0017">Preferably, the IC (4) is programmed so as to interrupt the operation of the appliance
(11) if has not been serviced (and the module reset) after a certain time, say 13
months. This feature has been designed to assist landlords trying to fulfil their 
obligations under statutory regulations requiring regular inspections. This obligation is
often difficult to meet as tenants are not always keen on allowing authorised staff
entry to perform the inspections. The IC can therefore be programmed to trigger an
alarm situation (e.g. a fuel cut-off) every 20 minutes or so causing the occupant to
have to re-light the appliance every 20 minutes or get it properly serviced. This will
encourage regular servicing. During the service the module can then be reset the to
provide a further 13 months of operation. Alternatively, or additionally, the IC (4) can
be programmed so that a specific number (e.g. five) operations of the reset function
will require the installation of a new sensor in line with e.g. warranty requirements.
Tamper-evident systems may also be provided.</p>
    <p num="0018">The invention therefore provides an integrated safety module for connection to a fuel-burning
appliance. The safety module connects to the existing circuitry of the
appliance and triggers an alarm response when certain predetermined conditions are
met. The safety module includes a CO sensor and processing means and can
respond not only to acutely high CO levels but also to chronically high CO levels and
can also respond to pre-set service schedules amongst other conditions. Means are
provided whereby the safety module can be programmed/reset.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A safety module (1) for a fuel-burning appliance (11), the said safety module being
adapted and arranged for connection to a fuel-burning appliance (11) so that an
alarm response of the fuel-burning appliance (11) is triggered by an alarm signal
of the said safety module (1), characterised in that the safety module (1)
comprises processing means (4) adapted so as to initiate a said safety module
alarm signal when one or more predetermined conditions have been reached.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A safety module according to claim 1 wherein the said processing means includes
a suitably programmed integrated circuit chip (4).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A safety module according to claim 1 or 2 wherein programming means (7) are
provided whereby programming of the said processing means (4) may be
effected.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A safety module according to any previous claim wherein the said safety module
(1) includes a carbon monoxide sensor (3) connected to the said processing
means (4).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A safety module according to any previous claim wherein the said safety module
(1) is adapted to be connected to the existing alarm circuitry (13) of a fuel-burning
appliance.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A safety module according to claim 5 wherein the said existing alarm circuitry
includes an oxygen depletion sensor (12).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A safety module according to any previous claim wherein the said predetermined
conditions include one or more of the following; the detection of a CO level by the
said carbon monoxide sensor (3) over a predetermined first threshold value at any
one time; the detection of a CO level by the said carbon monoxide sensor (3) over
a predetermined second threshold value over a predetermined time period; a
predetermined time interval having elapsed and/or, where the said safety module
(1) is provided with reset means, the safety module having been reset a
predetermined number of times.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A safety module according to claim 8 wherein means are provided to provide a
permanent alarm signal when any or all or the said predetermined conditions have
been met.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>A safety module according to claim 3 and claim 7 or claim 8 wherein the
programming means (7) may be used to program the processing means (4) with a
value for one or more of the said first threshold value, second threshold value,
predetermined time interval and/or predetermined number of times.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>A safety module according to any previous claim wherein the components thereof
are provided on a printed circuit board (2) so as to provide an integrated safety
module.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>A fuel-burning appliance having a safety module as described in any previous
claim.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>A device substantially as herein described and illustrated in the accompanying
drawings.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
