<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1254780-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1254780" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="18981713" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021106">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1254780-A2" status="new" fvid="23584387">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1254780</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021106</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02253085-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02253085</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020501</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001133938-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001133938</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010501</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/28        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/28        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/30        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/30        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/337       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/40        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/40        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/42        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/44        20060101A N20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03F   7/004       20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03F   7/004       20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03F   7/26        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G03F   7/26        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41M   5/28M</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41M   5/337M</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41M   5/42D</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L41M5:337B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L41M5:337D</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L41M5:44</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Aufzeichnungsmaterial</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Recording material</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Matériau d'enregistrement</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>FUJI PHOTO FILM CO LTD</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>FUJI PHOTO FILM CO., LTD.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Fuji Photo Film Co., Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>210 Nakanuma Minamiashigara-shi</street>
              <city>Kanagawa-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NAGATA KOZO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>WASHIZU SHINTARO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>NAGATA, KOZO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>WASHIZU, SHINTARO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Nagata, Kozo, c/o Fuji Photo Film Co., Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>No. 200 Ohnakazato</street>
              <city>Fujinomiya-shi, Shizuoka-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Washizu, Shintaro, Fuji Photo Film Co., Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>No. 200 Ohnakazato</street>
              <city>Fujinomiya-shi, Shizuoka-ken</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Calamita, Roberto</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Frank B. Dehn &amp;amp; Co., European Patent Attorneys, 179 Queen Victoria Street</street>
              <city>London EC4V 4EL</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>The present invention provides a recording material
comprising a support, a recording layer provided on the support,
and at least one protective layer provided on the recording
layer, wherein, the recording layer contains a coloring
component A encapsulated in heat-responsive microcapsules, and
a substantially colorless compound B, which is outside the
heat-responsive microcapsules and has a coloring site that
colors when reacted with the coloring component A, and wherein,
at least one of the protective layer or a layer adjacent thereto
comprises a layer containing titanium oxide.</p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <heading>Field of the Invention</heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a recording material
that can record with high sensitivity to light in the
ultraviolet, visible and infrared regions and can be applied
to a wide range of fields, such as inks, color filters, holograms,
proofs, sealants, adhesives, surface printing, resin relief
printing and photoresists, and to an image forming method that
the recording material.</p>
    <heading>Description of the Related Art</heading>
    <p num="0002">Dry type image recording methods that do not use a liquid
developer and do not cause waste have been variously studied.
Among these recording methods, a method using a composition that
is cured with light is attracting attention. This method is
characterized in that a photocurable composition, which is
contained in the recording material, is cured by exposure to
form a latent image, and a component, which has a coloring or
decoloring reaction when heated, is moved to form a color image.
Specifically, light exposes a recording material through an
image copy, and a latent image is formed by curing the exposed
part. Thereafter, a visual image can be formed by heating the
recording material, and moving, in the uncured (unexposed) part,
the coloring or decoloring component, which is inside the 
recording material.</p>
    <p num="0003">According to the method, a completely dry system that
causes no waste can be realized. The method is characteristic
in recording a monochrome image and is particularly useful for
recording a color image.</p>
    <p num="0004">The inventors have proposed in JP-A No. 3-87827 and No.
4-211252 recording materials that suppress coloration in a
non-image part and provide a high image density. In the former
recording material, one of two components of a two-component
type photosensitive and heat-sensitive coloration recording
material is encapsulated in microcapsules, and the other is used
as a curable compound of a photo-curable composition, or the
other is contained outside the microcapsules with the
photo-curable composition. The later recording material has
a coated layer containing a photo-curable composition, which
contains microcapsules encapsulating an electron-donor
colorless colorant, and outside the microcapsules, an
electron-acceptor compound, a polymerizable vinyl monomer and
a photopolymerization initiator.</p>
    <p num="0005">There is a demand for these recording materials to provide
high glossiness to impart sophisticated feeling to an image.
Furthermore, improvements in light fastness of the image are
also desired in order to impart a value to the image such that
the image can be appreciated for a long period of time. </p>
    <p num="0006">The present invention is to solve the problems in the
conventional art and to attain the following objects.</p>
    <p num="0007">One of the objects of the invention is to provide a
recording material providing high glossiness and high light
fastness and a process for forming an image using the recording
material.</p>
    <heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0008">The objects of the present invention can be attained by
the following means. That is, the invention relates to, as one
aspect, a recording material comprising:
<sl><li>a support;</li><li>a recording layer provided on the support; and</li><li>at least one protective layer provided on the recording
layer,</li></sl>
   wherein, the recording layer contains a coloring
component A encapsulated in heat-responsive microcapsules, and
a substantially colorless compound B, which is outside the
heat-responsive microcapsules and has a coloring site that
colors when reacted with the coloring component A, and

   wherein, at least one of the protective layer or a layer
adjacent thereto comprises a layer containing titanium oxide.</p>
    <p num="0009">In one embodiment of the present invention, the
protective layer includes at least two layers, and an outermost
layer of the protective layer or a layer adjacent to the
outermost layer is the layer containing titanium oxide. </p>
    <p num="0010">In another embodiment of the present invention, the
recording layer further contains a photopolymerizable
composition.</p>
    <p num="0011">In a further embodiment of the present invention, the
compound B includes the coloring site and a polymerizable group
in one molecule.</p>
    <p num="0012">In a further embodiment of the present invention, the
recording layer further contains a substantially colorless
compound C, which has a site that suppresses a reaction between
the coloring component A and the compound B and a polymerizable
group in one molecule.</p>
    <p num="0013">In a further embodiment of the present invention,
titanium oxide contained in the layer containing titanium oxide
has a particle diameter of no more than 0.2 µm.</p>
    <p num="0014">In a further embodiment of the present invention, an
amount of titanium oxide contained in the layer containing
titanium oxide is from 5 to 90% by weight relative to the layer
containing titanium oxide.</p>
    <p num="0015">In a further embodiment of the present invention, the
layer containing titanium oxide comprises a binder formed in
a layer having titanium oxide dispersed on a surface thereof,
which binder comprises polyvinyl alcohol.</p>
    <p num="0016">The present invention also relates to, as another aspect,
a process for forming an image using a recording material
comprising: <sl><li>a support;</li><li>a recording layer provided on the support and containing
a photopolymerizable composition; and</li><li>at least one protective layer provided on the recording
layer,</li></sl>
   wherein, the process comprising the steps of:
<sl><li>exposing the recording material, causing the
photopolymerizable composition to form a latent image;</li><li>coloring after the exposing step, causing the coloring
component to form an image, which corresponds to the latent
image, by heating with a heat roller; and</li><li>fixing the formed image and decoloring the
photopolymerization initiator component contained in the
photopolymerizable composition by irradiating the recording
layer with light, wherein the recording layer containing:
<sl><li>a coloring component A encapsulated in heat-responsive
microcapsules; and</li><li>a substantially colorless compound B being present
outside the heat-responsive microcapsules and having a coloring
part coloring upon reacting with the coloring component A, and</li></sl></li></sl>
   wherein, at least one of the protective layer or a layer
adjacent thereto comprises a layer containing titanium oxide.</p>
    <heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
    <p num="0017">In the recording material of the present invention, at 
least one recording layer is formed on a support, encapsulated
the recording layer containing a coloring component A
encapsulated in heat-responsive microcapsules, and a
substantially colorless coloring component B, which is outside
the heat-responsive microcapsules and has a coloring site which
produces a color when reacted with the coloring component A.
The recording material has a protective layer, which contains
at least one layer, as the outermost layer of the recording
material on the side of the recording layer, and the protective
layer or a layer adjacent to the protective layer has a layer
containing titanium oxide (TiO<sub>2</sub>). Namely, when the protective
layer of the recording material of the present invention is
formed from one layer, this protective layer is formed as the
layer containing titanium oxide. Alternatively, when the
protective layer is formed from more than one layer, the layer
containing titanium oxide is formed on the outermost layer of
the recording layer and the protective layer, which is
different from the layer containing titanium oxide, is formed
on the layer containing titanium oxide. In both of these cases,
glossiness and light fastness can be imparted to the recording
material by the layer containing titanium oxide.</p>
    <p num="0018">Further, in the image forming method of the present
invention, image formation can be preferably performed onto
the recording material by an image forming method, which uses
the aforementioned recording material, and comprises an 
exposure step, a coloring step, and a fixing step.</p>
    <p num="0019">The recording material and the process for forming an
image of the present invention will be described in detail
below.</p>
    <heading>Recording Material</heading>
    <p num="0020">The recording material of the present invention may be
monochromatic or polychromatic. In the case of the
monochromatic recording material, one recording layer having
photosensitivity is provided, and a protective layer is
provided as the outermost layer of the recording material on
the recording layer side. In the case of polychromatic
recording material, at least one recording layer having
photosensitivity to a certain wavelength or lower is provided,
and at least one recording layer having sensitivity to a region
exceeding the certain wavelength is also provided, with a
protective layer being provided as the outermost layer. The
protective layer may have either a single layer structure or
a laminated layer structure having two or more layers. The
recording material may have an intermediate layer, and multiple
intermediate layers may be provided.</p>
    <p num="0021">The basic embodied structure of the recording material
of the present invention is not particularly limited and may
be appropriately selected depending on purposes there of.</p>
    <p num="0022">As one embodiment of the basic constitutional structure,
an example of image formation will be described below of a case 
in which the recording material of the invention is applied to
a positive recording material.</p>
    <p num="0023">In the positive recording material of this embodiment,
radicals are generated, upon imagewise irradiation with light,
from a radical generator contained in the photopolymerizable
composition on the irradiated part, and a polymerization
reaction of the polymerizable compound is initiated, hardening
the polymerizable compound so as to fix the photopolymerizable
compound thereon, whereby a latent image is formed. The
microcapsules have unpermeability to substances at or below
ordinary temperature, and thus the coloring component A
encapsulated in the microcapsules and the compound B having a
site, which colors when reacted with the coloring component A,
are not in contact with each other, and the microcapsules are
in a non-colored state.</p>
    <p num="0024">Thereafter, when heat is applied to the entire surface
of the recording material, the microcapsules are transformed
to have permeability to substances. B On the non-irradiated
portion, the compound penetrates into the microcapsules (and/or
the coloring component A is released to the outside of the
microcapsules), whereby the coloring component A and the
compound B react with each other to form a color only on the
non-irradiated part. On the other hand, because the
photopolymerizable composition is cured and in a fixed state
by the polymerization reaction in the irradiated portion, both 
the coloring component A and the compound B are immobilized and
are not in contact with each other, preventing coloration on
the irradiated part. Thereafter, by exposing the entire
surface of the recording material, the polymerizable
composition on the unpolymerized part are polymerized
(fixation), and the dye contained in the photopolymerizable
composition can be decolored.</p>
    <p num="0025">The recording material of the present invention may be
recording material of the following embodiments (first and
second embodiments), and the image forming method therefor may
also be appropriately selected in accordance with the
embodiments.</p>
    <p num="0026">In the recording material of the first embodiment of the
invention, the polymerizable compound contained in the
photopolymerizable composition is the compound B itself. That
is, the compound B has both the site coloring when reacted with
the coloring component A and the polymerizable group in one
molecule. The recording material comprises the coloring
component A, the compound B and the photopolymerizable
composition. In the case where the embodiment is applied to
an example of the positive recording material of the
aforementioned basic embodiment, the compound B has, as
described above, both the site that colors when reacted with
the coloring component A and the polymerizable group. The
compound B initiates a polymerization reaction and cures when 
irradiated with light in a shape of the image, whereby the
compound B is fixed thereon to form a latent image. Therefore,
the compound B is immobilized in the irradiated portion and does
not contact the coloring component A, and coloration does not
occur in the irradiated portion.</p>
    <p num="0027">In the second embodiment of the recording material of the
present invention, the recording layer contains the
substantially colorless compound B, which has a site that
colors when reacted with the coloring component A, the
substantially colorless compound C, which has a site that
suppresses the reaction between the coloring component A and
the compound B and a polymerizable group in the same molecule,
and a photopolymerizable composition.</p>
    <p num="0028">An example of image formation will be described where
the recording material of the present embodiment, having the
coloring component A encompassed in the heat-responsive
microcapsules, is applied to a negative recording material.</p>
    <p num="0029">Similar to the first embodiment, the microcapsules in the
negative recording material of the present embodiment have
unpermeability to substances at an ordinary temperature, and
thus the coloring component A and the compound B do not contact
each other, and are in a non-colored state. When the recording
material is irradiated with light in a form of an image, the
polymerization reaction of the polymerizable compound on the
irradiated portion is initiated and cured, and the 
polymerizable compound is fixed thereon to form a latent image.
Thereafter, when heat is applied to the entire surface of the
recording material, the microcapsules are transformed to be
permeable to substances, and the compound B on the
non-irradiated part penetrates into the microcapsules (and/or
the coloring component A is released to the outside of the
microcapsules). Simultaneously, on the non-irradiated portion,
the compound C penetrates into the microcapsules, as a
coloration suppressing compound, to suppress the coloring
reaction of the coloring component A and the compound B.
Therefore, the non-irradiated part is maintained in the
non-colored state. On the other hand, because the compound C
(coloration suppressing compound) on the irradiated part is
fixed thereon through a polymerization reaction, it does not
intervene in the reaction of the coloring component A and the
compound B, and the coloring reaction proceeds, and thus
coloration is effected only on the irradiated portion.
Thereafter, the entire surface of the recording material is
exposed to decolor the dye contained in the photopolymerization
composition.</p>
    <p num="0030">As a light source used in the image formation by the
recording material of the present invention, light sources of
blue to red and infrared lasers can be preferably selected.</p>
    <p num="0031">The respective layers constituting the recording
material of the invention will be described below. </p>
    <heading>Recording Layer</heading>
    <p num="0032">The recording material of the invention has a support
having a recording layer disposed thereon, and at least one
layer of the recording layer contains a coloring component A
encapsulated in heat-responsive microcapsules, at least one
substantially colorless compound B (hereinafter sometimes
referred to as a "coloring component B"), which is present
outside the heat-responsive microcapsules and has a coloring
site, which colors when reacted with the coloring component A,
and a photopolymerizable composition.</p>
    <p num="0033">The recording layer can be formed by coating a coating
composition, which is prepared by containing respective
components. An image can be formed on the coated recording layer
by, as described above, an image forming method having a step
of irradiating the recording layer with light, which
corresponds to sensitive wavelengths of the respective layers
to form a latent image (exposing step), a step of coloring a
color image by coloring the coloring components, which
correspond to the latent image, by heating (coloring step), and
a step of fixing the formed image and decoloring the dye through
irradiation of the surface of the recording layer with light
(fixing step).</p>
    <heading>Photopolymerizable Composition</heading>
    <p num="0034">The photopolymerizable composition constituting the
recording layer has at least a polymerizable compound, a 
photopolymerization initiator and an organic boron compound.</p>
    <heading>Polymerizable Compound</heading>
    <p num="0035">The polymerizable compound has at least one ethylenic
unsaturated double bond in the molecule thereof, is not
particularly limited and can be appropriately selected
depending on purposes. Examples thereof include acrylic acid
derivatives, such as acrylates and acrylamides, acrylic acids
and salts thereof, methacrylic acid derivatives, such as
methacrylates and methacrylamides, methacrylic acids and salts
thereof, maleic anhydrides, maleates, itaconic acids,
itaconates, styrene compounds, vinyl ethers, vinyl esters,
N-vinyl heterocyclic compounds, allyl ethers and allyl esters.</p>
    <p num="0036">The polymerizable compound may have one or more olefinic
double bonds and may have either a low molecular weight
(monomer) or a relatively high molecular weight (oligomer).</p>
    <p num="0037">Examples of the monomer containing a double bond include
alkyl or hydroxyalkyl acrylates or methacrylates, such as
methyl acrylates, ethyl acrylates, butyl acrylates,
2-ethylhexyl acrylates, 2-hydroxyethyl acrylates, isobornyl
acrylates, methyl methacrylates and ethyl methacrylates. A
silicon acrylate is also advantageously used.</p>
    <p num="0038">Other examples thereof include acrylonitriles,
acrylamides, methacrylamides, N-substituted
(meth)acrylamides, vinyl esters, such as vinyl acetates,
vinyl ethers, such as isobutyl vinyl ethers, styrenes, 
alkyl- and halostyrene, N-vinylpyrrolidone, vinyl chlorides
and vinylidene chlorides.</p>
    <p num="0039">Examples of the monomer containing two or more double
bonds include diacrylates, such as ethylene glycols, propylene
glycols, neopentyl glycols, hexamethylene glycols and
bisphenol A, 4,4'-bis(2-acryloyloxyethoxy)diphenylpropanes,
trimethylolpropane triacrylates, pentaerythritol
triacrylates or tetraacrylates, vinyl acrylates,
divinylbenzenes, divinyl succinates, diallyl phthalates,
triallyl phosphate, triallyl isocyanurate and
tris(2-acryloylethyl) isocyanurate.</p>
    <p num="0040">Examples of the polyunsaturated compound having a
relatively high molecular weight (oligomer) include epoxy
resins having a (meth)acrylic group, polyesters having a
(meth)acrylic group, and polyesters, polyurethanes or
polyethers having a vinyl ether or an epoxy group. Furthermore,
examples of the unsaturated oligomer include an unsaturated
polyester resin that is generally produced from maleic acid,
phthalic acid and at least one diol and has a molecular weight
of about from 500 to 3, 000. Additionally, vinyl ether monomers
and oligomers, and oligomers terminated by maleates having a
polyester, polyurethane, polyether, polyvinyl ether or epoxy
main chain. Particularly preferred examples thereof include
a combination of an oligomer having a vinyl ether group and a
polymer disclosed in International Patent Application 
WO90/01512. Copolymers of vinyl ether and monomers having
maleic acid functionality are also preferred. These kinds of
unsaturated oligomers can also be categorized as prepolymers.</p>
    <p num="0041">Particularly preferred examples include esters of an
ethylenic unsaturated carboxylic acid and polyols or
polyepoxides, polymers having an ethylenic unsaturated bond on
a main chain or a side chain thereof, such as unsaturated
polyesters, polyamides or polyurethanes and copolymers thereof,
alkyd resins, polybutadienes, butadiene copolymers,
polyisoprenes, isoprene copolymers, polymers or copolymers
having a (meth)acrylate group on a side chain thereof, and
mixtures containing one or more of these polymers.</p>
    <p num="0042">Examples of the unsaturated carboxylic acid include
acrylic acids, methacrylic acids, crotonic acids, itaconic
acids, cinnamic acids, and unsaturated fatty acids, such as
linoleic acids and oleic acids. Among these, acrylic acids and
methacrylic acids are preferred.</p>
    <p num="0043">Suitable examples of the polyol include an aromatic, and
particularly aliphatic and alicyclic polyols. Examples of the
aromatic polyol include hydroquinone, 4,4'-dihydroxydiphenyl,
2,2-di(4-hydroxyphenyl)propane, novolak and resorcin.
Examples of the polyepoxide include those based on the
aforementioned polyols, particularly the aromatic polyol, and
epichlorohydrin. Other suitable examples of the polyol
include polymers or copolymers containing a hydroxyl group on 
a polymer chain or a side chain thereof, such as polyvinyl
alcohols and copolymers thereof, and polyhydroxyalkyl
methacrylates and copolymers thereof. Further suitable
examples of the polyol include oligoesters having a hydroxyl
end group.</p>
    <p num="0044">Examples of the aliphatic and alicyclic polyols include
an alkylenediols preferably having from 2 to 12 carbon atoms,
such as ethylene glycols, 1,2- or 1,3-propanediols, 1,2-,
1,3- or 1,4-butanediols, pentanediols, hexanediols,
octanediols, dodecanediols, diethylene glycols and
triethylene glycols, polyethylene glycols having a molecular
weight of from 200 to 1,500, 1,3-cyclopentanediols, 1,2-,
1,3- or 1,4-cyclohexanediols,
1,4-dihydroxymethylcyclohexanes, glycerols,
tris(β-hydroxyethyl)amines, trimethylolethanes,
trimethylolpropanes, pentaerythritols, dipentaerythritols
and sorbitols.</p>
    <p num="0045">The polyol may be partially or completely esterified with
one kind of a carboxylic acid or different kinds of unsaturated
carboxylic acids, and in the partial ester, the free hydroxyl
group may be modified, for example, by being etherified or
esterified with another carboxylic acid.</p>
    <p num="0046">Examples of the ester include trimethylolpropane
triacrylates, trimethylolethane triacrylates,
trimethylolpropane trimethacrylates, trimethyloethane 
trimethacrylates, tetramethylene glycol dimethacryates,
triethylene glycol dimethacrylates, tetraethylene glycol
diacrylates, pentaerythritol diacrylates, pentaerythritol
triacrylates, pentaerythritol tetraacrylates,
dipentaerythritol diacrylates, dipentaerythritol
triacrylates, dipentaerythritol tetraacrylates,
dipentaerythritol pentaacrylates, dipentaerythritol
hexaacrylates, tripentaerythritol octaacrylates;
pentaerythritol dimethacrylates, pentaerythritol
trimethacrylates, dipentaerythritol dimethacyrlates,
dipentaerythritol tetramethacrylates, tripentaerythritol
octamethacrylates, pentaerythritol diitaconates,
dipentaerythritol trisitaconates, dipentaerythritol
pentaitaconates, dipentaerythritol hexaitaconates, ethylene
glycol diacrylates, 1,3-butanediol diacrylates,
1,3-butanediol dimethacrylates, 1,4-butanediol diitaconates,
sorbitol triacrylates, sorbitol tetraacrylates,
pentaerythritol modified triacrylates, sorbitol
tetramethacrylates, sorbitol pentaacrylates, sorbitol
hexaacrylates, oligoester acrylates and methacrylates,
glycerol diacrylates and triacrylates, 1,4-cyclohexane
diacrylates, bisacrylates and bismethacrylates of
polyethylene glycol having a molecular weight of from 200 to
1,500, and mixtures thereof.</p>
    <p num="0047">Suitable examples of the polymerizable compound include 
amides of one kind or amides of two or more different kinds of
unsaturated carboxylic acids and aromatic, alicyclic or
aliphatic polyamines preferably having from 2 to 6,
particularly preferably from 2 to 4, amino groups.</p>
    <p num="0048">Examples of the polyamine include ethylene diamines,
1,2- or 1,3-propylene diamines, 1,2-, 1,3- or 1,4-butylene
diamines, 1,5-pentylene diamines, 1,6-hexylene diamines,
octylene diamines, dodecylene diamines,
1,4-diaminocyclohexanes, isophorone diamines, phenylene
diamines, bisphenylene diamines, di-β-aminoethyl ethers,
diethylene triamines, triethylene tetramines and
di(β-aminoethoxy)- or di(β-aminopropoxy)ethanes.
Furthermore, polymers or copolymers further having an amino
group, preferably on a side chain thereof, and oligoamides
having an amino end group are preferred. Examples of the
unsaturated polyamide include methylene bisacrylamides,
1,6-hexamethylene bisacrylamides, diethylene triamine
trismethacrylamides, bis(methacrylamide propoxy)ethanes,
β-methacrylamideethyl methacrylates and
N-((β-hydroxyethoxy)ethyl) acrylamides.</p>
    <p num="0049">Suitable examples of the unsaturated polyester and
polyamide can be derived from maleic acid and a diol or a diamine.
A certain proportion of the maleic acid can be substituted by
other dicarboxylic acids. These may be used with an ethylenic
unsaturated comonomer, such as styrene. The polyester and the 
polyamide can be derived from dicarboxylic acids and from
ethylenic unsaturated diols or diamines, and particularly from
those having a relatively long chain, such as those having from
6 to 20 carbon atoms. Examples of the polyurethane include
those constituted with saturated or unsaturated diisocyanates
and unsaturated or saturated diols.</p>
    <p num="0050">The polybutadienes, the polyisoprenes and the copolymers
thereof are known in the art. Suitable examples of the
comonomer include olefins, such as ethylenes, propenes, butenes
and hexyenes, (meth)acrylates, acrylonitriles, styrenes and
vinyl chlorides. The polymer having a (meth)acrylate group on
a side chain thereof is also known in the art. It can be obtained,
for example, as a reaction product of epoxy resins based on
novolaks and (meth)acrylic acids, homo- or copolymers of vinyl
alcohol or (meth)acrylic acids and esterified hydroxyalkyl
derivatives thereof, or homo- or copolymers of a (meth)acrylate
that is esterified with a hydroxyalkyl (meth)acrylate.</p>
    <p num="0051">The polymerizable compound may have a site exhibiting
other functions in the structure thereof, depending on the
purpose of the photopolymerizable composition. For example, in
the case where the photopolymerizable composition is utilized
in a recording material, the compound may have a site, which
accelerates the coloring reaction of the coloring component
constituting an image portion, and a site, which suppresses
coloration. These will be described later. </p>
    <p num="0052">The total content of the polymerizable compound is
preferably from 30.0 to 99.9% by weight, and more preferably
from 50.0 to 90.0% by weight, of the total solid content of the
photopolymerizable composition.</p>
    <p num="0053">When the content is less than 30.0% by weight, a latent
image might not form in the exposing step, and when it exceeds
99.9% by weight, a considerable reduction in recording density
may occur.</p>
    <heading>Photopolymerization Initiator</heading>
    <p num="0054">The photopolymerization initiator contains a spectral
sensitizing compound having a maximum absorption wavelength in
a region of from 300 to 1,000 nm and a compound, which interacts
with the spectral sensitizing compound. A single compound may
be used as both the spectral sensitizing compound and the
compound, which interacts with the spectral sensitizing
compound.</p>
    <p num="0055">As the spectral sensitizing compound having a maximum
absorption wavelength of from 300 to 1,000 nm, a spectral
sensitizing dye having a maximum absorption wavelength in that
region is preferred.</p>
    <p num="0056">In order to increase the sensitivity of the recording
material, the spectral sensitizing dye is selected such that
the wavelength of light irradiated from the light source used
coincides with or is in the vicinity of the maximum absorption
wavelength. </p>
    <p num="0057">As the spectral sensitizing dye, known compounds
disclosed in: "Research Disclosure", vol. 200, item 20036,
December 1980; K. Tokumaru and M. Ogawara ed., "Zoukanzai"
(Sensitizers), pp. 160-163, Kodansha Ltd., 1987; JP-A No.
3-87827 and No. 4-211252 can be used.</p>
    <p num="0058">Specific examples thereof include 3-ketocoumarin
compounds disclosed in JP-A No. 58-15603, thiopyrylium salts
disclosed in JP-A No. 58-40302, naphthothiazole merocyanine
compounds disclosed in JP-B No. 59-28328 and No. 60-53300, and
merocyanine compounds disclosed in JP-B No. 61-9621, No.
62-3842, JP-A No. 59-89303 and No. 60-60104.</p>
    <p num="0059">Dyes disclosed in "Kinousei Sikiso no Kagaku" (Chemistry
of Functional Dyes), pp. 393-416, CMC Press 1981;
and "Shikizai" (Coloring Materials), vol. 60(4), pp. 212-224;
(1987) can also be exemplified, and specific examples thereof
include a cationic methine dye, a cationic carbonium dye, a
cationic quinonimine dye, a cationic indoline dye and a cationic
stylyl dye.</p>
    <p num="0060">The following are also included in the spectral
sensitizing dye, keto dyes, such as coumarin (including
ketocoumarin and sulfocoumarin) dyes, merostyryl dyes,
oxonole dyes and hemioxonole dyes; non-keto dyes, such as
non-ketopolymethine dyes, triarylmethane dyes, xanthene dyes,
anthracene dyes, rhodamine dyes, acridine dyes, aniline dyes
and azo dyes; non-ketopolymethine dyes, such as azomethine dyes, 
cyanine dyes, carbocyanine dyes, dicarbocyanine dyes,
tricarbocyanine dyes, hemicyanine dyes and styryl dyes; and
quinonimine dyes, such as azine dyes, oxazine dyes, thiazine
dyes, quinoline dyes and thiazole dyes.</p>
    <p num="0061">The spectral sensitivity of the photopolymerization
initiator used in the recording material of the invention can
be obtained for a region from ultraviolet to infrared by
appropriately using the spectral sensitizing dye.</p>
    <p num="0062">The spectral sensitizing dye may be used singly or may
be used in combinations of two or more.</p>
    <p num="0063">The spectral sensitizing dye is preferably used in an
amount of from 0.1 to 5% by weight, and more preferably in an
amount of from 0.5 to 2% by weight, based on the total weight
(solid content) of the photosensitive and heat-sensitive
recording layer.</p>
    <p num="0064">The compound, which interacts with the spectral
sensitizing compound, can initiate polymerization of the
polymerizable group contained in the compound B or the compound
C (the photopolymerizable monomer) . When the compound is made
to co-exist with the spectral sensitizing compound, the
recording material effectively responds to the exposing light
source, which has a wavelength in the spectral absorption
wavelength region, whereby high sensitivity can be obtained,
and the formation of radicals can be controlled by using an
arbitrary light source in regions from ultraviolet to infrared. </p>
    <p num="0065">Examples of the compound exerting mutual action with the
spectral sensitizing compound include an organic boron compound
and compounds disclosed in JP-A No. 3-87827, No. 4-211252, and
paragraphs (0145) to (0151) of Japanese Patent Application No.
11-36308.</p>
    <heading>Organic Boron Compound</heading>
    <p num="0066">The amount of the organic boron compound in the
photopolymerizable composition, relative to the content of the
compound having an ethylenic unsaturated bond, is preferably
from 0.01 to 20% by weight, and more preferably from 0.1 to 10%
by weight. However, the preferred amount varies depending on
the kind of the "polymerizable compound" to be used therewith,
and therefore is not limited to these ranges.</p>
    <p num="0067">The coated amount of the photopolymerizable composition
per one layer of the recording layer is preferably from 1 to
30 g/m<sup>2</sup>, and more preferably from 2 to 10 g/m<sup>2</sup>. When the coated
amount is less than 1 g/m<sup>2</sup>, a sufficient coloring density might
not be obtainable, and when it exceeds 30 g/m<sup>2</sup>, the coating
appropriateness might deteriorate.</p>
    <heading>Coloring Component</heading>
    <p num="0068">The coloring component contained in the recording layer
will be described.</p>
    <p num="0069">In the recording material of the invention, the recording
layer contains the coloring component A and the compound B
(coloring component B) as a coloring source. </p>
    <p num="0070">Examples of the combination of the coloring component A
and the coloring component B as the coloring source constituting
the image part include the following combinations (a) to (s).
In the following combinations, the coloring component A and the
coloring component B are given in sequential order.
<sl><li>(a) An electron-donating dye precursor and an
electron-accepting compound</li><li>(b) A diazo compound and a coupling component
(hereinafter referred to as a "coupler compound")</li><li>(c) A metallic salt of an organic acid, such as silver
behenate and silver stearate, and a reducing agent, such as
protocatechinic acid, spiroindane and hydroquinone</li><li>(d) An iron salt of a long-chain fatty acid, such as
ferric stearate and ferric myristate, and a phenol, such as
tannic acid, gallic acid and ammonium salicylate</li><li>(e) A heavy metal salt of an organic acid, such as nickel,
cobalt, lead, copper, iron, mercury and silver salts of acetic
acid, stearic acid and palmitic acid, and a sulfide of an alkali
metal or an alkaline earth metal, such as calcium sulfide,
strontium sulfide and potassium sulfide, and combination of the
heavy metal salt of an organic acid and an organic chelating
agent, such as s-diphenylcarbazide and diphenylcarbazone</li><li>(f) A sulfate of a heavy metal, such as sulfates of
silver, lead, mercury and sodium, and a sulfur compound, such
as sodium tetrathionate, sodium thiosulfate and thiourea </li><li>(g) An aliphatic ferric acid, such as ferric stearate,
and an aromatic polyhydroxy compound, such as
3,4-hydroxytetraphenylmethane</li><li>(h) A metallic salt of an organic acid, such as silver
oxalate and mercury oxalate, and an organic polyhydroxy
compound, such as polyhydroxy alcohol, glycerin and glycol</li><li>(i) A ferric salt of a fatty acid, such as ferric
pelargonate and ferric laurate, and thiosemicarbazide and a
thiosemicarbazide derivative</li><li>(j) A lead salt of an organic acid, such as lead caproate,
lead pelargonate and lead behenate, and a thiourea derivative,
such as ethylene thiourea and N-dodecyl thiourea</li><li>(k) A higher aliphatic heavy metal salt, such as ferric
stearate and copper stearate, and zinc dialkyldithiocarbamate</li><li>(l) An oxazine dye, formed by a combination such as a
combination of resorcin and a nitroso compound</li><li>(m) A formazan compound and a reducing agent and/or a
metallic salt</li><li>(n) A protected precursor of a dye (or a leuco dye) and
a deprotecting agent</li><li>(o) An oxidizable coloring agent and an oxidizing agent</li><li>(p) A phthalonitrile and a diiminoisoindoline (i.e.,
a combination forming phthalocyanine)</li><li>(q) An isocyanate and a diiminoindoline (i.e., a
combination forming a colored pigment) </li><li>(r) A pigment precursor and an acid or a base (i.e.,
a combination forming a pigment)</li><li>(s) An oxidant precursor of a paraphenylene diamine
derivative or a paraaminophenol derivative and a coupling
component (coupling compound)</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0071">Preferred examples of the combination of two components
as the coloring source include (a) the combination of an
electron-donating dye precursor and an electron-accepting
compound, (b) the combination of a diazo compound and a coupling
component (hereinafter referred to as a "coupling compound"),
(n) the combination of a protected precursor of a dye (or a leuco
dye) and a deprotecting agent, and (s) the combination of an
oxidant precursor of a paraphenylene diamine derivative or a
paraaminophenol derivative and a coupling component (coupling
compound).</p>
    <p num="0072">In the case where an electron-donating colorless dye
precursor is used as the coloring component A, examples of the
electron-donating colorless dye precursor include various
compounds, such as phthalide compounds, fluoran compounds,
phenothiazine compounds, indolylphthalide compounds,
leucoauramine compounds, rhodamine lactam compounds,
triphenylmethane compounds, triazene compounds, spiropyran
compounds, pyridine and pyrazine compounds, and fluorene
compounds.</p>
    <p num="0073">Examples of the phthalide compounds include those 
compounds that are disclosed in U.S. Reissue Patent No. 23,024,
U.S. Patent No. 3,491,111, No. 3,491,112, No. 3,491,116 and No.
3,309,174, and specific examples thereof include
3,3-bis(p-dimethylaminophenyl)-6-diemthylaminophthalides,
3,3-bis(p-diethylaminophenyl)phthalides, 3,3-bis(2-methyl-1-octylindole-3-yl)phthalides,
3-(4-dipropylamino-2-acetylaminophenyl)-3-(2-methyl-1-octylindole-3-yl)-4-azaphthalides,
3-4-diethylamino-2-ethoxyphenyl)-3-(2-methyl-1-octylindole-3-yl)phthalides,
3-(4-diethylamino-2-ethoxyphenyl)-3-(2-methyl-1-octylindole-3-yl)-4-azaphthalides,
3-(4-diethylamino-2-methylphenyl)-3-(1-ethyl-2-methylindole-3-yl)-4-azaphthalides,
3,3-bis(4-diethylamino-2-butyloxyphenyl)-4-azaphthalides
and 3-(4-diethylamino-2-butyloxyphenyl)-3-(2-methyl-1-pentylindole-3-yl)-4-azaphthalides.</p>
    <p num="0074">Examples of the fluoran compound include those compounds
that are disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 3,624,107, No. 3,627,787,
No. 3,641,011, No. 3,462,828, No. 3,661,390, No. 3,920,510 and
No. 3,959,571, and specific examples thereof include
2-anilino-3-methyl-6-diethylaminofluorans, 2-anilino-3-methyl-6-dibutylaminofluorans,
2-anilino-3-methyl-6-N-ethyl-N-isoamylaminofluorans,
2-anilino-3-methyl-6-N-methyl-N-cyclohexylaminofluorans,
2-anilino-3-methyl-6-N-ethyl-N-isobutylaminofluorans,
2-anilino-6-dibutylaminofluorans
and 2-anilino-3-methyl-6-N-methyl-N-tetrahydrofurfurylaminofluorans. </p>
    <p num="0075">Examples of the thiazine compounds include benzoyl leuco
methylene blue and p-ntirobenzoyl leuco methylene blue.</p>
    <p num="0076">Examples of the leucoauramine compounds include
4,4'-bis-dimethylaminobenzhydrine benzylethers,
N-halophenyl-leucoauramines and N-2,4,5-trichlorophenyl
leucoauramines.</p>
    <p num="0077">Examples of the rhodamine lactam compounds include
rhodamine-B-anilinolactams and rhodamine-(p-anilino)lactams.</p>
    <p num="0078">Examples of the spiropyran compounds include those
compounds that are disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 3,971,808, and
specific examples thereof include 3-methyl-spiro-dinaphthopyrans,
3-ethyl-spiro-dinaphthopyrans,
3,3'-dichloro-spiro-dinaphthopyrans, 3-benzyl-spiro-dinaphthopyrans,
3-methyl-naphtho-(3-methoxybenzo)spiropyrans
and 3-propyl-spiro-dibenzopyrans.</p>
    <p num="0079">Examples of the pyridine and pyradine compound include
those compounds that are disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 3,775,424,
No. 3,853,869 and No. 4,246,318.</p>
    <p num="0080">Examples of the fluorene compound include those compounds
that are disclosed in Japanese Patent Application No.
61-240989.</p>
    <p num="0081">As the dye precursor coloring cyan, magenta or yellow,
those dye precursors that are disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 
4,800,149 can be used.</p>
    <p num="0082">As the electron-donating dye precursor for a yellow
coloring dye, those dye precursors that are disclosed in U.S.
Patent No. 4,800,148, No. 5,126,233 and JP-B No. 7-88105 can
be used, and as the electron-donating dye precursor for a cyan
coloring dye, those dye precursors that are disclosed in JP-A
No. 63-53542 can be used.</p>
    <p num="0083">In the case where the electron-donating dye precursor is
used, an electron-accepting compound is used as the coloring
component B that colors the electron-donating dye precursor.</p>
    <p num="0084">Examples of the electron-accepting compound include
those electron-accepting compounds that are known in the fields
of heat-sensitive paper and pressure-sensitive paper, such as
a phenol derivatives, salicylic acid derivatives, metallic
salts of aromatic carboxylic acids, acid clays, bentonites,
novolak resins, metal-treated novolak resins and metallic
complexes. Specific examples thereof include those disclosed
in JP-B No. 40-9309, No. 45-14039, JP-A No. 52-140483, No.
48-51510, No. 57-210886, No. 58-87089, No. 59-11286, No.
60-176795 and No. 61-95988.</p>
    <p num="0085">Among the foregoing compounds, examples of the phenol
derivative include 2,2-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)propanes,
1,1-bis(3-chloro-4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexanes,
4-hydroxyphenyl-4'-isopropyloxyphenylsulfones, bis(3-allyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)sulfones,
α,α'-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)-1,4-diisopropylbenzenes 
and benzyl p-hydroxybenzoates.</p>
    <p num="0086">Examples of the salicylic acid derivatives include
4-pnetadecylsalicylic acids, 3,5-di(α-methylbenzyl)salicylic
acid, 3,5-di(tert-octyl)salicylic acid, 5-octadecylsalicylic
acids, 5-α-(p-α-methylbenzylphenyl)ethylsalicylic acids,
3-α-methylbenzyl-5-tert-octylsalicylic acids,
5-tetradecylsalicylic acids, 4-hexyloxysalicylic acids,
4-cyclohexyloxysalicylic acids, 4-decyloxysalicylic acids,
4-dodecyloxysalicylic acids, 4-pentadecyloxysalicylic acids,
4-octadecyloxysalicylic acids, and zinc, aluminum, calcium or
copper salts thereof.</p>
    <p num="0087">In the recording material of the first embodiment, the
coloring component B also functions as the compound having a
polymerizable group. Therefore, at least one of the
polymerizable compound of the recording material of the first
embodiment is an electron-accepting compound, and contains an
electron-accepting group and an ethylenic unsaturated bond
(hereinafter referred to as a "polymerizable group") in the
molecule thereof.</p>
    <p num="0088">Examples of the coloring component B in this case include
those compounds that can be synthesized with reference to
3-halo-4-hydroxybenzoic acid disclosed in JP-A No. 4-226455.
a methacryloxyethyl esters and acryloxyethyl ester of benzoic
acids having a hydroxyl group disclosed in JP-A No. 63-173682,
esters of benzoic acid having a hydroxyl group and 
hydroxymethylstyrene disclosed in JP-A No. 59-83693, No.
60-141587 and No. 62-99190, hydroxystyrene disclosed in
European Patent No. 29,323, an N-vinylimidazole complex of zinc
halogenate disclosed in JP-A No. 62-167077 and No. 62-16708,
and an electron-accepting compound disclosed in JP-A No.
63-317558.</p>
    <p num="0089">Among the compounds having an electron-accepting group
and a polymerizable group in one molecule, a 3-halo-4-hydroxybenzoic
acid represented by the following formula is
preferred.
<img id="img-00310001" orientation="unknown" wi="63" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00310001.tif" inline="no" he="33"/></p>
    <p num="0090">In the formula, X represents a halogen atom, and a
chlorine atom is preferred. Y represents a monovalent group
having an ethylenic polymerizable group, and an aralkyl group
having a vinyl group, an acryloyloxyalkyl group and a
methacryloyloxyalkyl group are preferred, with an
acryloyloxyalkyl group having from 5 to 11 carbon atoms and a
methacryloyloxyalkyl group having from 6 to 12 carbon atoms
being more preferred. Z represents a hydrogen atom, an alkyl
group or an alkoxy group.</p>
    <p num="0091">Examples of the 3-halo-4-hydroxybenzoic acid include
vinylphenethyl 3-chloro-4-hydroxybenzoates,
vinylphenylpropyl 3-chloro-4-hydroxybenzoates, 
2-acryloyloxyethyl 3-chloro-4-hydroxybenzoates,
2-methacryloyloxyethyl 3-chloro-4-hydroxybenzoates,
2-acryloyloxypropyl 3-chloro-4-hydroxybenzoates,
2-methacryloyloxypropyl 3-chloro-4-hydroxybenzoates,
3-acryloyloxypropyl 3-chloro-4-hydroxybenzoates,
3-methacryloyloxypropyl 3-chloro-4-hydroxybenzoates,
4-acryloyloxybutyl 3-chloro-4-hydroxybenzoates,
4-methacryloyloxy 3-chloro-4-hydroxybenzoates,
2-acryloyloxyethyl 3-chloro-4-hydroxybenzoates,
5-acryloyloxypentyl 3-chloro-4-hydroxybenzoates,
5-methacryloyloxypentyl 3-chloro-4-hydroxybenzoates,
6-acryloyloxyhexyl 3-chloro-4-hydroxybenzoates,
6-methacryloyloxyhexyl 3-chloro-4-hydroxybenzoates,
8-acryloyloxyoctyl 3-chloro-4-hydroxybenzoates and
8-methacryloyloxyoctyl 3-chloro-4-hydroxybenzoates.</p>
    <p num="0092">Further preferred examples thereof include styrene
sulfonyl aminosalicylic acids, vinylbenzyloxyphthalic acids,
zinc β-methacryloxyethoxysalicylates, zinc
β-acryloxyethoxysalicylates, vinyloxyethyloxybenzoic acids,
β-methacryloxyethyl orseillinates, β-acryloxyethyl
orseillinates, β-methacryloxyethoxyphenols,
β-acryloxyethoxyphenols,
β-methacryloxyethyl-β-resorcinates, β-acryloxyethyl-β-resorcinates,
hydroxystyrene sulfonic acid-N-ethylamides,
β-methacryloxypropyl-p-hydroxybenzoates, β-acryloxypropyl-p-hydroxybenzoates, 
metahcryloxymethylphenols,
acryloxymethylphenols, methacrylamide propanesulfonic acids,
acrylamide propanesulfonic acids, β-methacryloxyethoxy-dihydroxybenzenes,
β-acryloxyethoxy-dihydroxybenzenes,
γ-styrenesulfonyloxy-β-methacryloxypropanecarboxylic acids,
γ-acryoxypropyl-α-hydroxyethyloxysalicylic acids,
β-hydroxyethoxyphenols, β-methacryoxyethyl-p-hydroxycinnamates,
β-acryoxyethyl-p-hydroxycinnamates,
3,5-distyrenesulfonic acid amide phenols,
methacryloxyethoxyphthalic acid, acryloxyethoxyphthalic
acids, methacrylic acids, acrylic acids,
methacryloxyethoxyhydroxynaphthoic acids,
acryloxyethoxyhydroxynaphthoic acids,
3-β-hydroxyethoxyphenols, β-methacryloxyethyl-p-hydroxybenzoates,
β-acryloxyethyl-p-hydroxybenzoates,
β'-methacryloxyethyl-β-resorcinates,
β-methacryloxyethyloxycarbonylhydroxy benzoic acids,
β-acryloxyethyloxycarbonylhydroxy benzoic acids,
N,N'-di-β-methacryloxyethylaminosalicylic acids,
N,N'-di-β-acryloxyethylaminosalicylic acids,
N,N'-di-β-methacryloxyethylaminosulfonylsalicylic acids,
N,N'-di-β-acryloxyethylaminosulfonylsalicylic acids and
metallic salts (such as a zinc salt) thereof.</p>
    <p num="0093">In the case where an electron-donating dye precursor is
used as the coloring component A, and an electron-accepting 
compound is used as the coloring component B, the amount of the
electron-donating dye precursor in the recording layer is
preferably from 0.05 to 5 g/m<sup>2</sup>, and more preferably from 0.1
to 3 g/m<sup>2</sup>.</p>
    <p num="0094">The amount of the electron-accepting compound used is
preferably from 0.5 to 20 parts by weight, and more preferably
from 3 to 10 parts by weight, per 1 part by weight of the
electron-donating colorless dye used. When the amount of the
election acceptor compound used is less than 0.5 part by weight,
a sufficient coloring density might not cannot be obtainable,
and when it exceeds 20 parts by weight, reduction in sensitivity
and deterioration of coating suitability may occur.</p>
    <p num="0095">In the case where a diazo compound is used as the coloring
component A, on the other hand, a compound represented by the
following formula is preferably used.
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/">Ar - N<sub>2</sub><sup>+</sup>Y</st32:che></p>
    <p num="0096">In the formula, Ar represents an aromatic ring group, and
Y- represents an acid anion.</p>
    <p num="0097">In the formula, Ar represents a substituted or
unsubstituted aryl group, Examples of the substituent include
alkyl groups, alkoxy groups, alkylthio groups, aryl groups,
aryloxy groups, arylthio groups, acyl groups, alkoxycarbonyl
groups, carbamoyl groups, carboamide groups, sulfonyl groups,
sulfamoyl groups, sulfoneamide groups, ureido groups, a halogen
atom, amino groups and heterocyclic groups, and these 
substituents may be further substituted.</p>
    <p num="0098">As the aryl group, an aryl group having from 6 to 30 carbon
atoms is preferred, and examples thereof include phenyl groups,
2-methylphenyl groups, 2-chlorophenyl groups, 2-methoxyphenyl
groups, 2-butoxyphenyl groups, 2-(2-ethylhexyloxy)phenyl
groups, 2-octyloxyphenyl groups,
3-(2,4-di-t-pentylphenoxyethoxy)phenyl groups,
4-chlorophenyl groups, 2,5-dichlorophenyl groups,
2,4,6-trimethylphenyl groups, 3- chlorophenyl groups,
3-methylphenyl groups, 3-methoxyphenyl groups, 3-butoxyphenyl
groups, 3-cyanophenyl groups, 3-(2-ethylhexyloxy)phenyl
groups, 3,4-dichlorophenyl groups, 3,5-dichlorophenyl groups,
3,4-dimethoxyphenyl groups,
3-(dibutylaminocarbonylmethoxy)phenyl groups,
4-cyanophenyl groups, 4-methylphenyl groups, 4-methoxyphenyl
groups, 4-butoxyphenyl groups, 4-(2-ethylhexyloxy)phenyl
groups, 4-benzylphenyl groups, 4-aminosulfonylphenyl groups,
4-N,N-dibutylaminosulfonylphenyl groups,
4-ethoxycarbonylphenyl groups,
4-(2-ethylhexylcarbonyl)phenyl groups, 4-fluorophenyl groups,
3-acetylphenyl groups, 2-acetylaminophenyl groups,
4-(4-chlorophenylthio)phenyl groups,
4-(4-methylphenyl)thio-2,5-butoxyphenyl groups and
4-(N-benzyl-N-methylamino)-2-dodecyloxycarbonylphenyl
groups. </p>
    <p num="0099">These groups may be further substituted, for example, by
alkyloxy groups, alkylthio groups, substituted phenyl groups,
cyano groups, substituted amino groups, a halogen atom and
heterocyclic groups.</p>
    <p num="0100">Examples of a diazo group that can be preferably used as
the coloring component A include those diazo groups that are
disclosed in paragraphs 44 to 49 of JP-A No. 7-276808. However,
the invention is not limited to these compounds.</p>
    <p num="0101">The maximum absorption wavelength λ<sub>max</sub> of the diazo
compound is preferably 450 nm or less in view of the effect,
and more preferably from 290 to 440 nm. It is preferable that
the diazo compound have 12 or more carbon atoms, a solubility
in water of 1% or less and a solubility in ethyl acetate of 5%
or more.</p>
    <p num="0102">The diazo compound as the coloring component A may be used
singly or may be used as a combination of two or more kinds
thereof for various purposes, such as hue adjustment.</p>
    <p num="0103">In the case where the diazo compound is used, a coupler
compound (having no polymerizable group) or a coupler compound
having a polymerizable group is used as the coloring component
B.</p>
    <p num="0104">Both the coupler compounds form a dye by coupling with
the diazo compound in a basic atmosphere and/or a neutral
atmosphere, and it can be used as a combination of two or more
kinds thereof for various purposes, such as hue adjustment. </p>
    <p num="0105">Specific examples of the coupler compound having a
polymerizable group include so-called active methylene groups
having a methylene group adjacent to a carbonyl group, phenol
derivatives, naphthol derivatives, azole derivatives and a
condensed heterocyclic azole derivatives. These may be used
after appropriate selection within a range that conforms to the
objects of the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0106">Examples of a coupler skeleton compound (coupler) in the
coupler compound having a polymerizable group include those
couplers, such as a so-called active methylene groups having
a methylene group adjacent to a carbonyl group, phenol
derivatives, naphthol derivatives, azole derivatives and
condensed heterocyclic azole derivatives. Specific examples
thereof include resorcins, fluoroglycins,
2,3-dihydroxynaphthalenes, sodium 2,3-dihydroxynaphthalene-6-sulfonates,
1-hydroxy-2-naphthoic acid
morpholinopropylamides, sodium 2-hydroxy-3-naphthalenesulfonates,
2-hydroxy-3-naphthalenesulfonic
acid anilides, 2-hydroxy-3-naphthalenesulfonic acid
morpholinopropylamides, 2-hydroxy-3-naphthalenesulfonic acid
2-ethylhexyloxypropylamides, 2-hydroxy-3-naphthalenesulfonic
acid 2-ethylhexylamides, 5-acetamide-1-naphthols,
sodium 1-hydroxy-8-acetamidenaphthalene-3,6-disulfonates,
1-hydroxy-8-acetamidenaphthalene-3,6-disulfonic 
acid anilides, 1,5-dihydroxynaphthalenes,
2-hydroxy-3-naphthoic acid morpholinopropylamides,
2-hydroxy-3-naphthoic acid octylamides, 2-hydroxy-3-naphtoic
acid anilides, 5,5-dimethyl-1,3-cyclohexanedions,
1,3-cyclopentanediones, 5-(2-n-tetradecyloxyphenyl)-1,3-cyclohexanediones,
5-phenyl-4-methoxycarbonyl-1,3-cyclohexanediones,
5-(2,5-di-n-octyloxyphenyl)-1,3-cyclohexanediones,
N,N'-dicyclohexylbarbituric acids,
N,N'-di-n-dodecylbarbituric acids,
N-n-octyl-N'-n-octadecylbarbituric acids, N-phenyl-N'-(2,5-di-n-octyloxyphenyl)barbituric
acids,
N,N'-bis(octadecyloxycarbonylmethyl)barbituric acids,
1-phenyl-3-methyl-5-pyrazolones, 1-(2,4,6-trichlorophenyl)-3-anilino-5-pyrazolones,
1-(2,4,6-trichlorophenyl)-3-benzamide-5-pyrazolones,
6-hydroxy-4-methyl-3-cyano-1-(2-ethylhexyl)-2-pyridones,
2,4-bis(benzoylacetamide)toluenes,
1,3-bis(pivaloylacetamidemethyl)benzenes,
benzoylacetonitriles, thenoylacetonitriles, acetanilides,
benzoylacetanilides, pivaloylacetanilides, 2-chloro-5-(N-n-butylsulfamoyl)-1-pyvaloylacetamide
benzenes,
1-(2-ethylhexyloxypropyl)-3-cyano-4-methyl-6-hydroxy-1,2-dihydropyridine-2-ones,
1-(dodecyloxypropyl)-3-acetyl-4-methyl-6-hydroxy-1,2-dihydropyridine-2-ones
and
1-(4-n-octyloxyphenyl)-3-tert-butyl-5-aminopirazoles. </p>
    <p num="0107">The coupler compounds are also described in detail in JP-A
No. 4-201483, No. 7-223367, No. 7-223368, No. 7-323660, No.
5-278608, No. 5-297024, No. 6-18669, No. 6-18670, No. 7-316280,
No. 9-216468, No. 9-216469, No. 9-319025, No. 10-035113, No.
10-193801 and No. 10-264532.</p>
    <p num="0108">The coupler compound forms a dye by coupling with the
diazo compound in a basic atmosphere and/or a neutral atmosphere,
and may be used in combination of plurality thereof for various
purposes, such as hue adjustment.</p>
    <p num="0109">Specific examples of the coupler having a polymerizable
group will be shown below, but the invention is not limited to
them. <img id="img-00400001" orientation="unknown" wi="121" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00400001.tif" inline="no" he="40"/><img id="img-00400002" orientation="unknown" wi="119" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00400002.tif" inline="no" he="37"/><img id="img-00400003" orientation="unknown" wi="112" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00400003.tif" inline="no" he="33"/><img id="img-00400004" orientation="unknown" wi="119" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00400004.tif" inline="no" he="38"/><img id="img-00400005" orientation="unknown" wi="114" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00400005.tif" inline="no" he="53"/><img id="img-00410001" orientation="unknown" wi="123" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00410001.tif" inline="no" he="42"/><img id="img-00410002" orientation="unknown" wi="124" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00410002.tif" inline="no" he="37"/><img id="img-00410003" orientation="unknown" wi="125" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00410003.tif" inline="no" he="40"/><img id="img-00410004" orientation="unknown" wi="125" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00410004.tif" inline="no" he="41"/><img id="img-00410005" orientation="unknown" wi="125" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00410005.tif" inline="no" he="47"/><img id="img-00420001" orientation="unknown" wi="98" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00420001.tif" inline="no" he="44"/><img id="img-00420002" orientation="unknown" wi="126" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00420002.tif" inline="no" he="36"/><img id="img-00420003" orientation="unknown" wi="130" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00420003.tif" inline="no" he="37"/><img id="img-00420004" orientation="unknown" wi="109" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00420004.tif" inline="no" he="35"/><img id="img-00420005" orientation="unknown" wi="120" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00420005.tif" inline="no" he="53"/><img id="img-00430001" orientation="unknown" wi="119" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00430001.tif" inline="no" he="46"/><img id="img-00430002" orientation="unknown" wi="119" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00430002.tif" inline="no" he="36"/><img id="img-00430003" orientation="unknown" wi="120" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00430003.tif" inline="no" he="40"/><img id="img-00430004" orientation="unknown" wi="121" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00430004.tif" inline="no" he="33"/><img id="img-00430005" orientation="unknown" wi="121" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00430005.tif" inline="no" he="52"/><img id="img-00440001" orientation="unknown" wi="132" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00440001.tif" inline="no" he="46"/><img id="img-00440002" orientation="unknown" wi="132" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00440002.tif" inline="no" he="49"/><img id="img-00440003" orientation="unknown" wi="133" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00440003.tif" inline="no" he="45"/><img id="img-00440004" orientation="unknown" wi="133" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00440004.tif" inline="no" he="52"/><img id="img-00450001" orientation="unknown" wi="110" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00450001.tif" inline="no" he="47"/><img id="img-00450002" orientation="unknown" wi="111" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00450002.tif" inline="no" he="46"/><img id="img-00450003" orientation="unknown" wi="111" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00450003.tif" inline="no" he="44"/><img id="img-00450004" orientation="unknown" wi="111" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00450004.tif" inline="no" he="53"/><img id="img-00460001" orientation="unknown" wi="132" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00460001.tif" inline="no" he="39"/><img id="img-00460002" orientation="unknown" wi="133" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00460002.tif" inline="no" he="36"/><img id="img-00460003" orientation="unknown" wi="134" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00460003.tif" inline="no" he="32"/><img id="img-00460004" orientation="unknown" wi="134" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00460004.tif" inline="no" he="33"/><img id="img-00460005" orientation="unknown" wi="134" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00460005.tif" inline="no" he="52"/></p>
    <p num="0110">Examples of the coupler having no polymerizable group
include those compounds enumerated as the coupler skeleton
compounds of the coupler compound having a polymerizable group.</p>
    <p num="0111">In the case where a diazo compound is used as the coloring
component A, and a coupler is used as the coloring component
B, the amount of the diazo compound in the recording layer is
preferably from 0.02 to 5.0 g/m<sup>2</sup>, and more preferably from 0.05
to 3.0 g/m<sup>2</sup>.</p>
    <p num="0112">When the content is less than 0.02 g/m<sup>2</sup>, a sufficient
coloring density might not be obtainable, and when it exceeds
5.0 g/m<sup>2</sup>, the coating suitability of the coating composition
may deteriorate.</p>
    <p num="0113">The amount of the coupler compound used is preferably from
0.5 to 20 parts by weight, and more preferably from 1 to 10 parts
by weight, per 1 part by weight of the diazo compound. When
the amount used is less than 0.5 part by weight, sufficient
coloring property might not be obtainable, and when it exceeds
20 parts by weight, the coating suitability may deteriorate.</p>
    <p num="0114">The coupler compound can be used as the coloring component
B by adding a water-soluble polymer along with other components,
followed by solid dispersion by a sand mill or the like, and
can be also used as an emulsified product by emulsifying with
a suitable emulsifying assistant. The method for solid
dispersion or emulsification is not particularly limited, and
known methods may be employed. The methods are described in 
detail in JP-A No. 59-190886, No. 2-141279 and No. 7-17145.</p>
    <p num="0115">In order to accelerate the coupling reaction of the diazo
compound and the coupler, it is preferred to use organic bases,
such as tertiary amine compounds, a piperidine compounds, a
piperazine compounds, amidine compounds, formamidine
compounds, pyridine compounds, guanidine compounds on
morpholine compounds.</p>
    <p num="0116">Examples of the organic base include a piperazine
compounds, such as N,N'-bis(3-phenoxy-2-hydroxypropyl)piperazine,
N,N'-bis(3-(p-methylphenoxy)-2-hydroxypropyl)piperazine,
N,N'-bis(3-(p-methoxyphenoxy)-2-hydroxypropyl)piperazine,
N,N'-bis(3-phenylthio-2-hydroxypropyl)piperazine,
N,N'-bis(3-(β-naphthoxy)-2-hydroxypropyl)piperazine,
N-3-(β-naphthoxy)-2-hydroxypropyl-N'-methylpiperazine
and
1,4-bis((3-(N-methylpiperazino)-2-hydroxy)propyloxy)benzene,
morpholine compounds, such as
N-(3-(β-naphthoxy)-2-hydroxy)propylmorpholine,
1,4-bis((3-morpholino-2-hydroxy)propyloxy)benzene and
1,3-bis((3-morpholino-2-hydroxy)propyloxy)benzene,
piperidine compounds, such as N-(3-phenoxy-2-hydroxypropyl)piperidine
and N-dodecylpiperidine,
triphenylguanidines, tricyclohexylguanidines,
dicyclohexylphenylguanidines, 2-N-methyl-N-benzylaminoethyl
4-hydroxybenzoates, 2-N,N-di-n-butylaminoethyl 
4-hydroxybenzoates, 4-(3-N,N-dibutylaminopropoxy)benzene
sulfonamides and
4-(2-N,N-dibutylaminoethoxycarbonyl)phenoxyacetic acid
amides.</p>
    <p num="0117">These organic bases can be used singly or in combinations
of two or more.</p>
    <p num="0118">These are organic bases disclosed in JP-A No. 57-123086,
No. 60-49991, No. 60-94381, Japanese Patent Application No.
7-228731, No. 7-235157 and No. 7-235158.</p>
    <p num="0119">In the case where an organic base is used, an organic base
having a polymerizable group may be used as the organic base.</p>
    <p num="0120">In the case where an organic base having a polymerizable
group is used in the recording medium of the first embodiment,
both the diazo compound and the coupler may be encapsulated in
the microcapsules as the coloring component A, and the organic
base having a polymerizable group is used as the coloring
component B. In the case where both the diazo compound and the
coupler are encapsulated in the microcapsules as the coloring
component A, a combination of the diazo compound and the coupler
is used such that a coloring reaction does not occur unless a
base is present.</p>
    <p num="0121">In the recording material of the first embodiment, the
diazo compound may be used as the coloring component A, and the
coupler having a polymerizable group and the organic base having
a polymerizable group may be used in combination as the coloring 
component B.</p>
    <p num="0122">The using amount of the organic base used is not
particularly limited, and is preferably in a range of from 1
to 30 mole per 1 mole of the diazo compound.</p>
    <p num="0123">A coloring assistant may be added in order to accelerate
the coloring reaction. Examples of the coloring assistant
include phenol derivatives, naphthol derivatives, alkoxy-substituted
benzenes, alkoxy-substituted naphthalenes,
hydroxyl compounds, carboxylic amide compounds and sulfonamide
compounds.</p>
    <p num="0124">The polymerizable compound used in the recording material
of the second embodiment will be described.</p>
    <p num="0125">In the recording material of the first embodiment, the
recording layer contains a coloring component A and a compound
C, which has a site that suppresses a reaction of the coloring
component A and the coloring component B, which colors when
reacted with the coloring component A and a polymerizable group
in one molecule (hereinafter sometimes referred to as a
"polymerizable coloration suppressing compound), as
polymerizable compounds.</p>
    <p num="0126">In the case where an electron-donating dye precursor is
used as the coloring component A, and an electron-accepting
compound having no polymerizable group is used as the coloring
component B, the compound C used is preferably a
photopolymerizable monomer, which has at least one vinyl group 
and a site that suppresses between reaction of the
electron-donating dye precursor and the electron-accepting
compound in one molecule (hereinafter sometimes referred to as
a "photopolymerizable monomer D<sub>1</sub>")</p>
    <p num="0127">Specific examples of the photopolymerizable monomer D<sub>1</sub>
include acrylic acids and salts thereof, acrylates, acrylamides,
methacrylic acids and salts thereof, methacrylates,
methacrylamides, maleic anhydrides, maleates, itaconic acids,
itaconates, styrene compounds, vinyl ether compounds, vinyl
ester compounds. N-vinyl heterocyclic compounds, allyl ether
compounds and allyl ester compounds.</p>
    <p num="0128">Among these, a compound having maltiple vinyl groups in
one molecule is preferred, and specific preferred examples
thereof include acrylates and methacrylates of a polyvalent
alcohol, such as trimethylolpropanes and pentaerythritols;
acrylates and methacrylates of polyvalent phenol and bisphenols,
such as resorcinols, pyrogallols and fluoroglycinols; epoxy
resins terminated with an acrylate or a methacrylate; and
polyesters terminated with an acrylate or a methacrylate.</p>
    <p num="0129">Among these, ethylene glycol diacrylate, ethylene glycol
dimethacrylate, trimethylolpropane triacrylate,
pentaerythritol tetraacrylate, dipentaerythritol
hydroxypentaacrylate, hexanediol-1,6-dimethacrylate and
diethylene glycol dimethacryalte are particularly preferred.</p>
    <p num="0130">the photopolymerizable monomer D<sub>1</sub> preferably has a 
molecular weight of from about 100 to 5,000, and more preferably
from about 300 to 2,000.</p>
    <p num="0131">In the case where the photopolymerizable monomer D<sub>1</sub> is
used as the compound C, the amount thereof used is preferably
from 0.1 to 10 parts by weight, and more preferably from 0.5
to 5 parts by weight, per 1 part by weight of the electron-donating
compound used in combination with the coupler compound,
which has no polymerizable group. When the amount used is less
than 0.1 part by weight, a latent image might not cannot be
formable in the exposing step, and when it exceeds 10 parts by
weight, the coloring density may decreased.</p>
    <p num="0132">In the case where a diazo compound is used as the coloring
component A, and a coupler compound having no polymerizable
group is used as the coloring component B, the compound C used
is preferably a photopolymerizable monomer having an acidic
group, which suppresses a coupling reaction of the diazo
compound and the coupler compound, and at least one vinyl group
in one molecule (hereinafter sometimes referred to as a
"photopolymerizable monomer D<sub>2</sub>").</p>
    <p num="0133">Preferred examples of the photopolymerizable monomer D<sub>2</sub>
include styrene sulfonylaminosalicylic acids,
vinylbenzyloxyphthalic acids, zinc
β-methacryloxyethoxysalicylates, zinc
β-acryloxyethoxysalicylates, vinyloxyethyloxybenzoic acids,
β-methacryloxyethyl orseillinates, β-acryloxyethyl 
orseillinates, β-methacryloxyethoxyphenols,
β-acryloxyethoxyphenols, β-methacryloxyethyl-β-resorcinates,
β-acryloxyethyl-β-resorcinates, hydroxystyrene sulfonic
acid-N-ethylamides, β-methacryloxypropyl-p-hydroxybenzoates,
β-acryloxypropyl-p-hydroxybenzoates,
metahcryloxymethylphenols, acryloxymethylphenols,
methacrylamide propanesulfonic acids, acrylamide
propanesulfonic acids, β-methacryloxyethoxy-dihydroxybenzenes,
β-acryloxyethoxy-dihydroxybenzenes,
γ-styrenesulfonyloxy-β-methacryloxypropanecarboxylic acids,
γ-acryoxypropyl-α-hydroxyethyloxysalicylic acids,
β-hydroxyethoxyphenols, β-methacryoxyethyl-p-hydroxycinnamates,
β-acryoxyethyl-p-hydroxycinnamates,
3,5-distyrenesulfonic acid amide phenols,
methacryloxyethoxyphthalic acids, acryloxyethoxyphthalic
acids, methacrylic acids, acrylic acids,
methacryloxyethoxyhydroxynaphthoic acids,
acryloxyethoxyhydroxynaphthoic acids,
3-β-hydroxyethoxyphenols, β-methacryloxyethyl-p-hydroxybenzoates,
β-acryloxyethyl-p-hydroxybenzoates,
β'-methacryloxyethyl-β-resorcinates,
β-methacryloxyethyloxycarbonylhydroxy benzoic acids,
β-acryloxyethyloxycarbonylhydroxy benzoic acids,
N,N-di-β-methacryloxyethylaminosalicylic acids,
N,N-di-β-acryloxyethylaminosalicylic acids, 
N,N-di-β-methacryloxyethylaminosulfonylsalicylic acids and
N,N-di-β-acryloxyethylaminosulfonylsalicylic acids.</p>
    <p num="0134">In the case where the photopolymerizable monomer D<sub>2</sub> is
used as the compound C, the amount used is preferably from 0.1
to 10 parts by weight, and more preferably from 0.5 to 5 parts
by weight, per 1 part by weight of the coupler compound used
in combination with the coupler compound having no
polymerizable group. When the using amount is less than 0.1
part by weight, a latent image might not be formable in the
exposing step, and when it exceeds 10 parts by weight, the
coloring density might decrease.</p>
    <heading>Microcapsules</heading>
    <p num="0135">In the recording material of the invention, the coloring
component (for example, the electron-donating colorless dye or
the diazonium salt compound) is used by encapsulating in
microcapsules. As the method for microencapsulation, known
methods can be used.</p>
    <p num="0136">Examples thereof include a method utilizing coacervation
of a hydrophilic wall forming material disclosed in U.S. Patent
No. 2,800,457 and No. 2,800,458, an interface polymerization
method disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 3,287,154, British Patent
No. 990,443, JP-B No. 38-19574, No. 42-446 and No. 42-771, a
method utilizing polymer deposition disclosed in U.S. Patent
No. 3,418,250 and No. 3,660,304, a method using an isocyanate
polyol wall material disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 3,796,669, 
a method utilizing an isocyanate wall material disclosed in U.S.
Patent No. 3,914,511, a method utilizing a urea-formaldehyde
or urea-formaldehyde-resorcinol wall forming material
disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 4,001,140, No. 4,087,376 and No.
4,089,802, a method utilizing wall materials, such as a
melamine-formaldehyde resin and hydroxypropylcellulose
disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 4,025,455, an in situ method by
polymerization of a monomer disclosed in JP-B No. 36-9168 and
JP-A No. 51-9079, an electrolytic dispersion cooling method
disclosed in British Patent No. 952,807 and No. 965,074, and
a spray drying method disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 3,111,407
and British Patent No. 930,422.</p>
    <p num="0137">The method for microencapsulation is not limited to these
methods, and in the recording material of the invention, the
interface polymerization method is preferably used, in which
an oily phase prepared by dissolving or dispersing the coloring
component in a hydrophobic organic solvent to be a core of
capsules is mixed with an aqueous phase having a water soluble
polymer dissolved therein, and after emulsification dispersion
by a means such as a homogenizer, the mixture is heated to cause
a polymer forming reaction on an interface of oil droplets, so
as to form a microcapsule wall of a polymer substance.</p>
    <p num="0138">According thereto, capsules having a uniform diameter can
be formed in a short period of time, and a recording material
excellent in storage stability can be obtained. </p>
    <p num="0139">A reactant forming the polymer substance is added to the
interior of the oil droplets and/or the exterior of the oil
droplets. Specific examples of the polymer substance include
polyurethanes, polyureas, polyamides, polyesters,
polycarbonates, urea-formaldehyde resins, melamine resins,
polystyrenes, styrene-methacrylate copolymers and styrene-acrylate
copolymers. Among these, polyurethanes, polyureas,
polyamides, polyesters and polycarbonates are preferred, and
polyurethanes and polyureas are particularly preferred. The
polymer substances may be used in combinations of two or mor.</p>
    <p num="0140">Examples of the water-soluble polymer include gelatins,
polyvinyl pyrrolidones and polyvinyl alcohols.</p>
    <p num="0141">In the case, for example, where polyurethane is used as
the capsule wall material, a polyvalent isocyanate and a second
substance, which forms a capsule wall by reacting therewith (for
example, a polyol and a polyamine) are mixed in the water soluble
polymer aqueous solution (aqueous phase) or an oily medium to
be encapsulated (oily phase), and after subjecting them to
emulsification dispersion, they are heated to cause a polymer
forming reaction at the interface of the oil droplets, whereby
a microcapsule wall can be formed.</p>
    <p num="0142">The polyvalent isocyanate and the polyol or polyamine
that is reacted therewith that are disclosed in U.S. Patent No.
3,281,383, No. 3,773,695, No. 3,793,268, JP-B No. 48-40347, No.
49-24159, JP-A No. 48-80191 and No. 48-84086 can be used. </p>
    <p num="0143">In the invention, when preparing the microcapsules
encapsulating the coloring component, the coloring component
to be encapsulated (for example, the electron-donating
colorless dye or the diazonium salt compound) is present in the
microcapsules in either a solution or a solid state.</p>
    <p num="0144">In the case where the coloring component is encapsulated
in the capsules in a solution state, the electron-donating
colorless dye or the diazonium salt compound are encapsulated,
for example, in such a state that they are dissolved in an organic
solvent, and in this case, the amount of the organic solvent
used is preferably from 1 to 500 parts by weight per 100 parts
by weight of the coloring component.</p>
    <p num="0145">In general, the organic solvent can be appropriately
selected from high boiling point organic solvents, and examples
thereof include phosphates, phthalates, acrylates,
methacrylates, esters of other carboxylic acids, fatty acid
amides, alkylated biphenyls, alkylated terphenyls,
chlorinated paraffins, alkylated naphthalenes, diallylethanes,
compound s, which are solid at ordinary temperature, oligomer
oils and polymer oils. Specific examples thereof include those
organic solvents that are disclosed in JP-A Nos. 59-178451 to
59-178455, No. 59-178457, No. 60-242094, No. 63-85633, No.
6-194825, No. 7-13310, No. 7-13311, No. 9-106039 and Japanese
Patent Application No. 62-75409.</p>
    <p num="0146">Upon encapsulation, oilless capsules can be formed 
without using the organic solvent.</p>
    <p num="0147">In the case where the solubility of the electron-donating
colorless dye or the diazonium salt compound to be encapsulated
is poor, a low boiling point solvent exhibiting high solubility
may be subsidiarily used in conjunction therewith. Examples
of the low boiling point solvent include ethyl acetates, propyl
acetates, isopropyl acetates, butyl acetate and methylene
chlorides.</p>
    <p num="0148">In the aqueous phase, however, an aqueous solution having
a water soluble polymer dissolved therein is used as a
protective colloid, and after adding the oily phase thereto,
emulsification dispersion is carried out by a means such as a
homogenizer. The water soluble polymer is used as a dispersion
medium, which makes dispersion uniform and easy and stabilizes
the emulsified and dispersed aqueous solution. In order to make
the emulsification dispersion more uniform and stabile, a
surfactant may be added to at least one of the oily phase and
the aqueous phase. Known surfactants for emulsification can
be used as the surfactant. In the case where the surfactant
is added, the amount of the surfactant added is preferably from
0.1 to 5% by weight, and particularly preferably from 0.5 to
2% by weight, based on the weight of the oily phase.</p>
    <p num="0149">The surfactant contained in the aqueous phase can be
preferably used by selecting on anionic or nonionic surfactants
that does not cause precipitation or aggregation through action 
with the protective colloid.</p>
    <p num="0150">Preferred examples of the surfactant include sodium
alkylbenzenesulfonates, sodium alkylsulfates, octyl sodium
sulfosuccinates and polyalkylene glycols (such as
polyoxyethylene nonyl phenyl ethers).</p>
    <p num="0151">As described above, the water soluble polymer contained
as a protective colloid in the aqueous phase to be mixed with
the oily phase can be appropriately selected from anionic
polymers, nonionic polymers and amphoteric polymers that are
known in the art.</p>
    <p num="0152">The anionic polymer may be natural or synthetic, and
examples thereof include those having a -COO- group and an
-SO<sub>2</sub>- group.</p>
    <p num="0153">Specific examples thereof include natural matters, such
as gum arabic, alginic acids and pectins; semisynthetic matters,
such as caboxymethylcelloloses, gelatin derivatives, e.g.,
phthalated gelatins, sulfated starchs, sulfated celluloses and
lignin sulfonates and synthetic matters, such as a maleic
anhydride group (including hydrolyzed products) copolymers, an
acrylic acid group (methacrylic acid group) polymers and
copolymer, benzenesulfonic acid group polymers and copolymers,
and carboxyl-modified polyvinyl alcohols.</p>
    <p num="0154">Examples of the nonionic polymer include polyvinyl
alcohols, hydroxyethylcelluloses and methylcelluloses.</p>
    <p num="0155">Examples of the amphoteric polymer include gelatins. 
Among these, gelatins, gelatin derivatives and polyvinyl
alcohols are preferred.</p>
    <p num="0156">The water soluble polymer is used as an aqueous solution
of from 0.01 to 10% by weight.</p>
    <p num="0157">All of the components, including the coloring components
to be used for encapsulation,can be used by being solid
dispersed with a means such as a sand mill along with the water
soluble polymer and other coloration assistants, but are more
preferably used as an emulsion dispersion, which is produced
by dissolving the oily components, such as the coloring
components, in a high boiling point organic solvent hardly
soluble or insoluble in water to form an oily phase, and mixing
a polymer aqueous solution (aqueous phase) containing the
surfactant and/or the water soluble polymer with the oily phase
as a protective colloid, followed by emulsificating with a
homogenizer. In this case, a low boiling point solvent may be
used as a dissolution assistant.</p>
    <p num="0158">Furthermore, all of the components, including the
coloring components, can be separately emulsion dispersed, and
can be preliminary mixed and then dissolved in a high boiling
point solvent, followed by subjecting to emulsion dispersing.
The emulsion dispersed particles preferably have a diameter of
1 µm or less.</p>
    <p num="0159">The emulsion dispersion can be easily carried out, for
example, by a means that is generally used for fine particle 
emulsification, such as high-speed agitation and ultrasonic
wave dispersion, and by known emulsifying apparatuses, such as
a homogenizers, Manton Goreys, an ultrasonic dispersing
apparatuses, dissolvers and KD mills.</p>
    <p num="0160">After the emulsion dispersion, the emulsified product is
heated to 30 to 70°C to accelerate the capsule wall forming
reaction. In order to prevent aggregation of capsules during
the reaction, it is necessary that water is added to decrease
the collision probability of the capsules, and sufficient
agitation is effected.</p>
    <p num="0161">A dispersant for preventing aggregation may be newly
added during the reaction. Formation of carbon dioxide gas is
observed in association with progress of the polymerization
reaction, and the end point of the capsule wall formation
reaction can be detected by termination of the formation thereof.
In general, microcapsules encapsulating the objective dye can
be obtained by continuing the reaction for several hours.</p>
    <p num="0162">The average particle diameter of the microcapsules used
in the recording medium of the invention is preferably 20 µm
or less, and more preferably, from the standpoint for obtaining
high resolution, 5 µm or less. When the diameter of the
microcapsules thus formed is too small, the surface area per
unit solid content becomes large and requires a large amount
of the wall material, and therefore, the average particle
diameter is preferably 0.1 µm or more. </p>
    <heading>Other Recording Layers</heading>
    <p num="0163">Other recording layers can be formed, for example, by
applying an applied coat liquid, which is prepared to have
photosensitivity in a prescribed wavelength region.</p>
    <heading>Other Materials</heading>
    <p num="0164">The recording layer may contain, in addition to the
foregoing components, various kinds of surfactants for various
purposes, such as applying assistance, static charge prevention,
sliding improvement, emulsion dispersion and adhesion
prevention.</p>
    <p num="0165">Examples of the surfactant include nonionic surfactants,
such as saponins, polyethylene oxides, polyethylene oxide
derivatives, such as alkyl ether of polyethylene oxides,
anionic surfactants, such as alkylsulfonates,
alkylbenzenesulfonates, alkylnaphthalenesulfonates,
alkylsulfates, N-acyl-N-alkyltaurines, sulfosuccinates and
sulfoalkylpolyoxyethylene alkylphenyl ethers, amphoteric
surfactants, such as alkylbetaines and alkylsulfobetains, and
cationic surfactants, such as aliphatic or aromatic quaternary
ammonium salts.</p>
    <p num="0166">As other additives depending on necessity, for example,
dye, ultraviolet ray absorbents, plasticizers, fluorescent
whitening agents, matting agents, coating assistants,
hardening agents, antistatic agents and sliding improvers may
also be added. </p>
    <p num="0167">Representative examples of the additives are disclosed
in "Research Disclosure", vol. 176, item 17643, December 1978.
and "Research Discloure", vol. 187, item 18716, November 1979.</p>
    <p num="0168">In the recording layer, and in the intermediate layer,
the protective layer and the like described later, a hardening
agent may be used in combination depending on necessity. In
particular, it is preferred to use a hardening agent in the
protective layer to reduce adhesiveness of the protective
layer.</p>
    <p num="0169">As the hardening agent, for example, gelatin hardening
agents used for production of photographic photosensitive
materials are useful, and examples thereof include aldehyde
compounds, such as formaldehyde and glutaric aldehyde, reactive
halogen compounds disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 3,635,718,
compounds having a reactive ethylenic unsaturated bond
disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 3,635,718, aziridine compounds
disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 3,017,280, epoxy compounds
disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 3,091,537,
halogenocarboxyaldehydes, such as mucochloric acids, dioxanes,
such as dihydroxydioxanes and dichlorodioxanes, vinylsulfones
disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 3,642,486 and No. 3,687,707,
vinylsulfone precursors disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 3,841,872,
and ketovinyls disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 3,640,720.
Furthermore, chromium alum, zirconium sulfate and boric acid
are examples of an inorganic hardening agent. </p>
    <p num="0170">Among these, preferable compounds are
1,3,5-triacryloyl-hexahydro-s-triazines,
1,2-bisvinylsulfonylmethanes,
1,3-bis(vinylsulfonylmethyl)propanol-2s,
bis(α-vinylsulfonylacetamide)ethanes, 2,4-dichloro-6-hydroxy-s-triazine
sodium salts, 2,4,6-triethylenimino-s-triazines
and boric acids.

The hardening agent is preferably added in an amount of from
0.5 to 5% by weight based on the amount of the binder used, which
will be described later.</p>
    <heading>Intermediate Layer</heading>
    <p num="0171">An intermediate layer may be provided between the
respective monochrome recording layers. The intermediate
layer formed mainly with a binder, and depending on necessity,
may contain additives, such as hardening agents, polymer
latexes, filter dyes, micas and an ultraviolet ray absorbents.</p>
    <p num="0172">The binder is preferably a polymer having a molecular
weight of about from 5,000 to 2,000,000, and more preferably
about from 10,000 to 1,000,000. Examples thereof include a
homopolymers or copolymers of acrylate and methacrylate (such
as, copolymers of methylmethacrylate, ethylacrylate and
methacrylic acid, poly(alkyl methacrylate) and poly(alkyl
acrylate)), cellulose esters or cellulose ethers (such as
cellulose acetates, cellulose acetate butylates,
methylcelluloses and ethylcelluloses), polyvinyl butyrals, 
polyvinyl formals, cyclized rubbers, polyethers (such as
polyethylene oxides, polypropylene oxides and
polytetrahydrofurans), polystyrenes, polycarbonates,
polyurethanes, chlorinated polyolefins, polyvinyl chlorides,
vinyl chloride-vinylidene chloride copolymers, copolymers of
vinylidene chloride and acrylonitrile, methyl methacrylates,
vinyl acetates, polyvinyl acetates, copoly(ethylene-vinyl
acetates), polycaprolactams, poly(hexamethylene adipamides),
polyesters (such as poly(ethylene glycol terephthalates) and
poly(hexamethylene glycol succinates), polyamides and
polyureas.</p>
    <p num="0173">Examples thereof also include gelatin compounds,
(modified) polyvinyl alcohols, polyvinyl pyrrolidones, a
hydrolyzed products of a styrene-maleic acid copolymer, sodium
polystyrenesulfonates and sodium alginates. Furthermore,
latexes, such as styrene-butadiene rubber latexes, an
acrylonitrile-butadiene rubber latexes and methyl
methacrylate-butadiene rubber latexes may also be used.</p>
    <p num="0174">An unsaturated compound may also be used as a mixture with
components for forming a non-photopolymerizable film, and
examples thereof include physically dried polymers and a
polymer solutions in an organic solvent, for example,
nitrocellulose or cellulose acetate butylates. However, they
may be a chemically and/or thermally curable (i.e.,
thermosetting) resins, such as polyisocyanates, polyepoxides, 
a melamine resins and polyimide precursors. The use of the
thermosetting resin is important upon using in such a system
that is known as a hybrid system, which is crosslinked by
photopolymerization in the first step and then by a post heat
treatment in the second step.</p>
    <p num="0175">As the binder, solvent soluble polymers, such as
polystyrenes, polyvinyl formals, polyvinyl butyrals, an
acrylic resin, e.g., polymethyl methacrylates, polybutyl
acrylates, polymethyl methacrylates, polybutyl methacrylates
and copolymers thereof, phenol resins, styrene-butadiene
resins, ethylcelluloses, epoxy resins and urethane resins, and
latexes of the polymers may be used in addition to the water
soluble polymer used in the aqueous phase upon encapsulation
of the coloring components. Among these, gelatins and
polyvinyls alcohol are preferred.</p>
    <p num="0176">These binder may be used in the protective layer described
later and the recording layer.</p>
    <p num="0177">In order to prevent interlayer diffusion of the active
ingredients in the recording layer, it is preferred to contain
mica or synthetic mica (such as Suzulite 40H, produced by MRI
Corp.). The addition of the filter dye is preferred since a
high definition image can be obtained. The filter dye can be
selected from the organic dyes having been described herein,
and it is preferred that the dye is appropriately selected from
such compounds that have light absorption wavelengths of the 
upper layers of the respective intermediate layers.</p>
    <p num="0178">The thickness of the intermediate layer is preferably
from 0.1 to 10 µm, and more preferably from 0.5 to 3 µm.</p>
    <heading>Protective Layer and Layer containing Titanium Oxide</heading>
    <p num="0179">The protective layer of the recording material of the
invention is provided as the outermost layer on the side of the
recording layer of the recording material, which is the incident
side of irradiated light, as described above. The protective
layer or a layer adjacent to the protective layer is formed as
a layer containing titanium oxide. By providing the layer
containing titanium oxide, titanium oxide absorbs ultraviolet
rays, whereby the light fastness is improved, and glossiness
can be improved.</p>
    <p num="0180">As described above, the protective layer may contain
either a single layer or multiple layers. In the case where
the protective layer contains multiple layers, and the layer
containing titanium oxide is formed in the protective layer,
the layer containing titanium oxide is formed as the outermost
layer of the protective layer or a layer adjacent to the
outermost layer.</p>
    <p num="0181">The titanium oxide contained in the layer containing
titanium oxide preferably has a particle diameter of 0.2 µm or
less. When the particle diameter of titanium oxide is 0.2 µm
or less, the transparency of the layer containing titanium oxide
can be further increased. The particle diameter of titanium 
oxide is more preferably 0.1 µm or less.</p>
    <p num="0182">It is known that titanium oxide has three kinds of
crystalline structures, i.e., rutile, brookite and anatase, and
the rutile type is most preferably used in the layer containing
titanium oxide of the recording layer of the invention.</p>
    <p num="0183">The content ratio of titanium oxide contained in the layer
containing titanium oxide is preferably from 5 to 90% by weight
based on the layer containing titanium oxide. When the content
ratio of titanium oxide is in this range, more preferrable
results can be obtained in glossiness, light fastness and
transparency of the recording material. It is more preferably
from 20 to 80% by weight.</p>
    <p num="0184">Examples of a material (binder) used in the protective
layer and the layer containing titanium oxide include water
soluble polymers, such as gelatins, polyvinyl alcohols,
carboxyl-modified polyvinyl alcohols, a vinyl acetate-acrylamide
copolymers, silicon-modified polyvinyl alcohols,
starchs, modified starches, methylcelluloses,
carboxymethylcelluloses, hydroxymethylcelluloses, gelatins,
gum arabic, caseins, a hydrolyzed products of a styrene-maleic
acid copolymer, half ester hydrolyzed products of a
styrene-maleic acid copolymer, hydrolyzed products of an
isobutylene-maleic anhydride copolymer, polyacrylamide
derivatives, polyvinylpyrrolidones, sodium
polystyrenesulfonates and sodium alginates, and latexes, such 
as styrene-butadiene rubber latexes, acrylonitrile-butadiene
rubber latexes, methyl methacrylate-butadiene rubber latexes
and vinyl acetate emulsions.</p>
    <p num="0185">The layer containing titanium oxide can be formed, for
example, by dispersing titanium oxide on the surface of the
binder, which is formed as a layer. As the binder, polyvinyl
alcohol (PVA) is preferably used. By forming the layer
containing titanium oxide by using polyvinyl alcohol,
particularly high light fastness can be imparted.</p>
    <p num="0186">It is possible that the materials used in the protective
layer are crosslinked, whereby the storage stability can be
further improved. In this case, known crosslinking agents can
be used as a crosslinking agent used for the crosslinking, and
specific examples thereof include N-methylolureas,
N-methylolmelamines, water soluble initial condensates of
urea-formalin and the like, glyoxals, dialdehyde compounds,
such as glutaric aldehydes, inorganic crosslinking agents, such
as boric acids and boraxes, and polyamide epichlorohydrins.</p>
    <p num="0187">In the protective layer, pigments, metallic soaps, waxes,
surfactants and the like, which are known in the art, can be
added, and UV absorbents and UV absorbent precursors, which are
known in the art can also be added.</p>
    <p num="0188">The coated amount of the protective layer is preferably
from 0.2 to 5 g/m<sup>2</sup>, and more preferably from 0.5 to 3 g/m<sup>2</sup>.</p>
    <heading>Support</heading>
    <p num="0189">Examples of the support include papers, coated papers,
synthetic papers, such as laminated papers, films, such as
polyethylene terephthalate films, cellulose triacetate films,
polyethylene films, polystyrene films and polycarbonate films,
metallic plates, such as aluminum, zinc and copper, and those
obtained by subjecting the surface of the supports to various
kinds of treatments, such as surface treatments, base coating
treatments and metallized treatments.</p>
    <p num="0190">Furthermore, supports disclosed in "Research Disclosure",
vol. 200, Item 20036, Section XVII, December 1980, can also be
exemplified. The supports may contain fluorescent whitening
agents, blueing agents, pigments, and the like. A sheet of
polyurethane foam or rubber which has elasticity, may be used
as the support by itself.</p>
    <p num="0191">Furthermore, depending on necessity, an antihalation
layer may be provided on the front surface of the support used,
and a sliding layer, an antistatic layer, a curl preventing
layer, an adhesive layer and the like may be provided on the
back surface thereof. An adhesive layer may be formed between
the support and the recording layer to provide a constitution
of seal form, in that the support is used as released paper.</p>
    <p num="0192">In the case where the antihalation layer is provided
between the support and the recording layer or on the surface
of the support, on which the recording layer is not provided,
an antihalation layer that can be bleached by irradiation of 
light or heat may be provided for a transparent support.</p>
    <p num="0193">In the case where the antihalation layer is the layer that
can be bleached by irradiation of light, for example, a
combination of an organic dye and an organic boron compound can
be utilized, and in the case where it is the layer that can be
bleached by heat, for example, such a constitution can be
utilized in that a base or a nucleophilic reagent is formed by
heat to bleach a coexisting organic dye.</p>
    <p num="0194">A layer containing a polymer having low oxygen
permeability, such as gelatins and polyvinyl alcohols (PVA),
may be provided between the support and the recording layer.
Color deterioration caused by photooxydation of the formed
image can be effectively prevented by providing this layer.</p>
    <heading>Production of Recording Material</heading>
    <p num="0195">The recording material of the invention can be produced
in such a manner that coating compositions for the recording
layer, the protective layer and the intermediate layer are
prepared by such a means that the components are dissolved in
a solvent depending on necessity, and they are coated on the
support by a known coating method, followed by drying. Examples
of the solvent include water; alcohols, such as methanols,
ethanols, n-propanols, isopropanols, n-butanols, sec-butanols,
methyl cellosolves and 1-methoxy-2-propanols; halogenated
solvents, such as methylene chlorides and ethylene chlorides;
ketones, such as acetones, cyclohexanones and methyl ethyl 
ketones; esters, such as methyl cellosolve acetates, ethyl
acetates and methyl acetates; toluenes; xylenes; and mixtures
of two or more of the above.</p>
    <p num="0196">Examples of the known coating method include methods
using, for example, blade coaters, rod coaters, knife coaters,
doctor roll coaters, reverse roll coaters, transfer roll
coaters, gravure coaters, kiss roll coaters, curtain coaters
and extrusion coaters.</p>
    <p num="0197">The coating operation can also be carried out with
reference to "Research Disclosure", vol. 200, Item 20036,
Section XV, December 1980.</p>
    <p num="0198">The multi-color recording material can be constituted,
for example, in the following manner.</p>
    <p num="0199">A first recording layer containing microcapsules, which
contain a coloring component that produces yellow and a
photopolymerizable composition sensitive to a center
wavelength λ<sub>1</sub> of a light source is provided on a support, a second
recording layer containing microcapsules, which contain a
coloring component that produces magenta and a
photopolymerizable composition sensitive to a center
wavelength λ<sub>2</sub> is provided on the first recording layer, and a
third recording layer containing microcapsules, which contain
a coloring component that poduces cyan and a photopolymerizable
composition sensitive to a center wavelength λ<sub>3</sub> is provided on
the second recording layer. In the invention, at least one 
layer of the first to third recording layers is constituted to
have the first embodiment or the second embodiment described
above. A layer containing titanium oxide is then provided as
a protective layer on the outer surface of the third recording
layer. In the case where the protective layer contains multiple
layers, the outermost layer of the protective layer or a layer
adjacent to the outermost layer is the layer containing titanium
oxide. An intermediate layer may be provided between the
respective recording layer depending on necessity. The center
wavelengths λ<sub>1</sub>, λ<sub>2</sub> and λ<sub>3</sub> of the light sources are different from
each other.</p>
    <p num="0200">In the case where a multi-color image is to be formed using
the recording material of the multi-color type, image exposure
is carried out in the exposing step described later by using
multiple light sources having different wavelengths, which are
adapted to the absorption wavelengths of the respective
recording layers, and thus the recording layers having the
absorption wavelengths of the light sources selectively form
respective latent images, thus forming a multi-color image of
high sharpness with high sensitivity. Thereafter, the surface
of the recording layer is further irradiated with light to
decolor the colored components (absorption components
corresponding to light of those wavelengths) remaining in the
layers, such as the organic dye, and therefore, a high quality
image having a low fog density and high contrast can be formed. </p>
    <p num="0201">According to the foregoing manner, the recording material
of the invention can be used in such purposes as a color printer,
a label, color proof, a duplicator, fax and intermediate paper.</p>
    <heading>Image Forming Method</heading>
    <p num="0202">The respective steps of the process for forming an image
of the invention using the foregoing recording material will
be described. The process for forming an image comprises an
exposing step, a coloring step and a fixing step, as described
above.</p>
    <p num="0203">In the exposing step, the photopolymerizable composition
and the substantially colorless compound, which has a site
producing a color through a reaction with the coloring component
in the recording layer, is exposed in a pattern of an image form,
whereby it is cured in the pattern.</p>
    <p num="0204">In the exposing step, the light source used for image
formation is preferably selected from light sources having
wavelengths adapted to the respective absorption wavelengths
from the standpoint of obtaining high sensitivity and high
sharpness. Specifically, known light sources having
wavelengths from ultraviolet to infrared regions can be used
by selecting from light sources having maximum absorption
wavelengths in a range of from 300 to 1,000 nm. For example,
laser light sources of blue, green, violet and red and an LED
are preferred since the apparatus can be simplified and
miniaturized, and the cost can be reduced. </p>
    <p num="0205">After carrying out the exposing step, the coloring step
is performed. In the coloring step, the surface of the
recording layer is heated to react the coloring component
contained in the recording layer and the substantially
colorless compound producing a color by reacting with the
coloring component and having a site that produces a color when
reacted with the coloring component, whereby coloration occurs
in the form of the latent image being formed and producing a
visual image.</p>
    <p num="0206">The heating operation is carried out with a heat roller,
and in general, the heating temperature is preferably from 80
to 200°C, and more preferably from 85 to 130°C. When the heating
temperature is less than 80°C, the coloring density may become
insufficient, and when it exceeds 200°C, the non-image part
(background part) may form a color, and the support may be
damaged. The heating time is preferably from 1 second to 5
minutes, and more preferably from 3 seconds to 1 minute.</p>
    <p num="0207">Upon carrying out the heating operation, further high
sensitivity can be obtained by performing a preheating step,
in which the entire surface of the recording material is
uniformly preheated to a prescribed temperature lower than the
coloring temperature.</p>
    <p num="0208">After carrying out the coloring step, the fixing step is
performed. In the fixing step, the entire surface of the
recording material is irradiated with light by a particular 
light source, whereby the image formed in the coloring step is
fixed, and the coloration due to the colored component (organic
dye) remaining in the recording layer is decolored.</p>
    <p num="0209">Through the fixing step, whiteness of the non-image part
can be improved to obtain a chemically stable final image. In
the case where a diazonium salt compound is used as the coloring
component, the diazonium salt compound remaining in the
recording material after the image formation can be deactivated
by irradiation with light, and thus it is useful for
stabilization upon storing the formed image without
fluctuations in density and discoloration.</p>
    <p num="0210">Preferred examples of the light source that can be used
in the fixing step include wide varieties of light sources, such
as mercury lamps, ultra-high pressure mercury lamps,
electrodeless discharge type mercury lamps, xenon lamps,
tungsten lamps, metal halide lamps and fluorescent lamps.</p>
    <p num="0211">The method for irradiation with light in the fixing step
is not particularly limited. While both the following methods
may be used, i.e., a method of irradiating the entire surface
of the recording layer at the same time, and a method of gradually
irradiating the recording surface, for example, by scanning,
whereby the entire surface is finally irradiated, a method can
be employed such that the entire recording surface of the
recording material after the image formation can be irradiated
with substantially uniform irradiation light. Accordingly, it 
is preferred that the entire recording surface is irradiated
with light from the standpoint that the effects of the invention
are effectively achieved.</p>
    <p num="0212">The time for irradiating with light in the fixing step
may be such a period that the formed image is fixed, and the
non-image part (background part) is sufficiently decolored, and
in order to obtaining sufficient image fixing property and
decoloration property with no deterioration in recording rate,
it is preferably from several seconds to several tens minutes,
and more preferably from several seconds to several minutes.</p>
    <p num="0213">According to the process for forming an image of the
invention, when the heating operation in the coloring step is
carried out with a heat roller, an image can be successfully
formed without any influence on the layer containing titanium
oxide of the recording layer. A thermal head, on the other hand,
is not preferrable since titanium oxide fine particles are
attached to the thermal head.</p>
    <heading>EXAMPLES</heading>
    <p num="0214">The invention will be described with reference to the
following examples, but the invention is not construed as being
limited to the examples. "Parts" and "percents" in the examples
denote "parts by weight" and "% by weight", respectively.</p>
    <heading>Preparation of Microcapsule Liquid encapsulating Electron-donating
Colorless Dye</heading>
    <p num="0215">4.4 parts of the following electron-donating colorless
dye (1) coloring yellow was dissolved in 18.4 parts by weight
of ethyl acetate, and 21 parts of a capsule wall material
(Takenate D-110N, a trade name, produced by Takeda Chemical
Industries, Ltd.) and 0.7 part of another capsule wall material
(Millionate MR200, a trade name, produced by Nippon
Polyurethane Co., Ltd.) were added thereto.</p>
    <p num="0216">The resulting solution was added to a mixed solution of
52 parts of 8%-phthalated gelatin and 0.3 part of a 10% sodium
dodecylbenzenesulfonate solution, and then emulsion dispersed
at a temperature of 20°C to obtain a emulsion liquid. 54 parts
of a 1.1% tetraethylenepentamine solution was added to the
resulting emulsion liquid, and the mixture was heated to 60°C
while being stirred. After two hours, a microcapsule liquid
having an average particle diameter of 0.5 µm containing the
electron-donating colorless dye (1) as a core. The solid
content thereof was then adjusted to 25% by adding water.</p>
    <heading>Electron-donating colorless dye (1)</heading>
    <p num="0217">
      <img id="img-00780001" orientation="unknown" wi="86" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00780001.tif" inline="no" he="45"/>
    </p>
    <heading>Preparation of Photopolymerizable Composition Emulsion Liquid</heading>
    <p num="0218">100.0 parts of a mixture of the following electron-accepting 
compounds having a polymerizable group (1) and (2)
(mixing ratio: 50/50) and 0.1 part of the following heat
polymerization inhibitor (ALI) were dissolved in 125.0 parts
of isopropyl acetate (solubility in water: ca. 4.3%) to obtain
a mixed solution I. 6.0 parts of the following organic boron
compound was added to the mixed solution I, followed by
dissolution at 42°C, to obtain a mixed solution II.</p>
    <p num="0219">The mixed solution II was added to a mixed solution of
300.1 parts of a 8% gelatin solution and 17.4 parts of the
following 10% surfactant (1) aqueous solution, and
emulsification was carried out at a rotation speed of 10,000
for 5 minutes by using a homogenizer (produced by Nippon Seiki
Co., Ltd.) to obtain a photopolymerizable composition emulsion
liquid (1). Thereafter, solvent removal was carried out at 40°C
for 3 hours, and then the solid content was adjusted to 30%.</p>
    <heading>Electron-accepting compounds
having a polymerizable group (1) and (2)</heading>
    <p num="0220">
      <img id="img-00790001" orientation="unknown" wi="94" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00790001.tif" inline="no" he="42"/>
      <img id="img-00790002" orientation="unknown" wi="59" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00790002.tif" inline="no" he="28"/>
      <img id="img-00800001" orientation="unknown" wi="65" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00800001.tif" inline="no" he="31"/>
      <img id="img-00800002" orientation="unknown" wi="104" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00800002.tif" inline="no" he="38"/>
    </p>
    <heading>Preparation of a light and heat sensitive recording layer and
a coating solution therefor</heading>
    <p num="0221">8.4 parts by weight of the aforementioned emulsion of a
photopolymerizable composition, 3.3 parts by weight of the
aforementioned thermally responsive microcapsule solution
including an electron-donating colorless dye and 0.9 parts by
weight of a 15% gelatin solution were mixed to prepare a coating
solution for a light and heat sensitive recording layer.</p>
    <p num="0222">8 mass by weight of water-swellable synthetic mica (trade
name: Somashif ME100, manufactured by Cope Chemical) was mixed
with 98 part by mass water and the mixture was wet-dispersed
using a viscomill to prepare a mica dispersion having an averge
particle diameter of 2.0 µm. 950 parts by weight of water was
added to 100 parts by weight the dispersion and the both were
uniformly mixed. Thereafter, 500 parts by weight of an aqueous
15% alkali-treated gelatin solution was added to the mixture
while the mixture was kept at 40°C and stirred. Further, 50 
parts by weight of 2% sodium (4-nonylphenoxyrioxyethylene)
butyl sulfonate was added to the resulting mixture to obtain
an undercoating solution containing mica. The resulting
undercoating solution was applied to the support (resin-coated
paper) such that the dry weight was 2.0 g/m<sup>2</sup> and dried to form
an undercoat layer.</p>
    <p num="0223">The aforementioned coating solution for a light and heat
sensitive recording layer was applied to the undercoat layer
such that the dry weight was 4.5 g/m<sup>2</sup> and dried to obtain a
recording material.</p>
    <heading>Example 1</heading>
    <p num="0224">16 g of a titanium oxide ultra-fine particle dispersion
liquid (ELCOM-P, a trade name, produced by Shokubai Kagaku Co.,
Ltd., solid content: 20% by weight), 1.5 g of a 2% surfactant
A and 4.5 g of a 2% surfactant B were added to 80g of a 4% gelatin
aqueous solution to produce a protective layer coating
composition 1. The protective layer coating composition 1 was
coated and dried on the sensitive material to make a solid
content after drying of 2 g/m<sup>2</sup> to obtain Sample 1. The content
ratio of titanium oxide with respect to gelatin was 100%, and
the particle diameter of titanium oxide was 10 nm.</p>
    <heading>Example 2</heading>
    <p num="0225">4 g of a titanium oxide ultra-fine particle dispersion
liquid (ELCOM-P, a trade name, produced by Shokubai Kagaku Co.,
Ltd., solid content: 20% by weight), 1.5 g of a 2% surfactant 
A and 4.5 g of a 2% surfactant B were added to 80 g of a 4% PVA
aqueous solution (PVA124C, a trade name, produced by Kuraray
Co., Ltd.) to produce a protective layer coating composition
2. The protective layer coating composition 2 was coated and
dried on the sensitive material to make a solid content after
drying of 2 g/m<sup>2</sup> to obtain Sample 2. The content ratio of
titanium oxide with respect to PVA was 25%, and the particle
diameter of titanium oxide was 10 nm.</p>
    <heading>Example 3</heading>
    <p num="0226">16 g of a titanium oxide ultra-fine particle dispersion
liquid (ELCOM-P, a trade name, produced by Shokubai Kagaku Co.,
Ltd., solid content: 20% by weight), 4.5 g of a 2% surfactant
A and 4.5 g of a 2% surfactant B were added to 80 g of a 4% PVA
aqueous solution (PVA124C, a trade name, produced by Kuraray
Co., Ltd.) to produce a protective layer coating composition
3. The protective layer coating composition 3 was coated and
dried on the sensitive material to make a solid content after
drying of 2 g/m<sup>2</sup> to obtain Sample 3. The content ratio of
titanium oxide with respect to PVA was 100%, and the particle
diameter of titanium oxide was 10 nm.</p>
    <heading>Example 4</heading>
    <p num="0227">16 g of a titanium oxide ultra-fine particle dispersion
liquid (ELCOM-P, a trade name, produced by Shokubai Kagaku Co.,
Ltd., solid content: 20% by weight), 1.5 g of a 2% surfactant
A and 4.5 g of a 2% surfactant B were added to 80 g of a 4% PVA 
aqueous solution (R2105, a trade name, produced by Kuraray Co.,
Ltd.) to produce a protective layer coating composition 4. The
protective layer coating composition 4 was coated and dried on
the sensitive material to make a solid content after drying of
2 g/m<sup>2</sup> to obtain Sample 4. The content ratio of titanium oxide
with respect to PVA was 100%, and the particle diameter of
titanium oxide was 10 nm.</p>
    <heading>Example 5</heading>
    <p num="0228">A protective layer coating composition produced in the
following Comparative Example 1 was further coated and dried
to make a solid content of 2 g/m<sup>2</sup> on Sample 4 produced in Example
4 to obtain Sample 5. The content ratio of titanium oxide with
respect to PVA was 100%, and the particle diameter of titanium
oxide was 10 nm.</p>
    <heading>Comparative Example 1</heading>
    <p num="0229">1.5 g of a 2% surfactant A and 4.5 g of a 2% surfactant
B were added to 94 g of 6% gelatin to produce a protective layer
coating composition 5. The protective layer coating
composition 5 was coated and dried on the sensitive material
to make a solid content after drying of 2 g/m<sup>2</sup> to obtain Sample
6.</p>
    <heading>Image Forming Method</heading>
    <p num="0230">Samples 1 to 6 obtained in the foregoing were subjected
to image formation in the following manner. Herein, the case
of Sample 1 will be shown as an example. </p>
    <p num="0231">Sample 1 was imagewise exposed from the side of the
protective layer to a step wedge form to make irradiation energy
being stepwise changed with a maximum irradiation energy of 12
mJ/cm<sup>2</sup> by using semiconductor laser light having a wavelength
of 405 nm (exposing step). Subsequently, Sample 1 thus exposed
to have a latent image formed therein was heated for 10 seconds
on a hot plate at 110°C (coloring step), and then the entire
surface of the recording layer was irradiated for 30 seconds
by using a fluorescent lamp irradiating apparatus of 38,000 lux
(fixing step).</p>
    <heading>Evaluation of Glossiness</heading>
    <p num="0232">The glossiness of the recorded sample was measured at an
incident angle of 20° with a digital angular displacement
glossmeter (UGV-5D, trade name, produced by Suga Test
Instruments Co., Ltd.).</p>
    <heading>Evaluation of Light Fastness</heading>
    <p num="0233">The light fastness of the recorded sample was measured
in such manner that the sample was exposed to light at 85,000
lux for 72 hours with a xenon weather-ometer (Ci5000, a trade
name, produced by Atlas Weathering Services), and the increment
of Y- OD on the background part (ΔOD-Y) was measured with a
Macbeth densitometer.</p>
    <p num="0234">The measurement results are shown in Table 1.</p>
    <heading>TABLE 1</heading>
    <p num="0235">
      <tables>
        <table>
          <tgroup cols="5">
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry align="center"/>
                <entry align="center">Binder</entry>
                <entry align="center">Coated amount</entry>
                <entry align="center">Glossiness (20°)</entry>
                <entry align="center">Light fastness Background coloration (ΔOD-Y)</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Example 1</entry>
                <entry align="center">Gelatin</entry>
                <entry align="center">2 g/m<sup>2</sup></entry>
                <entry align="center">30%</entry>
                <entry align="center">+0.12</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Example 2</entry>
                <entry align="center">PVA124C</entry>
                <entry align="center">2 g/m<sup>2</sup></entry>
                <entry align="center">30%</entry>
                <entry align="center">+0.12</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Example 3</entry>
                <entry align="center">PVA124C</entry>
                <entry align="center">2 g/m<sup>2</sup></entry>
                <entry align="center">33%</entry>
                <entry align="center">+0.06</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Example 4</entry>
                <entry align="center">R2105</entry>
                <entry align="center">2 g/m<sup>2</sup></entry>
                <entry align="center">36%</entry>
                <entry align="center">+0.06</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Example 5</entry>
                <entry align="center">R2105

Gelatin</entry>
                <entry align="center">2 g/m<sup>2</sup>

2 g/m<sup>2</sup></entry>
                <entry align="center">38%</entry>
                <entry align="center">+0.05</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Comparative Example 1</entry>
                <entry align="center">Gelatin</entry>
                <entry align="center">2 g/m<sup>2</sup></entry>
                <entry align="center">23%</entry>
                <entry align="center">+0.30</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </tables>
    </p>
    <p num="0236">It was understood from the results in Table 1 that images
having high glossiness could be obtained in the recording
materials of the examples (Samples 1 to 5) having a layer
containing titanium oxide in comparison to Sample 6 of the
comparative example. Such recording materials that are
excellent in light fastness on both the colored part and the
background part could be obtained.</p>
    <p num="0237">According to the invention, a recording material having
high glossiness and high light fastness and a process for
forming an image using the recording material can be provided.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A recording material comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a support;</claim-text><claim-text>a recording layer provided on the support; and</claim-text><claim-text>at least one protective layer provided on the recording
layer,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein, the recording layer contains a coloring
component A encapsulated in heat-responsive microcapsules, and
a substantially colorless compound B, which is outside the
heat-responsive microcapsules and has a coloring site that
colors when reacted with the coloring component A, and
   wherein, at least one of the protective layer or a layer
adjacent thereto comprises a layer containing titanium oxide.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The recording layer according to claim 1, wherein the
protective layer includes at least two layers, and an outermost
layer of the protective layer or a layer adjacent to the
outermost layer is the layer containing titanium oxide.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The recording layer according to any of claims 1 and 2,
wherein the recording layer further contains a
photopolymerizable composition.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The recording layer according to any of claims 1 to 3,
wherein the compound B includes the coloring site and a
polymerizable group in one molecule.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The recording layer according to any of claims 1 to 4,
wherein the recording layer further contains a substantially
colorless compound C, which has a site that suppresses a
reaction between the coloring component A and the compound B
and a polymerizable group in one molecule.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The recording layer according to any of claims 1 to 5,
wherein titanium oxide contained in the layer containing
titanium oxide has a particle diameter of no more than 0.2 µm.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>The recording layer according to any of claims 1 to 6,
wherein an amount of titanium oxide contained in the layer
containing titanium oxide is from 5 to 90% by weight relative
to the layer containing titanium oxide.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The recording layer according to any of claims 1 to 7,
wherein the layer containing titanium oxide comprises a binder
formed in a layer having titanium oxide dispersed on a surface
thereof, which binder comprises polyvinyl alcohol.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
