<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1227535-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1227535" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="26608086" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020731">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1227535-A1" status="new" fvid="23519761">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1227535</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20020731</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02001343-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02001343</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020118</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001013601-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001013601</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010122</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001342004-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001342004</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20011107</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01P   1/20        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01P   1/205       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01P   1/212       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">H01P   1/213       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">H01P   1/213E</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Dielektrischer Duplexer und Kommunikationsgerät</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Dielectric duplexer and communication apparatus</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Duplexeur diélectrique et dispositif de communication</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MURATA MANUFACTURING CO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MURATA MANUFACTURING CO., LTD.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Murata Manufacturing Co., Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>26-10, Tenjin 2-chome</street>
              <city>Nagaokakyo-shi Kyoto-fu 617-8555</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ISHIHARA JINSEI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KATO HIDEYUKI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>OKADA TAKAHIRO</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ISHIHARA, JINSEI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KATO, HIDEYUKI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>OKADA, TAKAHIRO</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Ishihara, Jinsei, c/oMurata Manufac. Co.,Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>(A170) IPD, 26-10, Tenjin 2-chome</street>
              <city>Nagaokakyo-shi, Kyoto-fu 617-8555</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Kato, Hideyuki, c/oMurata Manufac. Co.,Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>(A170) IPD, 26-10, Tenjin 2-chome</street>
              <city>Nagaokakyo-shi, Kyoto-fu 617-8555</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Okada, Takahiro, c/oMurata Manufac. Co.,Ltd.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>(A170) IPD, 26-10, Tenjin 2-chome</street>
              <city>Nagaokakyo-shi, Kyoto-fu 617-8555</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Schoppe, Fritz, Dipl.-Ing.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Schoppe, Zimmermann &amp;amp; Stöckeler Patentanwälte Postfach 71 08 67</street>
              <city>81458 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A dielectric duplexer includes a substantially rectangular
dielectric block (1). The dielectric block includes
inner-conductor-containing holes (2a - 2f) each having an inner
conductor (3a - 3f) on the inner surfaces thereof, and
inner-conductor-unformed portions (4a - 4f) on which the inner
conductors (3a - 3f) are not formed are formed in the vicinity
of first ends of the inner-conductor-containing holes (2a - 2f).</p>
    <p>The dielectric block (1) further includes an outer conductor (5)
and input/output electrodes (6, 7, 8) which are formed on the outer
surface thereof, and the input/output electrodes (6, 7, 8) are
separated from the outer conductor (5). A through-hole (9) having
a short circuited electrode (10) formed on the inner surface thereof
is provided between two (2d, 2c) of the inner-conductor-containing
holes (2a, 2f) so as to run from the mounting surface to the surface
opposite thereto.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="80" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="88"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <heading>1. Field of the Invention</heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a dielectric duplexer mainly
used in the microwave band, and a communication apparatus using the
same.</p>
    <heading>2. Description of the Related Art</heading>
    <p num="0002">A typical dielectric duplexer is described with reference to
Fig. 11.</p>
    <p num="0003">Fig. 11 is a perspective view of the appearance of a typical
dielectric duplexer.</p>
    <p num="0004">Referring to Fig. 11, a substantially rectangular dielectric
block 1 includes inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to 2f having
inner conductors 3a to 3f formed on the inner surfaces thereof,
respectively, and an outer conductor 5 formed on the entire outer
surface thereof. Inner-conductor-unformed portions 4a to 4f on
which the inner conductors 3a to 3f are not formed are formed in
the vicinity of first ends of the inner-conductor-containing holes
2a to 2f, and the first ends are open. Second ends that are opposite
to the first ends are short circuited. Thus, dielectric resonators
are constructed. Each of the inner-conductor-containing holes 2a
to 2f is stepped so that the open end side has a larger inner diameter
than the short circuited end side.</p>
    <p num="0005">On the outer surface of the dielectric block 1, input/output
electrodes 6 and 7, which are separated from the outer conductor
5, are formed so as to extend from the end surfaces in the alignment
direction of the inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to 2f to the
mounting surface that faces the mounting substrate. On the outer
surface of the dielectric block 1, an input/output electrode 8, which
is separated from the outer conductor 5, is further formed between
the inner-conductor-containing holes 2c and 2d so as to extend from
the open end surface of the inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to
2f to the mounting surface. With this structure, a first group of
the inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to 2c, and a second group
of the inner-conductor-containing holes 2d to 2f each form a 
three-stage dielectric filter having a coupling capacitor, thereby
forming a dielectric duplexer as a whole.</p>
    <p num="0006">Specifically, the dielectric block 1, the inner conductors 2a
to 2f, and the outer conductor 5 constitute TEM (transverse
electromagnetic) mode resonators, and the TEM mode resonators are
combline-coupled with each other by means of stray capacitance
generated in the inner-conductor-unformed portions 4a to 4f to form
dielectric filters. The plurality of dielectric filters are
combined to form a dielectric duplexer. The dielectric duplexer
has attenuation poles (coupling poles) because of coupling between
the resonators. The attenuation poles can be used to provide a sharp
attenuation characteristic from the pass band to the cut-off band
near a low frequency region or from the pass band to the cut-off
band near a high frequency region.</p>
    <p num="0007">However, such a typical dielectric duplexer has encountered
a problem to be overcome.</p>
    <p num="0008">In a dielectric duplexer having a substantially rectangular
dielectric block and an outer conductor formed on the outer surface
thereof, a resonance mode other than a basic resonance mode or a
TEM mode, including a TE<sub>101</sub> mode, may be generated by the dielectric
block and the outer conductor. Once a resonance mode different from
a basic resonance mode, such as a TE mode, is generated, the
dielectric duplexer will increase spurious responses.</p>
    <p num="0009">In order to overcome such a problem, approaches which have been
contemplated are (1) to modify the dimensions of a dielectric
duplexer to offset the resonant frequency of a TE mode, and (2) to
separately provide a transmission filter and a reception filter
which are combined so that the influence of a TE mode on the
dielectric duplexer may be reduced.</p>
    <p num="0010">In approach (1), the dimensions of the dielectric duplexer must
be defined with consideration of a TE mode, and a filter design
accommodating a TEM mode is required. Furthermore, since a compact
dielectric duplexer is desirable in the current state, there are
limitations to variable dimensions, leading to less flexibility in
design.</p>
    <p num="0011">In approach (2), since two components are required for a
transmission filter and a reception filter, the number of circuit
components increases, resulting in increased production cost. The 
transmission filter and the reception filter are bonded by soldering,
thereby reducing reliability.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0012">Accordingly, it is an object of the present invention to provide
a dielectric duplexer which eliminates or reduces the influence of
a TE mode and has low spurious responses without the need to modify
the dimensions or connect additional components, and to provide a
communication apparatus using the dielectric duplexer.</p>
    <p num="0013">To this end, in one aspect of the present invention, a
dielectric duplexer includes:
<sl><li>a dielectric block;</li><li>a plurality of inner-conductor-containing holes formed in the
dielectric block, each hole having an inner conductor formed on the
inner surface thereof, the inner-conductor-containing holes
extending from one surface to another surface opposite thereto of
the dielectric block;</li><li>an outer conductor and an input/output terminal which are
formed on the outer surface of the dielectric block, the input/output
terminal being separated from the outer conductor; and</li><li>at least one short circuited conductor formed between the
plurality of inner-conductor-containing holes on a transmitter side
and the plurality of inner-conductor-containing holes on a receiver
side, said at least one short circuited conductor extending from
one surface that is parallel to the axes of the inner-conductor-containing
holes to another surface opposite thereto and
conductively coupled to said outer conductor.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0014">Therefore, the dielectric duplexer is affected less by a TE
mode and has low spurious responses.</p>
    <p num="0015">The dielectric block may include an excitation hole for an
antenna, and the at least one short circuited conductor preferably
intersects the excitation hole. Therefore, the dielectric duplexer
has low spurious responses.</p>
    <p num="0016">In another aspect of the present invention, a communication
apparatus incorporates the dielectric duplexer, thereby achieving
the desired communication characteristics.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0017">Other features and advantages of the present invention will
become apparent from the following description of the invention
which refers to the accompanying drawings.
<sl><li>Fig. 1 is a perspective view of the appearance of a dielectric
duplexer according to a first embodiment of the present invention;</li><li>Fig. 2 is a cross-sectional view of the dielectric duplexer
shown in Fig. 1;</li><li>Figs. 3A and 3B are views each showing the magnetic field vector
of a TE mode which is generated in a dielectric duplexer;</li><li>Figs. 4A and 4B are graphs showing spurious responses of the
dielectric duplexer according to the first embodiment;</li><li>Fig. 5 is a perspective view of the appearance of a dielectric
duplexer according to a second embodiment of the present invention;</li><li>Fig. 6 is a cross-sectional view of the dielectric duplexer
shown in Fig. 5;</li><li>Fig. 7 is a perspective view of the appearance of a dielectric
duplexer according to a third embodiment of the present invention;</li><li>Figs. 8A and 8B are a top view and a cross-sectional view of
the dielectric duplexer shown in Fig. 7, respectively;</li><li>Figs. 9A and 9B are a perspective view and a cross-sectional
view of the appearance of a modified dielectric duplexer according
to the third embodiment, respectively;</li><li>Fig. 10 is a block diagram of a communication apparatus
according to a fourth embodiment of the present invention; and</li><li>Fig. 11 is a perspective view of the appearance of a typical
dielectric duplexer.</li></sl></p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF EMBODIMENTS OF THE INVENTION</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0018">A dielectric duplexer according to a first embodiment of the
present invention is described with reference to Figs. 1 to 4.</p>
    <p num="0019">Fig. 1 is a perspective view of the appearance of the dielectric
duplexer, and Fig. 2 is a cross-sectional view of the dielectric
duplexer shown in Fig. 1.</p>
    <p num="0020">Fig. 3A shows the magnetic field vector of a TE mode which is
generated in a typical dielectric duplexer, and Fig. 3B shows the
magnetic field vector of a TE mode which is generated in the
dielectric duplexer according to the first embodiment which includes 
a through-hole having a short circuited electrode formed on the inner
surface thereof.</p>
    <p num="0021">Figs. 4A and 4B are spurious response charts of the dielectric
duplexer.</p>
    <p num="0022">Referring to Figs. 1 and 2, a substantially rectangular
dielectric block 1 includes inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to
2f having inner conductors 3a to 3f formed on the inner surfaces
thereof, respectively, and an outer conductor 5 formed on the
substantially entire outer surface thereof. Inner-conductor-unformed
portions 4a to 4f on which the inner conductors 3a to 3f
are not formed are formed in the vicinity of first ends of the
inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to 2f, and the first ends are
open. Second ends that are opposite to the first ends are short
circuited. Thus, dielectric resonators are constructed. Each of
the inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to 2f is stepped so that
the open end side has a larger inner diameter than the short circuited
end side.</p>
    <p num="0023">On the outer surface of the dielectric block 1, input/output
electrodes 6 and 7, which are separated from the outer conductor
5, are formed so as to extend from the end surfaces in the alignment
direction of the inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to 2f to the
mounting surface which faces the mounting substrate. On the outer
surface of the dielectric block 1, an input/output electrode 8 which
is separated from the outer conductor 5 is further formed between
the inner-conductor-containing holes 2c and 2d so as to extend from
the open end surface of the inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to
2f to the mounting surface.</p>
    <p num="0024">The input/output electrode 6 is capacitively coupled with the
inner conductor 3a, and the input/output electrode 7 is capacitively
coupled with the inner conductor 3f. The input/output electrode
8 is capacitively coupled with the inner conductors 3c and 3d.</p>
    <p num="0025">With this structure, a first group of the inner-conductor-containing
holes 2a to 2c, and a second group of the inner-conductor-containing
holes 2d to 2f act as first and second
three-stage comb-line dielectric filters, respectively. An
apparatus which uses the first comb-line dielectric filter as a
transmission filter and the second comb-line dielectric filter as
a reception filter would act as a dielectric duplexer in which the 
input/output electrodes 6, 7, and 8 typically serve as a transmission
signal input terminal, a reception signal output terminal, and an
antenna terminal, respectively.</p>
    <p num="0026">As shown in Figs. 1 and 2, a through-hole 9 having a short
circuited electrode 10 formed on the inner surface thereof is
provided in the center of the dielectric block 1 between the
inner-conductor-containing holes 2c and 2d so as to run from the
mounting surface (the left hand surface in Fig. 1) to the surface
opposite (the right hand or rear surface in Fig. 1) thereto.</p>
    <p num="0027">In the thus constructed dielectric duplexer, the electric field
is short circuited by the short circuited electrode 10 in the
location where the electric field energy of a TE<sub>101</sub> mode shown in
Fig. 3A is most highly concentrated. As a result, a TE<sub>101</sub> mode is
not substantially generated or excited. As shown in Fig. 3B, a TE<sub>201</sub>
mode is not substantially affected by the short circuited electrode
10, and is not suppressed but may be sometimes rather enhanced. The
resonant frequency of a TE<sub>201</sub> mode is inherently higher than the
resonant frequency of a TE<sub>101</sub> mode, and the influence of a TE mode
on the frequency band used is reduced, resulting in reduced spurious
responses.</p>
    <p num="0028">It is not necessary for the through-hole 9 containing the short
circuited electrode 10 to be provided in the center of the dielectric
block 1, and the through-hole 9 may be alternatively provided in
the vicinity of an end surface, if desired. Rather than a single
through hole, a plurality of through-holes may be provided.</p>
    <p num="0029">Figs. 4A and 4B are graphs showing spurious responses for
transmission and reception in a dielectric duplexer having a
dimension of 10 x 6 x 2 mm. Each graph exhibits characteristics
when the short circuited electrode 10 is not included, when the short
circuited electrode 10 is inserted in the center, and when the short
circuited electrode 10 is inserted in an end portion.</p>
    <p num="0030">As is apparent from Figs. 4A and 4B, a TE<sub>101</sub> mode is generated
in the vicinity of 3.8 GHz when the short circuited conductor is
not included. On the other hand, the peak frequency can be shifted
to the vicinity of 4.1 GHz when the short circuited conductor is
inserted in an end portion, or to the vicinity of 4.5 GHz when the
short circuited conductor is inserted in the center, where an
attenuation amount increases in a range between 3.6 GHz and 3.9 GHz. 
Therefore, as a short circuited conductor is provided in closer
proximity to the center, the peak frequency is shifted to a higher
frequency region.</p>
    <p num="0031">In the dielectric duplexer according to the first embodiment
with reference to Figs. 1 to 3, the input/output electrodes 6 to
8 are capacitively coupled with predetermined inner conductors;
however, other types of input/output units may also be used. For
example, excitation holes are formed at outer positions than the
outermost inner-conductor-containing holes 2a and 2f so as to be
parallel to the inner-conductor-containing holes 2a and 2f. An
excitation hole is further formed between the inner-conductor-containing
holes 2c and 2d so as to be parallel to the inner-conductor-containing
holes 2c and 2d. Then, input/output
electrodes which conduct to conductors contained in the excitation
holes are formed so as to extend from the mounting surface to the
open end surface of the inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to 2f.</p>
    <p num="0032">In this case, the excitation holes are interdigital coupled
with the resonators formed by the associated inner-conductor-containing
holes which are adjacent to the excitation holes.</p>
    <p num="0033">One or two of the three input/output electrodes may be
externally coupled through the excitation holes.</p>
    <p num="0034">Besides the external coupling through the excitation holes,
trap resonators may be provided. More specifically, inner-conductor-containing
holes having the same structure as that of the
inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to 2f are formed in outwardly
of the outer position than the excitation holes which are coupled
with the inner-conductor-containing holes 2a and 2f. The
inner-conductor-containing holes are used as trap resonators.</p>
    <p num="0035">The trap resonators would provide an increased attenuation
characteristic at the boundary of the pass band, thereby improving
the capability of the dielectric duplexer in addition to the
aforementioned advantages. The trap resonator on the transmission
filter side exhibits a sharp drop in the amount of transmission from
the transmission frequency pass band to the reception frequency band.
A trap resonator on the reception filter side exhibits a sharp drop
in the amount of transmission from the reception frequency pass band
to the transmission frequency band. </p>
    <p num="0036">Either the trap resonator on the transmission filter side or
the trap resonator on the reception filter side may be provided.</p>
    <p num="0037">In Figs. 1 to 3, the short circuited electrode 10 is formed
on the inner surface of the through-hole 9. Instead of the
through-hole 9, a conductor such as an electrode film or a metal
bar may be embedded in the dielectric block 1 in order to electrically
short circuit both surfaces.</p>
    <p num="0038">A dielectric duplexer according to a second embodiment of the
present invention is described with reference to Figs. 5 and 6.</p>
    <p num="0039">Figs. 5A and 5B are perspective views of the appearance of two
different types of dielectric duplexers. Fig. 5A shows a dielectric
duplexer having input/output electrodes formed on the mounting
surface and on the end surfaces in the alignment direction of the
inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to 2f. Fig. 5B shows a
dielectric duplexer having input/output electrodes formed on the
mounting surface, the end surfaces in the alignment direction of
the inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to 2f, and on the open
surface of the inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to 2f.</p>
    <p num="0040">Fig. 6 is a cross-sectional view of the dielectric duplexer
shown in Fig. 5A.</p>
    <p num="0041">Referring to Figs. 5A and 6, a substantially rectangular
dielectric block 1 includes inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to
2f having inner conductors 3a to 3f formed on the inner surfaces
thereof, respectively, and an outer conductor 5 formed on the outer
surface thereof except for one surface where the inner-conductor-containing
holes 2a to 2f are formed, i.e., on five
surfaces. The surface where the inner-conductor-containing holes
2a to 2f are formed includes electrodes in the vicinity of the
openings of the inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to 2f, and that
surface is open. The other surface opposite thereto where the
inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to 2f are formed is short
circuited. Thus, dielectric resonators are constructed.</p>
    <p num="0042">On the outer surface of the dielectric block 1, input/output
electrodes 6 and 7 which are separated from the outer conductor 5
are formed so as to extend from the end surfaces in the alignment
direction of the inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to 2f to the
mounting surface which faces the mounting substrate. On the outer
surface of the dielectric block 1, an input/output electrode 8 which 
is separated from the outer conductor 5 is further formed between
the inner-conductor-containing holes 2c and 2d on the mounting
surface in the vicinity of the open surface of the inner-conductor-containing
holes 2a to 2f. With this structure, a first
group of the inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to 2c, and a second
group of the inner-conductor-containing holes 2d to 2f each form
a three-stage comb-line dielectric filter. The input/output
electrode 6 is capacitively coupled with the inner conductor 3a,
and the input/output electrode 7 is capacitively coupled with the
inner conductor 3f. The input/output electrode 8 is capacitively
coupled with the inner conductor 3c and 3d. Therefore, a dielectric
duplexer is formed as a whole.</p>
    <p num="0043">A through-hole 9 having a short circuited electrode 10 formed
on the inner surface thereof is provided in the center between the
inner-conductor-containing holes 2c and 2d so as to run from the
mounting surface to the surface opposite thereto.</p>
    <p num="0044">In the thus constructed dielectric duplexer, as in the first
embodiment, the lowest resonant frequency in a TE mode is shifted
to a higher frequency region, resulting in reduced spurious
responses.</p>
    <p num="0045">The dielectric duplexer shown in Fig. 5B includes input/output
electrodes 6 and 7 which are formed so as to extend from the mounting
surface to the end surfaces in the alignment direction of the
inner-conductor-containing holes 2a and 2f and to the open surface
of the inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to 2f. The dielectric
duplexer further includes an input/output electrode 8 which is
formed so as to extend from the mounting surface to the open surface
of the inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to 2f. The structure
of other components is the same as that in the dielectric duplexer
shown in Fig. 5A. In the thus constructed dielectric duplexer shown
in Fig. 5B, as in the first embodiment, the lowest resonant frequency
in a TE mode is shifted to a higher frequency region, resulting in
reduced spurious responses.</p>
    <p num="0046">A dielectric duplexer according to a third embodiment of the
present invention is described with reference to Figs. 7 and 8.</p>
    <p num="0047">Fig. 7 is a perspective view of the appearance of the dielectric
duplexer, and Figs. 8A and 8B are a top view and a cross-sectional
view of the dielectric duplexer shown in Fig. 7, respectively. </p>
    <p num="0048">The dielectric duplexer shown in Fig. 7 includes an excitation
hole 11 for an antenna (hereinafter simply referred to "excitation
hole") which penetrates through the input/output electrode 8 and
which penetrates through the dielectric block 1 in parallel to the
inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to 2f. The input/output
electrode 8 extends from the mounting surface to the open surface
in which the short circuited ends of the inner-conductor-containing
holes 2a to 2f are formed. The structure of the other components
is the same as that in the dielectric duplexer according to the first
embodiment. With this structure, the input/output electrodes 6 and
7 are capacitively coupled with the inner conductors 3a and 3f,
respectively. The input/output electrode 8 is interdigitally
coupled with the inner conductors 3c and 3d through the excitation
hole 11, resulting in magnetic field coupling.</p>
    <p num="0049">In the thus constructed dielectric duplexer, the through-hole
9 having a short circuited electrode 10 formed on the inner surface
thereof intersects the excitation hole 11.</p>
    <p num="0050">With this structure, as in the first embodiment, the lowest
resonant frequency in a TE mode is shifted to a higher frequency
region, resulting in reduced spurious responses.</p>
    <p num="0051">If the input/output electrode 8 is formed on the open surface
where the open ends of the inner-conductor-containing holes 2a to
2f are formed, the excitation hole 11 may be combline-coupled with
the inner conductors 3c and 3d, resulting in magnetic field coupling.
This structure would take the same advantages as those in the first
embodiment.</p>
    <p num="0052">A dielectric duplexer shown in Figs. 9A and 9B would take the
same advantages.</p>
    <p num="0053">Fig. 9A is a perspective view of the appearance of a modified
dielectric duplexer according to the third embodiment, and Fig. 9B
is a cross-sectional view of the dielectric duplexer shown in Fig.
9A.</p>
    <p num="0054">As in the dielectric duplexer shown in Fig. 7, the dielectric
duplexer shown in Figs. 9A and 9B includes a through-hole 9 having
a short circuited electrode 10 formed on the inner surface thereof
which runs from the mounting surface of the dielectric block 1 to
the surface opposite thereto. Unlike the dielectric duplexer shown
in Fig. 7, however, the through-hole 9 does not intersect the 
excitation hole 11. The structure of the other components is the
same as that in the dielectric duplexer shown in Figs. 7 and 8A and
8B.</p>
    <p num="0055">With this structure, as in the first embodiment, the lowest
resonant frequency in a TE mode is shifted to a higher frequency
region, resulting in reduced spurious responses. Since the
through-hole 9 does not intersect the excitation hole 11, it does
not functionally affect the excitation hole 11. However, the
dielectric duplexer shown in Fig. 7 can have a narrower width than
the dielectric duplexer shown in Fig. 9 by the width of the
through-hole 9. Thus, the dielectric duplexer shown in Fig. 7 may
be more compact.</p>
    <p num="0056">The dielectric duplexer according to the third embodiment shown
in Figs. 7 to 9 may include excitation holes formed at outer positions
than the outermost inner-conductor-containing holes 2a and 2f so
as to be parallel to the outermost inner-conductor-containing holes
2a and 2f, so that a transmission signal input unit or a reception
signal output unit is externally coupled through the excitation
holes.</p>
    <p num="0057">Although the through-hole 9 has a rectangular shape in
cross-section in the first to third embodiments, the through-hole
9 is not limited to this shape. A through-hole having a circular,
elliptic, or polygonal cross section would take the same advantages.</p>
    <p num="0058">A communication apparatus according to a fourth embodiment of
the present invention is described with reference to Fig. 10.</p>
    <p num="0059">Fig. 10 is a block diagram of the communication apparatus.</p>
    <p num="0060">In Fig. 10, the communication apparatus includes a
transmission/reception antenna ANT, a duplexer DPX, band-pass
filters BPFa and BPFb, amplifier circuits AMPa and AMPb, mixers MIXa
and MIXb, an oscillator OSC, and a synthesizer SYN. An intermediate
frequency signal to be transmitted or received is indicated by IF.
The mixer MIXa modulates an intermediate frequency signal output
from the synthesizer SYN with the IF signal, and the band-pass filter
BPFa passes only the transmission frequency band signal. The
resulting signal is amplified by the amplifier circuit AMPa, and
is then transmitted from the antenna ANT via the duplexer DPX. The
amplifier circuit AMPb amplifies the signal output from the duplexer
DPX. The band-pass filter BPFb passes only the reception frequency 
band signal in the signal output from the amplifier circuit AMPb.
The frequency signal output from the band-pass filter BPFb is mixed
with a reception signal by the mixer MIXb to output an intermediate
frequency signal IF.</p>
    <p num="0061">The duplexer DPX shown in Fig. 10 may be implemented as the
dielectric duplexer having any structure as described with respect
to Figs. 1 to 9. The communication apparatus incorporating such
a compact dielectric duplexer having low spurious responses would
be compact and highly efficient with predetermined communication
performance.</p>
    <p num="0062">Although the present invention has been described in relation
to particular embodiments thereof, many other variations and
modifications and other uses will become apparent to those skilled
in the art. It is preferred, therefore, that the present invention
be limited not by the specific disclosure herein, but only by the
appended claims.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A dielectric duplexer comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a dielectric block (1);</claim-text><claim-text>a plurality of inner-conductor-containing holes (2a - 2f) formed
in the dielectric block (1), each hole having an inner conductor
(3a - 3f) formed on the inner surface thereof, the
inner-conductor-containing holes (2a - 2f) extending from one surface
to another surface opposite thereto of the dielectric block (1);</claim-text><claim-text>an outer conductor (5) and an input/output terminal (6, 7,
8) which are formed on the outer surface of the dielectric block
(1), the input/output terminal (6, 7, 8) being separated from the
outer conductor (1); and</claim-text><claim-text>at least one short circuited conductor (10) formed between
the plurality of inner-conductor-containing holes (2a - 2c) on
a transmitter side and the plurality of inner-conductor-containing
holes (2d - 2f) on a receiver side, said at least one short circuited
conductor (10) extending from one surface that is parallel to the
axes of the inner-conductor-containing holes (2a - 2f) to another
surface opposite thereto and conductively coupled to said outer
conductor (5).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A dielectric duplexer according to Claim 1, wherein said
dielectric block (1) includes an excitation hole (11) for an antenna,
and said at least one short circuited conductor (10) intersects
said excitation hole (11).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A dielectric duplexer according to claim 1 or 2, wherein
said dielectric block (1) is a substantially rectangular block.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A communication apparatus comprising a dielectric duplexer
according to any of Claims 1 to 3.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
