<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1256635-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1256635" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="25309396" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021113">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1256635-A1" status="new" fvid="23581261">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1256635</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20021113</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02253095-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02253095</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020501</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="US-85089601-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>85089601</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010508</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  10/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  10/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  10/28        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F01D   5/28        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F01D   5/28        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F02C   7/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F02C   7/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C  10/04</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zum Aufbringen von Aluminid-Beschichtungen auf selektiven Flächen von Turbinemotorteilen</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Method for applying diffusion aluminide coating on a selective area of a turbine engine component</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé pour appliquer des revêtements d'aluminium à diffuser sur des régions sélectives d'un composant de moteur à turbine</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GEN ELECTRIC</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1 River Road</street>
              <city>Schenectady, NY 12345</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>DAS NRIPENDRA NATH</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GMEREK WALTER MICHAEL JR</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HEIDORN RAYMOND WILLIAM</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>JABLONKA DAVID ANDREW</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>DAS, NRIPENDRA NATH</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GMEREK, WALTER MICHAEL, JR.</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>HEIDORN, RAYMOND WILLIAM</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>JABLONKA, DAVID ANDREW</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>DAS, NRIPENDRA NATH</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>8168 North Legare Court, Apartment 1</street>
              <city>West Chester, Ohio 45069</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>GMEREK, WALTER MICHAEL, JR.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>5677 McCarthy Court</street>
              <city>West Chester, Ohio 45069</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>HEIDORN, RAYMOND WILLIAM</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>5644 Lake Mead Drive</street>
              <city>Fairfield, Ohio 45014</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>JABLONKA, DAVID ANDREW</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>6876 Hunting Horn Court</street>
              <city>Hamilton, Ohio 45011</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Pedder, James Cuthbert</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>GE London Patent Operation, Essex House, 12/13 Essex Street</street>
              <city>London WC2R 3AA</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A method for applying diffusion aluminide coating on a selective area of a
turbine engine component and the coating produced by that method is
disclosed. A quartz infrared lamp heats only substantially the localized area
of the component to be coated, rather than the complete part. Either halide
activated or non-activated tape (20) is applied on the area to be coated and is held
in place during coating using a high temperature dimensionally stable tape
holder manufactured from graphite or ceramic. The quartz infrared lamp is
used to heat only the desired area to a coating temperature of about 1800°F.
to about 2000°F. under an inert atmosphere for about 3 to about 8 hours to
achieve the desired aluminide coating thickness. No powder masking of the
machined surface area is required. Due to the localized heating, aluminum
vapor generated from the tape will only deposit aluminide coating on the
taped area.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="76" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="83"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">The invention relates generally to components of the hot section of gas
turbine engines, and in particular, to a diffusion aluminiding process for
depositing an aluminide coating onto a selective area of a turbine component.</p>
    <p num="0002">In gas turbine engines, for example, aircraft engines, air is drawn into the front
of the engine, compressed by a shaft-mounted rotary compressor, and mixed
with fuel. The mixture is burned, and the hot exhaust gases are passed
through a turbine mounted on a shaft. The flow of gas turns the turbine,
which turns the shaft and drives the compressor. The hot exhaust gases flow
from the back of the engine, providing thrust that propels the aircraft forward.</p>
    <p num="0003">During operation of gas turbine engines, the metal parts of the engine, are in
contact with hot, corrosive gases. The metal parts require particular attention
to protect them from these combustion gases. These metallic parts include
blades and vanes used to direct the flow of the hot gases, as well as other
components such as shrouds and combustors.</p>
    <p num="0004">In order to protect the metallic parts from the hot, oxidative and corrosive
effects of the combustion gases, environmental coatings typically are applied
to the metallic parts. These environmental coats may be produced by holding
the part to be coated at temperature in an atmosphere rich in a certain
element or elements, often aluminum. These elements diffuse into the
surface of the part to form a diffusion coating, a process called chemical vapor
deposition (CVD). In one form, the environmental coat is made of a diffusion
nickel aluminide or platinum aluminide. Diffusing Al into the substrate has
also proven effective against high temperature oxidation in addition to
improving adherence of the ceramic TBC. The CVD bond coat surface forms
an aluminum oxide scale during exposure to oxygen containing atmospheres
at elevated temperatures, providing increased resistance to further high
temperature oxidation. Other well-known methods are utilized to form
diffusion aluminide coatings. While not meant to be inclusive, some other of
these methods include "over the pack" aluminizing, pack aluminizing, flash 
electroplating of nickel and platinum onto a substrate followed by application
of aluminum by one of these well-known methods. Frequently, these
environmental layers also serve as a bond coat in a thermal barrier system
that utilizes a thermal barrier coating over the diffusion aluminide layer,
thereby impeding the transfer of heat from the hot exhaust gases to the parts
by providing an insulating layer and allowing the exhaust gases to be hotter
than would otherwise be possible.</p>
    <p num="0005">Chipping of the protective coating sometimes occurs during the life of the part.
This chipping damage may be caused during machining of the aluminide
coated component, by poor handling of the component during subsequent
manufacturing processes, during routine maintenance or through the normal
operational environment of the turbine component. When repairing chipping
damage, it is not cost effective to remove the remaining undamaged coating
and re-coat the entire turbine component. Instead, localized repair of only the
damaged surface is attempted. Current practice for localized repair of
aluminide coating on damaged or selective areas of the turbine component is
exemplified by, for example, U.S. Patent Nos. 5,334,417 and 6,045,863,
involving slurry or tape processes.</p>
    <p num="0006">For example, in a proprietary commercial form presently used by the
Assignee of the present invention, a self-adhesive halide activated or non-activated
iron aluminum alloy containing about 55-57 wt. % aluminum tape or,
alternatively, a cobalt aluminum alloy containing about 50-60 wt. % aluminum
tape is placed on the selective area to be coated. The taped component is
placed inside a metal coating box or can and packed in an inert aluminide
oxide powder to hold the tape in place and mask the machined area during
the coating operation. The coating box or can is heated to between about
1800° F. and about 2000° F. under an inert (reducing) atmosphere for a time
sufficient to permit diffusion of aluminum to achieve the desired aluminide
coating thickness, typically about three to eight hours just to accomplish the
soak at the temperature to achieve a coating thickness of about 1 to about 3
mils. One cycle can take from 14-32 hours. </p>
    <p num="0007">However, built up stress from the thermal expansion mismatch between the
engine component and the inert aluminum oxide powder creates warpage or
distortion of the selectively coated engine component, making the component
unusable in the engine. The unusable component must be discarded at great
cost.</p>
    <p num="0008">What is needed are improved methods to apply diffusion aluminide coating to
a selective area of an engine component, which results in little or no warpage
or distortion of the component, hence, less waste. The present invention
fulfills this need, and further provides related advantages.</p>
    <p num="0009">In one form, the present invention provides both an improved method for
applying diffusion aluminide coating on a selective area of a turbine engine
component and the coatings produced by that method, utilizing a quartz
infrared lamp to heat only the localized area of the component to be coated,
rather than the complete part.</p>
    <p num="0010">Either halide activated or non-activated aluminum source tape is applied on
the area to be coated and is held in place during coating using a high
temperature dimensionally stable tape holder. The quartz infrared lamp is
used to heat only the selective area to a coating temperature of about 1800°
F. to about 2000° F. under an inert atmosphere for about 3 to about 8 hours to
achieve the desired aluminide coating thickness. While the soak time remains
the same to achieve a desired coating thickness, the overall cycle time is
reduced to 6 to 12 hours. The desired thickness of the coating will vary with
time, with longer times providing thicker coatings..</p>
    <p num="0011">Due to the localized heating and application, aluminum vapor generated from
the tape will only deposit aluminide coating on the taped area. As a result, no
masking of the component machined surface area adjacent to the regions
undergoing coating is required.</p>
    <p num="0012">Optionally, a thermal barrier coating (TBC) such as yttrium-stabilized zirconia
(YSZ) may be deposited over the repaired aluminide coating of the present
invention when the diffusion aluminide is part of a thermal barrier coating
system. </p>
    <p num="0013">One advantage of the present invention is that the coating produced by this
invention demonstrates a distortion-free, aluminided engine component. By
avoiding the significant warpage caused by current practice of heating the
entire component in a packed coating box, there is little to no resultant waste
from scrapped parts, with significant cost savings.</p>
    <p num="0014">Another advantage of the present invention is that there is a 65% reduction in
heat up cycle time and a 75% reduction in cool down cycle time, with resultant
cost savings. Current practice requires long heat up and cool down cycles of
generally 5-12 hours per each cycle, due to the heating up and cooling down
of a large mass comprised of aluminum oxide powder plus the entire
component.</p>
    <p num="0015">Still another advantage of the present invention is a significant labor cost
reduction. Masking of machined surfaces with aluminum oxide powder is no
longer required due to the localized heating and application of coating
material utilized by the present invention.</p>
    <p num="0016">Because masking of the component is not necessary, yet another advantage
of the present invention is that the process is more environmentally friendly
than current practice since aluminum oxide powder waste is reduced.</p>
    <p num="0017">Continuing and often interrelated improvements in processes and materials,
such as the improvements of the present invention, can provide cost
reductions and major increases in the performance of devices such as aircraft
gas turbine engines.</p>
    <p num="0018">The invention will now be described in greater detail, by way of example, with
reference to the drawings, in which:-
<sl><li>Figure 1 is a representative view of a turbine vane with chipping damage.</li><li>Figure 2 is a representative view of the tape applied to the vane.</li><li>Figure 3 is a representative view of the tape holder positioned on the vane. </li><li>Figure 4 is a representative view of an alternate embodiment depicting
thermocouples attached to the vane.</li><li>Figure 5 is a photomicrograph of the repaired selective area of Example 1.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0019">Although the method of repair and the coating produced by the method of the
present invention are generally applicable to components that operate within
environments characterized by relatively high temperatures, and are therefore
subject to severe thermal stresses and thermal cycling, the present invention
is not limited to these "hot section" components of a jet turbine engine.</p>
    <p num="0020">Examples of such hot section components include the high and low-pressure
turbine nozzles and blades, shrouds, vanes, combustor liners and augmentor
hardware of gas turbine engines. Substrate materials often used in these
turbine parts or airfoils for aircraft engines and power generation equipment
may include nickel, cobalt, or iron based superalloys. The alloys may be cast
or wrought superalloys. Examples of such substrates are GTD-111, GTD-222,
René 80, René 41, René 125, René 77, René N4, René N5, René N6,
4<sup>th</sup> generation single crystal superalloy - MX-4, Hastalloy X, and cobalt-based
HS-188. These superalloys, although developed for high temperature
applications, still require protection resulting from environmental and/or
thermal deterioration.</p>
    <p num="0021">Referring now to the figures, where like parts have the same numbers, in
accordance with a preferred embodiment of the invention, there is shown in
Fig. 1 a jet turbine engine component, for example, a jet turbine vane 4,
having a selective area of imperfection in the environmental coating, for
example, a chipped region 6 in which substrate metal is exposed. The
environmental coating may be, for example, a diffusion aluminide applied for
environmental coating, for example, a chemical vapor deposition aluminide
coating, well known in the art.</p>
    <p num="0022">The present invention allows for the "spot" repair of the selective area of
imperfection in the environmental coating without the significant warpage and
distortion problems associated with current practice. Pre-treatment of the 
selective area is to the extent that it is free of dirt, grease, and other like
contaminants must be removed.</p>
    <p num="0023">As shown in Fig. 2, a metal source coating tape 20 is positioned using known
methods on the vane 4 to cover the chipped region 6. The metal source
coating tape 20 may be, for example, any of the current practice metal source
coating tapes, such as CODAL tape, manufactured by the Assignee of the
present invention. The tape 20 may contain, for example, halide activated or
non-activated iron aluminum alloy containing about 55-57 wt. % aluminum or,
alternatively, a cobalt aluminum alloy containing about 50-60 wt. % aluminum.
All that is required, however, is that the tape 20 contain a metallic source that
can serve as a reservoir of replacement material. The metal source may be,
for example, aluminum, chromium, aluminum chromium alloy, silicon
aluminum alloy, titanium aluminum alloy, vanadium, vanadium aluminum
alloy, cobalt aluminum and combinations thereof. The metal source coating
tape 20 may optionally contain a halide carrier compound, such as, for
example, aluminum fluoride, aluminum chloride, ammonium fluoride,
ammonium chloride, potassium fluoride, potassium bromide and mixtures
thereof. Addition of a halide carrier compound permits a halogen to react with
the metal source at elevated temperatures to carry the metal ions to the
surface of the component where they react with the substrate, the process of
which is well known.</p>
    <p num="0024">Optionally, to permit ease in placement and initial retention of the metal
source coating tape 20 over the imperfection, the metal source coating tape
20 is self-adhering. As shown in Fig. 3, a high temperature dimensionally
stable tape holder 30 is placed against the metal source coating tape 20 to
maintain the metal source coating tape 20 in contact with the vane 4. The
tape holder 30 is mechanically attached to the vane 4, for example, by nonreactive
wires 32 which circumscribe both the vane 4 and the tape holder 30,
or the tape holder may be attached with high temperature dimensionally
stable clips to maintain the tape holder 30 in position on the vane 4. The tape
holder 30 is required even though a self-adhesive metal source coating tape
20 is used, because as the component and tape 20 are brought to 
temperature, as described below, the adhesive binder which typically is an
organic material, is burned off, requiring mechanical attachment to maintain
the metal source contained within the tape 20 in contact with the component.</p>
    <p num="0025">The high temperature dimensionally stable wire 32, clips and tape holder 30
are fabricated from a material that will withstand temperatures above about
2000°F. without deforming, for example, graphite, ceramic, carbon-carbon-composites,
ceramic-matrix composites and combinations thereof. Optionally,
the high temperature dimensionally stable tape holder 30 further includes a
high temperature dimensionally stable cushioning material 34 intermediate the
tape holder 30 and the metal source coating tape 20, for example, a felt
material of, for example, graphite, ceramic, carbon-carbon composite, ceramic
matrix composite and combinations thereof. The cushioning material 34
compresses upon initial placement in contact with the metal source coating
tape 20, subsequently expanding to fill the void created as the adhesive
binder material is burned off.</p>
    <p num="0026">The high temperature dimensionally stable tape holder 30 may be any shape
that will maintain the metal source tape 20 in contact with the chipped region
6, as it is brought to and maintained at temperature. In a preferred
embodiment, the shape of the inner surface (not shown) of the tape holder 30
substantially mirrors the selective area of the region undergoing repair.</p>
    <p num="0027">A heat source (not shown), for example, a quartz infrared lamp, is positioned
to heat substantially only the selective area of the component to an effective
temperature for an effective amount of time under an inert atmosphere to
achieve the desired metal coating thickness. Optionally, as shown in Fig. 4,
one or more thermocouples 40 may be placed adjacent to the chipping
damage 6 to monitor the coating temperature. The thermocouples 40, when
used in conjunction with a controller, can precisely control the coating
temperature.</p>
    <p num="0028">In the preferred embodiment, the selective area is heated in an inert
atmosphere to a temperature of about 1800° F. to about 2000° F. for about 3
to about 8 hours to achieve a coating thickness of about 1 mil to about 3 mil. </p>
    <p num="0029">The inert atmosphere is, for example, argon or hydrogen but can be a non-oxidizing
atmosphere such as nitrogen. Because only the substantially
selective and localized area of the component is in contact with a metallic
source and is heated to a sufficiently elevated temperature, metal vapor, for
example, aluminum vapor, generated from the tape will only deposit metal, for
example, aluminide coating, on the taped area. Powder masking of the
machined surface of the component, as required in current practice, is
therefore not necessary, as no material capable of forming a coating is
present in any adjacent areas.</p>
    <p num="0030">The present method of applying a diffusion coating on a selective area of a
turbine engine component is also part of a novel jet turbine engine component
repair system whereby a thermal barrier coating (TBC) (not shown) is applied
to the selective area following the application of the diffusion coating of the
present invention. The TBC such as, for example, yttrium-stabilized zirconia
(YSZ) may be deposited over the repaired bond coat of the present invention
using techniques well known in the art.</p>
    <p num="0031">The following example demonstrates the present method of applying a
diffusion coating on a selective area of a turbine engine component:</p>
    <heading>EXAMPLE 1</heading>
    <p num="0032">A coated scrap aircraft engine vane segment manufactured from René 77
nickel-based superalloy was coated and the coating was intentionally
damaged. Aluminide coating was removed from a small area of the convex
side trailing edge of the airfoil exposing substrate metal to simulate chipping.
Halide activated self-adhesive CODAL tape was applied to the small area of
exposed substrate and held in place using a graphite tape holder and graphite
felt. Two thermocouples were placed adjacent to the exposed area of
substrate to be repaired for monitoring and to precisely control the coating
temperature in combination with a controller.</p>
    <p num="0033">The taped component was placed inside an argon atmosphere chamber and
the small area having the exposed substrate was heated to 1925° F. +/- 25° F. 
temperature using a 12,000 watt quartz lamp for four hours. The lamp was
cycled by the controller to maintain temperature within the temperature range.</p>
    <p num="0034">Inspection of the repaired vane segment showed no sign of distortion or
warpage of the component. Metallographic evaluation of the area showed
evidence of achieving the desired aluminide thickness of about 2 mil, see Fig.
5. The regions adjacent the small area were substantially unaffected.</p>
    <p num="0035">For the sake of good order, various aspects of the invention are set out in the
following clauses:-:
<sl><li>1. A method of applying a diffusion metal coating to a selective area of a
turbine engine component having a deficiency of metal coating comprising the
steps of:
<sl><li>positioning a metal source coating tape (20) in contact with the
selective area;</li><li>holding the coating tape (20) in contact with the selective area using a
tape holder (30) that is stable at high temperatures; and</li><li>heating the selective area to an effective temperature for an effective
amount of time under an inert atmosphere to form a metal coating of
predetermined thickness on the selective area.</li></sl></li><li>2. The method of clause 1 wherein step of positioning the metal source
coating tape (20) comprises positioning a metal source selected from the
group consisting of aluminum, chromium, aluminum chromium alloy, silicon
aluminum alloy, titanium aluminum alloy, vanadium, vanadium aluminum
alloy, cobalt aluminum and combinations thereof.</li><li>3. The method of clause 2 wherein the step of positioning the metal
source coating tape (20) further includes positioning a metal source coating
tape (20) that includes an activator compound.</li><li>4. The method of clause 3 wherein the activator compound includes a
halide. </li><li>5. The method of clause 4 wherein the carrier compound that includes
halide is selected from the group consisting of aluminum fluoride, aluminum
chloride, ammonium chloride, ammonium fluoride, potassium fluoride,
potassium bromide and mixtures thereof.</li><li>6. The method of clause 1 wherein the step of holding metal source
coating tape (20) in contact is accomplished with a self-adhering tape.</li><li>7. The method of clause 1 wherein the step of holding the coating tape
high temperature dimensionally stable tape holder (30) is fabricated from a
material selected from the group consisting of graphite, ceramic, carbon-carbon
composite, ceramic matrix composite and combinations thereof.</li><li>8. The method of clause 1 wherein an inner surface of the high
temperature dimensionally stable tape holder (30) substantially mirrors the
selective area.</li><li>9. The method of clause 1 wherein the high temperature dimensionally
stable tape holder (30) includes a cushioning material (34) intermediate the
tape holder (30) and the metal source coating tape (20).</li><li>10. The method of clause 8 wherein the cushioning material (34) is a felt
material selected from the group consisting of graphite, ceramic and
combinations thereof.</li><li>11. The method of clause 1 further including the step of fixing the high
temperature dimensionally stable tape holder (30) to the component.</li><li>12. The method of clause 10 wherein the method of fixing the high
temperature dimensionally stable tape holder (30) is mechanical.</li><li>13. The method of clause 11 wherein the mechanical method of fixing the
high temperature dimensionally stable tape holder (30) is selected from the
group consisting of wiring and clipping.</li><li>14. The method of clause 1 wherein the substantially selective area is
heated by a quartz infrared lamp. </li><li>15. The method of clause 1 further including the act of (step of) placing one
or more thermocouples (40) adjacent to the selective area to monitor and
precisely control the effective temperature.</li><li>16. The method of clause 1 wherein the effective temperature is about
1800° F. to about 2000° F.</li><li>17. The method of clause 1 wherein the effective amount of time is about 3
hours to about 8 hours.</li><li>18. The method of clause 1 wherein the inert atmosphere is selected from
the group consisting of argon and hydrogen.</li><li>19. The method of clause 1 wherein the predetermined metal coating
thickness is about 1 mil to about 3 mil.</li><li>20. The diffusion metal coating produce by the method of clause 1.</li><li>21. The diffusion metal coating of clause 19 wherein the coating is an
aluminide coating.</li><li>22. A turbine engine component repair system comprising the steps of:
<sl><li>selecting a turbine engine component, the component having a
selective area to be repaired;</li><li>positioning a metal source coating tape (20) on the selective area;</li><li>holding the coating tape (20) in place with a high temperature
dimensionally stable tape holder (30);</li><li>heating substantially only the selective area to an effective temperature
for an effective amount of time under an inert atmosphere to achieve a metal
coating of a predetermined thickness; and</li><li>applying a thermal barrier coating of predetermined thickness to the
metal coating.</li></sl></li><li>23. The turbine engine component repair system produced by the method of
clause 21.</li></sl></p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A method of applying a diffusion metal coating to a selective area of a
turbine engine component having a deficiency of metal coating comprising the
steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>positioning a metal source coating tape (20) in contact with the selective area;
holding the coating tape (20) in contact with the selective area using a tape
holder (30) that is stable at high temperatures; and</claim-text><claim-text>heating the selective area to an effective temperature for an effective amount
of time under an inert atmosphere to form a metal coating of predetermined
thickness on the selective area.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The method of claim 1 wherein step of positioning the metal source
coating tape (20) comprises positioning a metal source selected from the
group consisting of aluminum, chromium, aluminum chromium alloy, silicon
aluminum alloy, titanium aluminum alloy, vanadium, vanadium aluminum
alloy, cobalt aluminum and combinations thereof.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The method of claim 2 wherein the step of positioning the metal source
coating tape (20) further includes positioning a metal source coating tape (20)
that includes an activator compound.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The method of claim 3 wherein the activator compound includes a
halide.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The method of claim 4 wherein the carrier compound that includes
halide is selected from the group consisting of aluminum fluoride, aluminum
chloride, ammonium chloride, ammonium fluoride, potassium fluoride,
potassium bromide and mixtures thereof.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>The method of any preceding claim wherein the step of holding metal
source coating tape (20) in contact is accomplished with a self-adhering tape.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>The method of any preceding claim wherein the step of holding the
coating tape high temperature dimensionally stable tape holder (30) is
fabricated from a material selected from the group consisting of graphite,
ceramic, carbon-carbon composite, ceramic matrix composite and
combinations thereof.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The method of any preceding claim wherein an inner surface of the
high temperature dimensionally stable tape holder (30) substantially mirrors
the selective area.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>The method of any preceding claim wherein the high temperature
dimensionally stable tape holder (30) includes a cushioning material (34)
intermediate the tape holder (30) and the metal source coating tape (20).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>A turbine engine component repair system comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>selecting a turbine engine component, the component having a
selective area to be repaired;</claim-text><claim-text>positioning a metal source coating tape (20) on the selective area;</claim-text><claim-text>holding the coating tape (20) in place with a high temperature
dimensionally stable tape holder (30);</claim-text><claim-text>heating substantially only the selective area to an effective temperature
for an effective amount of time under an inert atmosphere to achieve a metal
coating of a predetermined thickness; and</claim-text><claim-text>applying a thermal barrier coating of predetermined thickness to the
metal coating.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
