<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1252859-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1252859" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="27214410" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021030">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1252859-A2" status="new" fvid="23587767">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1252859</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021030</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02009596-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02009596</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020426</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="DE-10120717-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>DE</country>
          <doc-number>10120717</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010427</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
      <priority-claim ucid="US-31230601-P" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>31230601</doc-number>
          <kind>P</kind>
          <date>20010814</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
      <priority-claim ucid="US-32790801-P" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>32790801</doc-number>
          <kind>P</kind>
          <date>20011009</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61B   1/24        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">A61B   1/24        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61B   1/24B</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Dentalkamera mit einem Mundstück</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Dental camera with mouthpiece</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Caméra à usage dentaire avec un embout buccal</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>IVOCLAR VIVADENT AG</name>
            <address>
              <country>LI</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>FIRMA IVOCLAR VIVADENT AG</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Firma Ivoclar Vivadent AG</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Bendererstrasse 2</street>
              <city>9494 Schaan</city>
              <country>LI</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KERSCHBAUMER HARALD</name>
            <address>
              <country>AT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>POKORNY WALTER</name>
            <address>
              <country>AT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>PYE GRAHAM</name>
            <address>
              <country>BE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ROHNER GOTTFRIED</name>
            <address>
              <country>CH</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KERSCHBAUMER, HARALD</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>POKORNY, WALTER</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>PYE, GRAHAM</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ROHNER, GOTTFRIED</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>KERSCHBAUMER, HARALD</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Gugger-Nussbaum, 35</street>
              <city>6833 Klaus</city>
              <country>AT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>POKORNY, WALTER</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Faschinastrasse 52</street>
              <city>6712 Thüringen</city>
              <country>AT</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>PYE, GRAHAM</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Oude Postbaan 46</street>
              <city>3600 Genk</city>
              <country>BE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>ROHNER, GOTTFRIED</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Forststrasse 6</street>
              <city>9450 Altstätten</city>
              <country>CH</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Baronetzky, Klaus, Dipl.-Ing.</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Splanemann Reitzner Baronetzky Westendorp Patentanwälte Rumfordstrasse 7</street>
              <city>80469 München</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A dental camera (10) and a mouthpiece attachment (12) therefor. The camera
(10) has a light source (42) and a light receiving element (44) configured for receiving
reflected light and producing an image (59) based on the received light. The mouthpiece
(12) is mountable to the housing (50) of the camera (10) and is configured for contacting a
patient's mouth for positioning the camera (10) with respect to at least a portion of the
mouth. The mouthpiece (12) has a light channel associated with the light source (42) for
permitting the emitted light to reflect off a tooth in a patient's mouth and permitting the
reflected light travel into the receiving element (44). A wing (22, 24) extends radially from
the light channel (20) and configured and dimensioned for placement between a lip and
teeth of a patient for substantially blocking light from entering the light channel from
outside the wing (22, 24). A display (18) on the housing (50) is associated with the
receiving element (44) for displaying the image (59). A sound receiving element (64A) on
the housing (50) allows a dentist to record voice comments and store these in connection
with the images (59).
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="75" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="71"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a dental camera and a mouthpiece therefor.
More specifically, the invention relates to a dental camera and a mouthpiece configured for
blocking light from entering the camera from outside of a patient's mouth.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0002">A conventional dental camera for determining the color of teeth is known
from EP-A1-376 647. In a conventional device of this type, a light source irradiates an
object such as, for example, a tooth. The reflected light is captured or sensed by an optic
capture device and is conducted to a reflected light receipt element. The reflected light
receipt element is, in this conventional arrangement, configured as a spectrometer. With
this arrangement, it is possible to specify or evaluate the color of an object.</p>
    <p num="0003">This conventional arrangement relies upon a capture or sensing of light
which is reflected at an angle from the surface of an object. This conventional arrangement
is, for all practical purposes, operable only to sense scattered light so that the actual
effective rate of light capture or sensing is substantially low.</p>
    <p num="0004">A diagnostic device for use in the dental field, disclosed in DE-OS 33 45
465, permits a co-axial capture or sensing of the light reflected from a tooth. In this
conventional arrangement, a light guide rod is provided which is overlaid by two light guide
elements. The reflected light is guided to a photo resistor, which registers the brightness of
the reflected light. By means of a filter, the capture or sensing of the reflected light can be
adjusted to the respective spectrum which is desired to be observed. In this conventional
arrangement, a determination or evaluation of the grade of reflection from the teeth is
possible; however, it is, for substantially all practical purposes, not possible to effect a color
comparison of a tooth in order to thereby specify a suitable replacement tooth.</p>
    <p num="0005">In connection with evaluation of color, it is especially important that the
lighting situation be reliably reproducible. The light source comprises a predetermined
emission spectrum and the reflected light receipt element that is, for example, a
CCD-cell-operates at a predetermined spectral sensitivity. In connection with avoiding a
false color sensing, it has become known to undertake a so-called white color comparison.
A unit comprising a light source and a reflected light receipt element can be calibrated by 
use of such a white color comparison. The calibration is, of course, relevant for the
respective unit only under the same lighting circumstances. If, for example, a bulb is used
as a light source and a bulb exchange of the existing bulb for another bulb is necessary, a
renewed or refreshed white color comparison must be undertaken. Also, in connection with
such white color comparisons, the conventional diagnosis devices reveal only partial color
deviations.</p>
    <p num="0006">U.S. Patent No. 6,246,471 teaches a unit for measuring color. The unit has a
display that displays data on color and optical properties or status or other information.</p>
    <p num="0007">There is a need for a dental camera that facilitates the process of producing
images of a portion of a patient's mouth, particularly for analyzing the color of teeth.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0008">The present invention offers a solution to the challenge of providing a dental
camera which makes possible a reliable and precise color evaluation and, especially, is
operable independent of the hand-held position of the dental camera.</p>
    <p num="0009">In a preferred embodiment, a mouthpiece attachment for a dental camera
includes a body having a light channel associated with the camera for permitting passage of
light therethrough to the camera. A first attachment portion of the mouthpiece body is
configured for attaching to a second attachment portion of the dental camera with the light
channel positioned to permit the passage of light to a light-receiving portion of the camera.
The camera is configured, dimensioned, and has a weight for enabling handheld operation
with a single hand for producing images of the patient's teeth.</p>
    <p num="0010">A wing preferably extends radially from the light channel and is configured
and dimensioned for placement between a lip and teeth of a patient for substantially
blocking light from entering the light channel from outside the wing when the mouthpiece
is attached to the camera. The preferred wing extends radially from the light channel in a
direction along the separation between the teeth of the upper and lower jaws of the patient
and also radially from the light channel in a direction transverse to the separation between
the teeth of the upper and lower jaws of the patient, most preferably extending radially
substantially all around the light channel. This wing also has a distal surface that is
substantially concave for placement against the teeth.</p>
    <p num="0011">The attachment portion of one embodiment is substantially stiffer than the
wing. A reference sample element is preferably provided in the mouthpiece and is 
configured for directing, and preferably reflecting, light with predetermined qualities to the
receiving element for calibrating the camera and comparison to the color being analyzed in
the patient's mouth. A blocking member of the mouthpiece is associated with the camera
for substantially blocking entry of light between the camera and light channel from outside
the camera, light channel, and patient's mouth, and the first attachment portion preferably
comprises the blocking member.</p>
    <p num="0012">A bite projection portion of the mouthpiece body extends adjacent to and
from the wing of the preferred embodiment and is configured and dimensioned for biting by
the patient to stabilize and position the camera. Preferably this bite projection portion
extends on each lateral side of the light channel. The bite projection portion can be
configured and dimensioned for positioning the light channel and teeth with respect to each
other for producing images of the teeth based on the light passed through the light channel
to the receiving portion.</p>
    <p num="0013">A light receiving element of the preferred camera is configured for receiving
light and producing an image base on the received light. A second attachment portion of
the camera is configured for attaching to the first attachment portion for positioning the
mouthpiece with respect to the receiving element for permitting the passage of light through
the light channel to the receiving element. The preferred dental camera also has a light
source, preferably a white light, configured and disposed for emitting light through the light
channel for reflecting off a tooth of the patient and back through the light channel to the
receiving element.</p>
    <p num="0014">In the preferred embodiment, the light channel defines an opening extending
through the channel. The width of the light channel is sufficient for allowing passage of
sufficient light therethrough to the receiving element reflected from at least two teeth of the
patient to form an image of the at least two teeth.</p>
    <p num="0015">The preferred camera includes an image transfer member for transferring the
image to a color analyzer for determining the color of the portion of the patient's mouth.
Also, the camera may have color analyzing electronics mounted to the camera housing and
connected to the receiving element for receiving the image and configured for determining
the color of the portion of the patient's mouth. A processor and associated input keys for
operating the camera are also mounted to the preferred housing.</p>
    <p num="0016">The preferred embodiment also includes a display mounted to the housing
and associated with the receiving element for displaying the image. The display can be 
movably mounted to the housing for tilting to adjust an angle between the light channel and
the display. The display is preferably mounted to the housing in a position in which the
image on the display is viewable from a side of the housing opposite from the light channel.</p>
    <p num="0017">In another embodiment of the dental camera, the housing has a first
elongated portion and an elongated handle connected to the elongated portion at an angle
thereto, with the mouthpiece mounted at an end of the first elongated portion. The display
of this embodiment is preferably mounted at an end of the elongated portion opposite from
the mouthpiece.</p>
    <p num="0018">The dental camera also preferably has a sound receiving element configured
for receiving sound for storing in association with the image. A storage medium is
preferably mounted to the housing and connected with the light and sound receiving
elements for recording image and sounds in association with each other.</p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0019">Further details, advantages, and features of the dental camera of the present
invention are provided in the hereinafter following description of one embodiment of the
dental camera taken in connection with the figures of the drawings, in which:
<sl><li>Fig. 1 is a perspective view of an embodiment of a dental camera constructed
according to the present invention;</li><li>Fig. 2 is a perspective view of a mouthpiece thereof;</li><li>Fig. 3 is a unit of the camera with a light source and a reflected light receipt
element;</li><li>Fig. 4 is a perspective view of another embodiment of a dental camera with a
tiltable display;</li><li>Figs. 5 and 6 are rear and rear perspective views of another embodiment of a
dental camera with input keys; and</li><li>Figs. 7 and 8 are rear and side views of another embodiment of a dental
camera with a handle that extends at an angle to the main camera body.</li></sl></p>
    <heading>
      <b>
        <u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</u>
      </b>
    </heading>
    <p num="0020">The dental camera of the present invention permits, in a surprising manner,
the possibility to reliably determine, with simple means, the color trueness of an object. In
accordance with the present invention, a mouthpiece is provided which, in the conventional 
manner of a mouthpiece, permits the disposal thereof in the space between the lips of a
patient and, in this manner, ensures the blocking off of undesired light which is different
than the light specified for the operation. In contrast, undesired outside light typically
enters into and irradiates a mouth region of a patient if an annular pipe or conduit passes
through the space between the patient's lips for the reason that a complete sealing around
the space between the lips is not possible. In accordance with the present invention, it is
provided that the light solely falls upon the reflected light receipt element; however, it is
also preferably provided that only light from the light source passed through the mouthpiece
falls upon the tooth so that a false reading corrupted by undesired outside light will not
occur.</p>
    <p num="0021">In a particularly advantageous embodiment of the dental camera of the
present invention, the mouthpiece operates also to provide reference points for the
orientation of the dental camera relative to the tooth of interest. These reference points
function at the same time as spacer or standoff distance fixing elements so that the dental
camera is always centered and fixedly positioned at the same uniform standoff distance
from the tooth surface. The analysis of front teeth by the camera at a fixed and centered
uniformed standoff distance is possible without additional measures by the provision of bite
projections which extend from side wings of the mouthpiece to the teeth and are each
horizontally oriented. Preferably, the dental camera includes a flat display screen for
permitting the exact positioning of the camera in the horizontal direction which thus permits
the immediate recognition or identification of the tooth which is to be evaluated.</p>
    <p num="0022">Preferably, a CCD sensor or other suitable sensor is provided for receipt of
the picture, whereby the selected reflected light receipt element is characterized by a good
resolution of the captured picture. The dental camera also operates, in this connection, to
intermediately store the received picture or, in accordance with another configuration of the
inventive dental camera, to immediately transfer the received picture via an interface, which
is connected in either a wireless manner or a wired manner, to a further location for
evaluation of and follow up work on the picture.</p>
    <p num="0023">Preferably, the mouthpiece includes a flat right-angled opening which is
dimensioned such that it permits the simultaneous evaluation of at least two teeth. The light
source is preferably integrated into the dental camera and its emission of light follows in a
substantially co-axial manner with the receipt of reflective light through the opening in the 
mouthpiece so that the creation of shadows is prevented. A conventional polarization filter
can be provided to shut out or preclude undesirable reflections.</p>
    <p num="0024">Also, while it is possible to provide for the transfer or through passage of
light through the mouthpiece via a light guide element, it is preferable to provide solely one
open channel through which the light passes. Preferably, the reflected light receipt element
is then blocked off by conventional black side walls so that no immediate or direct
irradiation of the reflected light receipt element by the light from the light source can occur.
It is also possible to couple the light source to a light guide element and to undertake the
light irradiation of the object to be evaluated - that is, for example, the tooth - in a direct
manner relative to this object so that special measures for blocking off the reflected light
receipt element against false light are not necessary.</p>
    <p num="0025">The outer configuration of the mouthpiece in the region of the lip gap is
preferably also of a flat right-angled geometry with rounded-off comers. Also, if this outer
configuration does not fully permit a complete sealing off from the lips, the penetration of
false light still need not be feared as the opened area is covered by the side wings of the
mouthpiece which each extend to respective sides of the mouthpiece opening.</p>
    <p num="0026">The mouthpiece can be comprised of any suitable desired material such as,
for example, plastic or polymeric material, whereby a black color or, at least, a non-light
transmitting color, is preferred. The mouthpiece is, for hygienic reasons at least, preferably
disposable and is mountable via a coupling to the dental camera. The inner radii of the
mouthpiece are configured to be relatively large so that a cleaning of the mouthpiece is
relatively easy.</p>
    <p num="0027">As explained above, a color reference sample is preferably integrated into
the mouthpiece by which a color evaluation of the tooth with the camera can be conducted
such that a calibration of the camera is possible. The color evaluation follows after the
camera is focused on the row of teeth following the positioning of the mouthpiece in the
mouth of the patient, with the assistance of the bite projections or other distance standoff
fixing elements. Preferably, the mouthpiece is comprised of at least two plastic materials
having differing hardness or differing elastic properties in order to ensure an optimal
disposal or mounting of the mouthpiece on the teeth structure and relative to the gums. As
suitable material, rubber, silicone, or other plastic materials having a hardness up to that of
elastic polymeric materials can be considered. </p>
    <p num="0028">As seen in Fig. 1, a dental camera 10 of the present invention includes a
mouthpiece 12 which extends forward at a transverse orientation from a front side of the
dental camera. In this connection, a attachment coupling 14 is provided, which is encircled
by a coupling sleeve 16 of the mouthpiece 12 in a light-sealing manner and is removable
therefrom. The preferred camera is configured and dimensioned and is sufficiently light to
permit handheld operation of the camera, preferably with a single hand, for taking pictures
of teeth of a patient.</p>
    <p num="0029">The dental camera 10, comprises an overall flat right-angled configuration
with rounded-off corners. On the back of the dental camera, which is the upper side and
turned toward the dentist or dental technician during operation, a display screen 18 is
provided which displays the just received picture. The display screen 18 is preferably
configured as a commercially available liquid crystal display, although other types of
displays may be used. The preferred display 18 includes a color display screen, which in
the embodiment shown s fixed to the camera housing 50.</p>
    <p num="0030">The dental camera 10 includes a reflected light receipt element as well as a
light source, as shown in Fig. 3. Furthermore, the dental camera 10 includes a connection
for the transfer of the received pictures in data form to a computer which can be configured
for the evaluation of, and the follow up work on, the pictures. Additionally, the dental
camera includes a suitable voltage supply such as, for example, a battery or an accumulator,
so that a cordless operation of the camera is also possible and the hand deployment of the
camera is facilitated.</p>
    <p num="0031">In the embodiment of the dental camera 52 shown in Fig. 4, the display
screen 18 is pivotably mounted so that the display screen can be tilted to accommodate the
viewing angle of the operator. In Fig. 4, the display is pivotable about an axis that is
transverse to the longitudinal length of the housing 50, but in other embodiments, the
display is pivotable with respect to the housing about one or more axes that may be
different than the one shown in Fig. 4.</p>
    <p num="0032">While the configuration of the embodiment of the dental camera 10 shown in
Fig. 1 comprises a right-angled orientation of the coupling 14 relative to the camera, it is to
be understood that other suitable configurations are possible. For example, it is possible to
select the angled orientation of the coupling 14 relative to the balance of the dental camera
10 or to the housing 50 such that the coupling 14 extends at a non-right angle to the
longitudinal extension of the main body of the dental camera 10. In a further modification 
of the one embodiment of the dental camera, it is provided that the position of the coupling
14 relative to the main body of the dental camera 10 can be adjusted.</p>
    <p num="0033">The body of the dental camera 10 supports the mouthpiece 12 in a manner
such that the mouthpiece 12 can be removed therefrom only by the application of a
considerable force such as, for example, a force of 100 newtons. In this manner, it is
ensured that the mouthpiece 12 cannot inadvertently be detached from the camera body
while in the mouth of a patient. The attachment coupling 14 of the housing 50 and the
coupling sleeve 16 of the mouthpiece 12 preferably have corresponding shapes and attach
together with a press-fit, where at least one of the coupling 14 and coupling sleeve 16 is
resiliently deformable and has a blocking member to block light from entering from outside
the housing 50 or mouthpiece 12. Preferably, the coupling sleeve 16 is resiliently stretched
about the coupling 14 when the mouthpiece 12 is attached to the housing 15.</p>
    <p num="0034">The coupling 14 has a substantially large inner diameter or cross-section. In
contrast thereto, the mouthpiece 12 tapers down in the area of the lips to form a lip through
passage channel 20. In this area, the outer diameter or cross-sectional dimension is
preferably substantially flat and right-angled, with curved edges, and is approximately 1
centimeter in height. The mouthpiece 12 preferably includes two side wings 22 and 24
extending transversely and radially from the channel 20 in a curved manner, following the
tooth curvature of the patient.</p>
    <p num="0035">Referring to Fig. 1, the mouthpiece 12 is configured and has a stiffness for
positioning the object location, where the teeth to be imaged are located during imaging, at
a proper focal length for the dental camera. The camera preferably has adjustable focusing
lenses that can focus on the teeth within a range of object locations. The side wings 22,24
are, however, substantially more flexible and softer than the middle region of the
mouthpiece and the channel portion 20. The side wings 22,24 extend in a rounded-off
manner with rounded edges so that the danger of injury to a patient is exceptionally low.
The mouthpiece 12 is preferably formed of a soft rubber or other suitable materials.</p>
    <p num="0036">Referring to Fig. 2, the mouthpiece 12 includes an opening 26 which extends
into the middle region 28 of the mouthpiece 12. The opening 26 is, in correspondence with
the configuration of the lip through passage channel 20, configured in a fat right-angled
configuration with rounded-off comers. The channel 20 is configured and dimensioned for
a human patient's lips to fit comfortably around the channel 20 with the patient's mouth
substantially closed. </p>
    <p num="0037">As can be seen in Fig. 2, each of the side wings 22,24, on each lateral side of
the channel 20, is provided with a bite projection 30,32, respectively. In this manner, a firm
fixing of the position of the mouthpiece 12 and consequently of the dental camera 10 can be
effected without further measures. The bite projections 30,32 also act as spacers and have a
thickness and stiffness selected to space the teeth as desired. The bite projections 30,32
preferably extend from and adjacent the wings 22,24 and are configured and dimensioned
so the patient can bite on them to stabilize and position the camera in a proper position for
taking a picture of the desired teeth. In the preferred embodiment, the bite projections
30,32 are disposed at a height, with respect to the patient's mouth while bitten by the patient
during use, substantially centered with respect to the channel 20. In an alternative
embodiment, the bite projections are disposed off center, preferably both towards the top of
the channel with respect to the center of the channel, or both towards the bottom of the
channel. Other arrangements and numbers of bite projections can also be provided to
change the desired position of the camera and channel with respect to the teeth, for example
to take pictures of only the upper or lower teeth or of other parts of the mouth.</p>
    <p num="0038">In the embodiment of Figs. 1-3, the upper as well as the lower front teeth can
be irradiated and the light reflected thereby can be received by the dental camera 10 in that
the bite projections 30,32 are each arranged approximately in the vertical middle and the
receipt field as explained above. The thickness and stiffness of the bite projections 30,32 is
selected to properly position the camera. In this embodiment, at least two teeth, and more
preferably at least four teeth, can be simultaneously irradiated, imaged, and evaluated, and it
is possible to obtain a picture image of the irradiated teeth, which is accommodated to the
desired color specification requirements. More than half of each of the imaged teeth is
preferably imaged, and more preferably each of these teeth is imaged in their entirety.</p>
    <p num="0039">The middle region 28 of the mouthpiece 12 includes a receipt slot for
mounting a reference sample element 33 to the dental camera which is immediately
neighboring the tooth to be evaluated. In this manner, a direct color comparison is possible
between the teeth and the sample element 33. The sample element 33 can also be used for
calibrating the receiving element as the sample element can be of a predetermined color.
The preferred sample element is white, and is a different color than the part of the
mouthpiece 12 and remainder of the camera 10 that is visible by the receiving element. The
sample element 13 is also preferably mounted generally transversely to the axis of the light
channel 20. </p>
    <p num="0040">In the illustrated this embodiment of the dental camera of the present
invention, the opening 26 is configured as a through passage. It is to be understood that,
without the provision of any further means, it is possible to provide a protection screen in
order to protect the reflected light receipt element shown in Fig. 3, such as from items from
the patient's mouth. Also, in any desired suitable manner, the receipt optics can be
provided, for example, through the opening 26 or by additional lenses or the like. It is also
possible to connect a light guide element or a light guide rod to the reflected light receipt
element.</p>
    <p num="0041">As shown in Fig. 3, an arrangement for receipt and production of the light is
preferably comprised of eight light diodes or laser diodes 40, which collectively form a
light source 42 that is arranged preferably in an annular manner around a reflected light
receipt element 44. The light source 42 and the reflected light receipt element 44 are
mounted on a base unit 46 in a fixed relative position to each other. By means of the
annular arrangement of the light diodes 40, a shadow-free illumination of the area to be
evaluated is possible.</p>
    <p num="0042">It is to be understood that the light source can be configured in any desired
suitable manner. For example, diodes producing lights of three colors can be used, such as
green, blue, and red light diodes distributed in a uniform manner around the receiving
elements of the light receipt element 44 in order to emit a white light.</p>
    <p num="0043">The light receipt element 44 preferably includes a CCD element for acquiring
an image based on the reflected light that it receives. Electronics in the housing 50 control
the light source 42, as well as the CCD and operation of the display 18 and of an image
storage medium, which is preferably contained within the housing.</p>
    <p num="0044">It is also possible to use white light diodes or other different suitable light
sources. A small tube or conduit 48 extends around the reflected light receipt element 44
and extends in a forward manner to the coupling 14, past the diodes 40 of the light source,
and the coupling member and walls surrounding the light source and light receipt elements
are preferably configured for substantially preventing light from reaching the receipt
element that has not been reflected off the user's mouth. In this manner, a false lighting of
the reflected light receipt element by the non-reflected light directly from the light source
42 is substantially eliminated.</p>
    <p num="0045">Figs. 5 and 6 show another embodiment of a dental camera 52 with a housing
54 that has a handle portion 56 extending below a mouth interface portion 57. Mouthpiece
51 has a coupling sleeve 61 with a rounded, preferably cylindrical or conical shape,
attached to a correspondingly shaped attachment coupling of the housing 54. The
attachment coupling and mouthpiece 51 have axes oriented at an angle with respect to the
handle portion 56 of preferably more than about 30°, more preferably more than about 45°, 
more preferably more than about 70° or at or substantially at about a right angle to the axis
thereof. The handle portion 56 is preferably tapered and shaped for easy gripping and single
handed handling, preferably such that the palm of the hand can fit around the lower portion
of the handle, with the thumb resting on keys 64, which are described below. The
mouthpiece has radially extending wings 53. The housing 54 and coupling sleeve 61 define
a finger engageable portion 55, which preferably comprises a protruding tab 65 that
protrudes from the coupling sleeve 61 sufficiently to facilitate engagement with a finger tip
to release the mouthpiece 51 from the housing 54.</p>
    <p num="0046">Color display 58 is disposed on the back of the housing 54 and is visible by an
operator when the front side is received in a patient's mouth. The display is configured to
show the image 59 acquired by the light reception element and specific photographs that are
taken, as well as operational data and user operable menus and information about the
image.</p>
    <p num="0047">Preferably adjacent and most preferably below the display is a control portion
62, which includes a plurality of keys 64 or other user interface. The keys 64 are positioned
for operation by the same hand of the user that holds the camera 52. As shown in Fig. 6,
the keys of this embodiment are positioned within reach of the thumb, with the remaining
fingers and palm of the user grasping the handle portion 56. The keys 64 control the
operation of the camera, including the image acquisition and the display thereof, voice
recording as described below, camera power, shutter or CCD operation, operational menu
control, mode selection, and operational help information.</p>
    <p num="0048">A sound receiving element, such as a microphone 64A, is disposed in a
position for capturing the voice of the camera operator. Associated electronics and storage
are provided inside the housing for recording the voice messages. The electronics are
preferably configured for associating or linking the voice to particular images, so that oral
notes can be stored in connection with each image, reducing the time it takes to annotate
each image. The images and associated sound recordings can preferably be recalled
together.</p>
    <p num="0049">Also contained within the housing 54 are preferably a power storage element
63, such as a battery or accumulator, and electronics for displaying the image produced, for
controlling the lights and optics and for storing captured images in a storage medium or
memory, which is also preferably housed in the housing 54. The storage medium may be a
digital storage medium and is preferably the same one used for storing the voice recordings.
A speaker 66 is preferably also provided to play back recordings with the images. A
connector is disposed at the bottom of the handle 56 for transferring image, sound,
operational, and other data as necessary to a computer, modem, or a network. The
connector also preferably includes a provision to charge the camera power supply, or to 
plug into an external supply and can comprise a USB interface connected to a smart media
card, which are known in the art.</p>
    <p num="0050">Referring to Figs. 7 and 8, housing 67 of camera 68 has a main camera body
70 of an elongated shape. A front end 72 of the main body 70 connects to mouthpiece 74,
which in the embodiment shown is a soft rubber member without wings. Alternatively,
wings as described in the previous embodiments may be employed. The light source and
receipt element are arranged to emit the light and receive the reflected light through the
front end 72 to obtain an image of the patient's teeth. Preferably the light source and the
receipt element are disposed in or near the front end 72, and light conduits, such as fiber
optics may be employed to guide the light as necessary. At a back end 76 of the main body
70, opposite from the mouthpiece 74, is a rearward-facing display 78.</p>
    <p num="0051">An elongated handle 80, generally having a pistol grip configuration, is
connected to the main body 70 at an angle thereto, preferably substantially transversely.
The handle preferably extends from a location near the center between the front and back
ends 72,76 of the main body 70, but may alternatively be disposed adjacent or at one of the
ends. A connector 82 is disposed at the bottom of the handle 80 for transferring image,
sound, operational, and other data as necessary to a computer, modem, or a network.</p>
    <p num="0052">A trigger 84, preferably depressible into the handle, is disposed near the
intersection of the main body 70 and the handle 80, and may alternatively extend from the
main body 70. The trigger is preferably employed to control the optical assembly to acquire
and store the image that is presently displayed on the display 78. The trigger can also serve
other functions, such as selection of operational menu items that are displayed on the
display 78. The trigger 84 is preferably disposed and operable as a pistol trigger, easily
falling within reach of an index finger of the user. Additional keys 86 are also preferably
provided for controlling other operations of the camera.</p>
    <p num="0053">While illustrative embodiments of the invention are disclosed herein, it will be
appreciated that numerous modifications and other embodiments may be devised by those
skilled in the art. Therefore, it will be understood that the appended claims are intended to
cover all such modifcations and embodiments that come within the spirit and scope of the
present invention.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>Mouthpiece attachment for a dental camera, comprising a
body that comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a light channel (20) associable with the camera (10) for
permitting passage of light therethrough to the camera
(10);</claim-text><claim-text>an attachment portion (14) configured for attaching the
body to the dental camera (10) with the light channel (20)
positioned to permit the passage of light to a light
receiving portion of the camera (10); and</claim-text><claim-text>a bite projection portion (30, 32), preferably a wing
extending radially from the light channel (20) and configured
and dimensioned for placement, which substantially blocks
light from entering the light channel (20) from outside the
projection portion (30, 32) when the mouthpiece (12) is
attached to the camera (10).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>Mouthpiece according to claim 1, characterized in that the
body further comprises a reference sample element (33)
configured for directing light with predetermined qualities to
the receiving element (44) for calibrating the camera (10).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>Mouthpiece according to claim 1 or 2, characterized in that the
first attachment portion (14) is substantially stiffer than
the wing (22, 24).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>Mouthpiece according to one of the claims 1 to 4,
characterized in that said bite projection portion (30, 32) is
configured and dimensioned for placement between upper and
lower teeth of a patient for producing images (59) of the
teeth based on the light passed through the light channel (20)
to the receiving portion (44).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>Dental camera, comprising the mouthpiece of one of the
claims 1 to 4, characterized by
a light receiving element (44), which is configured for
receiving light and producing an image based on the received
light; and
a second attachment portion (16) configured for attaching
to the first attachment portion (14) for positioning the
mouthpiece (12) with respect to the light receiving element
(44) for permitting the passage of light through the light
channel (20) to the light receiving element (44).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>Dental camera according to claim 5, characterized in that
the mouthpiece attachment portion (14) comprises a blocking
member associable with the camera (10) for substantially
blocking entry of light between the camera and light channel
(20) from outside the camera (10), light channel (20), and
patient's mouth.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>Dental camera according to one of the claims 5 and 6,
characterized in that said bite projection portion (30, 32)
extends adjacent the wing (22, 24) and is configured and
dimensioned for biting by the patient to stabilize and
position the camera (10) with respect to the mouth.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>Dental camera according to claim 7, characterized in that
the bite projection portion (30, 32) extends from the wing
(22, 24), preferably on each lateral side of the light channel
(20).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>Dental camera according to one of the claims 5 to 8,
characterized in that the light channel (20) defines an
opening (26) extending through the channel (20).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>Dental camera according to one of the claims 5 to 9,
characterized in that the wing (22, 24) extends radially from
the light channel (20) in a direction along the separation
between the teeth of the upper and lower jaws of the patient.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>Dental camera according to claims 10 to 11, characterized in that
the wing (22, 24) extends radially from the light channel (20)
in a direction transverse to the separation between the teeth
of the upper and lower jaws of the patient.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>Dental camera according to one of the claims 5 to 11,
characterized in that it further comprises a light source (42)
configured and disposed for emitting light through the light
channel (20) and upon one or more teeth of the patient, for
receiving light that is reflected from the one or more teeth
and directing the received light back through the light
channel (20) to the receiving element (44).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>Dental camera according to one of the claims 5 to 12,
wherein the light channel (20) has a width sufficient for
allowing passage therethrough of sufficient light reflected
from at least two teeth of the patient back to the receiving
element (44) to form an image (59) of the at least two teeth.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="14">
      <claim-text>Dental camera according to one of the claims 5 to 13,
wherein the camera (10) is configured, dimensioned, and has a
weight for enabling handheld operation with a single hand for
producing an image (59) of the patient's tooth or teeth.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="15">
      <claim-text>Dental camera according to one of the claims 5 to 14,
wherein the first and second attachment portions (14, 16) are
separably attachable to each other.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="16">
      <claim-text>Dental camera according to one of the claims 5 to 15,
wherein the wing (22, 24) has a distal surface that is
substantially concave for placement against the teeth.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="17">
      <claim-text>Dental camera according to one of the claims 5 to 16,
wherein the mouthpiece body (12) includes a reference sample
element (33) with predetermined reflective qualities and
disposed for reflecting the emitted light to the receiving
element (44) adjacent the light reflected from the teeth.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="18">
      <claim-text>Dental camera according to one of the claims 5 to 17,
characterized in that it comprises an image transfer member
for transferring the image (59) to a color analyzer for
determining the color of the portion of the patient's mouth
and preferably a color analyzing electronics mounted to the
housing (50) and connected to the receiving element (44) for
receiving the image (59) and configured for determining the
color of the portion of the patient's mouth.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="19">
      <claim-text>Dental camera, according to one of the claims 5 to 18,
characterized in that it comprises a processor mounted to the
housing (50); and input keys (64) connected with the processor
for operating the camera (52).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="20">
      <claim-text>Dental camera, comprising a housing (50), a light source
(42) mounted to the housing (50);
a receiving element (44) mounted to the housing (50) and
configured for receiving reflected light and producing an
image (59) based on the received light;
a mouthpiece (12) mounted to the housing (50) and configured
for contacting a patient's mouth for positioning the camera
(10) with respect to at least a portion of the mouth;
a light channel (20) associated with the light source (42) for
permitting the emitted light to reflect off a tooth in a
patient's mouth and permitting the reflected light travel into
the receiving eiement (44); and
a display (18) mounted to the housing (50) and associated with
the receiving element (44) for displaying the image (59).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="21">
      <claim-text>Dental camera according to claim 20, characterized in that
the display (18) is movably mounted to the housing (50) for
tilting to adjust an angle between the light channel (20) and
the display (18).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="22">
      <claim-text>Dental camera according to claim 20 or 21, characterized
in that the display (18) is mounted to the housing (50) in a
position in which the image (59) on the display (18) is
viewable from a side of the housing (50) opposite from the
light channel (20).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="23">
      <claim-text>Dental camera according to one of the claims 20 to 22,
characterized in that the housing (67) comprises a first
elongated portion (70) and an elongated handle (80) connected
to the elongated portion (70) at an angle thereto, wherein the
mouthpiece (74) is mounted at an end of the first elongated
portion (70).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="24">
      <claim-text>Dental camera according to one of the claims 23,
characterized in that the display (78) is mounted at an end
(76) of the elongated portion (70) opposite from the
mouthpiece (74).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="25">
      <claim-text>Dental camera according to one of the claims 5 to 24,
characterized in that it comprises a sound receiving element
(64A) configured for receiving sound for storing in
association with the image (59).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="26">
      <claim-text>Dental camera according to claim 25, characterized in that
it comprises a storage medium (63) mounted to the housing (50)
and connected with the light and sound receiving elements (44,
64A) for recording image and sounds in association with each
other.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="27">
      <claim-text>Dental camera, comprising a housing (54); a light source
(42) mounted to the housing (54);
a receiving element (44) mounted to the housing (54) and
configured for receiving reflected light and producing an
image (59) based on the received light;
a mouthpiece (51) mounted to the housing (54) and configured
for contacting a patient's mouth for positioning the camera
(52) with respect to at least a portion of the mouth;
a light channel (20) associated with the light source (42) for
permitting the emitted light to reflect off a tooth in a
patient's mouth and permitting the reflected light travel into
the receiving element (44); and
a sound receiving element (64A) configured for receiving sound
for storing in association with the image (59).</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
