<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1267127-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1267127" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="25372968" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021218">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1267127-A1" status="new" fvid="23636291">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1267127</doc-number>
        <kind>A1</kind>
        <date>20021218</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02253663-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02253663</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020524</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="US-87884801-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>US</country>
          <doc-number>87884801</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010611</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B23P   6/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B23P   6/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23R   3/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23R   3/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23R   3/04        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">F23R   3/08        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B23P   6/00</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F23R   3/00B</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">F23R   3/08</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zum Austausch von Brennkammerwandabschnitten</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Method for replacing combustor liner panels</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé pour remplacer des sections de chambre de combustion</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GEN ELECTRIC</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1 River Road</street>
              <city>Schenectady, NY 12345</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>CALDWELL JAMES MICHAEL</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>EMILIANOWICZ EDWARD JOHN</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>FARMER GILBERT</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MATINI JEFFREY MICHAEL</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>PATTERSON DAVID BRUCE</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>STIVERSON STEVEN ALLEN</name>
            <address>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>CALDWELL, JAMES MICHAEL</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>EMILIANOWICZ, EDWARD JOHN</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>FARMER, GILBERT</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>MATINI, JEFFREY MICHAEL</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>PATTERSON, DAVID BRUCE</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>STIVERSON, STEVEN ALLEN</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>CALDWELL, JAMES MICHAEL</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>109 Windsor Court</street>
              <city>Alexandria, Kentucky 41001</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>EMILIANOWICZ, EDWARD JOHN</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>6460 Leopard Lane</street>
              <city>West Chester, Ohio 45069</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>FARMER, GILBERT</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>2800 Royal Glen Drive</street>
              <city>Cincinnati, Ohio 45239</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>MATINI, JEFFREY MICHAEL</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>5195 Grandin Ridge Drive</street>
              <city>Liberty Township, Ohio 45011</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>PATTERSON, DAVID BRUCE</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>6350 Hummingbird Drive</street>
              <city>Mason, Ohio 45040</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>STIVERSON, STEVEN ALLEN</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>280 Francis Drive</street>
              <city>Blanchester, Ohio 45107</city>
              <country>US</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Pedder, James Cuthbert</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>GE London Patent Operation, Essex House, 12/13 Essex Street</street>
              <city>London WC2R 3AA</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>A replacement method facilitates replacing of a portion of a combustor liner
(40) within a gas turbine engine combustor (30) in a cost-effective and reliable
manner. The combustor includes a combustion zone (36) that is defined by
an inner and an outer liner (42,44). The inner and outer liners each include a
series of panels (50) and a plurality of nuggets (92) formed by adjacent
panels. The method includes the steps of cutting between an outer surface
(82) and an inner surface (80) of at least one liner panel, removing at least
one panel that is adjacent the area of the liner that was cut, and installing a
replacement panel into the combustor for each panel that was removed from
the combustor.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="106" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="84"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">This invention relates generally to gas turbine engine, and more particularly,
to methods for replacing combustor liner panels used with gas turbine
engines.</p>
    <p num="0002">A turbine engine includes a compressor for compressing air which is mixed
with a fuel and channeled to a combustor wherein the mixture is ignited within
a combustion chamber for generating hot combustion gases. At least some
known combustors include a dome assembly, a cowling, and liners to channel
the combustion gases to a turbine, which extracts energy from the
combustion gases for powering the compressor, as well as producing useful
work to propel an aircraft in flight or to power a load, such as an electrical
generator. The liners are coupled to the dome assembly with the cowling,
and extend downstream from the cowling to define the combustion chamber.</p>
    <p num="0003">At least some known liners include a plurality of panels that are connected
together with riveted, bolted, or welded connections. A portion of the panels
include cooling nuggets formed between adjacent panels, that extend radially
outwardly from the panels and away from the combustion chamber.
Accordingly, such cooling nuggets are not subjected to the same degree of
heat as portions of the panels adjacent the combustion chamber, and as
such, during operation thermal stresses may be induced within the panels.
Over time, continued operation with thermal stresses may cause panels to
thermally fatigue, causing weakening and/or cracking to develop within the
panels.</p>
    <p num="0004">Current repair methods include welding thermal fatigue cracks. Additionally,
patches may be attached to areas of panels that are weakened by thermal
stresses. However, if the thermal stresses have induced thermal fatigue or
distress in larger areas of the panels or in a plurality of panels, the combustor
may not have enough structural integrity within such panels to enable patches
to be attached. In such cases, repair of such panels is not a feasible option,
and instead the entire combustor liner is replaced. Because the liner is
coupled to the cowl and the dome assembly, often the entire combustor must
be disassembled for the liner to be replaced. Furthermore, when the 
fasteners are removed from the cowl and dome assembly, precise
dimensional relations between the components may be altered and as a
result, special tooling may be required during re-assembly. Thus, replacing a
combustor liner including cooling nuggets may be a time-consuming and
expensive process.</p>
    <p num="0005">In an exemplary embodiment, a method facilitates replacing of a portion of a
combustor liner within a gas turbine engine combustor in a cost-effective and
reliable manner. The combustor includes a combustion zone that is defined
by an inner and an outer liner. The inner and outer liners each include a
series of panels and a plurality of nuggets formed by adjacent panels. The
method includes the steps of cutting between an outer surface and an inner
surface of at least one liner panel, removing at least one panel that is
adjacent the area of the liner that was cut, and installing a replacement panel
into the combustor for each panel that was removed from the combustor.</p>
    <p num="0006">In another aspect of the invention, a method is used to replace at least one
deteriorated combustor liner panel within a gas turbine engine combustor that
includes an annular liner including a multinugget region, a mulithole region,
and an inner surface. The multihole region extends downstream from the
multinugget region, and the method includes the steps of cutting through at
least one of the liner multinugget region and the liner multihole region,
downstream from the at least one combustor liner panel to be replaced,
removing the at least one deteriorated combustor liner panel from the
combustor, and welding at least one replacement panel to at least one
existing panel within the combustor for each deteriorated combustor liner
panel removed.</p>
    <p num="0007">The invention will now be described in greater detail, by way of example, with
reference to the drawings, in which:-
<sl><li>Figure 1 is schematic illustration of a gas turbine engine;</li><li>Figure 2 is a partial cross-sectional view of a combustor assembly that may
be used with the gas turbine engine shown in Figure 1; </li><li>Figure 3 is an enlarged view of a combustor liner used with the combustor
shown in Figure 2 taken along area 3;</li><li>Figure 4 is an enlarged cross-sectional view of an alternative embodiment of
a combustor liner that may be used with the gas turbine engine shown in
Figure 1; and</li><li>Figure 5 is an enlarged plan view of the combustor liner shown in Figure 4.</li></sl></p>
    <p num="0008">Figure 1 is a schematic illustration of a gas turbine engine 10 including a low
pressure compressor 12, a high pressure compressor 14, and a combustor
16. Engine 10 also includes a high pressure turbine 18 and a low pressure
turbine 20. Compressor 12 and turbine 20 are coupled by a first shaft 22, and
compressor 14 and turbine 18 are coupled by a second shaft 21. In one
embodiment, gas turbine engine 10 is a GE90 engine commercially available
from General Electric Aircraft Engines, Cincinnati, Ohio. In another
embodiment, gas turbine engine 10 is a CF engine commercially available
from General Electric Aircraft Engines, Cincinnati, Ohio.</p>
    <p num="0009">In operation, air flows through low pressure compressor 12 and compressed
air is supplied from low pressure compressor 12 to high pressure compressor
14. The highly compressed air is delivered to combustor 16. Airflow from
combustor 16 drives turbines 18 and 20 and exits gas turbine engine 10
through a nozzle 24.</p>
    <p num="0010">Figure 2 is a partial cross-sectional view of a combustor 30. Figure 3 is an
enlarged view of a portion of combustor 30. Combustor 30 may be used with
gas turbine engine 10 shown in Figure 1, and includes a dome assembly 32.
A fuel injector (not shown) extends into dome assembly 32 and injects
atomized fuel through dome assembly 32 into a combustion zone 36 of
combustor 30 to form an air-fuel mixture that is ignited downstream of the fuel
injector</p>
    <p num="0011">Combustion zone 36 is formed by annular, radially outer and radially inner
supporting members (not shown) and combustor liners 40. Combustor liners
40 shield the outer and inner supporting members from the heat generated
within combustion zone 36 and includes an inner liner 42 and an outer liner 
44. Each liner 42 and 44 is annular and includes a multinugget region 46 and
a multihole region 48. Each multinugget region 46 extends from dome
assembly 32 downstream to each multihole region 48.</p>
    <p num="0012">Liners 42 and 44 define combustion zone 36. Combustion zone 36 extends
from dome assembly 32 downstream to a turbine nozzle (not shown). Outer
and inner liners 44 and 42 each include a plurality of panels 50 which include
a series of steps 52, each of which form a distinct portion of combustor liner
40.</p>
    <p num="0013">Outer liner 44 and inner liner 42 each include a bolt band 60 and 62,
respectively, and a first panel 64 and 66, respectively. Outer bolt band 60
and inner bolt band 62 are positioned adjacent to dome assembly 32 and
extend downstream from dome assembly 32 to first panels 64 and 66,
respectively. First panels 64 and 66 are connected downstream from bolt
bands 60 and 62, respectively. Each adjacent downstream panel 50 is
numbered sequentially, such that second panels 68 and 70 are connected
downstream from respective first panels 64 and 66. Bolt bands 60 and 62
include a plurality of openings 72 sized to receive fasteners 74 therethrough.
Fasteners 74 secure liners 42 and 44, bolt bands 60 and 62, and a cowl
assembly 78 to dome assembly 32.</p>
    <p num="0014">Each combustor panel 50 includes a combustor liner surface 80, an exterior
surface 82, and an overhang portion 84. Combustor liner surface 80 extends
from dome assembly 32 to the turbine nozzle. Combustor liner surface 80
and exterior surface 82 are connected together at overhang portion 84 and
form a rear facing edge 86. A plurality of air cooling features 88 separate
adjacent combustor panels 50.</p>
    <p num="0015">Air cooling features 88 include openings 90 which receive air therethrough
from an air plenum (not shown) such that a thin protective boundary of air is
formed between high temperature combustion gases and combustor liner
surface 80. Furthermore, openings 90 permit convective cooling of
combustor liner 40. Specifically, openings 90 extend through features 88
which are formed between adjacent panels 50 and radially inward from
nuggets 92 formed by panels 50. Panels 50 are connected serially, such that 
each panel downstream end 100 is connected to an upstream end 102 of an
adjacent downstream panel 50. Nuggets 92 are formed between adjacent
connected panels respective downstream and upstream ends 100 and 102.</p>
    <p num="0016">Liner multinugget region 46 includes a plurality of nuggets 92. In the
exemplary embodiment, region 46 includes three nuggets 92. Liner multihole
region 48 includes a plurality of openings (not shown).</p>
    <p num="0017">A layer 110 of thermal barrier material is applied on combustor liner surface
80. Thermal barrier material further insulates combustor liner surface 80 from
high temperature combustion gases. In an exemplary embodiment, thermal
barrier coating material is commercially available from Englehart Industries,
Wilmington Massachusetts.</p>
    <p num="0018">During operation, as atomized fuel is injecting into combustion zone 36 and
ignited, heat is generated within zone 36. Although air enters combustion
zone 36 through cooling features 88 and forms a thin protective boundary of
air along combustor liner surface 80, a variation in exposure of combustor
liner surfaces to high temperatures may induce thermal stresses into panels
50. As a result of continued exposure to thermal stresses, over time, panels
50 may become deteriorated.</p>
    <p num="0019">Deteriorated regions of combustor liner 40 may be removed and replaced
using the methods described herein. More specifically, deteriorated regions
of either liner multinugget region 46 and/or liner multihole region 44 may be
removed and replace using the methods described herein. If a field returned
engine, such as engine 10, indicates that combustor liner multinugget region
46 includes at least one deteriorated panel 50, a circumferential cut is made
through combustor liner 40 to remove deteriorated panels 50. More
specifically, as shown in Figure 3, the cut is made radially through liner 40
and through a panel body 104, as illustrated with line 120, such that the cut
extends from liner exterior surface 82 to liner interior surface 80, and such
that a portion 122 of panel body 104 of panel 50 being cut remains secured
within combustor 30. Furthermore, the cut is extended through liner 40
downstream from deteriorated panels 50 being replaced. Fasteners 74 may
be loosened to separate deteriorated panels 50 from liner 40 for removal. </p>
    <p num="0020">Alternatively, a second cut may then be made upstream from deteriorated
panels 50 being replaced, such that deteriorated panels 50 are separated and
removable from combustor liner 40.</p>
    <p num="0021">After deteriorated panels 50 are removed from combustor liners 40,
replacement panels (not shown) may be installed into combustor liners 42
and/or 44. The replacement panels are formed to include a nugget
configuration that is substantially identical to that portion of liner 40 being
replaced. In one embodiment, at least one of a forging, roll welded ring, or a
casting is used as a replacement panel.</p>
    <p num="0022">The replacement panel is then welded into combustor liner 42 and/or 44,
such that the replacement panel is welded to an existing panel 50 that
remains secured within combustor liner 42 and/or 44. More specifically, a
downstream side (not shown) of a body of the replacement panel is welded to
panel body portion 122 within combustor 30. In one embodiment, electron
beam, EB, welding is used to secure the replacement panel within combustor
30. In another embodiment, tungsten inert gas, TIG, welding is used to
secure the replacement panel within combustor 30. Thermal barrier coating
material may then be applied on replacement panel combustor liner surface
80, and fastener 74 is then re-tightened.</p>
    <p num="0023">If a field returned engine, such as engine 10, indicates that combustor liner
multihole region 48 includes at least one deteriorated panel 50, a cut is made
through combustor liner 40 to remove deteriorated panels 50. More
specifically, as shown in Figure 3, the circumferential cut is made radially
through liner 40 and through a panel body 104, as illustrated with line 120,
such that the cut extends from liner exterior surface 82 to liner surface 80,
and such that panel body portion 122 remains secured within combustor 30.
Furthermore, the cut is extended through liner 40 downstream from
deteriorated panels 50 being replaced. A second cut may then be made
within multihole region 48 and upstream from deteriorated panels 50 being
replaced, such that a deteriorated portion of multihole region 48 is separated
and removable from combustor liner 40. Fasteners 74 may then be loosened
to separate the deteriorated portion and multinugget region 46 from liner 40
for removal. </p>
    <p num="0024">After deteriorated portions of multihole region 48 are removed from
combustor 30, a replacement panel may be installed into combustor 30. In
one embodiment, at least one of a forging, roll welded ring, a casting, or a
sheet metal panel is manufactured and used as a replacement panel. The
multihole region openings may be formed after the replacement panel is
attached. In one embodiment, the openings are formed with a laser process.
In another embodiment, the openings are formed using an electron discharge
machining, EDM, process. In yet another embodiment, the newly formed
openings may be sized differently, reduced, or re-positioned, to facilitate
improving cooling of combustor 30.</p>
    <p num="0025">The replacement panel is then welded to an existing panel 50 that remains
secured within combustor 30. More specifically, a downstream side (not
shown) of a body of the replacement panel is welded to panel body portion
122 within combustor 30. In one embodiment, electron beam, EB, welding is
used to secure the replacement panel within combustor 30. In another
embodiment, tungsten inert gas, TIG, welding is used to secure the
replacement panel within combustor 30. Thermal barrier material may then
be applied on replacement panel combustor liner surface 80.</p>
    <p num="0026">Because deteriorated liners are replaced using the method described herein,
combustors 30 are returned to service using a replacement process that
facilitates improved savings in comparison to removing and replacing entire
combustor liners 40. Furthermore, because the replacement panels are
formed to be substantially identical to originally installed panels 50,
aerodynamic performance and combustor performance are not adversely
impacted by the replacement panels.</p>
    <p num="0027">Figure 4 is an enlarged cross-sectional view of an alternative embodiment of
an inner combustor liner 140 that may be used with gas turbine engine 10
(shown in Figure 1). Figure 5 is an enlarged plan view of combustor liner 140.
Liner 140 is substantially similar to liners 40 (shown in Figures 2 and 3), and
is installed within a combustor (not shown). The combustor includes a
combustor liner that includes annular inner liner 140 and an annular outer
liner (not shown) that is formed substantially similarly to inner liner 140. Inner 
liner 140 includes a plurality of panels 150 which include a series of steps
152, each of which form a distinct portion of combustor liner 140.</p>
    <p num="0028">Panels 150 are connected serially. Inner liner 140 includes a bolt band 160
and a first panel 164. Inner bolt band 160 is coupled to a dome assembly
(not shown) and extends downstream from the dome assembly to first panels
164. First panel 164 and panels 150 are connected downstream from bolt
band 160, such that each adjacent downstream panel 150 is numbered
sequentially. Accordingly, a second panel 168 is connected downstream from
first panel 164, and a third panel 170 is connected downstream from second
panel 168. Bolt band 160 includes a plurality of openings 172 sized to
receive fasteners 74 (shown in Figure 2) for securing liner 140 to the dome
assembly.</p>
    <p num="0029">Each combustor panel 150 includes a combustor liner surface 180, an
exterior surface 182, and an overhang portion 184. Combustor liner surface
180 extends from the dome assembly to the turbine nozzle. Combustor liner
surface 180 and exterior surface 182 are connected together at overhang
portion 184 and form a rear facing edge 186. A plurality of air cooling
features 188 separate adjacent combustor panels 150.</p>
    <p num="0030">Air cooling features 188 include a plurality of openings 190 which receive air
therethrough from an air plenum (not shown) such that a thin protective
boundary of air is formed between high temperature combustion gases and
combustor liner surface 180. Openings 190 are known as dilution openings
and extend between liner surface 180 and exterior surface 182 to facilitate
mixing of combustion gases within the combustor. In the exemplary
embodiment, openings 190 are substantially circular. Specifically, each panel
150 includes an upstream end 200, a downstream end 202, and a body 204
extending therebetween. Panels 150 are connected, such that each panel
downstream end 202 is connected to an upstream end 200 of an adjacent
downstream panel 150. Nuggets 192 are formed between adjacent
connected panels respective downstream and upstream ends 202 and 200.
Nuggets 192 are known as super slot nuggets. In the exemplary
embodiment, liner 140 includes six nuggets 192. </p>
    <p num="0031">In an alternative embodiment, a layer of thermal barrier material (not shown)
is applied on combustor liner surface 180, and enhances the thermal
protection of combustor liner surface 180 from high temperature combustion
gases.</p>
    <p num="0032">Deteriorated regions of combustor liner 140 may be removed and replaced
using the methods described herein. If a field returned engine, such as
engine 10, indicates that combustor liner 140 includes at least one
deteriorated panel 150, a cut is made circumferentially through combustor
liner 140 to remove deteriorated panels 150. More specifically, as shown in
Figure 4, the circumferential cut is made radially through liner 140 and
through a nugget 192, as illustrated with line 220, such that the cut extends
from liner exterior surface 182 to liner surface 180. In one embodiment, the
cut is made between third panel 170 and a fourth panel 222. Furthermore,
the cut is extended through liner 140 downstream from deteriorated panels 50
being replaced.</p>
    <p num="0033">After deteriorated portions liner 140 are removed from the combustor, a
replacement panel (not shown) may be installed into combustor liner 140. In
one embodiment, at least one of a forging, roll welded ring, a casting, or a
sheet metal panel is manufactured and used as a replacement panel.</p>
    <p num="0034">The replacement panel is then welded into combustor liner 140, such that the
replacement panel is secured within the combustor. More specifically, a
downstream end (not shown) of the replacement panel is welded to an
existing panel 150 such that a nugget 192 is formed between the replacement
panel and panel 150. In one embodiment, electron beam, EB, welding is
used to secure the replacement panel within combustor liner 140. In another
embodiment, tungsten inert gas, TIG, welding is used to secure the
replacement panel within combustor liner 140. Thermal barrier material may
then be applied on replacement panel combustor liner surface 180.</p>
    <p num="0035">The above-described combustor liner replacement method is cost-effective
and highly reliable. The method includes the steps of removing deteriorated
panels from the combustor liner, such that deteriorated panels may be
replaced with replacement panels. In one embodiment, deteriorated panels 
are removed by cutting through the body of the panel, and replacement
panels are then welded to into the combustor liner. As a result, a method is
provided which enables deteriorated combustor liner panels to be removed
and replaced in a cost-effective and reliable manner.</p>
    <p num="0036">For the sake of good order, various aspects of the invention are set out in the
following clauses:-
<sl><li>1. A method for replacing a gas turbine engine combustor liner panel
(50), the combustor (30) having a combustion zone (36) formed by inner and
outer liners (42, 44), the inner and outer liners each including a series of
panels (64, 66, 68, 70) and a plurality of cooling features (88), the cooling
features formed by overhanging portions (84) of the inner and outer liner
panels, the cooling featuress between adjacent panels, said method
comprising the steps of:
<sl><li>removing at least one panel from the combustor; and</li><li>installing at least one replacement panel into the combustor such that
the series of panels are arranged in steps relative to one another,</li></sl></li><li>2. A method in accordance with Clause 1 wherein each panel (50)
includes an upstream end (102), a downstream end (100), and a body (104)
extending therebetween, said step of removing at least one panel further
comprising the step of cutting radially through at least one panel body from an
outer surface (82) of the panel to an inner surface (80) of the panel.</li><li>3. A method in accordance with Clause 1 wherein said step of installing
at least one replacement panel further comprises the step of welding a body
of each replacement panel to a panel body (122) secured within the
combustor (30).</li><li>4. A method in accordance with Clause 3 wherein said step of welding a
body further comprises the step of using at least one of an EB welding
process and a TIG welding process to secure the replacement panel within
the combustor (30).</li><li>5. A method in accordance with Clause 1 wherein each panel (50)
includes an inner surface (80) and an outer surface (82), said method further 
comprising the step of applying thermal barrier coating material to the inner
surface of each replacement panel attached within the combustor (30).</li><li>6. A method for replacing a portion of a combustor liner (40) within a gas
turbine engine combustor (30), the combustor having a combustion zone (36)
formed by an inner and outer liner (42, 44), the inner and outer liners each
including a series of panels (64, 66, 68, 70) and a plurality of nuggets (92),
the nuggets formed by adjacent panels, said method comprising the steps of:
<sl><li>cutting between an outer surface (82) and an inner surface (80) of at
least one liner panel;</li><li>removing at least one panel adjacent an area of the liner cut (120); and</li><li>installing a replacement panel into the combustor to replace each
panel removed from the combustor.</li></sl></li><li>7. A method in accordance with Clause 6 wherein said step of cutting
between an outer surface (82) and an inner surface (80) further comprises
the step of cutting through a panel downstream (100) from a nugget (92).</li><li>8. A method in accordance with Clause 6 wherein said step of cutting
between an outer surface (82) and an inner surface (800 further comprises
the step of cutting through a panel body (104).</li><li>9. A method in accordance with Clause 8 wherein said step of installing a
replacement panel further comprises the step of welding each replacement
panel to respective existing panels (50) secured within the combustor (30).</li><li>10. A method in accordance with Clause 9 wherein said step of welding
each replacement panel further comprises the step of welding a body of each
replacement panel to respective panel bodies (122) of existing panels
secured within the combustor (30).</li><li>11. A method in accordance with Clause 6 further comprising the step of
applying thermal barrier coating material to the inner surface of each
replacement panel attached within the combustor (30).</li><li>12. A method for replacing at least one deteriorated combustor liner panel
(50) within a gas turbine engine combustor (30) including an annular liner (40) 
including a multinugget region (46), a mulithole region (48), and an inner
surface (80), the multihole region extending downstream from the multinugget
region, said method comprising the steps of:
<sl><li>cutting through at least one of the liner multinugget region and the liner
multihole region downstream from the at least one deteriorated combustor
liner panel to be replaced;</li><li>removing the at least one deteriorated combustor liner panel from the
combustor; and</li><li>welding at least one replacement panel to at least one existing panel
within the combustor for each deteriorated combustor liner panel removed.</li></sl></li><li>13. A method in accordance with Clause 12 wherein said step of welding
at least one replacement liner further comprises the step of using at least one
of an EB welding process and a TIG welding process to secure each
replacement panel to each respective existing panel (50) within the
combustor (30).</li><li>14. A method in accordance with Clause 13 wherein each panel (50)
includes an upstream end (102), a downstream end (100), and a body (104)
extending therebetween, said step of cutting through at least one of the liner
multinugget region (46) and the liner multihole region (48) further comprises
the step of cutting through a panel body within the liner multinugget region.</li><li>15. A method in accordance with Clause 14 wherein each panel (50)
includes an upstream end (102), a downstream end (100), and a body (104)
extending therebetween, said step of cutting through at least one of the liner
multinugget region (46) and the liner multihole region (48) further comprises
the step of cutting through a panel body within the liner multihole region.</li><li>16. A method in accordance with Clause 14 further comprising the step of
applying thermal barrier material to the inner surface of each replacement
panel welded into the combustor (30).</li></sl></p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>A method for replacing a gas turbine engine combustor liner panel
(50), the combustor (30) having a combustion zone (36) formed by inner and
outer liners (42, 44), the inner and outer liners each including a series of
panels (64, 66, 68, 70) and a plurality of cooling features (88), the cooling
features formed by overhanging portions (84) of the inner and outer liner
panels, the cooling features between adjacent panels, said method
comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>removing at least one panel from the combustor; and</claim-text><claim-text>installing at least one replacement panel into the combustor such that
the series of panels are arranged in steps relative to one another,</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>A method in accordance with Claim 1 wherein each panel (50) includes
an upstream end (102), a downstream end (100), and a body (104) extending
therebetween, said step of removing at least one panel further comprising the
step of cutting radially through at least one panel body from an outer surface
(82) of the panel to an inner surface (80) of the panel.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>A method in accordance with Claim 1 or 2 wherein said step of
installing at least one replacement panel further comprises the step of welding
a body of each replacement panel to a panel body (122) secured within the
combustor (30).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>A method in accordance with Claim 3 wherein said step of welding a
body further comprises the step of using at least one of an EB welding
process and a TIG welding process to secure the replacement panel within
the combustor (30).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>A method in accordance with Claim 1 wherein each panel (50) includes
an inner surface (80) and an outer surface (82), said method further
comprising the step of applying thermal barrier coating material to the inner
surface of each replacement panel attached within the combustor (30).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>A method for replacing a portion of a combustor liner (40) within a gas
turbine engine combustor (30), the combustor having a combustion zone (36)
formed by an inner and outer liner (42, 44), the inner and outer liners each
including a series of panels (64, 66, 68, 70) and a plurality of nuggets (92),
the nuggets formed by adjacent panels, said method comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>cutting between an outer surface (82) and an inner surface (80) of at
least one liner panel;</claim-text><claim-text>removing at least one panel adjacent an area of the liner cut (120); and</claim-text><claim-text>installing a replacement panel into the combustor to replace each
panel removed from the combustor.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>A method in accordance with Claim 6 wherein said step of cutting
between an outer surface (82) and an inner surface (80) further comprises
the step of cutting through a panel downstream (100) from a nugget (92).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>A method in accordance with Claim 6 wherein said step of cutting
between an outer surface (82) and an inner surface (800 further comprises
the step of cutting through a panel body (104).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>A method in accordance with Claim 6, 7 or 8 wherein said step of
installing a replacement panel further comprises the step of welding each
replacement panel to respective existing panels (50) secured within the
combustor (30).</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>A method in accordance with Claim 9 wherein said step of welding
each replacement panel further comprises the step of welding a body of each
replacement panel to respective panel bodies (122) of existing panels
secured within the combustor (30).</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
