<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1251499-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1251499" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="26612380" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021023">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1251499-A2" status="new" fvid="23590603">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1251499</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021023</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02252719-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02252719</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020417</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001093026-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001093026</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010328</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001123521-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001123521</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010420</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B   7/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B   7/005       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B   7/125       20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">G11B   7/125       20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">G11B   7/005</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">S11B7:125C1</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">S11B7:257D3</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">S11B7:257D7</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">S11B7:258D</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren und Vorrichtung zur Wiedergabe für optisches Informationsmedium</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Readout method and apparatus for optical information medium</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé et appareil de lecture pour support optique d'informations</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TDK CORP</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>TDK CORPORATION</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>TDK Corporation</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>1-13-1, Nihonbashi, Chuo-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo 103-8272</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KATO TATSUYA</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KIKUKAWA TAKASHI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SHINGAI HIROSHI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>UTSUNOMIYA HAJIME</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KATO, TATSUYA</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KIKUKAWA, TAKASHI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>SHINGAI, HIROSHI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>UTSUNOMIYA, HAJIME</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>KATO, TATSUYA</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>TDK Corporation, 1-13-1 Nihonbashi, Chuo-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo 103-8272</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>KIKUKAWA, TAKASHI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>TDK Corporation, 1-13-1 Nihonbashi, Chuo-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo 103-8272</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>SHINGAI, HIROSHI</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>TDK Corporation, 1-13-1 Nihonbashi, Chuo-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo 103-8272</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>UTSUNOMIYA, HAJIME</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>TDK Corporation, 1-13-1 Nihonbashi, Chuo-ku</street>
              <city>Tokyo 103-8272</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Wise, Stephen James</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>c/o RAWORTH, MOSS &amp;amp; COOK, Raworth House, 36 Sydenham Road</street>
              <city>Croydon, Surrey CR0 2EF</city>
              <country>GB</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>An information readout method for an optical
information medium comprising an information recording
layer having pits or recorded marks representative of
information data involves the step of irradiating a laser
beam to the information recording layer through an
objective lens for providing readings of the pits or
recorded marks. When the laser beam has a wavelength λ of
400 to 410 nm, the objective lens has a numerical aperture
NA of 0.70 to 0.85, and the pits or recorded marks have a
minimum size P<sub>L</sub> of up to 0.36λ/NA, readout is carried out
at a power Pr of at least 0.4 mW for the laser beam. When
the laser beam has a wavelength λ of 630 to 670 nm, the
objective lens has a numerical aperture NA of 0.60 to 0.65,
and the pits or recorded marks have a minimum size P<sub>L</sub> of up
to 0.36λ/NA, readout is carried out at a power Pr of at
least 1.0 mW for the laser beam. Pits or recorded marks of
a size approximate to the resolution limit determined by
diffraction can be read out at a high C/N.</p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p num="0001">This invention relates to a method and apparatus for
reading out information in an optical information medium.</p>
    <heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0002">Optical information media include read-only optical
discs such as compact discs, rewritable optical recording
discs such as magneto-optical recording discs and phase
change optical recording discs, and write-once optical
recording discs using organic dyes as the recording
material.</p>
    <p num="0003">Nowadays, optical information media are required to
further increase their information density in order to
process a vast quantity of information as in images. The
information density per unit area can be increased either
by narrowing the track pitch or by reducing the space
between recorded marks or between pits to increase a linear
density. However, if the track density or linear density
is too high relative to the beam spot of reading light, the
carrier-to-noise (C/N) ratio lowers, eventually to a level
where signals are unreadable. The resolution upon signal
readout is determined by the diameter of a beam spot. More
illustratively, provided that the reading light has a
wavelength λ and the optical system of the reading
equipment has a numerical aperture NA, the spatial
frequency 2NA/λ generally becomes a resolution limit.
Accordingly, reducing the wavelength of reading light and
increasing the NA are effective means for improving the C/N
and resolution upon readout. A number of technical studies
that have been made thus far reveal that many technical
problems must be solved before such effective means can be
introduced. </p>
    <p num="0004">Under the circumstances, several methods have been
proposed for going over the resolution limit (or
diffraction limit) determined by light diffraction. They
are generally known as super-resolution readout methods.</p>
    <p num="0005">The most common super-resolution readout method is to
form a mask layer over a recording layer. Based on the
fact that a laser beam defines a spot having an intensity
distribution approximate to the Gaussian distribution, an
optical aperture smaller than the beam spot is formed in
the mask layer whereby the beam spot is reduced below the
diffraction limit. This method is generally divided into a
heat mode and a photon mode, depending on the optical
aperture-forming mechanism.</p>
    <p num="0006">The heat mode is such that upon irradiation to a beam
spot, the mask layer changes its optical properties in a
region whose temperature is raised above a certain value.
The heat mode is utilized, for example, in the optical disc
disclosed in JP-A 5-205314. This optical disc has on a
transparent substrate in which optically readable recorded
pits are formed in accordance with information signals, a
layer of a material whose reflectance changes with
temperature. That is, the material layer serves as a mask
layer. The elements described in JP-A 5-205314 as the
material of which the mask layer is constructed are
lanthanoids, with Tb being used in Examples. In the
optical disc of JP-A 5-205314, when reading light is
irradiated, the reflectance of the material layer changes
due to temperature distribution within the scanned spot of
the reading light. After reading operation, the
reflectance resumes the initial state as the temperature
lowers. It never happens that the material layer be melted
during reading. Another known example of the heat mode is
a medium capable of super-resolution readout, as disclosed
in Japanese Patent No. 2,844,824, the medium having a mask
layer of an amorphous-crystalline phase transition material
in which a high-temperature region created within a beam 
spot is transformed into crystal for increasing the
reflectance. This medium, however, is impractical in that
after reading, the mask layer must be transformed back to
amorphous.</p>
    <p num="0007">The heat mode media require that the readout optical
power be strictly controlled in consideration of various
conditions including the linear velocity of the medium
since the size of the optical aperture depends solely on
the temperature distribution in the mask layer. This, in
turn, requires a complex control system and hence, an
expensive medium drive. The heat mode media also suffer
from the problem that reading characteristics degrade with
the repetition of reading operation because the mask layer
is prone to degradation by repetitive heating.</p>
    <p num="0008">On the other hand, the photon mode is such that upon
exposure to a beam spot, the mask layer changes its optical
properties in a region whose photon intensity is increased
above a certain value. The photon mode is utilized, for
example, in the information recording medium of JP-A 8-96412,
the optical recording medium of JP-A 11-86342, and
the optical information recording medium of JP-A 10-340482.
More illustratively, JP-A 8-96412 discloses a mask layer
formed of phthalocyanine or a derivative thereof dispersed
in a resin or inorganic dielectric, and a mask layer formed
of a chalcogenide. JP-A 11-86342 uses as the mask layer a
super-resolution readout film containing a semiconductor
material having a forbidden band which upon exposure to
reading light, is subject to electron excitation to the
energy level of excitons to change light absorption
characteristics. One illustrative mask layer is CdSe
microparticulates dispersed in a SiO<sub>2</sub> matrix. JP-A 10-340482
uses as the mask layer a glass layer in which the
intensity distribution of transmitted light varies nonlinearly
with the intensity distribution of irradiated
light.</p>
    <p num="0009">Unlike the super-resolution readout media of the heat 
mode, the super-resolution readout media of the photon mode
are relatively resistant to degradation by repetitive
reading.</p>
    <p num="0010">In the photon mode, the region whose optical
characteristics change is determined by the number of
incident photons which in turn, depends on the linear
velocity of the medium relative to the beam spot. Also in
the photon mode, the size of an optical aperture depends on
the power of reading light, indicating that supply of an
excessive power makes so large an optical aperture that
super-resolution readout may become impossible. Therefore,
the photon mode also requires to strictly control the power
of reading light in accordance with the linear velocity and
the size of pits or recorded marks (objects to be read
out). Additionally, the photon mode requires to select the
mask layer-forming material in accordance with the
wavelength of reading light. That is, the photon mode
media are rather incompatible with multi-wavelength
reading.</p>
    <p num="0011">Even in the case of recorded marks or pits of a large
size which do not need super-resolution readout, a fully
high C/N is not available if the size is approximate to the
resolution limit determined by light diffraction.</p>
    <heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
    <p num="0012">An object of the invention is to provide a readout
method for an optical information medium having pits or
recorded marks of a size approximate to the resolution
limit determined by diffraction, which method provides
readings of the pits or recorded marks at a high C/N.</p>
    <p num="0013">A first embodiment of the invention provides an
information readout method for an optical information
medium comprising an information recording layer having
pits or recorded marks representative of information data.
The method includes the step of irradiating a laser beam to
the information recording layer through an objective lens
for providing readings of the pits or recorded marks. When 
the laser beam having a wavelength λ of 400 to 410 nm is
irradiated through the objective lens having a numerical
aperture NA of 0.70 to 0.85 to the pits or recorded marks
having a minimum size P<sub>L</sub> of up to 0.36λ/NA, the laser beam
is given a power Pr of at least 0.4 mW. The minimum size
P<sub>L</sub> is preferably up to 0.31λ/NA and also preferably, at
least 0.25λ/NA. The power Pr is preferably at least 0.45
mW and more preferably at least 0.5 mW.</p>
    <p num="0014">A second embodiment of the invention provides an
information readout method for an optical information
medium comprising an information recording layer having
pits or recorded marks representative of information data.
The method includes the step of irradiating a laser beam to
the information recording layer through an objective lens
for providing readings of the pits or recorded marks. When
the laser beam having a wavelength λ of 630 to 670 nm is
irradiated through the objective lens having a numerical
aperture NA of 0.60 to 0.65 to the pits or recorded marks
having a minimum size P<sub>L</sub> of up to 0.36λ/NA, the laser beam
is given a power Pr of at least 1.0 mW. The minimum size
P<sub>L</sub> is preferably up to 0.27λ/NA and also preferably at
least 0.25λ/NA. The power Pr is preferably at least 1.4
mW, more preferably at least 2.0 mW, and even more
preferably at least 2.2 mW.</p>
    <p num="0015">Readout apparatus used in the information readout
methods of the first and second embodiments are also
contemplated herein.</p>
    <heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
    <p num="0016">
      <sl>
        <li>FIG. 1 is a fragmentary cross-sectional view of an
optical information medium according to one embodiment of
the invention.</li>
        <li>FIG. 2 schematically illustrates the operation of the
invention.</li>
        <li>FIG. 3 is a graph of C/N versus mark length.</li>
        <li>FIG. 4 is a graph of C/N versus readout power. </li>
        <li>FIG. 5 is a graph of C/N versus pit length.</li>
        <li>FIG. 6 is a graph of C/N versus readout power.</li>
        <li>FIG. 7 is a graph of C/N versus mark length.</li>
        <li>FIG. 8 is a graph of C/N versus readout power.</li>
        <li>FIG. 9 is a graph of C/N versus readout power.</li>
        <li>FIG. 10 is a graph of C/N versus readout power.</li>
        <li>FIG. 11 is a graph of C/N versus readout power.</li>
        <li>FIG. 12 is a graph of C/N versus readout power.</li>
        <li>FIG. 13 is a graph of C/N versus a tungsten content
in Mo-W alloy.</li>
      </sl>
    </p>
    <heading>DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
    <p num="0017">The information readout method of the invention is
applied to an optical information medium which includes a
specific layer to be referred to as "functional layer,"
hereinafter. According to the invention, pits or recorded
marks are read out by irradiating a laser beam thereto
through a readout light irradiating optical system while
setting the readout power Pr of the laser beam within a
specific range in accordance with the readout wavelength
and the optical system. This setting enables super-resolution
readout beyond the resolution limit determined
by light diffraction. In addition, the invention achieves
a higher C/N ratio than in the prior art, when the pits or
recorded marks having a size approximate to and slightly
greater than the resolution limit are read out.</p>
    <p num="0018">In the first embodiment of the invention, the laser
beam used in reading of pits or recorded marks (simply
abbreviated as "pit/mark," hereinafter) has a wavelength λ
of 400 to 410 nm. The laser beam is irradiated to the
medium through an objective lens having a numerical
aperture NA of 0.70 to 0.85.</p>
    <p num="0019">Since the cutoff spatial frequency is 2NA/λ,
rows of pits/marks in which the pit/mark length is equal to
the space between adjacent pits/marks are readable as long
as the spatial frequency is equal to or below 2NA/λ (line
pairs/nm). The pit/mark length (= space length) 
corresponding to the readable spatial frequency is given as
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">λ/4NA = 0.25λ/NA.</st32:df>
It is then concluded that super-resolution readout is
possible if a C/N is obtained from a pit/mark row with a
pit/mark length of less than 0.25λ/NA. Notably, the first
embodiment is characterized in that a high C/N is available
upon reading of pits/marks which are slightly larger than
the resolution limit. Then in the first embodiment, the
pits/marks preferably have a minimum size P<sub>L</sub> of at least
0.25λ/NA. Since too large a minimum size P<sub>L</sub> of pits/marks
compromises the benefits of the first embodiment, the upper
limit of the minimum size P<sub>L</sub> is 0.36λ/NA, which is slightly
larger than the resolution limit, and preferably up to
0.31λ/NA.</p>
    <p num="0020">In the first embodiment, the laser beam irradiated
for readout should have a power Pr of at least 0.4 mW,
preferably at least 0.45 mW, and more preferably at least
0.5 mW. In the situation that the wavelength λ and the
numerical aperture NA are within the limited ranges
according to the first embodiment, when pits/marks having
the above-defined size approximate to the resolution limit
corresponding to the λ and NA are read out, a satisfactory
C/N is available as long as the readout power Pr is within
the range limited by the first embodiment.</p>
    <p num="0021">In the second embodiment of the invention, the laser
beam used in reading of pits/marks has a wavelength λ of
630 to 670 nm. The laser beam is irradiated to the medium
through an objective lens having a numerical aperture NA of
0.60 to 0.65.</p>
    <p num="0022">The second embodiment is also characterized in that a
high C/N is available upon reading of pits/marks which are
slightly larger than the resolution limit. Then in the
second embodiment, the pits/marks preferably have a minimum
size P<sub>L</sub> of at least 0.25λ/NA. Since too large a minimum
size P<sub>L</sub> of pits/marks compromises the benefits of the
second embodiment, the upper limit of the minimum size P<sub>L</sub> 
is 0.36λ/NA, which is slightly larger than the resolution
limit, and preferably up to 0.27λ/NA.</p>
    <p num="0023">In the second embodiment, the laser beam irradiated
for readout should have a power Pr of at least 1.0 mW,
preferably at least 1.4 mW, more preferably at least 2.0
mW, and even more preferably at least 2.2 mW. In the
situation that the wavelength λ and the numerical aperture
NA are within the limited ranges according to the second
embodiment, when pits/marks having the above-defined size
approximate to the resolution limit corresponding to the λ
and NA are read out, a satisfactory C/N is available as
long as the readout power Pr is within the range limited by
the second embodiment.</p>
    <p num="0024">It is noted that in the first and second embodiments,
no particular upper limit is imposed on the readout power
Pr. In general, the C/N becomes higher as the readout
powder Pr increases. However, if the readout power Pr is
high, the functional layer can be degraded by readout
operation or repetition thereof. With a high readout power
Pr, a reflected light detecting system of the medium
readout apparatus can be saturated when the medium has a
certain reflectance, disabling readout operation. These
restraints impose a substantial upper limit on the readout
power Pr.</p>
    <p num="0025">Although the reason why the C/N is significantly
improved in proximity to the resolution limit by providing
the functional layer is not well understood, the inventors
believe that the mechanism described below participates
therein.</p>
    <p num="0026">The inventors presume as follows. When a laser beam
is irradiated to pits/marks, electric fields are created
around the pits/marks as shown in FIG. 2. The intensity of
the electric field or the extent to which the electric
field covers is correlated to the energy density on the
laser beam irradiated surface, that is, the energy per unit
area of the irradiated surface and the material of which 
the irradiated surface is made. When the distance between
adjacent pits/marks is relatively short, an interaction
occurs between the electric fields of adjacent pits/marks,
which enables super-resolution readout. This electric
field is likely to generate near an edge when a structure
has an edge like pits. The electric field is also likely
to generate at the site where dielectric constant or
electric conductivity sharply changes, such as the boundary
between crystalline and amorphous phases, like the outer
periphery of amorphous recorded marks in phase change
optical recording media.</p>
    <p num="0027">The interaction depends on the energy density of the
laser beam. Then the interaction becomes stronger in
proportion to the readout power Pr, if the readout
wavelength λ and the numerical aperture NA of the readout
optical system are the same. As a consequence, the C/N
becomes higher as the readout power Pr increases. Besides,
the laser beam spot diameter is in proportion to λ/NA,
which indicates that with the readout power Pr kept fixed,
the C/N becomes higher as the readout wavelength λ is
shorter and as the numerical aperture NA is larger.
Inversely, if λ/NA is small, an equivalent C/N is
obtainable with a lower readout power Pr.</p>
    <p num="0028">On the other hand, when the distance between adjacent
pits/marks is relatively long, the above-described
interaction does not occur, or only a little interaction
occurs if any, or the signal component produced by the
interaction is small as compared with the signal component
produced by ordinary readout operation. As a result, the
C/N improvement dependent on the readout power Pr is not
ascertained or is extremely little if any.</p>
    <p num="0029">It is noted that for a medium having a mask layer
(described in the preamble), as is evident from the
operation principle of the mask layer, effects are achieved
only when pits or recorded marks, which are objects to be
read out, have a small size below the resolution limit. 
The medium fails to produce a higher C/N than the prior art
mask layer-free media when the objects to be read out have
a size slightly larger than the resolution limit.</p>
    <p num="0030">The present invention is of great worth in the
industry. Optical discs featuring the highest recording
density among the currently available optical discs are
DVD. DVD-RW, which is DVD for Re-Recordable Disc, has a
phase change recording layer, which functions as the
functional layer. For the readout operation of DVD-RW, the
readout wavelength λ and numerical aperture NA fall within
the second embodiment of the invention. Therefore, the
application of the second embodiment to DVD-RW enables
super-resolution readout and significantly improves the C/N
in proximity to the resolution limit.</p>
    <p num="0031">The inventors carried out an experiment of applying
the second embodiment of the invention to a commercially
available DVD-RW disc (manufactured by TDK Corporation).
In this experiment, the readout wavelength λ was 650 nm,
and the objective lens of the readout optical system had a
numerical aperture NA of 0.60 according to the DVD-RW
standards. The results are shown in FIG. 3. In FIG. 3,
when the readout power Pr is 1 mW, a C/N of about 20 to 30
dB is obtained at a mark length of 0.28 to 0.3 µm which is
approximate to the resolution limit (0.271 µm). Also in
FIG. 3, when the readout power Pr is 2.4 mW, a C/N of about
40 dB is obtained at a mark length of 0.28 to 0.3 µm which
is approximate to the resolution limit, indicating that
fully practical readout is possible. Namely, the present
invention permits a conventional optical disc to achieve a
substantial C/N improvement in proximity to the resolution
limit simply by increasing the readout power Pr.</p>
    <p num="0032">In the disclosure, the medium is considered readable
(readout is possible) when a C/N of at least 20 dB is
obtained. For the medium to find practical use, a C/N of
preferably at least about 30 dB and more preferably at
least about 40 dB is necessary. </p>
    <p num="0033">FIG. 4 is a graph of C/N versus readout power Pr when
recorded marks of different length are read out in the
above-described DVD-RW disc. It is evident from FIG. 4
that the C/N improves in proximity to the resolution limit
as the readout power Pr increases.</p>
    <p num="0034">The inventors also carried out an experiment of
applying the second embodiment of the invention to a read-only
memory (ROM) type disc. This ROM disc includes a
resin substrate on which pits having a length shown in FIG.
5 are arrayed in rows, a Ge layer of 15 nm thick formed
thereon as a reflecting and functional layer, and a
protective layer formed thereon of a UV-curable resin to a
thickness of 10 µm. In the pit row, the space between
adjacent pits is equal to the length of pits.</p>
    <p num="0035">For C/N measurement, readout operation was carried
out on the ROM disc using a laser beam having a readout
wavelength λ of 635 nm and the objective lens of the
readout optical system having a numerical aperture NA of
0.60. The results are shown in FIG. 5. Under these
readout conditions, pits having a length of 0.3 µm are, for
the most part, readable, but their size is approximate to
the resolution limit (0.265 µm), and pits having a length
of 0.25 µm or less are, for the most part, unreadable.
FIG. 5 shows C/N as a function of pit length when the
readout power is 1 mW or 5 mW. It is seen from FIG. 5 that
at a pit length of 0.4 µm or more, approximately equal C/N
is obtainable from both the readout powers, but at a pit
length of 0.3 µm or less, the C/N increases as the readout
power rises. More specifically, when pits having a length
of 0.2 to 0.3 µm are to be read out, the readout power of 1
mW provides a C/N of less than 40 dB, and the readout power
of 5 mW provides a C/N of more than 40 dB, indicating that
fully practical readout is possible.</p>
    <p num="0036"><b>FIG. 6</b> shows C/N as a function of a readout power
when the pit length is 0.3 µm, 0.25 µm or 0.2 µm. It is
clearly seen from FIG. 6 that when pits having a size which 
is generally readable and approximate to the resolution
limit are to be read out, the C/N improves in proportion to
the increasing readout power.</p>
    <p num="0037">FIGS. 7 and 8 show the results of an experiment
demonstrating the benefits of the first embodiment of the
invention. This experiment used an optical disc having a
phase change recording layer, a readout wavelength λ of 405
nm and a numerical aperture NA of 0.85.</p>
    <p num="0038">FIG. 7 is a graph of C/N versus mark length when the
readout power Pr is 0.5 mW in accordance with the first
embodiment of the invention and 0.3 mW outside the scope of
the invention. FIG. 8 is a graph of C/N versus readout
power Pr when recorded marks of different length are read
out. FIGS. 7 and 8 demonstrate the benefits of the
invention, and it is also evident from FIGS. 7 and 8 that
in proximity to the resolution limit (0.119 µm), the C/N
improves as the readout power Pr rises.</p>
    <p num="0039">It is noted that the optical disc used in the
experiment the results of which are shown in FIGS. 7 and 8
includes a reflective layer, a second dielectric layer, a
recording layer, a first dielectric layer and a light
transmitting layer stacked in order on a supporting
substrate. Recording/reading light enters the recording
layer through the light transmitting layer. The supporting
substrate used was a polycarbonate disc having a diameter
of 120 mm and a thickness of 1.2 mm in which grooves are
formed at the same time as injection molding of the disc
itself. The reflective layer was 100 nm thick and formed
of Ag<sub>98</sub>Pd<sub>1</sub>Cu<sub>1</sub>. The second dielectric layer was 20 nm thick
and formed of Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>. The recording layer was 12 nm thick
and had the composition (atomic ratio) of

In<sub>1.1</sub>Sb<sub>74.6</sub>Te<sub>18.6</sub>Ge<sub>5.7</sub>. The first dielectric layer was 130 nm
thick and formed of 80 mol% ZnS and 20 mol% SiO<sub>2</sub>. The
light transmitting layer was 100 µm thick and formed by
spin coating a UV-curable resin, followed by UV curing.</p>
    <p num="0040">As the benefits of the invention are accomplished 
with not only recording media, but also read-only media
according to the second embodiment using the readout
optical system having a large λ/NA value, the benefits of
the invention are also accomplished with read-only media
according to the first embodiment using the readout optical
system having a small λ/NA value.</p>
    <p num="0041">The optical information medium according to the
invention has an information recording layer. The
information recording layer used herein is a layer that has
projections and depressions in the form of pits and/or
grooves, a layer where recorded marks can be formed, or a
layer that has projections and depressions and can form
recorded marks. This suggests that the invention is
applicable to both read-only media and optical recording
media (write-once or rewritable media). In the read-only
media, a reflective layer covering pits formed in a
substrate surface and composed of a metal, metalloid or
compound constitutes the information recording layer. In
the optical recording media, the recording layer
constitutes the information recording layer. The recording
layer may be any of a phase change layer, a layer based on
an organic dye, and a layer based on another organic
material or inorganic material. The recorded marks may
take the form of areas having a different optical constant
(e.g., reflectance) from the surrounding, concave areas or
convex areas.</p>
    <p num="0042">We have found that by providing an optical
information medium with a layer constructed of a specific
material and having an appropriate thickness for the
specific material, the optical information medium is given
a capability of super-resolution readout based on a
mechanism essentially different from the prior art and that
pits or recorded marks having a size somewhat larger than
the resolution limit can be read out at a significantly
higher C/N than in the prior art. The specific material
used herein is at least one element selected from among Nb, 
Mo, W, Mn, Pt, C, Si, Ge, Ti, Zr, V, Cr, Fe, Co, Ni, Pd,
Sb, Ta, Al, In, Cu, Sn, Te, Zn, and Bi or an alloy or
compound containing that element or elements, with the
element or compound thereof being preferred. Herein, the
layer capable of super-resolution readout is designated a
functional layer. The provision of the functional layer
enables to detect pits, grooves or recorded marks of a size
falling below the resolution limit determined by light
diffraction. As previously described, the information
recording layer can be utilized as the functional layer in
the practice of the invention.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Application to medium structure of FIG. 1</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0043">Referring to FIG. 1, there is illustrated one
exemplary construction of the optical information medium.
The optical information medium 1 shown in FIG. 1 is a read-only
medium including a light-transmissive substrate 2
having pits 21 formed on a surface and a layer 10 in close
contact with the pitted surface. Reading light comes from
below in the figure. The layer 10 serves as the functional
layer when it has a specific composition and a specific
thickness.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Layer 10 made of element or alloy</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0044">Optical disc samples of the structure shown in FIG. 1
were fabricated by the following procedure. The substrate
2 used was a disc which was injection molded from
polycarbonate (refractive index n = 1.58) to a diameter of
120 mm and a thickness of 0.6 mm in which phase pits were
formed simultaneous with injection molding. The substrate
2 is of the banded type that the substrate is provided with
a plurality of annular pit-forming regions having helical
tracks in a concentric pattern, and pits have an equal
length in each pit-forming region. Namely, phase pits of
different lengths are formed in a single substrate. The
pit length in each pit-forming region is 250 nm. The space
between adjacent pits is equal to the pit length. The
layer 10 was constructed of any one element selected from 
among Nb, Mo, W, Mn, Pt, C, Si, Ge, Ti, Zr, V, Cr, Fe, Co,
Ni, Pd, Sb, Ta, Al, In, Cu, Sn, Te, Zn, Bi, Au and Ag and
has a thickness of 5 to 100 nm. The layer 10 was formed by
sputtering.</p>
    <p num="0045">Using an optical disc tester (laser wavelength 635 nm
and numerical aperture 0.60), these samples were measured
for carrier to noise (C/N) ratio at a linear velocity of 11
m/s and a readout power changing in the range of 1 to 7 mW.
Since the optical disc tester used has a cutoff spatial
frequency 2NA/λ, which is calculated to be:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">2NA/λ = 1.89x10<st32:sup pos="post">3</st32:sup> (line pairs/mm),</st32:df>
rows of pits in which the pit length is equal to the space
between adjacent pits are readable as long as the spatial
frequency is equal to or below 1.89x10<sup>3</sup> (line pairs/mm).
The pit length (= space length) P<sub>L</sub> corresponding to the
readable spatial frequency is given as
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">P<st32:sub pos="post">L</st32:sub> ≥ λ/4NA = 265 (nm).</st32:df>
It is then concluded that super-resolution readout is
possible if a C/N is obtained from a pit row with a pit
length of less than 265 nm.</p>
    <p num="0046">Tables 1 to 4 show the relationship of C/N to the
thickness of the layer 10. In Tables 1 to 4, the highest
C/N obtained from the layer 10 of a certain thickness when
the readout power is changed between 1 mW and 7 mW is
reported for each of different materials of which the layer
10 is made. Table 1 picks up those samples which show a
maximum C/N of at least 40 dB, Table 2 picks up those
samples which show a maximum C/N of 30 dB to less than 40
dB, Table 3 picks up those samples which show a maximum C/N
of 20 dB to less than 30 dB, and Table 4 picks up those
samples which show a maximum C/N of less than 20 dB. <tables><table><tgroup cols="8"><tbody><row><entry nameend="8" namest="1">C/N (dB) versus thickness of layer 10 ( maximum C/N ≥ 40 dB)</entry></row><row><entry align="left" namest="1">Layer 10 Material</entry><entry nameend="8" align="left" namest="2">Thickness of layer 10 (nm)</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">15</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">100</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Nb</entry><entry align="center">38.4</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">34.3</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">44.1</entry><entry align="center">40.3</entry><entry align="center">32.8</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Mo</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">41.2</entry><entry align="center">43.0</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">39.6</entry><entry align="center">26.4</entry><entry align="center">9.2</entry></row><row><entry align="center">W</entry><entry align="center">32.2</entry><entry align="center">43.0</entry><entry align="center">43.6</entry><entry align="center">38.2</entry><entry align="center">32.7</entry><entry align="center">24.3</entry><entry align="center">7.7</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Mn</entry><entry align="center">33.2</entry><entry align="center">37.6</entry><entry align="center">35.3</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">40.7</entry><entry align="center">35.1</entry><entry align="center">22.7</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Pt</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">39.1</entry><entry align="center">40.2</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">30.2</entry><entry align="center">13.2</entry><entry align="center">4.3</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C</entry><entry align="center">33.2</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">40.9</entry><entry align="center">40.9</entry><entry align="center">31.0</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Si</entry><entry align="center">45.5</entry><entry align="center">43.2</entry><entry align="center">47.1</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">41.4</entry><entry align="center">44.9</entry><entry align="center">40.5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Ge</entry><entry align="center">37.4</entry><entry align="center">41.3</entry><entry align="center">45.0</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">44.4</entry><entry align="center">42.5</entry><entry align="center">40.7</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="8"><tbody><row><entry nameend="8" namest="1">C/N (dB) versus thickness of layer 10 (40 dB &gt; maximum C/N ≥ 30 dB)</entry></row><row><entry align="left" namest="1">Layer 10 Material</entry><entry nameend="8" align="left" namest="2">Thickness of layer 10 (nm)</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">15</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ti</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">29.6</entry><entry align="center">35.4</entry><entry align="center">37.2</entry><entry align="center">37.5</entry><entry align="center">37.4</entry><entry align="center">29.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Zr</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">20.9</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">36.7</entry><entry align="center">28.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">V</entry><entry align="center">33.1</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">31.1</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">36.6</entry><entry align="center">39.6</entry><entry align="center">32.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Cr</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">35.2</entry><entry align="center">26.8</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">20.4</entry><entry align="center">11.1</entry><entry align="center">4.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fe</entry><entry align="center">28.6</entry><entry align="center">29.5</entry><entry align="center">35.8</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">35.2</entry><entry align="center">29.4</entry><entry align="center">7.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Co</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">31.8</entry><entry align="center">37.0</entry><entry align="center">39.4</entry><entry align="center">35.9</entry><entry align="center">26.3</entry><entry align="center">6.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ni</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">36.3</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">37.1</entry><entry align="center">28.8</entry><entry align="center">5.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Pd</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">32.8</entry><entry align="center">38.0</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">31.4</entry><entry align="center">14.5</entry><entry align="center">5.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sb</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">29.4</entry><entry align="center">35.6</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">36.1</entry><entry align="center">33.3</entry><entry align="center">23.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ta</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">23.3</entry><entry align="center">25.0</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">31.5</entry><entry align="center">33.8</entry><entry align="center">21.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Al</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">34.9</entry><entry align="center">26.4</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">0.0</entry><entry align="center">0.0</entry><entry align="center">0.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">In</entry><entry align="center">33.6</entry><entry align="center">24.2</entry><entry align="center">21.3</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">27.9</entry><entry align="center">25.9</entry><entry align="center">22.2</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="8"><tbody><row><entry nameend="8" namest="1">C/N (dB) versus thickness of layer 10 (30 dB &gt; maximum C/N ≥ 20 dB)</entry></row><row><entry align="left" namest="1">Layer 10 Material</entry><entry nameend="8" align="left" namest="2">Thickness of layer 10 (nm)</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="left">15</entry><entry align="left">20</entry><entry align="left">30</entry><entry align="left">50</entry><entry align="left">100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Cu</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">21.9</entry><entry align="center">0.0</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">7.6</entry><entry align="center">9.3</entry><entry align="center">8.6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sn</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">25.5</entry><entry align="center">26.9</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">21.0</entry><entry align="center">9.9</entry><entry align="center">3.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Te</entry><entry align="center">28.0</entry><entry align="center">23.6</entry><entry align="center">25.9</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">27.0</entry><entry align="center">24.0</entry><entry align="center">18.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Zn</entry><entry align="center">0.0</entry><entry align="center">0.0</entry><entry align="center">12.8</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">0.0</entry><entry align="center">29.0</entry><entry align="center">10.6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Bi</entry><entry align="center">0.0</entry><entry align="center">0.0</entry><entry align="center">0.0</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">13.0</entry><entry align="center">23.7</entry><entry align="center">11.4</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="8"><tbody><row><entry nameend="8" namest="1">C/N (dB) versus thickness of layer 10 (maximum C/N &lt; 20 dB)</entry></row><row><entry align="left" namest="1">Layer 10 Material</entry><entry nameend="8" align="left" namest="2">Thickness of layer 10 (nm)</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">15</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">100</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Ag</entry><entry align="center">19.2</entry><entry align="center">7.4</entry><entry align="center">7.8</entry><entry align="center">_</entry><entry align="center">0.0</entry><entry align="center">0.0</entry><entry align="center">0.0</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Au</entry><entry align="center">12.2</entry><entry align="center">8.9</entry><entry align="center">5.5</entry><entry align="center">4.9</entry><entry align="center">8.3</entry><entry align="center">5.5</entry><entry align="center">7.1</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p>
    <p num="0047">It is evident from Tables 1 to 4 that the thickness
of the layer 10 must be optimized for a particular element
used in order that super-resolution readout become
possible. For example, as seen from Table 2, super-resolution
readout is possible when the layer 10 is an Al
layer and has a thickness of 15 nm. However, when the Al
layer has a thickness of 100 nm, which is approximate to
the thickness of the reflective layer in conventional ROM
discs such as CD-ROM and DVD-ROM, super-resolution readout
becomes impossible like conventional ROM discs.</p>
    <p num="0048">Only for those samples producing a maximum C/N among
the above samples, FIGS. 9 to 12 show C/N relative to
readout power Pr. The samples shown in FIGS. 9 to 12
correspond to the samples shown in Tables 1 to 4,
respectively. The C/N was measured on a pit row with a pit
length of 250 nm. The C/N measurement used the same
optical disc tester as above and a linear velocity of 11
m/s. It is seen from FIGS. 9 to 12 that in most samples,
C/N increases with an increasing readout power. Although
the signal intensity is not shown in these diagrams, the
signal intensity shows the same behavior as the C/N. In
FIGS. 9 to 12, the samples lacking data on the high Pr
region are those samples which failed to produce readout
signals on account of degradation of the layer 10 at such
Pr or mean that no data were available due to saturation of
the reflected light detecting system of the tester.</p>
    <p num="0049">Further, a sample having the layer 10 made of a
tungsten-molybdenum (W-Mo) alloy having a thickness of 15
nm was measured for C/N along a pit row with a pit length
of 250 nm using the same optical disc tester as above at a
linear velocity of 11 m/s. The results are shown in FIG.
13. It is seen from FIG. 13 that super-resolution readout
is also possible when an alloy is used.</p>
    <p num="0050">It is noted that although the above experiments
evaluated C/N for those media having rows of pits whose
size was smaller than the resolution limit, similar effects 
were accomplished for those media having rows of pits whose
size was equal to or greater than the resolution limit and
equal to or less than 0.31λ/NA. Namely, when the thickness
of the layer 10 is properly set in accordance with the
particular material thereof, a C/N improvement over media
having an aluminum layer of 100 nm thick is observable.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Layer 10 made of compound</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0051">Even when the layer 10 is constructed of various
compounds such as nitrides, oxides, fluorides, sulfides,
and carbides, the optical information medium of the
invention is also capable of super-resolution readout and
capable of improving C/N in reading out objects having a
size slightly larger than the resolution limit, and
intrinsic effects are exerted. It is noted that the
compounds used herein are not limited to stoichiometric
compounds and encompass mixtures of metals or metalloids
with nitrogen, oxygen, etc. in a proportion less than the
stoichiometric composition. Namely, the layer 10 falls
within the scope of the invention that contains a metal or
metalloid which is capable of super-resolution readout when
used in an elemental or alloy form and additionally,
another element, preferably at least one element selected
from among nitrogen, oxygen, fluorine, sulfur and carbon.
The construction of the layer 10 from such compounds is
effective for spreading the readout power margin, improving
the C/N, and suppressing degradation of C/N by repetitive
reading. For the layer 10 constructed of compounds,
operation and results are described below.</p>
    <p num="0052">First, the improvement in chemical stability of the
layer 10 due to compound formation is described together
with the concomitant advantages. In general, metals
excluding noble metals (e.g., Au) or metalloids naturally
produce in the form of compounds such as oxides and
sulfides. This fact indicates that in the ordinary
environment, metals or metalloids are more stable when
present in compound form than in pure elemental form. That 
is, metals or metalloids are significantly improved in
chemical stability by converting them into compounds. On
the other hand, the degradation of the layer 10 by high
power reading and repetitive reading is presumably due to a
chemical change (typically oxidation) caused by a
temperature rise of the layer 10. Since the layer 10 is in
contact with air, it is susceptible to degradation by
heating during application of readout power. However, if
the layer 10 is formed of a compound, it is restrained from
a chemical change. Then, reading becomes possible with a
higher power, the maximum C/N is improved, and the
degradation of C/N by repetitive reading is restrained.
Therefore, the formation of the layer 10 from a compound is
quite effective when a material which undergoes degradation
at a relatively low readout power is used.</p>
    <p num="0053">Next, the increase in transparency of the layer 10
due to compound formation is described together with the
concomitant advantages. When the layer 10 is formed of a
compound, its transparency increases, and its optical
reflectance lowers accordingly. When the layer 10 is
reduced in optical reflectance, it becomes unlikely that
the reflected light detecting system is saturated. This
results in an increase of the permissible readout power and
hence an improvement in maximum C/N. Since the layer 10
formed of a compound is improved in transparency per unit
thickness, the layer 10 of a compound avoids saturation of
the reflected light detecting system even when the layer 10
is made thicker. For this reason, the thickness range of
the layer 10 within which super-resolution readout is
possible is significantly expanded. Therefore, the
formation of the layer 10 from a compound is quite
effective when a material which causes the reflected light
detecting system to be saturated at a relatively low
readout power is used.</p>
    <p num="0054">In order that the layer 10 be formed of a compound,
use is preferably made of a reactive sputtering technique 
using a reactive gas such as nitrogen or oxygen or a
sputtering technique using a compound target. Other
techniques such as CVD may also be utilized.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Thickness of layer 10</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0055">As seen from the results of the above-described
experiments, the layer which is constructed of an elemental
metal or metalloid should preferably have the following
thickness, which is given for the respective elements.
<sl><li>Nb: up to 100 nm</li><li>Mo: up to 70 nm, especially up to 45 nm</li><li>W: up to 70 nm, especially up to 40 nm</li><li>Mn: up to 100 nm, especially up to 70 nm</li><li>Pt: up to 40 nm, especially up to 30 nm</li><li>C: up to 100 nm</li><li>Si: up to 100 nm</li><li>Ge: up to 100 nm</li><li>Ti: up to 100 nm</li><li>Zr: up to 100 nm, especially 25 to 100 nm</li><li>V: up to 100 nm</li><li>Cr: up to 30 nm, especially less than 15 nm</li><li>Fe: up to 80 nm, especially up to 50 nm</li><li>Co: up to 70 nm, especially up to 45 nm</li><li>Ni: up to 70 nm, especially up to 50 nm</li><li>Pd: up to 40 nm, especially up to 30 nm</li><li>Sb: up to 100 nm, especially up to 60 nm</li><li>Ta: up to 100 nm, especially up to 60 nm</li><li>Al: up to 20 nm, especially less than 15 nm</li><li>In: up to 100 nm, especially less than 10 nm</li><li>Cu: up to 10 nm</li><li>Sn: up to 40 nm</li><li>Te: up to 70 nm</li><li>Zn: 40 to 90 nm</li><li>Bi: 25 to 70 nm</li></sl>
It is noted that for those elements which produce a
satisfactorily high C/N even at a thickness of 100 nm, the
thickness upper limit of 100 nm need not be set from the 
performance standpoint, but limiting the thickness to 100
nm or less is preferred for preventing a productivity drop.
Also preferably, the layer 10 should have a thickness of at
least 2 nm regardless of the element of which the layer is
made. If the layer 10 is too thin, the reflectance may
become too low for the tracking servo system to perform
well, failing to produce a satisfactory C/N.</p>
    <p num="0056">When the layer 10 is formed of compounds, the
appropriate thickness range of the layer 10 is expanded as
described above.</p>
    <p num="0057">Now the functional layer constructed by an alloy is
described. By the term "functional element" used below is
meant an element which alone can construct the functional
layer.</p>
    <p num="0058">When the functional layer is constructed by a binary
alloy in the simple solid solution form as typified by the
above-described W-Mo alloy wherein both the elements are
functional elements, the alloy layer serves as the
functional layer as seen from FIG. 13.</p>
    <p num="0059">For an alloy layer in the simple solid solution form,
it is desired that at least one, preferably all of the
constituent elements be functional elements. The molar
proportion of functional elements is preferably at least
50% of the entire constituent elements.</p>
    <p num="0060">Like the alloy layer in the simple solid solution
form, it is desired for an amorphous alloy layer such as a
magneto-optical recording material layer that at least one,
preferably all of the constituent elements be functional
elements. The molar proportion of functional elements is
preferably at least 50% of the entire constituent elements.</p>
    <p num="0061">Ag-In-Sb-Te base phase change materials are phase
separation type alloys in which the Sb phase separates from
other phases upon crystallization. For such a phase
separation type alloy, it is desired that at least one,
preferably all of the constituent phases can construct a
functional layer alone. For example, the Sb phase in a 
crystallized Ag-In-Sb-Te alloy serves as a functional layer
alone.</p>
    <p num="0062">Like the single element layer, the alloy layer must
satisfy the thickness requirement in order to serve as the
functional layer. For example, the alloy layer in the
simple solid solution form may be set to a sufficient
thickness for a single element layer of each functional
element to serve as the functional layer, as shown in FIG.
13.</p>
    <p num="0063">The specific composition and thickness of an alloy
layer are preferably determined only after it is actually
inspected whether an alloy layer having a particular
composition and thickness serves as the functional layer.
For example, intermetallic compounds such as the above-described
phase change material of Ge<sub>2</sub>Sb<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>5</sub> often exhibit a
behavior unexpected from the respective constituent
elements alone.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Reading method</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0064">In the medium of the invention, an upper limit is
imposed on the applicable readout power, depending on the
material of the layer 10 and the structure of the medium.
It is therefore convenient that an optimum readout power
for these conditions is previously recorded in the medium
of the invention. Then, the optimum readout power can be
read out before the start of reading operation, and the
reading operation be performed with this optimum power.
Also, if necessary, a trial reading operation may be
performed to determine the optimum readout power.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>An information readout method for an optical
information medium comprising an information recording
layer having pits or recorded marks representative of
information data, said method comprising the step of
irradiating a laser beam to the information recording layer
through an objective lens for providing readings of the
pits or recorded marks, wherein
   when the laser beam having a wavelength λ of 400 to
410 nm is irradiated through the objective lens having a
numerical aperture NA of 0.70 to 0.85 to the pits or
recorded marks having a minimum size PL of up to 0.36λ/NA,
the laser beam is given a power Pr of at least 0.4 mW.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>The information readout method of claim 1 wherein the
minimum size PL is up to 0.31λ/NA.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>The information readout method of claim 1 or 2
wherein the minimum size PL is at least 0.25λ/NA.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>The information readout method of any one of claims 1
to 3 wherein the power Pr is at least 0.45 mW.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>The information readout method of any one of claims 1
to 3 wherein the power Pr is at least 0.5 mW.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>An information readout method for an optical
information medium comprising an information recording
layer having pits or recorded marks representative of
information data, said method comprising the step of
irradiating a laser beam to the information recording layer
through an objective lens for providing readings of the
pits or recorded marks, wherein
   when the laser beam having a wavelength λ of 630 to
670 nm is irradiated through the objective lens having a
numerical aperture NA of 0.60 to 0.65 to the pits or
recorded marks having a minimum size PL of up to 0.36λ/NA,
the laser beam is given a power Pr of at least 1.0 mW.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>The information readout method of claim 6 wherein the
minimum size PL is up to 0.27λ/NA.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>The information readout method of claim 6 or 7
wherein the minimum size PL is at least 0.25λ/NA.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>The information readout method of any one of claims 6
to 8 wherein the power Pr is at least 1.4 mW.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="10">
      <claim-text>The information readout method of any one of claims 6
to 8 wherein the power Pr is at least 2.0 mW.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="11">
      <claim-text>The information readout method of any one of claims 6
to 8 wherein the power Pr is at least 2.2 mW.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="12">
      <claim-text>A readout apparatus used in the information readout
method of any one of claims 1 to 5.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="13">
      <claim-text>A readout apparatus used in the information readout
method of any one of claims 6 to 11.</claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
