<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE patent-document PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.ir-facility.org/dtds/patents/v1.4/patent-document.dtd">
<patent-document ucid="EP-1245384-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1245384" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="18945113" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021002">
  <bibliographic-data>
    <publication-reference ucid="EP-1245384-A2" status="new" fvid="23563330">
      <document-id status="new" format="original">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>1245384</doc-number>
        <kind>A2</kind>
        <date>20021002</date>
      </document-id>
    </publication-reference>
    <application-reference ucid="EP-02090123-A" status="new" is-representative="NO">
      <document-id status="new" format="epo">
        <country>EP</country>
        <doc-number>02090123</doc-number>
        <kind>A</kind>
        <date>20020326</date>
      </document-id>
    </application-reference>
    <priority-claims status="new">
      <priority-claim ucid="JP-2001090312-A" status="new">
        <document-id status="new" format="epo">
          <country>JP</country>
          <doc-number>2001090312</doc-number>
          <kind>A</kind>
          <date>20010327</date>
        </document-id>
      </priority-claim>
    </priority-claims>
    <technical-data status="new">
      <classifications-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41C   1/10        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
        <classification-ipcr status="new">B41C   1/10        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr>
      </classifications-ipcr>
      <classification-ecla status="new">
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41C   1/10P</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41C   1/10S</classification-symbol>
        <classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L41P227:700</classification-symbol>
      </classification-ecla>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Bildaufzeichnungsteuervorrichtung in einer Mehrfarbendruckmaschine</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Image exposure control apparatus in multicolor printing press</invention-title>
      <invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Dispositif de commande d'exposition d'images dans une presse d'impression polychrome</invention-title>
    </technical-data>
    <parties>
      <applicants>
        <applicant status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KOMORI PRINTING MACH</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>KOMORI CORPORATION</name>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
        <applicant status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Komori Corporation</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>11-1, Azumabashi 3-chome</street>
              <city>Sumida-ku Tokyo</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </applicant>
      </applicants>
      <inventors>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ENDO YASUJI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="epo">
          <addressbook>
            <name>FUSEKI TAKASHI</name>
            <address>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>ENDO, YASUJI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="intermediate">
          <addressbook>
            <name>FUSEKI, TAKASHI</name>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>ENDO, YASUJI, C/O TORIDE PLANT</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Komori Corporatio, 5-1, Higashi 4-chome</street>
              <city>Toride-shi, Ibaraki</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
        <inventor status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Fuseki, Takashi, C/O Toride Plant</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Komori Corporatio, 5-1, Higashi 4-chome</street>
              <city>Toride-shi, Ibaraki</city>
              <country>JP</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </inventor>
      </inventors>
      <agents>
        <agent status="new" format="original">
          <addressbook>
            <last-name>Patentanwälte Wenzel &amp;amp; Kalkoff</last-name>
            <address>
              <street>Grubesallee 26</street>
              <city>22143 Hamburg</city>
              <country>DE</country>
            </address>
          </addressbook>
        </agent>
      </agents>
    </parties>
    <international-convention-data>
      <designated-states>
        <ep-contracting-states>
          <country>AT</country>
          <country>BE</country>
          <country>CH</country>
          <country>CY</country>
          <country>DE</country>
          <country>DK</country>
          <country>ES</country>
          <country>FI</country>
          <country>FR</country>
          <country>GB</country>
          <country>GR</country>
          <country>IE</country>
          <country>IT</country>
          <country>LI</country>
          <country>LU</country>
          <country>MC</country>
          <country>NL</country>
          <country>PT</country>
          <country>SE</country>
          <country>TR</country>
        </ep-contracting-states>
      </designated-states>
    </international-convention-data>
  </bibliographic-data>
  <abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <p>An image exposure control apparatus includes a
memory (110h-110o) and an adjustment section (110a).
The memory (110j,110k) stores a
correction amount for each color in accordance with a
stretch amount of a printing paper sheet in multicolor
printing operation. The adjustment section (110a) adjusts an
exposure position of a pixel of an image to be exposed
for each color, on the basis of the correction amount
read out from said memory means (110j,110k), in exposing the image
on a printing plate.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="108"/></p>
  </abstract>
  <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Background of the Invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0001">The present invention relates to a control
apparatus for an image exposure apparatus which exposes
an image on a printing plate, an image exposure
apparatus, and a control apparatus which controls a
multicolor printing press.</p>
    <heading>[Plate Making on Press]</heading>
    <p num="0002">In recent years, in order to improve the
efficiency of plate making operation or to improve the
registration accuracy, a plate making apparatus is
attached to a printing press itself whereby plate making
operation is directly performed on the printing press by
the plate making apparatus. That is, instead of using a
plate making apparatus separated from a printing press,
a printing plate (raw plate) mounted on a plate cylinder
is irradiated with a laser beam from the head of a plate
making apparatus attached to a printing unit, thereby
exposing an image. This operation is called plate
making on press.</p>
    <p num="0003">More specifically, the rotation speed of the
printing press is increased to a designated value. When
the rotational speed has stabilized, laser irradiation 
(exposure) from the head to the printing plate is
started. After that, the head is moved in the axial
direction of the plate cylinder while continuing
exposure, thereby exposing an image on the entire plate
mounted on the plate cylinder. The exposure time is
determined by the plate size and the designated
rotational speed at the time of exposure. Techniques
for exposing an image on a printing plate by laser
irradiation are disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 5,379,698
(reference 1) and the like, and a detailed description
thereof will be omitted.</p>
    <p num="0004">Fig. 4 shows the attached state of plate
making apparatuses to a four-color rotary printing
press. Referring to Fig. 4, plate making apparatuses
102-1 to 102-4 are attached to printing units 101-1 to
101-4 of the respective colors. The plate making
apparatuses 102-1 to 102-4 are normally at positions
indicated by the alternate long and two dashed lines in
Fig. 4. When exposure operation is to be performed,
they are moved close to plate cylinders 103-1 to 103-4
in the printing units 101-1 to 101-4. Reference
numerals 104-1 to 104-4 denote blanket cylinders on
which blankets are mounted. Impression cylinders (not
shown) are arranged under the blanket cylinders 104-1 to
104-4.</p>
    <p num="0005">Fig. 5 shows main part of a plate making
apparatus 102. The plate making apparatus 102 has an 
exposure unit 102b having a head 102a. The exposure
unit 102b is fixed on a table 102c. The table 102c
moves in the axial direction (indicated by a
double-headed arrow A-B) of a plate cylinder 103 while
being guided along rails 102f1 and 102f2 on a base 102f
by a ball screw 102e rotated by a motor 102d. A
printing plate (raw plate) 105 is mounted on the surface
of the plate cylinder 103.</p>
    <p num="0006">In plate making on press, the exposure range
of an image onto the printing plate 105 is set before
the start of actual image exposure by causing an
operator to input the X-coordinate distance (X1,0) from
the origin (0,0) at the left edge on the leading edge
side of the printing plate 105 to the left edge of the
image range and the Y-coordinate distance (0,Y1) to the
leading edge of the image range, as shown in Fig. 6.
That is, let W be the image size in the X-axis
direction, and H be the image size in the Y-axis
direction. The origin (0,0) is defined at the left edge
on the leading edge side of the printing plate 105. The
image range is defined by X-coordinates "X1" and "X1 +
W" and Y-coordinates "Y1" and "Y1 + H".</p>
    <p num="0007">Assume that the number of pixels of the image
is n in the X-axis direction and m in the Y-axis
direction, as shown in Fig. 7. A distance ΔX between
the pixels in the X-axis direction is given by ΔX =
W/n, and a distance ΔY between the pixels in the Y-axis 
direction is given by ΔY = H/m. The plate making
apparatus 102 defines ΔX and ΔY as the exposure
intervals in the X- and Y-axis directions and exposes
image data that is input in advance within that image
range.</p>
    <p num="0008">More specifically, the head 102a of the plate
making apparatus 102 is moved from the left to the right
while rotating the plate cylinder 103 at a predetermined
rotational speed. The head 102a is stopped at the
position X1, and the pixels of one line in the Y
direction are exposed at the interval ΔY. That is,
pixels within the range from (X1,Y1) to (X1,Y1+H) are
exposed. Next, the head 102a is moved to the right by
ΔX. At the next position, the pixels of the next line
in the Y direction are exposed at the interval ΔY.
This operation is repeated until the X-coordinate "X1 +
W".</p>
    <p num="0009">The image data (image "1"/non-image "0") of
each pixel is not stored in correspondence with the data
of its exposure position. Only data of image
"1"/non-image "0" are sequentially stored. In actual
exposure, the image data are sequentially read out, and
the pixels are sequentially exposed from the position
(X1,Y1) at the interval ΔY in the Y direction and at
the interval ΔX in the X direction. This is because
the number of image data to be processed is enormous.
If the image data are collated with position data and 
exposed one by one, a very long time and large storage
capacity are impractically required.</p>
    <p num="0010">In printing by a rotary printing press, a high
pressure must be applied to printing paper between the
blanket cylinder and the impression cylinder. For this
reason, the printing paper stretches toward the trailing
edge side. Hence, the image printed by the preceding
printing unit expands into a wide trapezoidal shape
toward the trailing edge side, resulting in
misregistration between colors. This tendency is
especially conspicuous in offset printing because
printing is executed with water supplied.</p>
    <p num="0011">Fig. 8 shows an image state on printing paper
after printing of the second color. A printing paper
sheet 106 stretches due to printing by the second-color
printing unit, and a first-color image 107 expands into
a trapezoidal shape. For this reason, shifts are
generated between the first-color image 107 and a
second-color image 108. That is, shifts w1 and w2 in
the horizontal direction (a direction perpendicular to
the sheet convey direction) of the printing paper sheet
106, a shift h in the vertical direction (sheet convey
direction), and shifts (distortion amounts) s1 and s2
due to distortions are generated. Similarly, the
first- and second-color images further expand into
trapezoidal shapes due to printing by the third-color
printing unit. The first-, second-, and third-color 
images further expand into trapezoidal shapes due to
printing by the fourth-color printing unit. In this
way, shifts are generated between the color images,
resulting in a defective printing product.</p>
    <p num="0012">To solve this problem, the present applicant
proposed in Japanese Patent Laid-Open No. 2000-309084
(U.S. Patent No. 6,283,467; reference 2) a sheet-like
object convey apparatus which stretches the trailing
edge side of a printing paper sheet in the horizontal
direction (right-to-left direction) upon transferring
the printing paper sheet to a printing section whereby
the shape of the printing paper sheet is deformed in
advance into a trapezoidal shape whose width increases
toward the trailing edge side to eliminate or reduce
stretching of the printing paper sheet during printing,
thereby eliminating or reducing the shift of the image
due to distortion by the stretch of the printing paper
sheet during printing. The correction operation of the
sheet-like object convey apparatus disclosed in
reference 2 will be described with reference to Figs. 10
and 11.</p>
    <p num="0013">Referring to Fig. 10, when a swing 1 pivots
from a point b to a point <u style="single">a</u>, i.e., the gripping position
of a feeding cylinder 4 along with rotation of a feeding
cylinder shaft 4a, the edge portion of a paper sheet 6
is gripped by a plurality of gripper units (not shown)
each formed from a gripper and gripper pad. 
Simultaneously, the central portion of a support shaft
(not shown) that supports the gripper units is pressed
and deflected by α, as indicated by the alternate long
and two dashed line in Fig. 11. When the support shaft
deflects, the gripper units at the central portion
retreat from those on both sides by α. In this state,
when the feeding cylinder shaft 4a rotates to move the
swing 1 from the point <u style="single">a</u> to the point b, press against
the support shaft is canceled. All the gripper units
are aligned on one line, as indicated by the solid line
in Fig. 11.</p>
    <p num="0014">When the gripper units at the central portion
move, the directions of gripper units are changed toward
the left and right end sides of the paper sheet 6 from
the central portion relatively to those in gripping the
paper sheet. The paper sheet 6 is stretched to become
wide toward the trailing edge side. With this
operation, the paper sheet 6 is deformed in advance into
a trapezoidal shape whose width increases toward the
trailing edge side before printing. Since stretching
of the printing paper sheet during printing is
eliminated or reduced, the shift of the image due to
distortion by the stretch of the printing paper sheet
during printing is eliminated or reduced. Hence,
fan-out registration is corrected. Reference numeral 5
denotes a lower swing; 6a, a feedboard; and 7, an
impression cylinder. </p>
    <p num="0015">According to the sheet-like object convey
apparatus described in reference 2, of the shifts of the
image, the shifts s1 and s2 due to distortions are
corrected, as shown in Fig. 9. However, since the
shifts w1 and w2 in the horizontal direction and the
shift h in the vertical direction cannot be corrected,
defective printing products cannot be completely
avoided.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Summary of the Invention</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0016">It is an object of the present invention to
provide a control apparatus for an image exposure
apparatus, which eliminates misregistration between
colors due to stretch of a printing paper sheet and
prevents any defective printing product.</p>
    <p num="0017">In order to achieve the above object,
according to the present invention, there is provided an
image exposure control apparatus comprising memory means
for storing a correction amount for each color in
accordance with a stretch amount of a printing paper
sheet in multicolor printing operation, and adjustment
means for adjusting an exposure position of a pixel of
an image to be exposed for each color, on the basis of
the correction amount read out from the memory means, in
exposing the image on a printing plate.</p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Brief Description of the Drawings</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0018">
      <sl>
        <li>Fig. 1 is a block diagram of a control
apparatus for an image exposure apparatus according to 
an embodiment of the present invention;</li>
        <li>Fig. 2 is a block diagram of a paper convey
apparatus shown in Fig. 1;</li>
        <li>Fig. 3 is a block diagram of the image
exposure apparatus shown in Fig. 1;</li>
        <li>Fig. 4 is a side view showing the schematic
arrangement of a four-color rotary printing press to
which plate making apparatuses are attached;</li>
        <li>Fig. 5 is a perspective view showing main part
of the plate making apparatus shown in Fig. 4;</li>
        <li>Fig. 6 is a view showing the image exposure
range on a printing plate;</li>
        <li>Fig. 7 is a view for explaining a pixel
interval ΔX in the X-axis direction and a pixel
interval ΔY in the Y-axis direction of an image to be
exposed onto the printing plate;</li>
        <li>Fig. 8 is a view showing a printing paper
sheet after printing by the second-color printing unit
and an image printed on the printing paper sheet;</li>
        <li>Fig. 9 is a view for explaining image shift
correction in a conventional correction apparatus;</li>
        <li>Fig. 10 is a side view showing the schematic
arrangement of a conventional sheet-like object convey
apparatus having a conventional correction function; and</li>
        <li>Fig. 11 is a view showing the positions of
gripper units at the times of paper gripping and
gripping change.</li>
      </sl>
    </p>
    <heading>
      <u style="single">Description of the Preferred Embodiment</u>
    </heading>
    <p num="0019">The present invention will be described below
in detail with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
    <p num="0020">First, the principle of the present invention
will be described. Referring to Fig. 9, to align a
second-color image 108 with a first-color image 107, the
X-coordinate at which image exposure to the second-color
printing plate starts is moved by -w1 to set an X-axis
direction pixel interval ΔX given by
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">ΔX = (W + w1 + w2)/n</st32:df>
In addition, a Y-axis direction pixel interval ΔY is
set to
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.ir-facility.org/ns/st32/" align="center">ΔY = (H + h)/m</st32:df></p>
    <p num="0021">That is, w1, w2, and h are measured in
advance. The start position of image exposure to the
second-color printing plate is adjusted from (X1,Y1) to
(X1-w1,Y1). The pixel interval ΔX in the X-axis
direction is adjusted from W/n to (W + w1 + w2)/n. The
pixel interval ΔY in the Y-axis direction is adjusted
from H/m to (H + h)/m. Then, the second-color image 108
matches the first-color image 107.</p>
    <p num="0022">In the present invention, for example, to
expose an image to the second-color printing plate, w1,
w2, and h are read out as correction amounts set in
accordance with the stretch amount of the printing paper
sheet. Next, on the basis of the readout correction
amounts, the image exposure start position is adjusted 
from (X1,Y1) to (X1-w1,Y1). In addition, the pixel
interval ΔX in the X-axis direction is adjusted from
W/n to (W + w1 + w2)/n. The pixel interval ΔY in the
Y-axis direction is adjusted from H/m to (H + h)/m.</p>
    <p num="0023">Fig. 1 shows a control apparatus for an image
exposure apparatus according to an embodiment of the
present invention. Referring to Fig. 1, reference
numeral 110 denotes an image position correction control
apparatus; 111, a paper convey apparatus; 112-1, an
image exposure apparatus for the first-color printing
plate; 112-2, an image exposure apparatus for the
second-color printing plate; 112-3, an image exposure
apparatus for the third-color printing plate; 112-4, an
image exposure apparatus for the fourth-color printing
plate; and 113, an image data generation apparatus. The
paper convey apparatus 111, image exposure apparatuses
112-1 to 112-4, and image data generation apparatus 113
are connected to the image position correction control
apparatus 110.</p>
    <p num="0024">The image position correction control
apparatus 110 comprises a CPU (Central Processing Unit)
110a, a ROM (Read Only Memory) 110b, a RAM (Random
Access Memory) 110c, an input device 110d constructed by
switches and operation keys, a display device 110e, and
an input/output device 110f formed from a flexible disk
drive and the like. The CPU 110a operates in accordance
with a program stored in the ROM 110b in advance. The 
input device 110d comprises a reference correction
amount storage mode switch 110d1, exposure start switch
110d2, correction reference amount storage switch 110d3,
unique correction amount storage mode switch 110d4, and
fan-out registration correction switch 110d5. The input
device 110d, display device 110e, and input/output
device 110f are connected to a bus BUS1 through an I/O
interface (I/F) 110g.</p>
    <p num="0025">An image position data memory 110h for storing
image position data, an image data memory 110i for
storing image data, a reference correction amount memory
110j for storing reference correction amounts, a unique
correction amount memory 110k for storing unique
correction amounts in correspondence with each type of
printing paper sheet, a coordinate/interval memory 1101
for storing X-axis direction pixel interval and Y-axis
direction pixel interval of images of the respective
colors, an average distortion amount memory 110m for
storing an average distortion amount, a sum correction
amount memory 110n for storing correction amounts to be
output to the paper convey apparatus, and a conversion
table memory 110o for storing a conversion table which
converts a distortion amount into a correction amount of
the paper convey apparatus are connected to the bus
BUS1.</p>
    <p num="0026">The image data generation apparatus 113 is
connected to the bus BUS1 through an I/O interface (I/F) 
110p. The paper convey apparatus 111 and image exposure
apparatuses 112-1 to 112-4 are connected to the bus BUS1
through an I/O interface (I/F) 110q. The image data
generation apparatus 113 supplies to the image position
correction control apparatus 110 the image data of an
image to be exposed to the printing plate of each color.
The image data supplied to the image position correction
control apparatus 110 is stored in the memory 110i.</p>
    <p num="0027">The paper convey apparatus 111 has a paper
convey mechanism 111p having the same structure as that
of the sheet-like object convey apparatus disclosed in
reference 2. The paper convey apparatus 111 deflects
the gripper shaft in the paper convey direction in
gripping, with swing grippers, the end portion of a
sheet-like object that is supplied from the convey
direction at the time of conveying a paper sheet in
accordance with rotation of a motor (to be described
later), thereby correcting the shape of the sheet-like
object. When a printing paper sheet is transferred to a
first-color printing unit 101-1 (Fig. 4) of the printing
section, the paper convey mechanism 111p stretches the
rear end portion of the printing paper sheet in the
horizontal direction (a direction perpendicular to the
paper convey direction) to deform in advance the paper
into a trapezoidal shape whose width increases toward
the leading edge side. As a result, the image after
printing has an almost rectangular shape. For the 
arrangement of the paper convey mechanism 111p, the
arrangement of the sheet-like object convey apparatus
described in reference 2 is incorporated in this
specification.</p>
    <p num="0028">As shown in Fig. 2, the paper convey apparatus
111 comprises, in addition to the paper convey mechanism
111p, a CPU 111a, ROM 111b, RAM 111c, input device 111d,
display device 111e, and input/output device 111f. The
CPU 111a operates in accordance with a program stored in
the ROM 111b. The input device 111d, display device
111e, and input/output device 111f are connected to a
bus BUS2 through an I/O interface (I/F) 111h.</p>
    <p num="0029">A correction motor 111j for the paper convey
mechanism 111p, a motor driver 111k, a D/A converter
1111, a rotary encoder 111m, and a counter 111n are
connected to the bus BUS2 through an I/O interface (I/F)
111i. A correction amount memory 111g for storing
correction amounts is connected to the bus BUS2. As the
motor 111j rotates, the press member (not shown) of the
paper convey mechanism 111p displaces and deflects the
gripper shaft (not shown).</p>
    <p num="0030">The image exposure apparatuses 112-1 to 112-4
construct plate making apparatuses 102-1 to 102-4 shown
in Fig. 4. The image exposure apparatuses expose images
by irradiating printing plates (raw plates) mounted on
the surfaces of plate cylinders 103-1 to 103-4 in
printing units 101-1 to 101-4 with laser beams. </p>
    <p num="0031">As shown in Fig. 3, each of the image exposure
apparatuses 112-1 to 112-4 comprises a CPU 112a, ROM
112b, RAM 112c, and image exposure head 112d for
exposing an image on a printing plate. The CPU 112a
operates in accordance with a program stored in the ROM
112b in advance. The image exposure head 112d is
connected to a bus BUS3 through an I/O interface (I/F)
112e. An image position memory 112f for storing image
position data, and a coordinate/interval memory 112g for
storing the X-coordinate of the left edge of an image to
be exposed to the printing plate of each color and the
X-axis direction pixel interval and Y-axis direction
pixel interval of a color image are connected to the bus
BUS3.</p>
    <heading>[Generation of Database]</heading>
    <p num="0032">At the beginning of operation, a database for
various kinds of correction amounts (reference
correction amounts and unique correction amounts for
each type of printing paper sheet) is generated. This
database is generated in the following way.</p>
    <heading>[Generation of Reference Correction Amounts]</heading>
    <p num="0033">The operator turns on the reference correction
amount storage mode switch 110d1 of the input device
110d at the start of database generation. When the
reference correction amount storage mode switch 110d1 is
turned on, the CPU 110a sets all data in the memory 110j
to 0. The memory 110j stores reference correction 
amounts w1Fi, w2Fi, and hFi (i = 1 to 4) of the exposure
positions of images of the respective colors and a
reference correction amount s1F of the paper convey
apparatus, as will be described later. All the
reference correction amounts are reset to 0.</p>
    <p num="0034">Next, the CPU 110a reads out image sizes "W"
and "H" which are stored in the memory 110i together
with image data. The CPU 110a calculates data (X1,Y1)
of the accurate image position (exposure start position)
and sets them in the memory 110h such that the W × H
image matches the X-direction central position of the
printing plate and the printing start position on the
leading edge side.</p>
    <p num="0035">The operator turns on the exposure start
switch 110d2 of the input device 110d. When the
exposure start switch 110d2 is turned on, the CPU 110a
reads out, from the memory 110j, the reference
correction amounts w1Fi, w2Fi, and hFi of the exposure
position of images of the respective colors and the
reference correction amount s1F of the paper convey
apparatus. In this case, all the reference correction
amounts w1Fi, w2Fi, hFi, and s1F of each color are 0.</p>
    <p num="0036">The CPU 110a obtains the X-coordinate
(X1 - w1Fi) of the left edge of the image to be exposed
to the printing plate of each color on the basis of the
readout reference correction amounts w1Fi, w2Fi, and
hFi. The CPU 110a also obtains the pixel interval ΔX 
in the X-axis direction of the image of each color as Δ
X = (W + w1Fi + w2Fi)/n and the pixel interval ΔY in
the Y-axis direction as ΔY = (H + hFi)/m. In this
case, since the reference correction amounts w1Fi, w2Fi,
and hFi of each color are 0, the X-coordinate of the
left edge of the image to be exposed to the printing
plate of each color is X1. The pixel interval ΔX in
the X-axis direction of the image of each color is
obtained as ΔX = W/n. The pixel interval ΔY in the
Y-axis direction is obtained as ΔY = H/m.</p>
    <p num="0037">The CPU 110a stores, in the memory 1101, the
obtained values, i.e., the X-coordinate X1 of the left
edge of the image to be exposed to the printing plate of
each plate, the pixel interval ΔX = W/n in the X-axis
direction of the image of each color, and the pixel
interval ΔY = H/m in the Y-axis direction of the image
of each color. The CPU 110a also sets identical data in
the memory 112g of the image exposure apparatus 112 of
each color. Next, the CPU 110a sets the data (X1,Y1) of
the image position, which is stored in the memory 110h,
in the memory 112f of the image exposure apparatus 112
of each color. The CPU 110a also sets the reference
correction amount s1F (in this case, s1F = 0) read out
from the memory 110j in the memory 111g of the paper
convey apparatus 111.</p>
    <p num="0038">In the image exposure apparatus 112 of each
color, the CPU 112a reads out the image position data 
(X1,Y1) set in the memory 112f, and the X-coordinate X1
of the left edge of the image to be exposed to the
printing plate of a corresponding color, the pixel
interval ΔX = W/n in the X-axis direction of the image
of a corresponding color, and the pixel interval ΔY =
H/m in the Y-axis direction of the image of a
corresponding color, which are set in the memory 112g.
On the basis of the readout data, the exposure start
position is set at (X1,Y1). The image is exposed to the
printing plate (raw plate) of each color at the interval
ΔX = W/n in the X-axis direction and at the interval Δ
Y = H/m in the Y-axis direction.</p>
    <p num="0039">The operator executes four-color printing on a
reference printing paper sheet using the printing plates
of the respective colors with the exposed images. After
printing, the operator checks the image printed on the
reference printing paper sheet and obtains the
correction amount s1F of the paper convey apparatus 111
which prevents any shift in the distortion direction.
The obtained correction amount s1F is set in the memory
110j of the image position correction control apparatus
110.</p>
    <p num="0040">Next, shift amounts w1F2 and w2F2 in the
horizontal direction and a shift amount hF2 in the
vertical direction between the first-color image and the
second-color image are obtained. In addition, shift
amounts w1F3 and w2F3 in the horizontal direction and a 
shift amount hF3 in the vertical direction between the
first-color image and the third-color image are
obtained. Also, shift amounts w1F4 and w2F4 in the
horizontal direction and a shift amount hF4 in the
vertical direction between the first-color image and the
fourth-color image are obtained. The obtained shift
amounts are set in the memory 110j of the image position
correction control apparatus 110.</p>
    <p num="0041">Then, the operator exchanges the printing
plates to which the second-, third-, and fourth-color
images are exposed with raw plates and turns on the
exposure start switch 110d2 of the input device 110d.
When the exposure start switch 110d2 is turned on, the
CPU 110a reads out, from the memory 110j, the reference
correction amounts w1F2, w2F2, and hF2, the reference
correction amounts w1F3, w2F3, and hF3, the reference
correction amounts w1F4, w2F4, and hF4, and the
reference correction amount s1F of the paper convey
apparatus.</p>
    <p num="0042">On the basis of the readout reference
correction amounts w1F2, w2F2, and hF2, the CPU 110a
obtains the X-coordinate of the left edge of the image
to be exposed to the second-color printing plate as
(X1 - w1F2). The CPU 110a also obtains the pixel
interval ΔX in the X-axis direction of the second-color
image as ΔX = (W + w1F2 + w2F2)/n and the pixel
interval ΔY in the Y-axis direction as ΔY = (H + 
hF2)/m.</p>
    <p num="0043">Similarly, on the basis of the readout
reference correction amounts w1F3, w2F3, and hF3, the
CPU 110a obtains the X-coordinate of the left edge of
the image to be exposed to the third-color printing
plate as (X1 - w1F3). The CPU 110a also obtains the
pixel interval ΔX in the X-axis direction of the
third-color image as ΔX = (W + w1F3 + w2F3)/n and the
pixel interval ΔY in the Y-axis direction as ΔY = (H +
hF3)/m.</p>
    <p num="0044">Similarly, on the basis of the readout
reference correction amounts w1F4, w2F4, and hF4, the
CPU 110a obtains the X-coordinate of the left edge of
the image to be exposed to the fourth-color printing
plate as (X1 - w1F4). The CPU 110a also obtains the
pixel interval ΔX in the X-axis direction of the
fourth-color image as ΔX = (W + w1F4 + w2F4)/n and the
pixel interval ΔY in the Y-axis direction as ΔY = (H +
hF4)/m.</p>
    <p num="0045">The CPU 110a sets the readout reference
correction amount s1F of the paper convey apparatus in
the memory 111g of the paper convey apparatus 111. The
CPU 110a also sets the X-coordinate (X1 - w1F2), the
pixel interval ΔX = (W + w1F2 + w2F2)/n in the X-axis
direction, and the pixel interval ΔY = (H + hF2)/m in
the Y-axis direction of the second-color image in the
memory 112g of the image exposure apparatus 112-2. In a 
similar way, the CPU 110a sets the X-coordinate
(X1 - w1F3), the pixel interval ΔX = (W + w1F3 +
w2F3)/n in the X-axis direction, and the pixel interval
ΔY = (H + hF3)/m in the Y-axis direction of the
third-color image in the memory 112g of the image
exposure apparatus 112-3. The CPU 110a also sets the
X-coordinate (X1 - w1F4), the pixel interval ΔX = (W +
w1F4 + w2F4)/n in the X-axis direction, and the pixel
interval ΔY = (H + hF4)/m in the Y-axis direction of
the fourth-color image in the memory 112g of the image
exposure apparatus 112-4.</p>
    <p num="0046">In the image exposure apparatus 112-2, the CPU
112a reads out the image position data (X1,Y1) in the
memory 112f, and the X-coordinate (X1 - w1F2) of the
left edge of the image to be exposed to the printing
plate, the pixel interval ΔX = (W + w1F2 + w2F2)/n in
the X-axis direction, and the pixel interval ΔY = (H +
hF2)/m in the Y-axis direction, which are set in the
memory 112g. On the basis of the readout data, the CPU
112a sets the exposure start position at (X1-w1F2,Y1).
The image is exposed to the second-color printing plate
at the interval ΔX = (W + w1F2 + w2F2)/n in the X-axis
direction and at the interval ΔY = (H + hF2)/m in the
Y-axis direction.</p>
    <p num="0047">Similarly, in the image exposure apparatus
112-3, the CPU 112a reads out the image position data
(X1,Y1) in the memory 112f, and the X-coordinate 
(X1 - w1F3) of the left edge of the image to be exposed
to the printing plate, the pixel interval ΔX = (W +
w1F3 + w2F3)/n in the X-axis direction, and the pixel
interval ΔY = (H + hF3)/m in the Y-axis direction,
which are set in the memory 112g. On the basis of the
readout data, the CPU 112a sets the exposure start
position at (X1-w1F3,Y1). The image is exposed to the
third-color printing plate at the interval ΔX = (W +
w1F3 + w2F3)/n in the X-axis direction and at the
interval ΔY = (H + hF3)/m in the Y-axis direction.</p>
    <p num="0048">In addition, in the image exposure apparatus
112-4, the CPU 112a reads out the image position data
(X1,Y1) in the memory 112f, and the X-coordinate
(X1 - w1F4) of the left edge of the image to be exposed
to the printing plate, the pixel interval ΔX = (W +
w1F4 + w2F4)/n in the X-axis direction, and the pixel
interval ΔY = (H + hF4)/m in the Y-axis direction,
which are set in the memory 112g. On the basis of the
readout data, the CPU 112a sets the exposure start
position at (X1-w1F4,Y1). The image is exposed to the
fourth-color printing plate at the interval ΔX = (W +
w1F4 + w2F4)/n in the X-axis direction and at the
interval ΔY = (H + hF4)/m in the Y-axis direction.</p>
    <p num="0049">The operator executes four-color printing on a
reference printing paper sheet using the second- to
fourth-color printing plates with the exposed images,
and the first-color printing plate with the already 
exposed image. In printing, when the printing paper
sheet is transferred to the printing section, the paper
convey apparatus 111 reads out the reference correction
amount s1F set in the memory 111g and stretches the rear
end portion of the printing paper sheet in the
horizontal direction on the basis of the readout
reference correction amount s1F, thereby deforming in
advance the printing paper sheet into a trapezoidal
shape whose width increases toward the trailing edge
side.</p>
    <p num="0050">After printing, the operator checks the image
printed on the reference printing paper sheet. If the
misregistration between the colors falls within the
allowable range, the correction reference amount storage
switch 110d3 of the input device 110d is turned on to
determine the reference correction amounts w1Fi, w2Fi,
hFi, and s1F of the respective colors in the memory
110j. If the misregistration between the colors falls
outside the allowable range, the above-described
operation is repeated until the misregistration falls
within the allowable range.</p>
    <heading>[Generation of Unique Correction Amounts for Each Type
of Printing Paper Sheet]</heading>
    <p num="0051">After the above-described reference correction
amount generation, the operator turns on the unique
correction amount storage mode switch 110d4 of the input
device 110d. When the unique correction amount storage 
mode switch 110d4 is turned on, the CPU 110a resets all
data in the memory 110k to 0. The memory 110k stores
unique correction amounts w1i, w2i, and hi (i = 1 to 4)
of the exposure positions of images of the respective
colors in correspondence with each type of printing
paper sheet and unique distortion amounts s1i and s2i of
the respective colors in correspondence with each type
of printing paper sheet, as will be described later.
All the unique values are reset to 0.</p>
    <p num="0052">After that, the operator executes four-color
printing on a printing paper sheet (a printing paper
sheet is to be used, which is of a type different from the
reference printing paper sheet) other than the reference
printing paper sheet using the printing plates of the
respective colors. The operator checks the image
printed on the printing paper sheet of a different type
and obtains shift amounts w12 and w22 in the horizontal
direction and a shift amount h2 in the vertical
direction between the first-color image and the
second-color image. In addition, shift amounts w13 and
w23 in the horizontal direction and a shift amount h3 in
the vertical direction between the first-color image and
the third-color image are obtained. Also, shift amounts
w14 and w24 in the horizontal direction and a shift
amount h4 in the vertical direction between the
first-color image and the fourth-color image are
obtained. These shift amounts are set in the memory 
110k of the image position correction control apparatus
110 as unique correction amounts.</p>
    <p num="0053">The operator also obtains shift amounts s12
and s22 in the distortion direction between the
first-color image and the second-color image, shift
amounts s13 and s23 in the distortion direction between
the first-color image and the third-color image, and
shift amounts s14 and s24 in the distortion direction
between the first-color image and the fourth-color
image. These shift amounts are set in the memory 110k
of the image position correction control apparatus 110
as unique distortion amounts.</p>
    <p num="0054">In a similar way, unique correction amounts
and distortion amounts are obtained for all types of
printing paper sheets and set in the memory 110k of the
image position correction control apparatus 110.</p>
    <heading>[Fan-Out Registration Correction Procedure In Actual
Printing]</heading>
    <p num="0055">In actual printing, the operator turns on the
fan-out registration correction switch 110d5 of the
input device 110d. When the fan-out registration
correction switch 110d5 is turned on, the CPU 110a reads
out the images sizes "W" and "H" which are stored in the
memory 110i together with image data. The CPU 110a
calculates the data (X1,Y1) of the accurate image
position and sets them in the memory 110h such that the
W × H image matches the X-direction central position of 
the printing plate and the printing start position on
the leading edge side.</p>
    <p num="0056">The operator inputs the type of printing paper
sheet to be used and turns on the exposure start switch
110d2 of the input device 110d. When the exposure start
switch 110d2 is turned on, the CPU 110a reads out, from
the memory 110j, the reference correction amounts w1Fi,
w2Fi, and hFi of the exposure positions of images of the
respective colors and the reference correction amount
s1F of the paper convey apparatus. The CPU 110a also
reads out, from the memory 110k, the unique correction
amounts w1i, w2i, and hi of the exposure positions of
images of the respective colors and the unique
distortion amounts s1i and s2i of the respective colors
in correspondence with the input printing paper sheet
type.</p>
    <p num="0057">The CPU 110a obtains the X-coordinate
(X1 - w1Fi - w1i) of the left edge of the image to be
exposed to the printing plate of each color on the basis
of the readout reference correction amounts w1Fi, w2Fi,
and hFi and unique correction amounts w1i, w2i, and hi.
The CPU 110a also obtains the pixel interval ΔX in the
X-axis direction of the image of each color as ΔX = (W
+ w1Fi + w2Fi + w1i + w2i)/n and the pixel interval ΔY
in the Y-axis direction as ΔY = (H + hFi + hi)/m.</p>
    <p num="0058">The CPU 110a stores, in the memory 1101, the
obtained value, i.e., the X-coordinate (X1 - w1Fi - w1i) 
of the left edge of the image to be exposed to the
printing plate of each color, the pixel interval ΔX =
(W + w1Fi + w2Fi + w1i + w2i)/n in the X-axis direction
of the image of each color, and the pixel interval ΔY =
(H + hFi + hi)/m in the Y-axis direction of the image of
each color. The CPU 110a also sets these data in the
memory 112g of the image exposure apparatus 112 of each
color. Next, the CPU 110a sets the data (X1,Y1) of the
image position, which is set in the memory 110h, in the
memory 112f of the image exposure apparatus 112 of each
color.</p>
    <p num="0059">In the image exposure apparatus 112 of each
color, the CPU 112a reads out the image position data
(X1,Y1) set in the memory 112f, and the X-coordinate
(X1 - w1Fi - w1i) of the left edge of the image to be
exposed to the printing plate of a corresponding color,
the pixel interval ΔX = (W + w1Fi + w2Fi + w1i + w2i)/n
in the X-axis direction of the image of a corresponding
color, and the pixel interval ΔY = (H + hFi + hi)/m in
the Y-axis direction, which are set in the memory 112g.
On the basis of the readout data, the CPU 112a sets the
exposure start position at (X1,Y1). The image is
exposed to the printing plate (raw plate) of each color
at the interval ΔX = (W + w1Fi + w2Fi + w1i + w2i)/n in
the X-axis direction and at the interval ΔY = (H + hFi
+ hi)/m in the Y-axis direction.</p>
    <p num="0060">In the image position correction control 
apparatus 110, the CPU 110a reads out, from the memory
110k, the unique distortion amounts s1i and s2i of each
color in correspondence with the type of printing paper
sheet and obtains an average distortion amount (s1i +
s2i)/2 of each color. Next, from the average distortion
amount (s1i + s2i)/2 of each color, the CPU 110a obtains
a unique correction amount s1 of the paper convey
apparatus in correspondence with the type of printing
paper sheet using a conversion table which is stored in
the memory 110o and converts the distortion amount into
the correction amount of the paper convey apparatus.
The CPU 110a obtains a sum (s1F + s1) of the obtained
unique correction amount s1 and the reference correction
amount s1F stored in the memory 110j for storing
reference correction amounts and stores the sum in the
memory 110n. The CPU 110a sets this data in the memory
111g of the paper convey apparatus 111.</p>
    <p num="0061">After that, the operator executes four-color
printing on the printing paper sheet whose type is input
in the preceding step, using the printing plates of the
respective colors with the exposed images. During printing,
when the printing paper sheet is transferred to the
printing section, the paper convey apparatus 111
stretches the rear end portion of the printing paper
sheet in the horizontal direction on the basis of the
correction amount (s1F + s1) which is stored in the
memory 111g in correspondence with the printing paper 
sheet, thereby deforming in advance the printing paper
sheet into a trapezoidal shape whose width increases
toward the trailing edge side.</p>
    <p num="0062">The image is printed on the printing paper
sheet which is deformed into the trapezoidal shape with
a width increasing toward the trailing edge side.
Hence, stretching of the printing paper sheet during
printing is eliminated or reduced, and the shift of the
image due to distortion by the stretch of the printing
paper sheet during printing is eliminated or reduced.
For this reason, a normal printing product can be
obtained.</p>
    <p num="0063">To the contrary, when the image data (image
"1"/non-image "0") of each pixel is paired with the data
of its exposure position and stored, and only the
exposure position of each image is corrected, the
resultant printing product has an image with a
trapezoidal distortion as shown in Fig. 8. Hence, no
normal printing product can be obtained.</p>
    <p num="0064">According to this embodiment, since correction
in the distortion direction is done using the image
position correction control apparatus 110, only
correction in the horizontal and vertical directions
needs to be executed in exposing the image data of each
pixel to the printing plate. For this reason, only the
reference correction amounts w1Fi, w2Fi, hFi, and s1F
and unique correction amounts w1i, w2i, hi, s1i, and s2i 
corresponding to the type of printing paper sheet need
to be stored. Hence, a small storage capacity suffices.
In addition, since only the X-coordinate of the left
edge of the image to be exposed to the printing plate
and the X-axis direction pixel interval and Y-axis
direction pixel interval of the image need to be
corrected, processing can easily be done in a short
time.</p>
    <p num="0065">This applies not only to a case wherein the
paper convey apparatus is automatically controlled using
the motor for the paper convey apparatus, as described
in the above embodiment, but also to a case wherein the
operator manually operates the paper convey apparatus.</p>
    <p num="0066">In this embodiment, the reference correction
amounts w1Fi, w2Fi, and hFi (i = 1 to 4) of the exposure
positions of images of all the four colors are stored in
the memory 110j. In addition, the unique correction
amounts w1i, w2i, and hi (i = 1 to 4) of the exposure
positions of images of all the four colors are stored in
the memory 110k in correspondence with the type of
printing paper sheet. However, the correction amounts
w1F w2F1, and hF1 of the first-color image or the
unique correction amounts w11, w21, and h1 of the
first-color image corresponding to the type of printing
paper sheet need not always be stored. That is, the
reference correction amounts and unique correction
amounts of the first-color image are always 0. Hence, 
when the image is to be exposed to the first-color
printing plate, (X1,Y1) is used as the exposure start
position, ΔX = W/n is used as the pixel interval in the
X-axis direction, and ΔY = H/m is used as the pixel
interval in the Y-axis direction.</p>
    <p num="0067">In this embodiment, plate making is executed
on the printing press as plate making on press.
However, the present invention can also be applied to a
case wherein an image is exposed to a printing plate by
a dedicated plate making machine separated from a
printing press, and then, printing is executed by
attaching the printing plate with the exposed image to
the printing press.</p>
    <p num="0068">In this embodiment, correction amounts are
supplied from the image position correction control
apparatus 110 to the paper convey apparatus 111.
However, correction amounts to the paper convey
apparatus 111 may be manually set as input values from
the operator.</p>
    <p num="0069">As has been described above, according to the
present invention, in exposing an image to a printing
plate, correction amounts set in accordance with the
stretch amount of a printing paper sheet are read out,
and the exposure position of each pixel of the image is
adjusted on the basis of the correction amounts. With
this arrangement, when the exposure start position
(X1,Y1) of the image on the printing plate, the pixel 
interval ΔX in the X-axis direction, and the pixel
interval ΔY in the Y-axis direction are adjusted, any
misregistration between the colors due to stretch of the
printing paper sheet can be eliminated, and any
defective printing product can be prevented.</p>
  </description>
  <claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">
    <claim num="1">
      <claim-text>An image exposure control apparatus
characterized by comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>memory means (110j, 110k) for storing a
correction amount for each color in accordance with a
stretch amount of a printing paper sheet in multicolor
printing operation; and</claim-text><claim-text>adjustment means (110a) for adjusting an
exposure position of a pixel of an image to be exposed
for each color, on the basis of the correction amount
read out from said memory means, in exposing the image
on a printing plate.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="2">
      <claim-text>An apparatus according to claim 1, further
comprising distortion preventing means (111) for
deforming a trailing edge side of the printing paper
sheet before start of printing, thereby preventing
distortion of a shape of the image after printing.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="3">
      <claim-text>An apparatus according to claim 2, wherein
said distortion preventing means comprises
<claim-text><claim-text>a motor (111j) which rotates in accordance
with the set correction amount, and</claim-text><claim-text>a paper convey mechanism (111p) which
stretches in advance the trailing edge side of the
printing paper sheet as said motor rotates at the time
of conveying the paper.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="4">
      <claim-text>An apparatus according to claim 1, wherein
said memory means comprises
<claim-text><claim-text>a first memory which stores a reference
correction amount for each color in correspondence with
a stretch amount of a reference paper sheet, and</claim-text><claim-text>a second memory which stores a unique
correction amount set in correspondence with a type of
printing paper sheet, and</claim-text><claim-text>said adjustment means adjusts the image
exposure position on the basis of a value obtained by
adding the reference correction amount and unique
correction amount, which are respectively read out from
said first and second memories.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="5">
      <claim-text>An apparatus according to claim 4, wherein, as
the reference correction amount for each color, said
first memory stores a shift amount between an image of a
first color and each of images of second and subsequent
colors, which are printed on the reference printing
paper sheets using the printing plates for respective
colors, to which the image is exposed on the basis of
image data and image position data obtained from an
image size and the number of pixels in the image.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="6">
      <claim-text>An apparatus according to claim 4, wherein, as
the unique correction amount, said second memory stores
a shift amount between an image of a first color and
each of images of second and subsequent colors, which
are printed on all printing paper sheets to be used,
using the printing plates for respective colors, to
which the image is exposed on the basis of image data
and image position data obtained from an image size and
the number of pixels in the image.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="7">
      <claim-text>An apparatus according to claim 1, wherein
said adjustment means adjusts, as the image exposure
position, an image exposure start position and a pixel
interval.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="8">
      <claim-text>An apparatus according to claim 7, wherein
said adjustment means adjusts, as the image exposure
position, the image exposure start position in an X-axis
direction and pixel intervals in the X- and Y-axis
directions.</claim-text>
    </claim>
    <claim num="9">
      <claim-text>An image exposure control apparatus
characterized by comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>memory means (110j, 110k) for storing a
correction amount in accordance with a stretch amount of
a printing paper sheet in printing operation; and</claim-text><claim-text>adjustment means (110a) for adjusting an
exposure position of a pixel of an image to be exposed,
on the basis of the correction amount read out from said
memory means, in exposing the image on a printing plate.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
    </claim>
  </claims>
  <copyright>User acknowledges that the Information Retrieval Facility (IRF) and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws. User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format. User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.ir-facility.org/legal/marec/data_licence</copyright>
</patent-document>
